<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0916-0822-0793-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">MONTREAL</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 16, page 793</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1134794">Streets</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:845200">Canadians</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1028366">Mountains</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zv9m">Streets</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kj6q">Canadians</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4r20rx5q">Presbyterianism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204310">Canada</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204305">Vermont</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205049">Victoria</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204832">Ontario</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n822/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MONTREAL</label>, the largest city in the Dominion of Canada,
                    its chief seat of commerce and principal port of entry, is situated on an island
                    of about 30 miles in length and 7 in breadth, at the confluence of the rivers
                    Ottawa and St Lawrence, 45° 32' N. lat. and 73° 32' W. long. It stands at the
                    head of ocean navigation, 160 miles above Quebec, and nearly 1000 miles (986)
                    from the Atlantic Ocean, and lies at the foot of the great chain of river, lake,
                    and canal navigation which extends westward through the great lakes. Montreal is
                    built upon a series of terraces, the former levels of the river or of a more
                    ancient sea. Behind those rises Mount Royal, a mass of trap-rock thrown up
                    through the surrounding limestone strata to a height of 700 feet above the level
                    of the river. From this rock the city derives its name, though its original
                    founder, Paul de Chomedey, sire de Maisonneuve, in 1642, gave it the name of
                    Ville-Marie, when it was dedicated with religious enthusiasm, not as a centre of
                    commercial enterprise, but as the seat of a mission which aimed specially at the
                    conversion of the native Indians. The modern city of Montreal occupies an area
                    of about eight square miles,—its principal streets running parallel with the
                    river. On the north side of the Mountain the Trenton limestone approaches the
                    surface, and is there quarried for building purposes. Of this grey limestone
                    most of the public edifices and many of the better class of private dwellings
                    are built. But both brick and wood are largely used for workshops and private
                    houses of a humbler class. The western slope of the Mountain is occupied by the
                    Côte des Neiges (Roman Catholic) cemetery, and the Mount Royal (Protestant)
                    cemetery. The upper portion of the Mountain, embιacing an area of 430 acres, is
                    now laid out as a public park, with fine drives shaded by well-grown trees. From
                    its commanding site, and the wide expanse of the valley of the St Lawrence, the
                    views on all sides are of great variety and beauty. A well-cultivated and wooded
                    country, watered by the Ottawa and the St Lawrence, stretches away on either
                    hand, being bounded on the west by the lakes of St Louis and the Two Mountains,
                    and on the distant horizon by <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n823/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0916-0823-0794"/> the Laurentian Hills, the Adirondacks, and the
                    Green Mountains of Vermont. On the east side the city occupies the slope towards
                    the river St Lawrence, which has here a breadth of from one to two miles. Two
                    islands, the Nun’s and St Helen’s Isles—the latter rising to a height of 150
                    feet, beautifully wooded, and laid out as a public park—occupy the bed of the
                    river immediately below the Lachine Falls, and between them the river is spanned
                    by the great Victoria Bridge. This wonderful triumph of engineering skill is a
                    tubular iron bridge supported on twenty-four piers of solid masonry, with the
                    terminal abutments of the same, and measuring 9184 feet in length. The river
                    descends at the rate of 7 miles an hour at the point where it is thus crossed;
                    and the piers are constructed with a view to resist the enormous pressure of the
                    ice in spring. Near at hand the towers, spires, and domes of numerous churches
                    and public buildings rise from the general mass of houses. The wharves and docks
                    are crowded with shipping during the season of navigation, for the St Lawrence
                    is navigable to Montreal by the largest ocean steamers. But immediately above
                    the city the river is impeded by a natural dyke of trap and limestone which here
                    arrests the waters in their descent, forming the Lake St Louis at a height of 44
                    feet above the level of Montreal harbour. The river here forces its way through
                    a channel of about half a mile wide, with a rapidity of about 18 miles an hour,
                    forming the Lachine or St Louis Rapids. Owing to the immense volume of water
                    concentrated in a narrow channel, steamers drawing ten feet of water are safely
                    navigated down the rapids, but these necessarily present an insuperable barrier
                    to the ascent of the river. This is accordingly surmounted by means of the
                    Lachine Canal, which, commencing at the port of Montreal, passes round the falls
                    by a series of locks, in a course of nine miles, to Lake St Louis, opposite the
                    Indian village of Caughnawaga. The fall of water in the canal furnishes
                    water-power for saw-mills, boiler and engine works, sash, blind, door,
                    edge-tool, and other factories, established on its banks. Sugar-refining has
                    also been carried on here with great profit. Woollen and cotton mills, silk
                    factories, a large rubber factory, rope and cordage works, boot and shoe
                    factories, &lt;fcc., are likewise organized on an extensive scale. The water
                    supply of Montreal is derived from the river above the city; and, after passing
                    along an open canal 5 miles in length, it is raised to a reservoir excavated out
                    of the solid rock on the east slope of the Mountain, 205 feet above the level of
                    the harbour.</p>
                <p>The circumstances attendant on the foundation of Montreal, and the marked
                    contrasts in its mixed population of French and English, give a peculiar
                    character to its religious and benevolent institutions. This has led to the
                    multiplication of churches, colleges, convents, and religious and charitable
                    foundations, and to a rivalry in the zeal of their promoters, one result of
                    which is seen in the scale and imposing character of many of their buildings.
                    The Metropolitan Cathedral of St Peter, designed to reproduce on a reduced scale
                    the chief features of St Peter’s at Rome, was projected by Bishop Bourget after
                    the destruction of his church and palace in the great fire of 1852. It occupies
                    a prominent site in Dorchester Street, at the corner of Dominion Square; and,
                    when surmounted by the projected dome and finished in front with its classic
                    façade, it will form a striking feature in the general view of the city. The
                    parish church of Notre-Dame, on the Place d’Armes, affords accommodation for
                    10,000 worshippers. The Jesuits’ Church is another large church, elaborately
                    painted in the interior. Near it is the College of St Mary. Christchurch
                    Cathedral (Protestant) is a fine specimen of Decorated Gothic, built externally
                    of the native limestone, but with the chief facings and carvings of the exterior
                    and the whole of the interior of fine Caen stone. It was erected under the
                    direction of Bishop Fulford, the first Anglican bishop of Montreal, to whose
                    memory a memorial cross, after the model of the Queen Eleanor crosses, has been
                    erected on the south side of the cathedral. The other churches of the various
                    Protestant denominations include St George’s, Anglican, St Andrew’s and St
                    Paul’s (Presbyterian), St James Street Methodist Church, the Church of the
                    Messiah, Unitarian, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>The Hôtel Dieu, founded in 1644 for the cure of the sick, now occupies a building
                    at the head of St Famille Street. A body of professed sisters and novices
                    perform the duties of nursing and attendance, and upwards of 3000 sick persons
                    are annually received into its wards. The order of the Grey Nuns, founded in
                    1737, have built a new hospital in Guy Street. The professed sisters of this
                    religious community, numbering at present 310, receive under their care the aged
                    and infirm and orphan and foundling children of the French Canadian population.
                    They also undertake the care of various asylums and schools in different parts
                    of the city. Montreal has also a General Hospital, founded in 1822; a Protestant
                    House of Industry, the Mackay Institution for Deaf-Mutes, the Protestant Orphan
                    Asylum, Infants’ Home, &amp;c. The curiously mixed character of the population
                    of Montreal is further shown in its separate daily an&lt;I weekly newspapers in
                    the English and French languages, and in its various national societies, of St
                    George, St Andrew, St Patrick, St Jean Baptiste, and New England,—each confining
                    its charitable operations to those of the nationality which it represents. There
                    are two theatres in Montreal, but the Roman Catholic clergy have systematically
                    discountenanced the stage, and the diverse languages have further tended to
                    limit the numbers who patronize the drama.</p>
                <p>Among the chief civic buildings is the city hall, built in the modern French
                    style, with lofty mansard roofs, and a central pavilion. It affords
                    accommodation for all the municipal offices, including the waterworks and fire
                    alarm departments, the recorder’s court, the police office, and for the meetings
                    of the city corporation, which consists of a mayor and twenty-seven aidermen.
                    Three aidermen are elected by each of the nine ward⅛ one of whom retires every
                    year. The court house, situated close to the city hall, between the Champ de
                    Mars and Jacques Cartier Square, is a handsome classical building where all the
                    law courts hold their sittings: and accommodation is provided for the Advocates’
                    Library, which numbers upwards of 10,000 volumes, including a fine collection of
                    books in the department of old French civil law. Bonsecours Market in St Paul
                    Street is a large structure surmounted by a dome, which forms a prominent
                    feature in every view of the city. When it is crowded with the peasants bringing
                    in their country produce, and by the French Canadian city populace as
                    purchasers, as is the case especially on Tuesdays and Fridays, the scene is very
                    striking to a stranger.</p>
                <p>Foremost among the educational institutions is the university of Μ‘Gill College,
                    founded by James Μ‘Gill, a Scotchman, who in the later years of the 18th century
                    engaged in the north-west fur trade, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n824/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0916-0824-0795"/> and ultimately became one of the leading
                    merchants in Montreal. At his death in 1813 he left his property for the
                    founding of a college. The most recent and liberal addition to it is the Peter
                    Red-path Museum, valued at upwards of $100,000, the gift of a wealthy citizen.
                    The university embraces the faculties of arts, law, and medicine, and has also a
                    department of practical science. The college buildings stand in a pleasant park
                    fronting on Sherbrooke Street, at the base of the Mountain. Theological colleges
                    in connection with the Church of England, the Presbyterian, Methodist, and
                    Congregational Churches, occupy buildings in the vicinity, and their students
                    attend the classes at Μ‘Gill College for secular instruction. The Seminary of St
                    Sulpice is a theological training school for priests, where the larger portion
                    of the Roman Catholic clergy of the province of Quebec have received their
                    training, and also a college where a large number of the French Canadian youth
                    obtain their education. This seminary is held in high esteem, and attracts many
                    Roman Catholic students from the United States. Laval University, which has its
                    chief seat at Quebec, has also a branch at Montreal, with a large staff of
                    professors, chiefly in theology, law, and medicine. The Μ‘Gill and the Jacques
                    Cartier Normal Schools for training teachers for the Protestant and Roman
                    Catholic public schools are conducted under the Protestant and Roman Catholic
                    boards of public instruction; and model schools attached to them afford the
                    requisite practical training for teachers. The principal public monuments are
                    the column erected in honour of Lord Nelson, and a bronze statue of Queen
                    Victoria, by the late Marshall Wood, which occupies a good site in Victoria
                    Square.</p>
                <p>The commerce of Montreal is well represented by the architectural character of
                    its banking establishments and many of the large mercantile houses. It is also
                    the seat of a large manufacturing industry. But the most substantial evidence of
                    its importance as a commercial centre is its harbour. The solidly-built basins,
                    wharves, quays, and canal locks extend for upwards of a mile and a half along
                    the river-side. In 1849, at a period of depression, the total value of the
                    imports and exports amounted to £2,013,478 sterling. In 1882 they had risen to
                    £15,633,657 sterling. The business of the port at the same date is thus
                    expressed in Canadian currency:—total valueof exports $26,334,312, of imports
                    $49,749,461; customs duties collected estimated at $8,100,366. The number of
                    sea-going vessels in port was 648, of which fully one-half were ocean steamers,
                    in addition to which the inland vessels arriving at the port numbered 6543. The
                    estimated value of real estate in Montreal is $65,978,930. The population in
                    1851 numbered 57,715; in 1881 it had increased to 140,747, of whom 78,684 were
                    of French and 28,995 of Irish origin, and of the whole number, 103,579 were
                    Roman Catholic.</p>
                <p>The city returns three members to the Canadian House of Commons, and the same
                    number to the provincial legislature of Quebec.</p>
                <p>When the first French explorers landed on the island of Montreal under the
                    leadership of Jacques Cartier in 1535, a large Indian palisaded town existed a
                    little to the west of Mount Royal, and not far from the present English
                    cathedral. To this fortified town the Indians gave the name of Hochelaga, and
                    Jacques Cartier describes it as surrounded by fields of grain and other
                    evidences of a settled native population. The name is now applied to the eastern
                    suburb of the modern city. Sixty years later, when Samuel de Champlain made his
                    way up the St Lawrence, and climbed to the summit of Mount Royal, the populous
                    native town had disappeared, and only two Indians were found from whom some
                    obscure hints were derived of war between rival tribes, followed by the
                    destruction of the town and the extermination or flight of its former occupants.
                    The enmity thus established between the Wyandotts or Hurons of Canada and the
                    Iroquois settled in the valley of the Hudson and south of Lake Ontario was
                    perpetuated throughout the whole period of French occupation. Champlain took the
                    side of the Hurons, while the Iroquois allied themselves with the Dutch and
                    English settlers on the Hudson. Thus the early history of Montreal is largely
                    occupied with incidents of Indian warfare. In 1665 the marquis de Tracy arrived
                    from France, bringing with him a regiment of French soldiers, with whose aid the
                    Indian assailants were driven off, and forts erected and garrisoned to repel
                    their incursions; thus protected, Montreal became the centre of the fur trade
                    with the west, and entered on its history as a commercial city. In 1722 it was
                    fortified with a bastioned wall and ditch, under the directions of De Lery; and
                    the citadel was erected on a height now laid out as Dalhousie Square. The taking
                    of Quebec by the English under General Wolfe in 1759 was followed ere long by
                    the surrender of Montreal. Since that date it has rapidly developed as an
                    important centre of commercial and manufacturing enterprise. (D. W.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
