<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0916-0499-0478-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">MINSK</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 16, page 478</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1206891">Poland</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1227863">Lithuania</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:850620">Cent</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1010775">Marshes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:932562">Foresters</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1068347">Poles</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1000435">Lithuanians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1139996">Swedes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g03">Cent</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b42z12q4d">Marshes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tv2w">Canals</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4697039w">Lithuanians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vt81">Swedes</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n499/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MINSK</label>, a western government of Russia, is bounded by
                    Vilna, Vitebsk, and Moghileff on the N. and E., and by Tchernigoff, Kieff,
                    Volhynia, and Grodno on the S. and W., and has an area of 35,175 square miles.
                    The surface is undulating and hilly in the north-west, where a narrow plateau
                    and a range of hills of the Tertiary formation runs to the north-east,
                    separating the basin of the Niemen, which flows into the Baltic, from that of
                    the Dnieper, which sends its waters into the Black Sea. The range, which
                    averages from 800 to 1000 feet, culminates in Lysaya Gora (1129 feet). The
                    remainder of the province is flat, 450 to 650 feet above the sea-level, covered
                    with sands and clays of the glacial and post-glacial periods. Two broad shallow
                    depressions, drained by the Berezina and the Pripet, cross the province from
                    north to south and from west to east; and these, as well as the triangular space
                    between them, are covered with immense marshes (often occupying 200 to 600
                    square miles), numberless ponds and small lakes, peat-bogs, downs, and moving
                    sands, as well as with dense forests. This country, and especially its
                    south-western part, is usually known under the name of Polyesie (“The Woods”).
                    Altogether, marshes take up 15 per cent, and marshy forests no less than 55 per
                    cent, of the entire area of the province (60 to 71 per cent, in several
                    districts). The forests, however, consist of full-grown trees in the higher
                    districts of the north-west only, those which occupy the marshy ground
                    consisting of small and stunted pine, birch, and aspen. The climate of the
                    Polyesie is harsh and extremely unhealthy; malarias and an endemic disease of
                    the bulbs of the hair <hi rend="italic">(koltun, plica Polonicd)</hi> are the
                    plagues of these tracts, the evil being intensified by the dreadful poverty of
                    the population. Communication is very difficult. The railway from Poland to
                    Moscow has, so far as Minsk is concerned, taken advantage of the plateau above
                    mentioned; but still it has to cross the broad marshy depression of the
                    Berezina. A successful attempt was recently made to drain the marshes of the
                    Polyesie by a system of canals, and more than 4,500,000 acres have thus been
                    rendered suitable for pasture and agriculture. Two great tributaries of the
                    Dnieper, the Berezina and the Pripet, both navigable, with numberless
                    subtributaries, many of which are also navigable, are the natural outlets for
                    the marshes of the province. The Dnieper flows along its south-eastern border
                    for 160 miles, and the Niemen on the north-western for 130 miles. The affluents
                    of the Baltic, the Duna (Dwina), and the Vistula are connected by three canals
                    with tributaries of the Dnieper. The population of the province (1,183,200 in
                    1873) may be estimated at about 1,350,000, mostly White Russians (67 per cent.);
                    there are also Poles (about 11 per cent.), especially in the western districts,
                    Jews (more than 10 per cent.), Little Russians (5 per cent.), and Russians (2
                    per cent.). About 70,000 are considered to be Lithuanians; there are also 4000
                    Tartars, whose presence can be traced to the raids of their ancestors on
                    Lithuania in the 13th century, and about 2000 German agriculturists who settled
                    in last century</p>
                <p>The chief occupation of the inhabitants is agriculture, which is, however, very
                    unproductive in the lowlands; in the Polyesie the peasants rarely have pure
                    bread to eat. Only 23 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 8 per cent, of th⅛ <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n500/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0916-0500-0479"/> area ia under crops, the average yield being
                    1,600,000 quarters of corn and 1,170,000 quarters of potatoes. Cattle-breeding
                    is very imperfectly developed, the meadows being marshy throughout the lowlands.
                    Hunting and bee-keeping are sources of income in the Polyesie, and fishing gives
                    occupation to about twenty thousand persons. The chief source of income for the
                    inhabitants of the lowlands is the timber trade. Timber is floated down the
                    rivers, and tar, pitch, various products of bark, potash, charcoal, and numerous
                    sorts of timber-ware (wooden dishes, ⅛c.)are manufactured in villages to a great
                    extent; and shipbuilding is carried on along the Dnieper, Pripet, and Niemen.
                    Shipping is also an important source of income, owing to the traffic on the
                    canalsand rivers of the province. In 1877 560 boats and 1120 rafts with 170,000
                    cwts. of cargo left the banks of the Berezina and Pripet; and the traffic on the
                    Dnieper and Niemen was nearly as great. The industrial arts are almost entirely
                    undeveloped. There are, however, several distilleries and tanneries; and
                    woollen-stuffs, candles, tobacco, and sugar are manufactured to a limited
                    extent. Corn is exported from the western districts, but imported to the same
                    amount into the southern parts; the chief export trade is in produce of forest
                    industries. The province is crossed by two important railways, one of which
                    connects Poland with Moscow, ana the other Libau and Vilna with the provinces of
                    Little Russia; the great highway from Warsaw to Moscow crosses the province in
                    the south, and its passage through the Berezina is protected by the first-class
                    fortress of Bobruisk. Minsk is divided into nine districts, of which the
                    capitals are— Minsk (43,500 inhabitants), Bobruisk (26,850), Borisoff (5650),
                    close by the place where Napoleon I. crossed the Berezina on his retreat from
                    Moscow, Igumen (2200), Mozyr (4200), Novogrodek (9000), Pinsk (18,000),
                    Ryechitsa (4300), and Slutsk (17,200). The province is well provided with
                    secondary schools, but primary education, especially in the Polyesie, i⅛in a
                    very backward state.</p>
                <p>The country now occupied by the province of Minsk was, as far as historical
                    records extend, an abode of Slavonians. That portion of it which was occupied by
                    the Krivichi became part of the Polotsk principality and so of “White Russia”;
                    the other portion, occupied by the Dregovichi and Drevlans, became part of the
                    “Black Russia”; whilst the south-western portion of it was occupied by Yatvyags
                    or Lithuanians. During the 12tb, 13th, and 14th centuries it was divided among
                    several principalities, which were incorporated with the great principality of
                    Lithuania, and later were annexed to Poland. Russia took possession of this
                    country in 1793. In 1812 it was invaded by the army of Napoleon I.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Minsk,</hi> the capital of the above province, is situated
                    on the Svisloch, a tributary of the Berezina, at the junction of the Moscow and
                    Warsaw and the Libau and Kharkoff railways, 465 miles by rail west from Moscow.
                    It has 43,500 inhabitants, of whom one-third are Jews of the poorest class; the
                    others are White Russians, Poles, and Tartars (about 700). The manufactures are
                    few and insignificant. Since the introduction of railways the commercial
                    importance of the place, which formerly was slight, has begun to increase.</p>
                <p>Minsk is mentioned in Russian annals in the 11th century under the name of
                    Myen’sk or Menesk. In 1066 and 1096 it was devastated, first by Izyaslav and
                    afterwards by Vladimir. It changed rulers many times until the 13th century,
                    when it became a Lithuanian fief. In the 15th century it became part of Poland,
                    but as late as 1505 it was ravaged by Tartars, and in 1508 by Russians. In the
                    18th century it was taken several times by Swedes and Russians. Russia annexed
                    it in 1793. Napoleon I. took it in 1812.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
