<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0916-0854-0825-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">MORMONS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 16, page 825</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term n="15" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term n="15" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4z02z952">Cannon</term>
                    <term n="15" ref="lcsh1910:b4s756m31">Saints</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1026314">Mormons</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term>
                    <term n="15" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:944037">God</term>
                    <term n="15" ref="fasttopic:1103658">Saints</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="14" ref="fastgeo:1204563">Utah</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1205075">Ohio</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1204724">Missouri</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204305">Vermont</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1205835">Iowa</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1211709">Idaho</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1242804">Scandinavia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204928">California</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n854/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MORMONS</label>, or The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day
                    Saints, are a religious sect founded by Joseph Smith at Manchester, New York, in
                    1830, and for the last thirty-six years settled in Salt Lake City, Territory of
                    Utah, United States. Smith was born 23d December 1805 at Sharon, Windsor county,
                    Vermont, from which place ten years later his parents, a poor, ignorant,
                    thriftless, and not too honest couple, removed to New York, where they settled
                    on a small farm near Palmyra, Wayne county (then Ontario). Four years later, in
                    1809, they removed to Manchester, some 6 miles off; and it was at the latter
                    place when fifteen years old that Joseph began to have <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n855/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0916-0855-0826"/> his alleged visions, in one of which on the night
                    of 21st September 1823 the angel Moroni appeared to him three times, and told
                    him that the Bible of the Western Continent, the supplement to the New
                    Testament, was buried in a certain spot near Manchester. Thither, four years
                    later and after due disciplinary probation, Smith went, and had delivered into
                    his charge by an angel of the Lord a stone box, in which was a volume, 6 inches
                    thick, made of thin gold plates 8 inches by 7, and fastened together by three
                    gold rings. The plates were covered with small writing in the “reformed
                    Egyptian” tongue, and were accompanied by a pair of supernatural spectacles,
                    consisting of two crystals set in a silver bow, and called “Urim and Thummim;”
                    by aid of these the mystic characters could be read. Being himself unable to
                    read or write fluently, Smith employed as amanuensis one Oliver Cowdery, to
                    whom, from behind a curtain, he dictated a translation, which, with the aid of a
                    farmer, Martin Harris, who had more money than wit, was printed and published in
                    1830 under the title of <hi rend="italic">The Book of Mormon,</hi> and
                    accompanied by the sworn statement of Oliver Cowdery, David Whitmer, and Martin
                    Harris that an angel of God had shown them the plates of which the book was a
                    translation. This testimony all three, on renouncing Mormonism some years later,
                    denounced as false; but meanwhile it helped Smith to impose on the credulous,
                    particularly in the absence of the gold plates themselves, which suddenly and
                    mysteriously disappeared. The <hi rend="italic">Book of Mormon,</hi> in which
                    Joseph Smith was declared to be God’s “prophet,” with all power and entitled to
                    all obedience, professes to give the history of America from its first
                    settlement by a colony of refugees from among the crowd dispersed by the
                    confusion of tongues at the Tower of Babel down to the year 5 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> These settlers having in course of time destroyed one
                    another, nothing of importance occurred until 600 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b.c.,</hi> when Lehi, his wife, and four sons, with ten friends, all from
                    Jerusalem, landed on the coast of Chili. All went well until the death of Lehi,
                    when the divine appointment to the leadership of Nephi, the youngest son, roused
                    the resentment of his elder brothers, who were in consequence condemned to have
                    dark skins and to be an idle mischievous race,—hence the North-American Indians.
                    Between the Nephites and the bad Hebrews a fierce war was maintained for
                    centuries, until finally, in spite of divine intervention in the person of the
                    crucified Christ, the Nephites fell away from the true faith, and in 384 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> were nearly annihilated by their dark-skinned foes in
                    a battle at the hill of Cumorah, in Ontario county, New York. Among the handful
                    that escaped were Mormon and his son Moroni, the former of whom collected the
                    sixteen books of records, kept by successive kings and priests, into one volume,
                    which on his death was supplemented by his son with some personal reminiscences
                    and by him buried in the hill of Cumorah,— he being divinely assured that the
                    book would one day be discovered by God’s chosen prophet. This is Smith’s
                    account of the book; but in reality it was written in 1812 as an historical
                    romance by one Solomon Spalding, a crackbrained preacher; and the MS. falling
                    into the hands of an unscrupulous compositor, Sidney Rigdon, was copied by him,
                    and subsequently given to Joseph Smith. Armed with this book and with
                    self-assumed divine authority, the latter soon began to attract followers. On
                    6th April 1830 the first conference of the new sect, called by their neighbours
                    Mormons, but by themselves subsequently Latter-Day Saints of Jesus Christ, was
                    held at Fayette, Seneca county, New York, and in the same year another
                    revelation was received by Smith, proclaiming him “seer, translator, prophet,
                    apostle of Jesus Christ, and elder of the church.” Smith now began to baptize;
                    but, his character, which was none of the best, being too well known in Fayette,
                    he found it convenient to remove with Ids followers, now thirty in number, to
                    Kirtland, Ohio, which was to be the seat of the New Jerusalem. Here he had
                    another revelation, directing the saints to consecrate all their property to God
                    and to start a bank. This being done and Smith appointed president of the bank,
                    the country was soon flooded with worthless notes, which fact, added to other
                    grievances, so enraged the neighbouring Christian settlers that on the night of
                    22d May 1832 a number of them dragged Smith and Rigdon from their beds and
                    tarred and feathered them. One year later, the church was fairly organized, with
                    three presidents, Smith, Rigdon, and Frederick G. Williams, who were styled the
                    first presidency, and entrusted with the keys of the last kingdom. About this
                    time the licentiousness of Smith might have led to the dissolution of the church
                    but for the accession of Brigham Young, a Vermont painter and glazier, thirty
                    years old, who turned up in Kirtland in 1832, and was immediately ordained
                    elder. Young’s indomitable will, persuasive eloquence, executive ability,
                    shrewdness, and zeal soon made their influence felt, and, when a further step
                    was taken in 1835 towards the organization of a hierarchy by the institution of
                    the quorum of the “twelve apostles,” who were sent out as proselytizing
                    missionaries among the “gentiles,” Young was ordained one of the “twelve” and
                    despatched to preach throughout the eastern States. In 1836 a large temple was
                    consecrated in Kirtland, and in the following year Orson Hyde and Heber C.
                    Kimball were sent off as missionaries to England, where, among the labouring
                    masses in Manchester, Liverpool, Birmingham, Leeds, Glasgow, and the mining
                    districts of South Wales they achieved a remarkable success. Early in 1838 the
                    Kirtland bank failed, and Smith and Rigdon fled to Caldwell county, Missouri,
                    where a large body of the saints, after having been driven successively from
                    Jackson and Clay counties, had taken refuge and flourished. Smith’s troubles,
                    however, continued to increase. His gross profligacy had repelled many of his
                    leading supporters and bred internal dissensions, while from the outside the
                    brethren were harassed and threatened by the steadily growing hostility of the
                    native Missourians. To counteract the efforts of his enemies, a secret society
                    was organized in Smith’s favour in October 1838, called the Danites, with the
                    avowed purpose of supporting Smith at all hazards, of upholding the authority of
                    his revelation and decrees as superior to the laws of the land, and of helping
                    him to get possession, first of the State, then of the United States, and
                    ultimately of the world. To such a height did the inner dissensions and the
                    conflicts with the “gentiles” grow that they assumed the proportions of a civil
                    war, and necessitated the calling out of the State militia. Defying the legal
                    officers, Smith fortified the town and armed the saints, but finally had to
                    succumb to superior numbers. Smith and Rigdon were arrested and imprisoned on a
                    charge of treason, murder, and felony, and their followers to the number of
                    15,000 crossed over into Illinois and settled near Commerce, Hancock county.
                    Here they were shortly afterwards rejoined by Smith, who succeeded in escaping
                    from prison, and, having obtained a charter, they founded the city of Nauvoo.
                    Such were the powers granted them by this charter as to render the city
                    practically independent of the State Government, and to give Smith all but
                    unlimited civil power. He organized a military body called the Nauvoo legion, of
                    which he constituted himself commander with the title of lieutenant-general,
                    while he was also president of the church and mayor of the city. On 6th April
                    1841 the foundations of the new temple were laid, and the city continued to grow
                    rapidly in prosperity and size. But Smith’s vices were beginning to bear fruit.
                    Some years previously he had prevailed on several women to cohabit <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n856/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0916-0856-0827"/> with him, and in order to pacify his lawful wife
                    and silence the objections of the saints he had a revelation on 12th July 1843
                    expressly establishing and approving polygamy. The proclamation of the new
                    doctrine excited widespread indignation, which found special expression in the
                    pages of the <hi rend="italic">Expositor,</hi> a newspaper published by an old
                    friend of Smith, one Dr Foster. Smith at once caused the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Expositor</hi> printing-office to be razed and Foster expelled, on which the
                    latter procured a warrant for the arrest of Smith, his brother Hyrum, and
                    sixteen others. Smith resisted; the militia was called out; the Mormons armed
                    themselves; and a civil war seemed imminent, when the governor of the State
                    persuaded Smith to surrender and stand his trial. Accordingly, on 27th June 1844
                    he and Hyrum were imprisoned in Carthage jail; but that same night a mob broke
                    into the prison and shot the two men dead. This shooting was the most fortunate
                    thing that had ever happened to the Mormon cause, investing the murdered
                    president with the halo of martyrdom, and effacing public recollection of his
                    vices in the lustre of a glorious death. Of the confusion that followed Smith’s
                    “taking off’’Brigham Young profited by procuring his own election to the
                    presidency by the council of the “twelve apostles,”—a position for which his
                    splendid executive abilities well fitted him, as subsequent events abundantly
                    proved. The following year witnessed what appeared to be the culmination of
                    their misfortunes. The legislature of Illinois repealed the charter of Nauvoo,
                    and so critical did the situation become that the leaders resolved to emigrate
                    immediately, and preparations were begun for a general exodus westward. Early in
                    1846 a large number of the body met at Council Bluffs, Iowa, and those who had
                    stayed behind soon found cause to regret that they too had not left Nauvoo, as
                    in the September of the same year that city was cannonaded, and the Mormons were
                    driven out. Meanwhile pioneers had been despatched to the Great Salt Lake
                    valley, Utah, and, their report proving favourable, a large body of emigrants
                    was marched with military discipline across the wilderness to the valley, where
                    they immediately proceeded to found Salt Lake City, and where on 24th July 1847
                    they were joined by their chief, Brigham Young. In the May following the main
                    body of the saints set out to rejoin their brethren, and in the autumn of that
                    year reached Salt Lake City. Large tracts of land were at once put under
                    cultivation, a great city sprang up as by magic, and the untiring industry,
                    energy, and zeal of the emigrants turned a barren wilderness into a fertile and
                    blooming garden. An emigration fund was organized, missionaries were sent out,
                    and soon settlers began to pour in from all quarters of the globe, particularly
                    from Great Britain, Sweden and Norway, and in less numbers from Germany,
                    Switzerland, and France. Strangely enough, and the fact deserves emphasis,
                    Ireland has furnished few if any recruits to the cause of Mormonism. In March
                    1849 a convention was held at Salt Lake City, and a State was organized under
                    the name of Deseret, meaning “the land of the honey-bee.” A legislature was also
                    elected, and a constitution framed, which was sent on to Washington. This
                    Congress refused to recognize, and by way of compromise for declining to admit
                    the proposed new State into the Union President Fillmore in 1850 organized the
                    country occupied by the Mormons into the Territory of Utah, with Brigham Young
                    as governor. District judges were also appointed by the Federal Government; but
                    in 1851, a few months after their appointment, they were forced to leave by the
                    aggressive tactics of Young. Such bold defiance of the Federal Government could
                    not be ignored; Brigham was suspended from the governorship, and Colonel Steptoe
                    of the United States army appointed in his stead. The new governor, backed by a
                    battalion of soldiers, arrived in Utah in August 1854; but so strong was the
                    opposition which he met with that he dared not assume office, and was forced to
                    content himself with merely wintering in Salt Lake City, after which he withdrew
                    his troops to California. Nor did the other civil officers appointed by the
                    United States Government at the same time show any bolder front. In February
                    1856 a band of armed Mormons broke into the courtroom of the United States
                    district judge, and forced Judge Drummond to adjourn his court <hi rend="italic"
                    >sine die.</hi> His surrender precipitated the flight of the other civil
                    officers, and with the sole exception of the United States Indian agent they
                    withdrew from Salt Lake City. These facts led President Buchanan to appoint a
                    new governor in the person of Alfred Cumming, the superintendent of Indian
                    affairs on the upper Missouri, who in 1857 went to Utah, accompanied by Judge
                    Eckels of Indiana as chief justice, and by a force of 2500 soldiers. Enraged by
                    this aggressive action, Brigham Young boldly called the saints to arms. In
                    September the United States army reached Utah, but on 5th and 6th October a band
                    of mounted Mormons destroyed a number of its supply trains, and a few days later
                    cut off 800 oxen from its rear and drove them into Salt Lake City. The result
                    was that the United States army, now commanded by Colonel A. S. Johnston, was
                    compelled—it being now mid-November—to go into winter quarters at Black’s Forks,
                    near Fort Bridger. In the same year a party of Mormons and Indians, instigated
                    and led by a Mormon bishop named John D. Lee, attacked a train of 150 non-Mormon
                    emigrants at Mountain Meadows, near Utah, and massacred every soul. Governor
                    Cumming at once declared the Territory in a state of rebellion; but in the
                    spring of 1858, through the inteι vention of Thomas I.. Kane of Pennsylvania,
                    armed with letters of authority from President Buchanan, the Mormons were
                    induced to submit to the Federal authority, and accepted a free offer of pardon
                    made to them by the United States Government as the condition of their
                    submission. Matters being thus settled, the Federal troops encamped on the
                    western shore of Lake Utah, some 40 miles from Salt Lake City, where they
                    remained until withdrawn from the Territory in 1860. On the close of the
                    American Civil War a Federal governor was again appointed, and in 1871 polygamy
                    was declared to be a criminal offence, and Brigham Young was arrested. This
                    action, however, on the part of the United States Government was merely
                    spasmodic, and the Mormons continued to practise polygamy, and to increase in
                    wealth and numbers until 29th August 1877, when Brigham Young died, leaving a
                    fortune of $2,000,000 (£400,000) to 17 wives and 56 children. He was succeeded
                    in office by John Taylor, an Englishman, although the actual leadership fell to
                    George Q. Cannon, “first counsellor” to the president, and one of the ablest men
                    in the sect. The year 1877 was otherwise signalized in Mormon history by the
                    trial, conviction, and execution of John D. Lee for the Mountain Valley massacre
                    of 1857. Of late years the question of Mormonism has largely occupied public
                    attention. In 1873 Mr Frelinghuysen introduced a bill severely censuring
                    polygamy, and declaring that the wives of polygamists could claim relief by
                    action for divorce. In 1874 the committee of the House of Representatives
                    reported a bill which reduced Utah to the position of a province, placing the
                    control of affairs in the hands of Federal officials, and practically abolishing
                    polygamy. In the same year George Q. Cannon was elected a delegate from Utah,
                    and though his election was contested it was confirmed by the House of
                    Representatives. This decision, however, was accompanied by the passing of a
                    resolution by a vote of 127 to 51, appointing a committee of investigation into
                    Delegate Cannon’s alleged polygamy,—he having, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n857/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0916-0857-0828"/> it was asserted, four wives. Later in the same
                    year the Utah Judiciary Bill, attacking the very foundation of Mormonism, passed
                    the House in spite of the eloquent opposition of Cannon. Other steps in the same
                    direction have since been taken, and bills passed, having for their object the
                    extirpation of polygamy, but all without immediate and practical effect. It is,
                    however, a question of time merely; polygamy is doomed. The secession, chiefly
                    because of his opposition to the practice, of Brigham Young’s son, a Christian
                    preacher, and of a large body of other anti-polygamists who claim to be the true
                    Latter-Day Saints, represents not an individual opinion but the deep-rooted
                    conviction of a great party, and the day is not far distant when the Mormons who
                    acknowledge John Taylor as chief prophet must consent to lop off polygamy or
                    cease to exist as a corporate body of the United States. Already there are not
                    wanting signs of approaching dissolution, of which perhaps the most significant
                    is the con-ferenceof the “Reorganized Church of Jesus Christof Latter-Day
                    Saints,” held on 6th April 1883, at Kirtland, Lake county, Ohio. This sect
                    originated in 1851, seven years after the death of Joseph Smith, when several
                    officers of the church met and claimed to have received a revelation from God,
                    directing them to repudiate Brigham Young, as not being the divinely-appointed
                    and legitimate successor of Joseph Smith, and as being the promulgator of such
                    false doctrines as polygamy, Adam-God worship, and the right to shed the blood
                    of apostates. Nothing of special importance occurred, however, until 1860, when
                    Joseph Smith jun., the eldest son of the founder of the faith, became identified
                    with the Reorganized Church as its president. Since then the seceders have
                    prosecuted missionary work throughout the United States, Great Britain, Canada,
                    Scandinavia, Switzerland, Australia, and the Society Islands, until their
                    communicants are said to number over 27,000. Their headquarters are at Plano,
                    Illinois, to which place they removed from Lamoni, Iowa, in 1881. The
                    Reorganized Church holds that the legitimate successor to Joseph Smith was his
                    eldest son, that the allegation that Smith introduced polygamy on the strength
                    of divine revelation was an invention of Brigham Young, that the Utah Church has
                    departed grievously from the faith and practices laid down in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Book of Mormon</hi> and subsequent revelations to Joseph Smith,
                    and that the Reorganized Church is the only true and lawful continuation of, and
                    successor to, the original church, and as such is legally entitled to all that
                    church’s property and rights. And it was to celebrate the decision of the United
                    States Court of Ohio confirming this last claim, and vesting in them the right
                    to the temple consecrated in Kirtland, Ohio, in 1836, and for nearly forty years
                    disused owing to litigation, that the Reorganized Church met in that temple on
                    the 6th of April 1883.</p>
                <p>Returning to the main body, it may be added that the population of Utah is
                    147,000, of whom 123,000 are Mormons; but as the saints are scattered over the
                    globe it is difficult to arrive at a just estimate of their complete numerical
                    strength. In Idaho, Arizona, Washington, Colorado, Montana, and Wyoming they
                    have of late years made great progress, and their number in the United States
                    outside of Utah cannot fall much under 27,000. In Europe they have also many
                    adherents, and a careful study, based on recent official statistics, would place
                    their entire number at 213,000.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Government.—</hi> At the head of the body is a president, who
                    possesses supreme authority, supported by two counsellors. These three are
                    supposed to be the successors of Peter, James, and John, and constitute what is
                    known as the “first presidency.” Then comes the “patriarch,” whose chief duty is
                    to bless and lay on hands, and after him the “twelve apostles,” forming a
                    travelling high council, and receiving a salary of $1500 a year each. Of these
                    the president is <hi rend="italic">ex officio</hi> one, and endowed with
                    authority equal to the other eleven. Their duties are important. They ordain all
                    other officers, elders, priests, teachers, and deacons, lead all religious
                    meetings, and administer the rites of baptism and sacrament. Fourth come the
                    seven presidents of the “seventies,” each body comprising seventy elders; there
                    are eighty seventies in Utah, each of which has seven presidents, and every
                    seven one president. These seventies make annual reports, and are the
                    missionaries and propagandists of the body. Fifth come the “high priests,” whose
                    chief duty is to officiate in all the offices of the church in the absence of
                    any higher authorities. After them comes the presiding bishop, who superintends
                    the collection of tithes, which amount to $1,100,000 annually. The church is
                    made up of 23 stakes, each having a president, and is divided into wards, which
                    are subdivided into districts, each of which has a certain number of teachers, a
                    meeting-house, Sunday school, day school, and dramatic, debating, and literary
                    societies.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Doctrine. —</hi> The Mormons no longer claim to be a Christian
                    sect, any more than do the Mohammedans. A system of polytheism has been grafted
                    on the original creed, according to which there are grades among the gods, the
                    place of Supreme Ruler of all being taken by the primeval Adam of Genesis, who
                    is the deity highest in spiritual rank, while Christ, Mohammed, Joseph Smith,
                    and Brigham Young also partake of divinity. The business of these deities is the
                    propagation of souls to people bodies begotten on earth, and the sexual relation
                    permeates every portion of the creed as thoroughly as it did that of ancient
                    India or Egypt. The saints on leaving this world are deified, and their glory is
                    in proportion to the number of their wives and children,—hence, the necessity
                    and justification of polygamy, and the practice of having many wives sealed to
                    one saint. Their distinguishing points of faith are :—religiously, a belief in a
                    continual divine revelation through the inspired medium of the prophet at the
                    head of the church; morally, polygamy, though this is expressly condemned in the
                    <hi rend="italic">Book of Mormon,</hi> and was grafted on the original faith by
                    Smith; and, socially, a complete hierarchical organization. They believe in the
                    Bible as supplemented by the <hi rend="italic">Book of Mormon</hi> and the <hi
                    rend="italic">Book of Doctrine;</hi> in the gift of prophecy, miracles, and
                    casting out devils; in the imminent approach of the end of the world; in their
                    own identity with the apocalyptic saints who shall reign with Christ in a
                    temporal kingdom, either in Missouri or Utah; in the literal resurrection of the
                    body; in absolute liberty of private judgment in religious matters; and in the
                    salvation of a man only if he believes in Christ’s atonement, repents, is
                    baptized by immersion by a Christ-appointed apostle, and receives the laying on
                    of hands for the gift of the Holy Ghost by duly authorized apostles. Among their
                    minor rules as laid down in <hi rend="italic">A Word of Wisdom,</hi> supposed to
                    have been revealed to Joseph Smith, 27th February 1833, are these
                    recommendations :—that it is not good to drink wine or strong drink, except at
                    the Lord’s Supper (and even then it should be home-made grape-wine), or to use
                    hot drinks or tobacco,—the former being meant for the washing of the body, and
                    the latter for the healing of bruises and sick cattle; man’s proper food is
                    herbs and fruit, that for beasts and fowls, grain; and, except in winter and in
                    case of famine and severe cold, flesh should not be eaten by man. Infant baptism
                    is also condemned, but the children of the saints who have reached their eighth
                    year should be baptized. The deceased, also, can be baptized by proxy, and in
                    this way Washington, Franklin, and others have been vicariously baptized into
                    the church.</p>
                <p>See <hi rend="italic">B∞k of Mormon</hi> (1879); <hi rend="italic">Book of
                    Doctrine and Covenants</hi> (1876); John Hyde jun., <hi rend="italic">Mormonism,
                    its Leaders and Designs</hi> (1857); B. G. Ferris, <hi rend="italic">Utah and
                    the Mormons</hi> (1854); N. W. Green, <hi rend="italic">Mormonism</hi> (1870);
                    T. B. H. Stenhouse, <hi rend="italic">Rocky Mountain Saints</hi> (1873); H.
                    Mayhew, <hi rend="italic">The Mormons</hi>; Elder John Jaques, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Catechism for Children</hi> (1877); John W. Gunnison, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Mormons, or Latter-Day Saints</hi> (1852); Hepworth Dixon, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Spiritual Wives</hi> (1868); J. H. Beadle, <hi rend="italic">Life in Utah</hi>
                    (1870). (J. FR.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
