<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0916-0744-0717-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">MONACO</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 16, page 717</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:848246">Casinos</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1079619">Protectionism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:948571">Growth</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="9" ref="fastgeo:1215184">Monaco</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4pv6bb1s">Tolls</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c72h">Gauls</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n744/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MONACO</label> (French <hi rend="italic">Moneguè),</hi> the
                    smallest of the sovereign principalities of Europe, with an area of 8 <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi> 34 square miles, a population (1878) of 7049, and an
                    army of 72 men, is situated on the coast of the Mediterranean, 9 miles east of
                    Nice, and bounded on all sides by the French department of the Maritime Alps.
                    Previous to 1861, when the communes of Mentone (Menton) and Roccabruna
                    (Roquebrun) were sold to France for 4,000,000 francs, the area was about a third
                    larger; but the population, which with those portions again included would now
                    be 15,000, was only about 8000. Monaco has long had the reputation of being one
                    of the most beautiful and sheltered spots on all the Franco-Italian coast: <hi
                    rend="italic">non Corus in ilium Jus</hi><hi rend="italic">habet aut
                    Zephyrus;</hi><hi rend="italic">solus</hi><hi rend="italic">sua</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">littora</hi><hi rend="italic">turbat Circius,</hi> said Lucan; and
                    a luxuriant growth of aloes and prickly pears (introduced in 1537), palm-trees,
                    eucalyptus, lemontrees, and geraniums gives a warmer colour to the scene than
                    Lucan can have known. The town occupies the level summit of a rocky headland,
                    rising about 195 feet from the shore, and still surrounded with ramparts. Though
                    largely modernized, the palace is a fine specimen of Renaissance architecture;
                    the new “cathedral” (French Renaissance style), the new church of St Charles,
                    and the museum may also be mentioned. Behind the rock, between Mont Tête de
                    Chien and Mont de la Justice, the high grounds rise towards Turbie, the village
                    on the hill which takes its name from the <hi rend="italic">tropaea</hi> with
                    which Augustus marked the boundary between Gaul and Italy. On the eastern side
                    lies the little port or bay of Monaco; along the lower ground, at the head of
                    the bay stretches the village of Condamine with orange-gardens, manufactures of
                    perfumes and liqueurs, and the chapel of Ste Dévote, the patron saint of Monaco;
                    farther to the east, on the rocky slopes of the Spélugues (Speluncae) are
                    grouped the various buildings of the Casino of Monte Carlo and the numerous
                    villas and hotels which it has called into existence. Previous to 1828 the
                    Spélugues were mere barren rocks; but after they were traversed by the new road
                    to Mentone, Count Rey caused them to be covered with soil by Italian convicts;
                    and since 1858, when the first stone of the Casino was laid, the process of
                    artificial embellishment has been carried <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n745/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0916-0745-0718"/> out on the most magnificent scale. The gaming
                    establishment is now in the hands of a joint-stock company with a capital of
                    15,000,000 francs. None of the inhabitants of Monaco have access to the tables;
                    and their interest in the maintenance of the <hi rend="italic">status quo</hi>
                    is secured by their complete exemption from taxation, and the large prices paid
                    for their lands. Gambling-tables were set up at Monaco in 1856; but it was not
                    till 1860, when Μ. Blanc, expelled from Homburg, took possession of the place,
                    that Monte Carlo began to be famous.</p>
                <p>A temple of Heracles Monoecus was built on the Monaco headland at a very early
                    date, probably by the Greeks of Massilia. Monoeci Portus or Portus Herculis is
                    frequently mentioned by the later Latin writers. From the 10th century the place
                    was associated with the Grimaldi, a powerful Genoese family who held high
                    offices under the republic and the emperors; but not till a much later date did
                    it become their permanent possession and residence. In the beginning of the 14th
                    century it was notorious for its piracies. Charles I. (a man of considerable
                    mark, who, after doing great service by sea and land to Philip of Valois in his
                    English wars, was severely wounded at Crecy) purchased Mentone and Roccabruna,
                    and bought up the claims of the Spinola to Monaco. The princes of Monaco
                    continued true to France till 1524, when Augustin Grimaldi threw in his lot with
                    Charles V. Honoré I., Augustin’s successor, was made marquis of Campagna and
                    count of Canosa, and people as well as rulers were accorded various important
                    privileges. The right to exact toll from vessels passing the port continued to
                    be exercised till the close of the 18th century. Honoré II., who renewed the
                    alliance with France in 1641, was compensated for the loss of Canosa, &amp;c.,
                    with the duchy and peerage of Valentinois and various lesser lordships; and duke
                    of Valentinois long continued to be the title of the heir-apparent of the
                    principality. The National Convention annexed the principality to France in
                    1793; restored to the Goyon Grimaldis by the Treaty of Paris in 1814, it was
                    placed by that of Vienna under the protection of Sardinia. King Albert of
                    Sardinia took the opportunity of disturbances that occurred in 1848 to annex
                    Mentone and Roccabruna; but this high-handed proceeding was condemned by the
                    protocol of 1856, and Charles III. (born 1818) entered upon his full rights.
                    With the transference of Nice to France in 1860 the principality passed again
                    under French protection.</p>
                <p>See Charles de Venasques, <hi rend="italic">Genealogica</hi><hi rend="italic">et
                    historica</hi><hi rend="italic">Grimaldiee</hi><hi rend="italic">gentis</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">arl·or</hi> (really the work of Honoré II.).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
