<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0916-0878-0847-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MORSE, Samuel Finley Breese (9th edition, volume 16,
                    page 847)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:891345">Designers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:891253">Design</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1128733">Sparks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1146190">Telegraphers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1146129">Telegraph</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dn3zz3k">Design</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47941253">Telegraphers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w24w">Telegraph</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20h6f">Inventors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210278">Belgium</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204537">Sweden</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208963">Turkey</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n878/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MORSE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Samuel Finley Breese</hi></label>
                    (1791-1872), artist and inventor, was born at the foot of Breed’s Hill,
                    Charlestown, Massachusetts, on 27th April 1791. His father was the Rev. Jedediah
                    Morse, D.D., the author of Morse’s <hi rend="italic">Geography.</hi> At the age
                    of fourteen Samuel Morse entered Yale College; under the instruction of
                    Professors Day and Silliman he received the first impulse towards those
                    electrical studies with which his name is mainly identified. In 1811 Morse,
                    whose tastes during his early years led him more strongly towards art than
                    towards science, became the pupil of Washington Allston, then the greatest of
                    American artists, and accompanied his master to England, where he remained four
                    years. His success at this period was considerable; but on his return to America
                    in 1815 he failed to obtain commissions for historical paintings, and after
                    working on portraits for two years at Charleston, S.C., he removed first to
                    Washington and afterwards to Albany, finally settling in New York. In 1825 he
                    laid the foundations of the National Academy of Design, and was elected its
                    first president, an office which he filled until 1845. The year 1827 marks the
                    revival of Morse’s interest in electricity. It was at that time that he learned
                    from Professor J. F. Dana of Columbia College the elementary facts of
                    electromagnetism. As yet, however, he was devoted to his art, and in 1829 he
                    again went to Europe to study the old masters.</p>
                <p>The year of his return, 1832, may be said to close the period of his artistic,
                    and to open that of his scientific life. On board the packet-ship “Sully,” which
                    sailed from Havre 1st October 1832, while discussing one day with his
                    fellow-passengers the properties of the electromagnet, he was led to remark: “If
                    the presence of electricity can be made visible in any part of the circuit, I
                    see no reason why intelligence may not be transmitted by electricity.” It was
                    not a novel proposition, but the process of formulating it started in his mind a
                    train of new and momentous ideas. The current of electricity, he knew, would
                    pass instantaneously any distance along a wire; and if it were interrupted a
                    spark would appear. It now occurred to him that the spark might represent a part
                    of speech,, either a letter or a number; the absence of the spark, another part;
                    and the duration of its absence, or of the spark itself, a third, so that an
                    alphabet might be easily formed, and words indicated. In a few days he had
                    completed rough drafts of the necessary apparatus, which he displayed to his
                        fellow-passengers.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                            ><p>Five years later the captain of the ship identified under oath
                            Morse’s completed instrument with that which Morse had explained, ou
                            board the “Sully” in 1832.</p></note> During the twelve years that
                    followed Morse was engaged in a painful struggle to perfect his invention and
                    secure for it a proper presentation to the public. The refusal of the Government
                    to commission him to paint one of the great historical pictures in the rotunda
                    of the Capitol seemed to destroy all his old artistic ambition. In poverty he
                    pursued his new enterprise, making his own models, moulds, and castings, denying
                    himself the common necessaries of life and encountering embarrassments and
                    delays of the most disheartening kind. It was not until 1836 that he completed
                    any apparatus-that would work, his original idea having been supplemented by his
                    discovery in 1835 of the “relay,” by meansof which the electric current might be
                    reinforced or renewed where it became weak through distance from its source.
                    Finally, on 2d September 1837, the instrument was exhibited to a few friends at
                    his room in the university building, New York, where a circuit of 1700 feet of
                    copper wire had been set up, with such satisfactory results as to awaken the
                    practical interest of the Messrs Vail, iron and brass workers in New Jersey, who
                    thenceforth became associated with Morse in his undertaking. Morse’s petition
                    for a patent was dated 28th September 1837, and was soon followed by a petition
                    to Congress for an appropriation to defray the expense of subjecting the
                    telegraph to actual experiment over a length sufficient to establish its
                    feasibility and demonstrate its value. The committee on commerce, to whom the
                    petition was referred, reported, favourably. Congress, however, adjourned
                    without making the appropriation, and meanwhile Morse sailed for Europe to take
                    out patents there. The trip was not a success. In England his application was
                    refused, on the alleged, ground that his invention had been already published -
                    and, while he obtained a patent in France, it was subsequently appropriated by
                    the French Government without compensation to himself. His negotiations also
                    with Russia-proved futile, and after a year’s absence he returned to New York.
                    On 23d February 1843 Congress passed the long-delayed appropriation, steps were
                    at once taken to construct a telegraph from Baltimore to Washington, and on the
                    24th of May 1844 it was used for the first time. Morse’s patents were already
                    secured to him and his associates, and companies were soon formed for the
                    erection of telegraph lines all over the United States. In the year 1847 Morse
                    was compelled to defend his invention in the courts, and successfully vindicated
                    his claim to be called the original inventor of the electromagnetic recording
                    telegraph. Thenceforward Morse’s life was spent in witnessing the growth of his
                    enterprise and in gathering the honours· which an appreciative public bestowed
                    upon him. As years went by he received from the various foreign Governments
                    their highest distinctions, while in 1858 the representatives of Austria,
                    Belgium, France, the Netherlands, Piedmont, Russia, the Holy See, Sweden,
                    Tuscany, and Turkey appropriated the sum of 400,000 francs in recognition of the
                    use of his instruments in those countries. In the preparations for laying the
                    first Atlantic cable he took an active part, though the attempt of 1857, in
                    which he personally engaged, was not successful. He died 2d April <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n879/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0916-0879-0848"/> 1872, at New York, where his statue in bronze
                    now stands in the Central Park. His instrument and alphabet are now used on 95
                    per cent, of the telegraph wires of the world. (s. i. p.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
