<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0916-0011-0002-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MENANDER (9th edition, volume 16, page 2)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x63b58d">Kindness</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vb0p">Caesars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m03z504">Primers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:820856">Attics</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1149096">Thais</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1429783">Andrias</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:815177">Art</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n11/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MENANDER</label>, the most famous Greek poet of the New
                    Comedy, which prevailed from about the death of Alexander the Great (323 <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">b.c.)</hi> to 250. He was born at Athens in 342, and died,
                    it was said, by drowning in the harbour of that city (Piraeus) in 291. His
                    social tastes induced him to write plays rather for the upper classes, and to
                    raise comedy to a gentility which it had hardly possessed in the hands of the
                    preceding comic poets. He was the associate, if not the pupil, of Theophrastus,
                    who himself had been a disciple of Plato and Aristotle, and he was the intimate
                    friend and admirer of Epicurus; but he also enjoyed the more distinguished
                    patronage of Demetrius Phalereus (who was likewise a pupil of Theophrastus), and
                    of Ptolemy the son of Lagus.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p>In allusion to this Pliny writes (A <hi
                                rend="superscript"> r</hi>. <hi rend="italic">II.,</hi> vii. 30, §
                            111), “Magnum et Menandro in comico socco testimonium regum Aegypti et
                            Macedoniae contigit classe et per legatos petito; majus ex ipso, regiae
                            fortunae praelata litterarum conscientia.” This seems to say that
                            Menander had been invited to the courts of Alexander and Ptolemy, as
                            Euripides had been to that of Archelaus, king .of Macedonia, but had
                            preferred to write comedies for the Attic stage.</p></note> His
                    principal rival in the art was Philemon, who appears to have been more popular
                    with the multitude, and for that reason probably more successful. It is said
                    that out of a hundred comedies Menander gained the prize with but eight. All the
                    extant plays of Terence, with the exception of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Phormio,</hi> are avowedly taken from Menander; but some of them appear to
                    have been adaptations and combinations of more than one plot, although Terence
                    himself says in the prologue to the <hi rend="italic">Adelphi</hi> (11) that he
                    copied the Greek model closely, “verbum de verbo expressum extulit.” Julius
                    Caesar called Terence <hi rend="italic">dimidiatus</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Menander,</hi> as if two halves of different plays had been fitted into
                        one.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Thus the <hi
                                rend="italic">Andria, Heautontimorumenos,</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                                >Hecyra</hi> are described severally in the <hi rend="italic"
                                >tituli</hi> prefixed as <hi rend="italic">Greeca</hi> or <hi
                                rend="italic">tota Greeca Menandru.</hi> The <hi rend="italic"
                                >Eunuch</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Timor umenos</hi> are each based
                            on two plays of Menander, and the <hi rend="italic">Adelphi</hi> was
                            compiled partly from Menander and partly from Diphilus.</p></note></p>
                <p>The Attic New Comedy, says Dr Wagner,<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Introduction to Terence,</hi> p. 6
                            (Bell, 1869).</p></note> “may be designated as essentially domestic,”
                        <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> as opposed to that free discussion of the
                    politics of the day which gave to the Old Comedy the place which is held by the
                    “leading articles” of a modern newspaper. “The stock characters were such as the
                    stern or weak father, the son whose follies are seconded by a slave or a hungry
                    parasite, the pettifogger, active in stirring up law suits, and the gasconading
                    soldier of fortune.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                            ><p>Professor Jebb, <hi rend="italic">Primer of Greek Literature,</hi>
                            p. 101.</p></note> These and cognate subjects, which formed the
                    stock-in-trade of Menander’s plays, are summed up in two well-known lines of
                    Ovid—</p>
                <p>“Dum.fallax servus, durus pater, improba lena Vivet, dum meretrix blanda,
                    Menandros erit.”</p>
                <p>It is a good remark of Dr Wagner’s<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Ut sup.,</hi> p. 7.</p></note> that
                    the last-mentioned of these, the <hi rend="italic">meretrix blanda</hi> (which
                    probably refers especially to the <hi rend="italic">Thais),</hi> “holds the most
                    important and conspicuous part in the New Attic Comedy, while married ladies are
                    continually represented as the plague and bore of their husbands’ lives.”
                    Intrigues with these, generally through the medium of a clever confidential
                    slave, are for the most part the very point or pivot on which the plot
                    turns.</p>
                <p>The more literary Romans greatly admired Menander as a poet. Pliny (A <hi
                        rend="superscript"> r</hi>. <hi rend="italic">H.,</hi> xxx. 1, § 7) speaks
                    of him as “Menander litterarum subtilitati sine aemulo genitus.” Propertius,
                    contemplating a visit to Athens,<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">El.,</hi> iv. 21 27.</p></note>
                    anticipates the pleasure of reading Menander in his native city—</p>
                <p>“Persequar aut studium linguae, Demosthenis arma, Libaboque tuos, scite Menandre,
                    sales.”</p>
                <p>He elsewhere speaks of him as “mundus Menander,” neat, terse, and urbane; and his
                    skill in depicting the character of a fascinating Thais is alluded to here and
                    in ii. 6, 3 :—</p>
                <p>“Turba Menandreae fuerat nec Thaidos olim Tanta, in qua populus lusit
                    Erichthonius.”</p>
                <p>Of this comedy, the <hi rend="italic">Thais,</hi> Professor Mahaffy remarks<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Hist.
                                Class. Gr. Lit.</hi>, i. p. 488.</p></note> that perhaps it was the
                    most brilliant of Menander’s plays, “the manners and characters of the personage
                    being painted with thorough experience as well as genius.” Nevertheless, only
                    five verses of this play have been preserved to us, one of which is that quoted
                    by St Paul (1 Cor. xv. 33), “Evil communications corrupt good manners.” The same
                    critic, in praising Menander’s style as the purest model of the New Attic,
                    observes that a remarkable feature of the New Comedy was “its utter avoidance of
                    rhetoric” (p. 489). The influence which this art had on Euripides is well known.
                    Sophocles was not wholly exempt from a kind of rhetorical pedantry, and the
                    speeches in Thucydides are so many exercises of the author in that art. But, as
                    rhetoric pertained essentially to public life, it was likely to have a much less
                    scope in scenes borrowed almost solely from social and domestic experiences.</p>
                <p>Menander, however, did not neglect the other branch of a liberal Attic
                    education,—philosophy. A follower and a friend of Epicurus, whose <hi
                        rend="italic">summum bonum</hi> was the greatest amount of enjoyment to be
                    got out of life, he carried out in practice what he advocated by precept; for he
                    was essentially the well-to-do gentleman,<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p>Pliny calls Menander “diligentissimus luxuriae
                            interpres,” Λ <hi rend="superscript"> τ</hi>. <hi rend="italic">H.,</hi>
                            xxxvi. 5.</p></note> and moved in the upper circles of Athenian society.
                    “The philosophers of the day” <hi rend="italic">(i.e.,</hi> the schools and
                    universities in our modern systems of teaching) “were still,” says Professor
                        Mahaffy,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi
                                rend="italic">Hist. Class. Gr. Lit.,</hi> i. p. 480.</p></note>
                    viz., even during the period of the New Comedy, “the constant butt of the
                    dramatists.” He adds that, “what is still stranger, political attacks on living
                    personages, not excepting Alexander the Great, were freely and boldly made.”</p>
                <p>On the whole, our estimate of the spirit and object of Menander must be formed
                    rather from his imitator and copyist Terence than from the fragments which
                    remain, about 2400 verses in all, as collected by Meineke in his <hi
                        rend="italic">Fragmenta Comicorum</hi><hi rend="italic">Graecorum.</hi> For,
                    as Professor Mahaffy well observes,<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p>Wd,, p. 480.</p></note> the extracts made by Àthenaeus,
                    our principal authority, have reference chiefly to “the archaeology of cooks and
                    cookery,” while Stobaeus was a collector of <hi rend="italic">γvωμaι</hi> or
                    wise maxims,—“a most unfortunate and worthless kind of citation.” It follows
                    that no sound conclusions as to dramatic genius, or of the knowledge of human
                    nature, can be drawn from detached verses preserved without the least reference
                    to these particular points. The extraordinary popularity of Menander must have
                    been due to literary merit, if not to great originality. Mr Mahaffy observes on
                        this<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi
                                rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> p. 487.</p></note> that “there is so much
                    of a calm gentlemanly morality about his fragments, he is so excellent a teacher
                    of the ordinary world-wisdom—resignation, good temper, moderation,
                    friendliness—that we can well understand this popularity. Copies of his plays
                    continued long in existence, and were certainly known to Suidas and Eustathius
                    as late as the 11th and 12th centuries, if they did not survive to a yet later
                        period.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi
                                rend="italic">Ibid:,'γ.</hi> 490.</p></note></p>
                <p>In respect of language, Menander occupies the same position in poetry which his
                    contemporary Demosthenes does in prose. In both the New Attic is elaborated with
                    great finish, and with much greater grammatical precision than we find in
                    writers of the Old Attic, such as Sophocles and Thucydides. A considerable
                    addition to the vocabulary of every-day life had now been made, as was indeed
                    inevitable from the versatile character of the language and the genius of the
                    people who used it. Many new verb-forms, especially the perfect active,<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>A curious example is <hi
                                rend="italic">a∙κtκriyκaσι,</hi> the transitive perfect of <hi
                                rend="italic">h-κoκτttvfiv.</hi> Similarly we have the unusual forms
                                <hi rend="italic">κiχp∙ηκa</hi> (frag. 559), <hi rend="italic"
                                >tyiφ∙ηκa</hi> (727), <hi rend="italic">συyκiχυκa</hi>
                        (810).</p></note> now occur, and indeed form a characteristic innovation of
                    the style of Plato. The earlier prose was in its general vocabulary to a
                    considerable extent poetical, and such a concurrence of short syllables as in
                    the Platonic <hi rend="italic">aιrol&gt;eδoκιμaκ0τes</hi><pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n12/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0916-0012-0003"/><hi rend="italic">(ά τοδοκιμάζΐΐν)</hi> is
                    ill-suited even to choral metre. The Old Comedy was worked by men of real
                    genius, who “were indeed giants, while the men of Menander’s day only showed how
                    strong and thorough was the culture which in art and literature outlived the
                    decadence of the nation.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                            ><p>Mahaffy, <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> p. 490.</p></note></p>
                <p>In all, we have, as collected by Meineke, 1045 fragments of Menander, of which
                    515 can be referred to known plays, the titles of those quoted from amounting to
                    ninety, and including the Terentian <hi rend="italic">Andria,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Adelphi,</hi><hi rend="italic">Eunuchus,
                        Heautontimorumenos.</hi> These fragments contain about 1650 verses or parts
                    of verses, not including a considerable number of words quoted expressly as from
                    Menander by the old lexicographers. Besides all these there are not fewer than
                    758 xnonostich verses separately preserved in MSS., though some of these are met
                    with in the other and longer fragments. Many of the fragments are obscure, some
                    corrupt; and they have been a fertile field for critical acumen from the time of
                    Bentley. Not unfrequently we come upon the shrewd or original remark of an
                    observer. Thus (frag. 7) “A poor man has no relations, for no one acknowledges
                    him, lest he should beg.” Frag. 145, “Everything that takes place is brought
                    about by law, necessity, or fashion.” 237, “The gods do not save men through any
                    human means (prayer or sacrifices); if they did, the human would have more power
                    than the divine.” 275, “Poverty is the most easily cured of all evils; any
                    friend can do it by merely putting his hand in his pocket.” 397, ’ ‘ A poor man
                    who lives in a large town makes himself more wretched than he need; for he
                    cannot help comparing with his own the luxurious lives of the rich.” 435, “No
                    man realizes the extent of a sin when he commits it; it is afterwards that he
                    sees it.” 460, “A man is convinced not so much by what is said as by the manner
                    of saying it.” 474, “There is one thing only that hides vulgarity, villainy, and
                    every other fault,—wealth. Everything but that is carped at and criticized.”
                    517, “People who have no merit of their own generally boast of their birth and
                    their ancestors. But every living man has ancestors, or he would not be a living
                    man.” 578, “Wealth acts on a man as wind does on a ship,—it often forces him out
                    of his proper course.” 663, “Many a young lady says a great deal in her own
                    favour by saying nothing at all.” 688, “A man who abuses his own father is
                    practising blasphemy against the gods.” In fact, Menander is characteristically
                    a sententious writer, like Euripides, with whom in the general style of his
                    writings, though not, of course, in his somewhat loose and irregular
                    versification, he is sometimes compared. (F. A. P. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
