<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0916-0047-0038-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MERIONETH (9th edition, volume 16, page 38)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100524">Roses</term>
                    <term ref="fast:829528">Beds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:829474">Bedding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1163841">Valleys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:990901">Lakes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20h7x">Valleys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k931f29">Ruins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z892m1t">Celtic</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4833n637">Rose</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n29p83w">Prices</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n47/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MERIONETH</label> (Welsh <hi rend="italic">Meirionydd'),</hi>
                    a maritime county of North Wales, is bounded N. by Carnarvon and Denbigh, S.E.
                    by Denbigh and Montgomery, and W. by Cardigan Bay. It is triangular in shape,
                    its greatest length northeast to south-west being 45 miles, and its greatest
                    breadth north-west to south-east about 30miles. The area is 385,291 acres, or
                    about 600 square miles. Next to Carnarvon, Merioneth is the most mountainous
                    county in Wales. If the scenery is less bold and striking than that of
                    Carnarvon, it excels it in richness, variety, and picturesque beauty. Its lofty
                    mountains are interpenetrated by dark deep dells or smiling vales. The outlines
                    of its rugged crags are softened and adorned by rich foliage. The sea views are
                    frequently fine, and rivers, lakes, and waterfalls add a romantic charm to the
                    valleys. The highest summits in the county are the picturesque Cader Idris
                    (which divides into three peaks,—one, Pen-y-Gadair, having an altitude of 2914
                    feet), Aran Fawddwy (2955), Arenig-fawr (2818), Moel-wyn (2566), Rhobell-fawr
                    (2360). The finest valleys are those of Dyfi, Dysyni, Talyllyn, Mawddach, and
                    Festiniog. The river Dyfrdwy or Dee rises 10 miles north-west of Bala, and,
                    after passing through Bala Lake, flows northeast by Corwen to Denbighshire. The
                    Dyfi rises in a small lake near Aran Fawddwy, and expands into an estuary of
                    Cardigan Bay. The Mawddach or Maw, from the north of Aran Fawddwy, has a course
                    of 12 miles southwest, during which it is joined by several other streams. The
                    Dwyryd and other-streams unite in forming the estuary of Traeth Bach. The finest
                    waterfalls are the <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n48/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0916-0048-0039"/> Rhaiadr-y-Glyn near Corwen, Rhaiadr Du, and
                    Pistyll Cain, the latter 150 feet high. The lakes are very numerous, but small,
                    the largest being Bala Lake, or Pim-blemere (in Welsh, Llyn Tegid, fair lake), 4
                    miles long by 1 broad, and Llyn Mwyngil (lake in a sweet nook) in the vale of
                    Talyllyn. Both are much frequented by anglers. On account of frequent
                    indentations the coast-line is about 100 miles long. Sandy beaches intervene
                    between the rocky shores. Frequent shoals and sandbanks render navigation very
                    dangerous. There are only two harbours of importance, Barmouth and
                    Aberdovey.</p>
                <p>A mountain tract of the county 15 miles from north to south by 10 from east to
                    west, stretching from the coast inland, is of the Cambrian age, composed of
                    grits, quartzose, and slates, and comprising the Merionethshire anticlinal. This
                    tract is enclosed on the north, east, and south by the Menevian, Lingula,
                    Tremadoc, and Arenig beds, which are pierced by numerous dykes and intrusive
                    masses, mostly greenstone. Rhobell-fawr is one of the greatest igneous masses in
                    the whole area of the Lingula beds. The Arenig beds are interstratified with and
                    overlaid by accumulations of volcanic ashes, felspathic traps, or lava flows,
                    which form the rugged heights of Cader Idris, the Arans, the Arenigs, Manod, and
                    Moel-wyn; and these are in turn overlaid by the Llandeilo and Bala beds, the
                    latter including the Bala limestone. Extensive slate quarries are worked near
                    Festiniog, mostly underground, in strata of the Llandeilo age, giving employment
                    to about 4000 men. Gold, lead, copper, and manganese have been obtained in
                    various places.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Climate and Agriculture.—</hi> The climate varies much with the
                    elevation, in some places being bleak and cold, and in others remarkably equable
                    and genial. At Aberdovey it is proverbially mild, and the myrtle grows in the
                    open air. All attempts to introduce fruits have proved abortive in most parts of
                    the county. The soil is generally thin and poor, with fertile tracts in the
                    valleys. A great portion of the moss has been reclaimed within late years.</p>
                <p>According to the agricultural returns for 1882, there were 154,406 acres, or
                    considerably less than half the total area, under cultivation. Of this as much
                    as 119,133 acres were permanent pasture, and 13,755 under rotation grasses. Of
                    the 17,312 acres under corn crops, 11,232 were under oats and 4807 under barley.
                    Potatoes occupied 2392 acres, and turnips only 1496 acres. The area under woods
                    extended to 15,049 acres.</p>
                <p>The total number of horses in 1882 was 6088. A breed of ponies is peculiar to
                    this county and Montgomeryshire. The rearing of horned cattle and dairy-farming
                    are largely carried on, but the number of cattle (37,643) is considerably under
                    the average of Wales generally. On the other hand the number of sheep in 1882
                    was 400,553, a larger number than in any other county of Wales, and much beyond
                    the general average in the principality. They are a small hardy breed, which
                    grow heavy fleeces. Goats frequent the loftier crags.</p>
                <p>According to the latest return the number of proprietors was 1695, possessing
                    303,374 acres, with a gross annual value of £183,253. Of the owners 1044, or 62
                    percent., possessed less than 1 acre, the average extent of the properties being
                    189 acres, and the average value per acre a little over 12s. There were ten
                    proprietors who possessed over 5000 acres, viz., Sir w. W. Wynn, 20,295; R. J.
                    I.. Price, 17,718; T. P. Lloyd, 16,975; Mrs Kirkby, 13,410; Hon. C. H. Wynn,
                    10,504; A. J. G. Corbet, 9347; Sir E. Buckley, 8738; W. E. Oakeley, 6018; W. O.
                    Gore, 5497; and R. Μ. Rickards, 5701.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Manufactures.—</hi> Woollen goods are manufactured in various
                    places, especially at Dolgelly. They are principally coarse druggets,
                    Kerseymeres, and flannels. The knitting of stockings was a great industry at the
                    close of last century, the value of the sales at Bala being estimated at from
                    £17,000 to £19,000 annually.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Railways.—</hi> The Cambrian Railway skirts the coast from
                    Portmadoc to Aberdovey. At Barmouth Junction a branch of the same crosses to
                    Dolgelly, where it is joined by a branch of the Great Western Railway. Another
                    branch of the Great Western unites Bala and Festiniog, and the latter place has
                    railway connexion both with Llandudno Junction and with Portmadoc.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Administration and Population.—</hi> Merionethshire comprises
                    five hundreds and thirty-three civil parishes. It has one court of quarter
                    sessions, and the number of petty sessional divisions is six. Ecclesiastically
                    it is partly in the diocese of Bangor, partly in that of St Asaph. The county
                    returns one member to parliament. There is no municipal or parliamentary
                    borough. The towns returned in 1881 as urban sanitary districts are Bala (1653),
                    Barmouth (1512), Dolgelly (2457), Festiniog (11,272), and Towyn (3363). Since
                    1801 the population has nearly doubled. From 29,506 in that year it had
                    increased in 1851 to 38,963, in 1871 to 46,598, and in 1881 to 54,793, of whom
                    27,576 were males, and 27,217 females.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">History and Antiquities.—</hi> Originally Merioneth belonged to
                    the territory of the Ordovices, and under the Romans it was included in <hi
                        rend="italic">Britannia</hi><hi rend="italic">Secunda.</hi> There are many
                    Celtic, Roman, and mediaeval remains. Caer Drewyn on the Dee, near Corwen, was a
                    British camp. There are numerous cromlechs in various parts of the county,
                    especially near the sea-coast. The <hi rend="italic">Via</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Occidentalis</hi> of the Romans passed through Merioneth from south to
                    north, and at Tomen-y-Mur was joined by a branch of the South Watling Street,
                    the Castell Tomen-y-Mur being supposed to be identical with the Roman station of
                    Heriri Mons. The immense ruin of Castel-y-Bere was originally one of the largest
                    castles in Wales, but has not been occupied since the time of Edward I. During
                    the Wars of the Roses the castle of Harlech, still a fine ruin, was held by the
                    Lancastrians, and was the last in Wales to surrender. Of ecclesiastical remains
                    the most important is Cymmer Abbey, founded by the Cistercians in 1198, a very
                    fine ruin containing architecture of various periods from Norman to
                    Perpendicular. There are numerous interesting old churches.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
