<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0916-0240-0227-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">MICHAELIS, Johann David</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 16, page 227</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4w669c71">Views</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204622">Georgia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204537">Sweden</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1063905">Pietism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1166896">Views</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n240/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MICHAELIS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Johann David</hi></label>
                    (1717-1791), one of the most influential scholars and teachers of last century,
                    belonged to a family which had the chief part in maintaining that solid
                    discipline in Hebrew and the cognate languages which distinguished the
                    university of Halle in the period of Pietism. Johann Heinrich Michaelis (1668—
                    1738) was the chief director of Francke’s <hi rend="italic">Collegium</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Orientale Theologicum,</hi> a practical school of Biblical and
                    Oriental philology then quite unique, and the author of an annotated Hebrew
                    Bible and various exegetical works of reputation, especially the <hi
                    rend="italic">Adnot</hi><hi rend="italic">ationes</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >uberiores</hi><hi rend="italic">in Hagio-graphos,</hi> 1720. In his chief
                    publications J. H. Michaelis had as fellow-worker his sister’s son Christian
                    Benedict Michaelis (1680-1764), the father of Johann David, who was likewise
                    influential as professor at Halle, and a very sound scholar, especially in
                    Syriac. J. D. Michaelis was trained for academical life under his father’s eye.
                    Halle was not then the best of universities; a narrow theological spirit cramped
                    all intellectual activity, and the eager vivacious youth, already distinguished
                    by a love for realities and a distaste for small pedantries, found much of the
                    teaching wearisome enough. He acquired, however, a good knowledge of the Latin
                    classics,—Greek, he tells us, was hardly taught at all, and his knowledge of
                    Greek literature was gained by his own reading in later years,—learned all that
                    his father could teach, and was influenced, especially in philosophy, by
                    Baumgarten, the link between the old Pietism and Semler, while he cultivated his
                    strong taste for history under Ludwig. In the winter-semester 1739-40 he
                    qualified as university lecturer. One of his dissertations was a defence of the
                    antiquity and divine authority of the vowel points in Hebrew. His scholarship
                    still moved in the old traditional lines in which no further progress was
                    possible, and he was also much exercised by religious scruples, the conflict of
                    an independent mind with that submission to authority at the expense of reason
                    encouraged by the type of Lutheranism in which he had been trained. A long visit
                    to England in 1741-42 lifted him out of the narrow groove of his earlier
                    education. In passing through Holland he made the acquaintance of the great
                    Schultens, whose influence on his philological views was not immediate, but
                    became all-powerful a few years later. England offered to him no such commanding
                    personal influence, and he was not yet able to turn to profit the stores of the
                    great libraries, but his personality was strengthened by contact with a larger
                    life, and his theological views were turned aside from the pietistic channel.
                    Michaelis never ceased to regard himself as essentially orthodox, though he did
                    not feel able fully to subscribe the Lutheran articles, and more than once
                    declined on this account to be professor of theology. But his views acquired a
                    distinctly rationalistic complexion, and the orthodoxy of his Göttingen lectures
                    and publications on dogmatic (delivered from a philosophical chair) is of a very
                    washed-out kind. His really useful work, however, lay in other directions; the
                    change of his theological views was important because it relieved him from
                    trammels that hampered the free course of his development as a scholar. From
                    England Michaelis went back to Halle; but he felt himself out of place, and in
                    1745 gladly accepted an invitation to Göttingen as privat-docent. In 1746 he
                    became extraordinary, in 1750 ordinary, professor, and in Göttingen he remained
                    till his death in 1791. In the first years of his new position Michaelis passed
                    through a second education. In the young and intellectually vigorous Georgia
                    Augusta he came under the powerful personal influence of such men as Gesner and
                    Haller. His intellect was active in many directions; universal learning indeed
                    was perhaps one of his foibles. Literature—modern as well as ancient—occupied
                    his attention <hi rend="italic">; one of</hi> his works was a translation of
                    four parts of <hi rend="italic">Clarissa;</hi> and translations of some of the
                    then current English paraphrases on Biblical books manifested his sympathy with
                    a school which, if not very learned, attracted him by its freer air. His
                    Oriental studies were reshaped by diligent perusal of the works of Schultens <hi
                    rend="italic">; for</hi> the Halle school, with all its learning, had no
                    conception of the principles on which a fruitful connexion between Biblical and
                    Oriental learning can be established. His linguistic work indeed was always
                    hampered by the lack of MS. material which is felt in his philological writings,
                    <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> in his valuable <hi rend="italic">Supplementa</hi>
                    to the Hebrew lexicons (1784-92).<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>By a strange fortune of war it was the occupation of
                    Göttingen by the French in the Seven Years’ War, and the friendly relations he
                    <pb corresp="kp-eb0916-0241-0228" xml:id="pbn9228"/> formed with the officers,
                    that procured him the Paris MS. from which he edited Abulfeda’s description of
                    Egypt.</p></note> He could not become <pb corresp="pbn9228"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n241/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0916-0241-0228"/> such an Arabist as Reiske; and, though for many
                    years the most famous teacher of Semitic languages in Europe, he had little of
                    the higher philological faculty, and neither his grammatical nor his critical
                    work, highly praised as it then was, has left a permanent mark, with the
                    exception perhaps of his text-critical studies on the Peshito.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Curie In
                    Actus</hi><hi rend="italic">Apostolorum Syriacos,</hi> 1755.</p></note> His
                    tastes were all for <hi rend="italic">realia—</hi> history, antiquities,
                    especially geography and natural science; in his autobiography he half regrets
                    that he did not choose the medical profession. Here he found a field hardly
                    touched since Bochart, in whose footsteps he followed in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Spicilegium geographiae, Hebraeorum exterae</hi><hi rend="italic">post
                    Bochαrtum</hi> (1769-80). To his impulse we owe the famous Eastern expedition of
                    Von Haven, Forskâl, and Niebuhr. He prepared the instructions for their journey,
                    and drew up a series of questions and elucidations to guide their researches,
                    which place in strong relief his comprehensive grasp of all that was then known
                    of the East, and the keen delight in the knowledge of tangible and natural
                    things, paired with a sober and patient judgment, which was his chief
                    intellectual characteristic. The best part of this knowledge was turned to the
                    profit of Biblical study; in his exegetical writings, for example, one of the
                    main features is what was then the novelty of illustrations from Eastern travel.
                    In spite of his doctrinal writings—which at the time made no little noise, so
                    that his <hi rend="italic">Compendium of Dogmatic</hi> (1760) was confiscated in
                    Sweden, and the knighthood of the North Star was afterwards given him in
                    reparation—it was the natural side of the Bible that really attracted him, and
                    no man did more to introduce the modern method of studying Hebrew antiquity as
                    an integral part of ancient Eastern life. The permanent influence of his works
                    indeed has not been great, and many of them are now hardly readable; for, with
                    all his historic tastes and learning, he had no large historic conceptions, and,
                    what is closely akin to this defect, was singularly deficient in imagination and
                    poetic sympathy. But the vivacity of his mind, his manysidedness, his singularly
                    attractive though discursive method of lecturing, and above all his power of
                    feeling and inspiring interest in every kind of fact, was a potent stimulus much
                    needed in the Germany of that age, and did not soon die. Different as the three
                    men are, there is a true historic nexus between the three great Göttingen
                    Orientalists, Michaelis, Eichhorn, and Ewald.</p>
                <p>The personal character of Michaelis can be read between the lines of his
                    autobiography with the aid of the other materials collected by the editor
                    Hassencamp («Λ. <hi rend="italic">D. Michaelis</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Lebensbeschreibung,</hi> &amp;c., 1793). To understand the secret of his
                    enormous influence, it is not enough to read his books, now for the most part
                    dull enough to us; we must see the upright vivacious laborious man, with a good
                    deal of worldly prudence and a good deal of temper, much absorbed in his
                    manifold academic activities in the university and Royal Society of Göttingen,
                    yet ever full of interest in the larger world, and of shrewd judgmentsand lively
                    talk, with a strong sense of his rights and dignity, yet with a good and warm
                    heart; shining especially in the lecture-room, where he dealt forth knowledge
                    with discursive hand from a full store, displaying the methods as well as the
                    results of his all-sided research, not without a touch of the vanity of the
                    polyhistor, and loving to leave the chair under a storm of applause at a parting
                    bon-mot which he acknowledged at the door in a backward glance of triumph. The
                    same volume contains a full list of his works. Besides those already mentioned
                    it is sufficient to refer to his New Testament <hi rend="italic"
                    >Introduction</hi> (the first edition, 1750, preceded the full development of
                    his powers, and is a very different book from the later editions), bis reprint
                    of Lowth’s <hi rend="italic">Praelectiones</hi> with important additions
                    (1758-62), his German translation of the Bible with notes (1773-92), his <hi
                    rend="italic">Orientalische und Exegetische Bibliothek</hi> (1775-85), and <hi
                    rend="italic">Neue</hi><hi rend="italic">0. and E. Bib.</hi> (1786-91), his <hi
                    rend="italic">Mosaisches Recht</hi> (1770—71), and his edition of Castle’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Lexicon</hi><hi rend="italic">Syriacum</hi> (1787-88). His <hi
                    rend="italic">Litterarischer</hi><hi rend="italic">Briefwechsel</hi> (1794-96)
                    contains much that is interesting for the history of learning in his time. (W.
                    R. S.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
