<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0916-0827-0798-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">MOON, The</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 16, page 798</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="21" ref="fasttopic:1119194">Sin</term>
                    <term n="21" ref="fasttopic:1119629">Sins</term>
                    <term n="19" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1047254">Orbits</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1027064">Motion</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:984032">Journalism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:817721">Arts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2df3t">Moon</term>
                    <term n="28" ref="lcsh1910:b4df6k36b">Earth</term>
                    <term n="22" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5cj23">Sun</term>
                    <term n="21" ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vr70">Sin</term>
                    <term n="19" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4js9hb31">Motion</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4sf2mj12">Orbits</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n827/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MOON, <hi rend="smallcaps">The</hi></label>. The subject of
                    the moon divides itself into two separate branches, the one concerned with the
                    constitution of the lunar globe, the other with its motions. For the first
                    subject the reader is referred to the article <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Astronomy</hi> (vol. ii. p. 801 <hi rend="italic">sq.}</hi>; the present
                    article is confined to the second, which is commonly called the <hi
                    rend="italic">Lunar Theory.</hi></p>
                <p>The lunar theory does not yet form a well-defined body of reasoning and doctrine,
                    like other branches of mathematical science, but consists only of a series of
                    researches, extending through twenty centuries or more, and incapable of being
                    welded into a consistent whole.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n828/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0916-0828-0799"/>
                <p>This state of things arises from the inherent difficulties and complexities of
                    the subject, and from the fact that no one method or system has yet been
                    discovered by which all the difficulties can be surmounted and all the
                    complexities disentangled. Hence each investigator, when he has desired to make
                    any substantial advance beyond his predecessors, has been obliged to take up the
                    subject from a new point of view, and to devise such method as might seem to him
                    most suitable to the special object in hand. The historical treatment is
                    therefore that best adapted to give a clear idea of the results of these
                    investigations. The ancient and modern histories of the subject are quite
                    distinct, the modern epoch commencing with Newton. The great epoch made by
                    Copernicus did not extend to the case of the moon at all, because in every
                    investigation of the moon’s motion, modern as well as ancient, the motion is
                    referred to the earth as a centre. Hence the heliocentric system introduced no
                    new conception of this motion, except that of taking place round a moving earth
                    instead of round a fixed one. This change did not affect the consideration of
                    the relative motion of the earth and moon, with which alone the lunar theory is
                    concerned. The two stages of the lunar theory are therefore—(1) that in which
                    the treatment was purely empirical, (2) that in which it was founded rationally
                    on the law of gravitation.</p>
                <p>It is in the investigation of the moon’s motion that the merits of ancient
                    astronomy are seen to the best advantage. In the hands of Hipparchus (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Astronomy,</hi> vol. ii. p. 749) the theory was brought to a
                    degree of precision which is really marvellous when we compare it, either with
                    other branches of physical science in that age, or with the remarks and
                    speculations of contemporary non-scientific writers. Whether this was wholly the
                    work of Hipparchus, or whether he simply perfected a system already devised by
                    his predecessors, it is now impossible to say; but, so far as certain knowledge
                    extends, the works of his predecessors did not embrace more than the
                    determination of the mean motion of the moon and its nodes. Although the general
                    fact of a varying motion may have been ascertained, the circumstances of the
                    variation had probably never been thoroughly investigated. The discoveries of
                    Hipparchus were :—</p>
                <p>1. <hi rend="italic">The Eccentricity of the Moon's Orbit.—</hi> He found that
                    the moon moved most rapidly near a certain point of its orbit, and most slowly
                    near the opposite point. The law of this motion was such that the phenomena
                    could be represented by supposing the motion to be actually circular and
                    uniform, the apparent variations being explained by the hypothesis that the
                    earth was not situated in the centre of the orbit, but was displaced by an
                    amount about equal to one-twentieth of the radius of the orbit. Then, by a
                    well-known law of kinematics, the angular motion round the earth would be most
                    rapid at the point nearest the earth—that is, at <hi rend="italic">perigee—</hi>
                    and slowest at the point most distant from the earth—that is, at <hi
                    rend="italic">apogee.</hi> Thus the apogee and perigee became two definite
                    points of the orbit, indicated by the variations in the angular motion of the
                    moon.</p>
                <p>2. <hi rend="italic">The Motion of the Perigee and Apogee.—</hi> As already
                    defined, the perigee and apogee are at the ends of that diameter of the orbit
                    which passes through the eccentrically situated earth, or, in other words, they
                    are on that line which passes through the centre of the earth and the centre of
                    the orbit. This line was called the <hi rend="italic">line of apsides.</hi> On
                    comparing observations made at different times, it was found that the line of
                    apsides was not fixed, but made a complete revolution in the heavens, in the
                    order of the signs of the zodiac, in-about nine years.</p>
                <p>3. <hi rend="italic">The Numerical Determination of the Elements of the Moon's
                    Motion.—</hi> In order that the two capital discoveries just mentioned should
                    have the highest scientific value it was essential that the numerical values of
                    the elements involved in these complicated motions should be fixed with
                    precision. This Hipparchus was enabled to do by lunar eclipses. Each eclipse
                    gave a moment at which the longitude of the moon was 180° different from that of
                    the sun, and the latter admitted of ready calculation. Assuming the mean motion
                    of the moon to be known and the perigee to be fixed, three eclipses observed in
                    different points of the orbit would give as many true longitudes of the moon,
                    which longitudes could be employed to determine three unknown quantities—the
                    mean longitude at a given epoch, the eccentricity, and the position of the
                    perigee. By taking three eclipses separated at short intervals, both the mean
                    motion and the motion of the perigee would be known beforehand, from other data,
                    with sufficient accuracy to reduce all the observations to the same epoch, and
                    thus to leave only the three elements already mentioned unknown. In the hands of
                    a modern calculator the problem would be a very simple one, requiring little
                    more than the solution of a system of three equations with as many unknown
                    quantities. But without algebra the solution was long and troublesome, and not
                    entirely satisfactory. Still, it was probably correct within the necessary
                    limits of the errors of the observations. The same three elements being again
                    determined from a second triplet of eclipses at as remote an epoch as possible,
                    the difference in the longitude of the perigee at the two epochs gave the annual
                    motion of that element, and the difference of mean longitudes gave the mean
                    motion. Such was the method of determining the elements of the moon’s motion
                    down to the time of Copernicus.</p>
                <p>The determination of the eccentricity from eclipses, as above described, leads to
                    an important error in the resulting value of the eccentricity, owing to the
                    effect of the neglected evection. We know from our modern theory that the two
                    principal inequalities in the moon’s true longitude are—</p>
                <p>6 <hi rend="superscript"> 0,</hi> 29 sin <hi rend="italic">g</hi> (Equation of
                    centre)</p>
                <p>+ l <hi rend="superscript"> o-</hi> 27 sin <hi rend="italic">{2D-g)</hi>
                    (Evection), where <hi rend="italic">g</hi> = mean anomaly, and <hi rend="italic"
                    >D =</hi> mean angular distance of the moon from the sun. Now during a lunar
                    eclipse we always have <hi rend="italic">D =</hi> 180° very nearly, and 2Z&gt; =
                    360°. Hence the evection is then - l <hi rend="superscript"> o-</hi> 27 sin <hi
                    rend="italic">g,</hi> and so has the same argument, <hi rend="italic">g,</hi> as
                    the equation of centre, and so is confounded with it. The value of the equation
                    of centre derived from eclipses is thus (6 <hi rend="superscript"> 0,</hi> 29 -
                    l <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> ∙27 = δ <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> 02) sin
                    <hi rend="italic">g.</hi> Therefore the eccentricity found by Hipparchus and
                    Ptolemy was only 5°, and was more than a degree less than its true value.</p>
                <p>The next important step in advance was the discovery of the “evection,” which is
                    described by Ptolemy (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Astronomy,</hi> vol. ii. p. 750)
                    as if made by himself. In view of the bad habit which Ptolemy had of making his
                    own observations verify results previously arrived at, which were sometimes in
                    error, we must view such a discovery by him as quite exceptional, and as best
                    explainable by the large magnitude of the outstanding error. Although, as just
                    shown, the erroneous eccentricity found by Hipparchus would always represent
                    eclipses, so that the error could never be detected by eclipses, the case was
                    entirely different when the moon was in quadratures. Comparing the inequalities
                    already written with that found by Hipparchus, we see that the latter required
                    the correction—</p>
                <p>l <hi rend="superscript"> o,</hi> 27 {si11&lt;7 + sin (2Z&gt;-y)} =</p>
                <p>Γ ’ 27 {(1 - cos <hi rend="italic">2D)</hi> sin <hi rend="italic">g</hi> + sin
                    <hi rend="italic">2D</hi> cos <hi rend="italic">g) .</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >At</hi> quadratures we have D=±90°, <hi rend="italic">2D</hi> = 180°, and hence
                    cos 2Z&gt; = - 1 and sin <hi rend="italic">2D =</hi> 0. The omitted inequalities
                    at these points of the orbit have therefore the value 2° '54 sin <hi
                    rend="italic">g,</hi> a quantity so large that it could not fail to be detected
                    by careful observations with the astrolabe. Such an inequality as this,
                    superposed upon the eccentric motion of the moon, was very troublesome to
                    astronomers who had no way of representing the celestial motions except by
                    geometrical construction. The construction proposed by Ptolemy was so different
                    from those employed for the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n829/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0916-0829-0800"/> motions of the planets, and withal so intricate,
                    that little interest attaches to it.</p>
                <p>The student of Arabian science may find much to interest him in the astronomical
                    speculations of the Arabs, but this people do not seem to have furnished
                    anything in the way of suggestive theory. In the fourth book of <hi
                    rend="italic">De Reυolu-tionibus,</hi><note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>The full title, <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Revolutionibus Orbium Coelestium Libri VI.</hi> (small folio, Nuremberg,
                    1543).</p></note> where we find the lunar theory of Copernicus, no writer later
                    than Ptolemy is referred to. Moreover, as already intimated, the work of
                    Copernicus in this particular direction forms little more than an episode in the
                    history of the subject. The working hypothesis of the great founder of modern
                    astronomy was borrowed from the ancients, and was that the celestial motions
                    were all either circular or compounded of circular motions. The hypothesis of
                    equal circular motions, though accepted by Ptolemy in name, was so strained by
                    him in its applications that little was left of it in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Almagest</hi> (the Arabic translation of his <hi rend="italic">Syntaxis').</hi>
                    But, by taking the privilege of compounding circular motions indefinitely—in
                    other words, of adding one epicycle to another—Copernicus was enabled to
                    represent the planetary and lunar inequalities on a uniform system, though his
                    heavens were perhaps worse “scribbled o’er” than those of Ptolemy. To one
                    epicycle representing the equation of the centre he added another for the
                    evection, and thus represented the longitude of the moon both at quadratures and
                    oppositions. But the third inequality, “variation,” which attains its maxima at
                    the octants and vanishes at all four quarters, was unknown to him. To Tycho
                    Brahe is commonly and justly ascribed the discovery of the variation. Joseph
                    Bertrand of Paris has indeed claimed the discovery for Abù Ί-Wefâ, an Arabian
                    astronomer, and has made it appear probable that Abù Ί-Wefä, really detected
                    inequalities in the moon’s motion which we now know to have been the variation.
                    But he has not shown, on the part of the Arabian, any such exact description of
                    the phenomena as is necessary to make clear his claim to the discovery. As
                    regards Tycho, although he discovered the fact, he could add nothing in the way
                    of suggestive theory. To the double epicycle of Copernicus he was obliged to add
                    a motion of the centre of the whole lunar orbit round a circle whose
                    circumference passed through the centre of the earth, two revolutions round this
                    circle being made in each lunation. Kepler, by introducing a moving ellipse
                    having the earth as its focus, was enabled to make a nearer approach to the
                    truth than any of his predecessors. But the geometrical hypotheses by which he
                    represented the inequalities due to the action of the sun form no greater epoch
                    in the progress of science than do the geometrical constructions of his
                    predecessors. We may therefore dispose of the ancient history of the lunar
                    theory by saying that the only real progress from Hipparchus to Newton consisted
                    in the more exact determination of the mean motions of the moon, its perigee and
                    its line of nodes, and in the discovery of three new inequalities, the
                    representation of which required geometrical constructions increasing in
                    complexity with every step.</p>
                <p>The modern lunar theory commenced with Newton, and consists in determining the
                    motion of the moon deductively from the theory of gravitation. But the great
                    founder of modern mechanics did not employ the method best adapted to lead to
                    the desired result, and hence his efforts to construct a lunar theory are of
                    more interest as illustrations of his wonderful power and correctness in
                    mathematical reasoning than as germs of new methods of research. He succeeded
                    perfectly in explaining the elliptic motion of two mutually attracting bodies
                    round their common centre of gravity by geometrical constructions. But when the
                    prob lem was one of determining the variations from the elliptic motion which
                    would be produced by a third body, such constructions could lead only to
                    approximate results. The path to modern methods was opened up by the Continental
                    mathematicians, whose great work consisted in reducing the problem to one of
                    pure algebra. The chasm between the laws of motion laid down by Newton and a
                    problem of algebra seems so difficult to bridge over that it is worth while to
                    show in what the real spirit of the modern method consists. We call to mind the
                    statement of Newton’s first two laws of motion: that a body uninfluenced by any
                    force moves in a straight line and with uniform velocity for ever, and that the
                    change of motion is proportional to the force impressed upon the body and in the
                    direction of such force. These two laws admit of being expressed in algebraic
                    language thus :—let us put <hi rend="italic">m</hi> the mass of a material
                    point; <hi rend="italic">x</hi> its distance from any fixed plane whatever; <hi
                    rend="italic">t</hi> the time <hi rend="italic">; X</hi> the sum of the
                    components of all the forces acting upon the point in the direction
                    perpendicular to the fixed plane, it being supposed that each force is resolved
                    into three mutually perpendicular components, one of which is perpendicular to
                    the fixed plane; then the differential equation <hi rend="italic">cPx</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> m</hi><hi rend="italic">dt*</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> X</hi> expresses Newton’s first two laws of motion with a
                    completeness and precision which is entirely wanting in all statements in
                    ordinary language. The latter can be nothing more than lame attempts to express
                    the equation in language which may be understood by the non-mathematical reader,
                    but which bear the same relation to the algebraic equation that a statement of
                    the operations of the Bank of England in the symbolic language of a tribe of
                    savages would bear to the bank statement in pounds, shillings, and pence. By
                    taking two other planes, perpendicular to each other and to the first plane, we
                    have three equations like the one last written. The law of gravitation and
                    Newton’s third law of motion enable us to substitute for <hi rend="italic"
                    >X</hi> and the other forces the masses and coordinates of the various
                    attracting bodies. Thus the data of the problem are expressed by a triplet of
                    three equations for each attracting body. The integration of these equations is
                    a problem of pure algebra, which, when solved, leads to expressions that give
                    the position of each body in terms of the time, which is what is wanted. The
                    special form which it is necessary to give the equations has not been radically
                    changed during the century and a half since this method of research was opened
                    out. The end aimed at is the algebraic expression of all the quantities involved
                    in the form of an infinite series of terms, each consisting of a constant
                    coefficient multiplied by the sine or cosine of an angle increasing uniformly
                    with the time. It is indeed a remarkable fact that, notwithstanding the great
                    advances which modern mathematics has made in the discovery of functions more
                    general than the old-fashioned sines and cosines of elementary trigonometry,
                    especially of elliptic functions, yet the form of development adopted by the
                    mathematicians of the last century has remained without essential change.</p>
                <p>It will be instructive to notice the general and simple property of the
                    trigonometric functions to which is due their great advantage in the problems of
                    celestial mechanics. It may be expressed thus :— <hi rend="italic">If we have
                    any number of quantities, each of which is expressed in the form of a
                    trigonometric series in which the angles increase uniformly with the time, then
                    all the powers and products of these qτιantities, and all their differentials
                    and integrals with respect to the time, may be expressed in series of the same
                    form.</hi> This theorem needs only an illustration by an example. Let our
                    quantities be <hi rend="italic">X</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Y,</hi> and let us
                    suppose them expressed in the form <hi rend="italic">X—a</hi> cos <hi
                    rend="italic">A + b</hi> cos <hi rend="italic">B + c</hi> cos C ’ + ,
                    &amp;c.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Y-a</hi> ’ sin <hi rend="italic">A</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">+
                    b</hi> ’ sin <hi rend="italic">B</hi> ’ + c' sin <hi rend="italic">C + ,</hi>
                    &amp;c., in which <hi rend="smallcaps">λvθ</hi> may suppose that the quantities
                    <hi rend="italic">a, b, c,</hi> &amp;c., converge towards zero. In forming their
                    product, the first term will be <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n830/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0916-0830-0801"/><hi rend="italic">aa'</hi> cos <hi rend="italic"
                    >A</hi> sin <hi rend="italic">A'.</hi> But we have cos <hi rend="italic">A</hi>
                    sin <hi rend="italic">A' = ⅛</hi> sin <hi rend="italic">{A' + A)</hi> + ⅜ sin
                    <hi rend="italic">{A' - A).</hi> Hence the product <hi rend="italic">X</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Y</hi> will be of the form <hi rend="italic">X Y= ⅛ aa'</hi> sin
                    <hi rend="italic">{A' + A</hi>) + ⅛ αα'sin <hi rend="italic">(A' - A) + ⅜
                    ab'</hi> sin (Λ + <hi rend="italic">B'</hi> + ),&amp;c., which is another series
                    of the same general form. Moreover, if we suppose the angles <hi rend="italic"
                    >A, B,</hi> &amp;c., to increase uniformly with the time—that is, to admit of
                    expression in the form <hi rend="italic">A = a + mt, A'=a' + m't,</hi> &amp;c—
                    we shall have, by integrating, <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">∫</hi><hi rend="italic                     superscript">
                    xrM</hi><hi rend="italic">= ∞</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> s</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">&lt;</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> j</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >'^'</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> l</hi><hi rend="italic">-'</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> kc</hi><hi rend="italic">∙</hi> which, again, is a
                    trigonometric series of the same general form, which admits of being manipulated
                    at pleasure in the same way as the original expressions <hi rend="italic">X</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">Y.</hi> This property does not belong to the elliptic
                    functions, and in consequence, notwithstanding the great length of the
                    trigonometric series, no attempt to supersede them has been successful.</p>
                <p>The efforts to express the moon’s motion by integrating the differential
                    equations of the dynamical theory may be divided into three classes. (1) Laplace
                    and his immediate successors found the problem so complex that they sought to
                    simplify it by reversing its form; instead of trying from the beginning to
                    express the moon’s coordinates in terms of the time, they effected the
                    integration by expressing the time in terms of the moon’s true longitude. Then,
                    by a reversal of the series, the longitude was expressed in terms of the time.
                    Although it would be hazardous to say that this method is unworthy of further
                    consideration, we must admit that its essential inelegance is such as to repel
                    rather than attract study, and that it holds out no promise of further
                    development. (2) By the second general method the moon’s coordinates are
                    obtained in terms of the time by the direct integration of the differential
                    equations of motion, retaining the algebraic symbols which express the values of
                    the various elements. Most of the elements are small numerical fractions: <hi
                    rend="italic">e,</hi> the eccentricity of the moon’s orbit, about 0'055 <hi
                    rend="italic">; e,</hi> the eccentricity of the earth’s orbit, about 0Ό17 <hi
                    rend="italic">; γ,</hi> the sine of half the inclination of the moon’s orbit,
                    about 0'046; <hi rend="italic">m,</hi> the ratio of the mean motions of the moon
                    and earth, about 0'075; and the expressions for the longitude, latitude, and
                    parallax appear as an infinite trigonometric series, in which the coefficients
                    of the sines and cosines are themselves infinite series proceeding according to
                    the powers of the above small numbers. This method was applied with success by
                    Pontécoulant and Sir John W. Lubbock, and afterwards by Delaunay. It should be
                    remarked that the solution by the first method appears in the same form as by
                    this one after the true longitude is expressed in terms of the mean longitude.
                    (3) By the method just mentioned the series converge so slowly, and the final
                    expressions for the moon’s longitude are so long and complicated, that the
                    series has never been carried far enough to insure the accuracy of all the
                    terms. This is especially the case with the development in powers of <hi
                    rend="italic">m,</hi> the convergence of which has often been questioned. Hence,
                    when numerical precision alone is aimed at, it has been found best to avoid this
                    difficulty by using the numerical values of the elements instead of their
                    algebraic symbols. This method has the advantage of leading to the more rapid
                    and certain determination of the numerical values of the several coefficients of
                    sines and cosines. It has the disadvantage of giving the solution of the problem
                    only for a particular case, and of being inapplicable in researches in which the
                    general equations of dynamics have to be applied. It has been employed by
                    Damoiseau, Hansen, and Airy.</p>
                <p>The methods of the second general class are those most worthy of study. And among
                    these we must assign the first rank to the method of Delaunay, developed in his
                    <hi rend="italic">Théorie du Mouvement</hi><hi rend="italic">de la, Lune,</hi>
                    because it contains a germ which may yet develop into the great desideratum of a
                    general method in celestial mechanics. To explain it, we must call to mind the
                    general method of “variation of elements,” due to Lagrange. This method is
                    applicable to cases in which a problem of dynamics can be completely solved when
                    any small forces which come into play are left out, but which does not admit of
                    direct solution when these forces are included. Omitting the small forces,
                    commonly called “disturbing forces,” let us suppose the problem of the motion of
                    a body under the influence of the “principal forces” completely solved. This
                    will mean that we have found algebraic expressions for the coordinates which
                    determine the position of the body in terms of the time, and (in the case of a
                    material point) of six constant quantities, to which we may assign values at
                    pleasure. Then Lagrange showed how, by supposing these constant quantities to
                    become variable, the same expressions could be used for the case in which the
                    effect of the disturbing forces was included. In other words, the effect of the
                    disturbing forces could be determined by assuming them to change the constants
                    of the first approximate solution into very slowly varying elements.</p>
                <p>In the researches on the lunar theory before Delaunay the principal force was
                    taken to be the attraction of the earth upon the moon, and the disturbing force
                    was that due to the sun’s attraction. When the action of the earth alone was
                    included the moon would move in an ellipse, in accordance with Kepler’s laws.
                    The effect of the sun’s action could be allowed for by supposing this ellipse to
                    be movable and variable. But when it was required to express this variation the
                    problem became excessively complicated, owing to the great number of terms
                    required to express the sun’s disturbing force. Now, instead of passing from the
                    elliptic to the disturbed motion by one single difficult step, Delaunay effected
                    the passage by a great number of easy steps. Out of several hundred periodic
                    terms, the sum of which expressed the disturbing force of the sun, he first took
                    one only, and determined the variations of the Keplerian ellipse on the
                    supposition that this term was the only one. In the solution the variable
                    elements of the ellipse would be expressed in terms of six new constants. He
                    then showed how these new constants could be taken as variables instead of the
                    elements of the original ellipse. Taking a second term of the disturbing force,
                    he expressed the new constants in terms of a third set of constants, and so
                    repeated the process until all the terms of the disturbing force were disposed
                    of.</p>
                <p>Among applications of the third or numerical method, the most successful yet
                    completed is that of Hansen. His first work appeared in 1838, under the title
                    <hi rend="italic">Fundamenta nova</hi><hi rend="italic">investigationis</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">orbitae</hi><hi rend="italic">verse</hi><hi rend="italic">quam
                    luna perlustrat,</hi> and contained an exposition ofhis ingenious and peculiar
                    methods of computation. During the twenty years following he devoted a large
                    part of his energies to the numerical computation of the lunar inequalities, the
                    re-determination of the elements of motion, and the preparation of new tables
                    for computing the moon’s position. In the latter branch of the work, he received
                    material aid from the British Government which published his tables on their
                    completion in 1857. The computations of Hansen were published some seven years
                    later by the Saxon Royal Society of Sciences.</p>
                <p>It is found on comparing the results of Hansen and Delaunay that there are some
                    outstanding discrepancies, which, though too small to be of great practical
                    importance, are of sufficient magnitude to demand the attention of those
                    interested in the mathematical theory of the subject. It is therefore desirable
                    that the numerical inequalities should be again determined by an entirely
                    different method. This is the object of Sir G. B. Airy’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Numerical Lunar Theory,</hi> which is not yet completely published, but is
                    sufficiently far advanced to give hopes of an early completion. The essence of
                    Sir George’s method consists in <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n831/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0916-0831-0802"/> starting with a provisional approximate solution
                    (that of Delaunay being accepted for the purpose), and substituting the
                    expressions for the moon’s coordinates in the fundamental differential equations
                    of the moon’s motion as disturbed by the sun. If the theory were perfect, the
                    two sides of each equation would come out equal. As they do not come out exactly
                    equal, Sir George puts the problem in the form: What corrections must be applied
                    to the expressions for the coordinates that the two sides may be made equal? He
                    then shows how these corrections may be found by solving a system of
                    equations.</p>
                <p>The several methods which we have described have for their immediate object the
                    determination of the motion of the moon round the earth under the influence of
                    the combined attractions of the earth and sun. In other words, the question is
                    that of solving the celebrated “problem of three bodies” in the special case
                    when one of the bodies, the sun, has a much greater mass than the other two, and
                    is at a much greater distance from them than they are from each other. All
                    methods lead to a solution of the same general form which we shall now describe.
                    Let us put <hi rend="italic">g</hi> the moon’s mean anomaly; <hi rend="italic"
                    >f</hi> the mean anomaly of the sun (or earth); ω the angular distance of the
                    lunar perigee from the moon’s node on the ecliptic; ω' the angular distance of
                    the sun’s perigee from the moon’s node on the ecliptic. When no account is taken
                    of the action of the sun the angles <hi rend="italic">g</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">f</hi> increase uniformly with the time, representing in fact the
                    uniform motion of the moon round the earth and of the earth round the sun, while
                    ω and ω' remain constant. When account is taken of the action of the sun all
                    four of the angles change with a uniform progressive motion. In consequence, the
                    mean orbit of the moon round the earth becomes a moving ellipse whose major axis
                    makes a revolution round the earth in about nine years, and the line of whose
                    nodes makes a revolution in about eighteen and a half years. All the other
                    elements of this ellipse—namely, its major axis, its eccentricity, and its
                    inclination to the ecliptic—remain absolutely constant however long the motion
                    may continue, unless some other disturbing force than that of the sun comes into
                    play. But in the actual motion of the moon there are periodic deviations from
                    this ellipse, which may be represented by an infinite trigonometric series, each
                    term of which is of the form <hi rend="italic">c</hi> (sin or cos) <hi
                    rend="italic">(ig + i'g</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">+jω+j'ω</hi> ’ <hi
                    rend="italic">),</hi> in which the quantities <hi rend="italic">c</hi> are
                    absolutely constant coefficients, and <hi rend="italic">i, i', j,</hi> and ∕ are
                    integers which may take all combinations of values —positive, negative, or zero.
                    The circular function is, a sine in the expression for longitude or latitude, a
                    cosine in the expression for the parallax. Also, <hi rend="italic">j</hi> and
                    <hi rend="italic">j'</hi> must be both even or both odd in the expressions for
                    longitude and parallax, but the one even and the other odd in the case of the
                    latitude. For example, if we suppose <hi rend="italic">j, j',</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">i</hi> all zero, we shall have terms of the form c <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi> sin &lt;∕ + c <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> sin 2g ’-f-¾
                    sin 3&lt;∕ + , &amp;c.</p>
                <p>To write other terms, suppose <hi rend="italic">i=l,</hi> then we have terms of
                    the form <hi rend="italic">e</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi> sin <hi
                    rend="italic">(g-f)+e</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> i</hi> sin (g+√) + ⅞ sin
                    (gf + 2^ ’) + , &amp;c.</p>
                <p>Taking the case whenj = 2 and <hi rend="italic">j'=</hi>-2, we shall have terms
                    of the form sin (g - &lt;/ + 2ω - 2ω') + τn <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> sin <hi
                    rend="italic">(g - 2g'</hi> + 2ω - 2ω') +, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>As the indices <hi rend="italic">i, i', j,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">j'</hi>
                    become larger, the coefficients c, <hi rend="italic">e, m, kc.,</hi> become
                    smaller; but the number of terms included in the theories of Hansen and Delaunay
                    amount to several hundreds. In the analytical theories, like that of Delaunay,
                    each of the coefficients <hi rend="italic">e, e, m,</hi> &amp;c., is a
                    complicated infinite series, but in the numerical theories it is a constant
                    number. And the principal problem of the modern theory of three bodies is to
                    find the appropriate coefficient for each of these hundreds of terms.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Action of the Planets on the Moon.—</hi> For nearly two
                    centuries it has been known from observations that the mean motion of the moon
                    round the earth is not absolutely constant, as it ought to be were there no
                    disturbing body but the sun. The general fact that the motion has been
                    accelerated since the time of Ptolemy was first pointed out by Halley, and the
                    amount of the acceleration was found by Dunthorne. After vain efforts by the
                    greatest mathematicians of the last century to find a physical cause for the
                    acceleration, Laplace was successful in tracing it to the secular diminution of
                    the eccentricity of the earth’s orbit, produced by the action of the planets. He
                    computed its amount to be 10" per century—that is, if the place of the moon were
                    calculated forward on its mean motion at the beginning of any century, it would
                    at the end of the century be 10" in advance of its computed place. This
                    theoretical result of Laplace agreed so closely with the acceleration found by
                    Lalande from the records of ancient and mediaeval eclipses that it was not
                    questioned for nearly a century. In 1852 Mr John C. Adams showed that Laplace
                    had failed to take account of a series of terms, the effect of which was to
                    reduce the acceleration to 6" or less. The result was inconsistent with the
                    accounts of ancient eclipses of the sun, and a cause for the discrepancy had to
                    be sought for. A probable cause was pointed out, first by Ferrel, and afterwards
                    by Delaunay. The former, in papers published in <hi rend="italic">Gould's
                    Astronomical Journal,</hi> and in the <hi rend="italic">Proceedings</hi> of the
                    American Academy of Arts and Sciences, showed that the action of the moon on the
                    tidal waves of the ocean would have the effect of increasing the time of the
                    earth’s axial rotation or the length of the day, which is necessarily taken as
                    the unit of time. Since, as the days became longer, the moon would move farther
                    in one day, though its absolute motion should remain unchanged, and hence an
                    apparent acceleration would be the result. That this cause really acts tlιere
                    can be no doubt. But the data for determining its exact amount are discrepant.
                    If we take only such data as are purely astronomical—namely, the eclipses
                    recorded by Ptolemy between 720 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> and 150 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">a.d.,</hi> and those observed by the Arabians between 800 and
                    1000 A.n.—the apparent excess of the observed acceleration to be accounted for
                    by the tidal retardation amounts to only 2" per century, and may be even less.
                    But this small acceleration is entirely incompatible with conclusions drawn from
                    certain supposed accounts of total eclipses of the sun, notably the eclipse
                    associated with the name of Thales. This is. the famous eclipse supposed to be
                    alluded to by Herodotus when he describes a battle as stopped by a sudden advent
                    of darkness, which had been predicted by Thales. If the true value of the
                    coefficient resulting from the combined effect of tidal retardation of the earth
                    and secular acceleration of the moon is less than 10", then not only could the
                    path of totality not have passed over the field of battle but the greatest
                    eclipse could not have occurred till after sunset. In fact, to represent this
                    and other supposed eclipses of the sun, the acceleration must be increased to
                    about 12", which is near the value found by Hansen from theory, and adopted in
                    his tables of the moon. But his theoretical computation is undoubtedly
                    incorrect, because in computing in what manner the eccentricity of the earth’s
                    orbit enters into the moon’s motion he took account only of the first
                    approximation, as Laplace had done. The following is a summary of the present
                    state of the question :—</p>
                <p>The theoretical value of the acceleration, assuming the</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>day to be constant, is, according to
                            Delaunay</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6"∙17(</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Hansen’s value, in his <hi
                            rend="italic">Tables de la Lune,</hi> is</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>12’18</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Hansen’s revised but still
                            theoretically erroneous result is The value which best represents the
                            supposed eclipses (1) of Thales, (2) at Larissa, (3) at Stikkelstad, is
                            about</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>12∙56</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>11 ∙7</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>The result from purely astronomical
                            observations is</p><p>The result from Arabian and modern observations
                            alone</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>8∙3</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>is about</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7’0</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Inequalities of Long Period.—</hi> Combined with the question
                    of the secular acceleration is another which is still entirely unsettled—
                    namely, that of inequalities of long period in the mean motion of the moon round
                    the earth. Laplace first showed that modern observations of the moon indicated
                    that its mean motion was really less during the second half of the 18th century
                    than during the first half, and hence inferred the existence of an inequality
                    having a period of more than a century. All efforts to find a satisfactory
                    explanation were, however, so unavailing that Poisson, in 1835, disputed the
                    reality of the inequality. But Airy, from his discussion of the Greenwich
                    observations between 1750 and 1830, conclusively proved its existence. About the
                    same time Hansen announced that he had found from theory two terms of long
                    period arising from the action of Venus which fully corresponded to the
                    inequalities indicated by the observations. These terms, as employed in his <hi
                    rend="italic">Tables de la Lune,</hi> are</p>
                <p>15"‘34 sin (-g-16√ + 18g" + 33° 36 ’) + 21" ’ 47 sin (8g" - 13g' + 4° 44 ’), in
                    which <hi rend="italic">g, g</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> f</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">g"</hi>
                    represent the mean anomalies of the moon, the earth, and. Venus respectively.
                    During the first few years after the publication of Hansen’s tables they
                    represented observations so well that their entire correctness was generally
                    taken for granted. But doubt soon began to be thrown upon the inequalities of
                    long period just mentioned. Indeed, Hansen himself admitted that the second and
                    larger term was partly empirical, being taken so as to satisfy observations
                    between 1750 and 1850. Delaunay re-computed both terms, and found for the first
                    term a result substantially identical with that of Hansen. But he found for the
                    second or empirical one a coefficient of only 0" ’ 27, which would be quite
                    insensible. With this smaller coefficient the observations from 1750 could not
                    be satisfied, so that, so far as observations could go in deciding a purely
                    mathematical question, the evidence was in favour of Hansen’s result. But on
                    comparing Hansen’s tables with observations between 1650 and 1750 it was found
                    that the supposed agreement with observation was entirely illusory. Moreover,
                    since 1865 the moon has been steadily falling behind the tabular place. These
                    inequalities of long period have not yet been satisfactorily explained. The most
                    plausible supposition is that they are due to the action of one or more of the
                    larger planets. But the problem of the action of the planets on the mcon <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n832/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0916-0832-0803"/> is the most difficult and intricate of celestial
                    mechanics, and no satisfactory general method of attacking it has yet been
                    found. The sources of difficulty are two in number. First, the disturbing action
                    of the planets is modified by that of the sun in such a way that the ordinary
                    equations of disturbed elliptic motion are no longer rigorous, and hence new and
                    more complicated ones must be constructed. And, secondly, the combination of the
                    four bodies —moon, earth, sun, and planet—leads to terms so numerous and
                    intricate that it has hardly been found possible to isolate them. The question
                    has, indeed, been raised whether the rotation of the earth on its axis, and
                    hence the unit of time, may not be subject to slow and irregular changes of a
                    nature to produce apparent corresponding changes in the motion of the moon. But
                    it has recently been found, from a discussion of the observed transits of
                    Mercury since 1677, that, although such inequalities may exist, they cannot have
                    the magnitude necessary to account for the observed changes of long period in
                    the moon's motion.</p>
                <p>The following is a summary of the present state of the various branches of the
                    lunar theory. (1) The numerical solution of the problem of the sun’s action on
                    the moon may be regarded as quite satisfactory, at least when Hansen’s results
                    shall have been verified by an independent method. (2) The analytic theory needs
                    to be perfected by finding some remedy for the slow convergence of the series by
                    which it is expressed, but its general form may be regarded as quite
                    satisfactory. (3) Except in one or two special cases, the action of the planets
                    on the moon, when treated with the necessary rigour, is so intricate that no
                    approach to a satisfactory solution has yet been attained. When this desideratum
                    is reached, the mathematical theory will be complete. (4) The general discussion
                    of ancient and modern observations with a view to finding what real or apparent
                    inequalities of long period in the mean motion may exist is still to be
                    finished. With it the astronomical theory will be complete. (S. N. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
