<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0916-0897-0866-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">MOSQUITO</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 16, page 866</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:894485">Diptera</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1028427">Mouth</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:834550">Blood</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:884950">Culex</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1026772">Mosquitoes</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1120047">Skin</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205805">Cuba</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qn8f">Diptera</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f39x">Mouth</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c374">Blood</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87k6z">Mosquito</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cv3f">Skins</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b45d8nd6f">Skin</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n897/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MOSQUITO</label> (sometimeswritten “Mosquita”), a Spanish
                    word signifying “little fly,” is a name popularly applied to certain annoying
                    dipterous insects, and, strictly speaking, it should probably be used only for
                    species of <hi rend="italic">Culicidae</hi> (and for the genus <hi rend="italic"
                    >Culex</hi> in particular), for which “gnat” is the English synonym; but in many
                    countries it is by almost common consent applied to all small dipterous insects
                    that suck human blood, and therefore includes what we know as “sand-flies,”
                    “midges,” &lt;fcc., of the genera <hi rend="italic">Ceratopogon, Simulium,</hi>
                    and others. By Englishmen a distinction is often falsely drawn between
                    “mosquito” and “gnat,” the former being supposed to represent an insect native
                    chiefly of hot climates, whereas the latter is their own too-well-known pest. In
                    effect the terms are really synonymous, and any actual difference can only be
                    specific. In very hot seasons we not uncommonly hear alarming reports of
                    mosquitoes having made their appearance in London and elsewhere in the British
                    Isles, and means whereby they were imported are often suggested,— the real facts
                    of the case being that extra heat may render the native species more annoying,
                    or that it causes a bodily condition in which their bites are more severely
                    felt.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>A few years ago a
                    London hotel, popular with American visitors, was said to harbour mosquitoes,
                    which some of the visitors had brought λvith them from the Southern States. An
                    examination revealed the fact that the cistern was uncovered and exposed, and
                    was the breeding-place for hosts of gnats.</p></note> The “mosquitoes” of high
                    northern latitudes may be species both of <hi rend="italic">Culex</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Simulium.</hi></p>
                <p>Accounts of the numbers of these insects in tropical countries and in high
                    latitudes, and of their irritating attacks, are to be met with—seldom
                    exaggerated—in most books of travel. Even in Britain the annoyance caused by
                    gnats is very great, and in marshy districts often unendurable, especially to
                    new-comers, for it seems probable that the insects really attack a visitor more
                    furiously than they do the natives of the district, but, on the other hand, the
                    latter may be more indifferent to their assaults. In some subjects even the
                    “piping” by which a hungry gnat announces its presence has most distressing
                    effects. In <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n898/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0916-0898-0867"/> high latitudes they are driven off by anointing
                    the body with fish-oil; and in hot climates “mosquito curtains” are part of the
                    ordinary bed-furniture. It is only the female that bites; and, as it is but a
                    very small proportion of them that can ever taste human blood or that of any
                    warm-blooded animal, blood would not appear to be essential to their welfare. It
                    has been suggested that warm blood may have an influence on the ova, but it
                    cannot be supposed that the eggs of those multitudes of individuals that never
                    get a chance to taste blood are necessarily infertile; everything tends to prove
                    the opposite.</p>
                <p>Of late mosquitoes have been accused of playing a hitherto unsuspected part in
                    the dissemination of certain entozoic diseases. According to the researches of
                    Drs Manson and Cobbold and others, it appears certain that the insects, in
                    sucking the blood of persons who are hosts of the entozoon known as <hi
                    rend="italic">Filaria sanguis-kominis,</hi> take these parasites into their own
                    system, and it is believed that they afterwards (by their death and otherwise)
                    contaminate drinking water with them, and thus convey the entozoa into the blood
                    of persons previously unaffected.</p>
                <p>Mosquitoes are aquatic in their early stages. The female deposits her eggs in
                    boat-shaped masses on the surface of the water. The larvae are very active, and
                    have a peculiar jerking motion; the last segment is furnished with a respiratory
                    apparatus, the form of which probably varies according to the species, but it is
                    usually a long tube, the extremity of which can be exposed to the external air.
                    Thepupae are also active (contrary to the condition in most dipterous pupae),
                    and are odd-looking creatures owing to the great development of the thoracic
                    region; the respiratory apparatus is in the thorax in this state, the extremity
                    of the body having two swimming-plates; the pupae do not eat, but their activity
                    is very great.</p>
                <p>No notice of the mosquito or gnat would be complete without an explanation of the
                    mouth-parts by which it is enabled to cause such extreme irritation. When these
                    parts are closed one upon the other the whole looks like a long proboscis; but
                    in reality this consists of seven distinct slender pieces separated to the base,
                    viz.— the labium, two maxillae, two mandibles, the lingua, and the labrum. The
                    nomenclature of the mouth-parts varies with different authors. G. Dimmock <hi
                    rend="italic">(Anatomy of the Mouth-parts and of the Sucking-apparatus of some
                    Diptera),</hi> the latest investigator of this complex apparatus, states that
                    the labium has for function, for the most part, the protection of the fine setae
                    which form the true piercing organ of <hi rend="italic">Culex.</hi> In the
                    female of <hi rend="italic">Culex</hi> the protective sheath is formed by ttfe
                    labium alone. When the mosquito has found a place which suits it for
                    piercing—for it often tides different places on our skin before deciding on
                    one—it plants its labellae firmly upon the spot, and a moment later the labium
                    is seen to be flexing backwards in its middle; the seta·, firmly grouped
                    together, remain straight and enter the skin. When the setae have entered to
                    nearly their full length, the labium is bent double beneath the body of the
                    insect. When the mosquito wishes to withdraw the setae it probably first
                    withdraws the two barbed maxillae beyond the other setae, that is, so that their
                    barbs or papillae will be kept out of action by the mandibles and hypopharynx;
                    then it readily withdraws the setae, perhaps aiding their withdrawal by the
                    muscles of the labium, for during the process of extracting the setae from the
                    skin, while they are slowly sinking back into the groove upon the upper side of
                    the straightening labium, the mosquito keeps the labellae pressed firmly upon
                    the skin. The withdrawal of blood is effected by means of a pumping apparatus at
                    the base of the mouth-parts. As no investigator appears to have been able to
                    detect a poison gland, it has been considered that the irritation caused by the
                    bite of a mosquito was solely of mechanical origin; but the extreme irritation
                    and its duration have not caused this idea to be commonly accepted. Dimmock
                    avows his belief that there is use made of a poisonous saliva. In the male of
                    <hi rend="italic">Culex</hi> the mouth-parts vary considerably from those of the
                    female,—a conspicuous point of difference being that in this sex the mandibles
                    are absent, and the maxillae are not barbed.</p>
                <p>About 35 species of <hi rend="italic">Culex</hi> (mosquito or gnat) have been
                    described as inhabiting Europe, and about 130 from the rest of the world, but
                    their differentiation is involved in great difficulty and uncertainty, and it is
                    probable that the number of true species may be very much less. A species from
                    Cuba has received the name <hi rend="italic">Culex</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >mosquito</hi>; but there is not one species that specially deserves the name
                    more than another from a popular point of view, nor from a scientific point of
                    view is there any difference between a mosquito and a gnat.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
