<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0916-0305-0288-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MIERIS (9th edition, volume 16, page 288)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1183341">Youth</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1183692">Youthfulness</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1052086">Paneling</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz5d">Youth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94k2c">Painters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n305/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MIERIS</label>, the name of a family of artists who practised
                    painting at Leyden for three generations in the 17th and 18th centuries.</p>
                <p>I. <hi rend="smallcaps">Frans van Mieris,</hi> the elder, son of Jan van Mierls,
                    a goldsmith and diamond setter, was born, according to Houbraken, at Leyden on
                    the 16th of April 1635, and died there on the 12th of March 1681. His father
                    wished to train him to his own business, but Frans preferred drawing to chasing,
                    and took service with Abraham Torenvliet, a glazier who kept a school of design.
                    As often happens, the youth’s style was influenced by his earliest surroundings.
                    In his father’s shop he became familiar with the ways and dress of people of
                    distinction. His eye was fascinated in turn by the sheen of jewellery and
                    stained glass; and, though he soon gave up the teaching of Torenvliet for that
                    of Gerard Dow and Abraham van den Tempel, he acquired a manner which had more of
                    the finish of the exquisites of the Dutch school than of the breadth of the
                    disciples of Rembrandt. It should be borne in mind that he seldom chose panels
                    of which the size exceeded 12 to 15 inches, and whenever his name is attached to
                    a picture above that size we may surely assign it to his son Willem or to some
                    other imitator. Unlike Gerard Dow when he first left Rembrandt, or Jan Steen
                    when he started on an independent career, he never ventured to design figures as
                    large as life. Characteristic of his art in its minute proportions is a shiny
                    brightness and metallic polish. The subjects which he treated best are those in
                    which he illustrated the habits or actions of the wealthier classes; but he
                    sometimes succeeded in homely incidents and in portrait, and not unfrequently he
                    ventured on allegory. He repeatedly painted the satin skirt which Terburg
                    brought into fashion, and he often rivalled Terburg in the faithful rendering of
                    rich and highly-coloured woven tissues. But he remained below Terburg and Metzu,
                    because he had not their delicate perception of harmony or their charming
                    mellowness of touch and tint, and he fell behind Gerard Dow, because he was hard
                    and had not his feeling for effect by concentrated light and shade. In the form
                    of his composition, which sometimes represents the framework of a window
                    enlivened with <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n306/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0916-0306-0289"/> greenery, and adorned with bas-reliefs within
                    which figures are seen to the waist, his model is certainly Gerard Dow. It has
                    been said that he possessed some of the humour of Jan Steen, who was his friend,
                    but the only approach to humour in any of his works is the quaint attitude and
                    look of a tinker in a picture at Dresden, who glances knowingly at a worn copper
                    kettle which a maid asks him to mend.</p>
                <p>It is a question whether Houbraken has truly recorded this master’s birthday. One
                    of his best-known pieces, a party of ladies and gentlemen at an oyster luncheon
                    in the hermitage at St Petersburg, bears the date of 1650. Celebrated alike for
                    composition and finish, it would prove that Mieris had reached his prime at the
                    age of fifteen. Another beautiful example, the Doctor Feeling a Lady’s Pulse in
                    the gallery of Vienna, is dated 1656; and Waagen, in one of his critical essays,
                    justly observes that it is a remarkable production for a youth of twenty-one. In
                    1657 Mieris was married at Leyden in the presence of Jan Potheuck, a painter,
                    and this is the earliest written record of his existence on which we can
                    implicitly rely. Of the numerous panels known to the writer of these lines,
                    twenty-nine at least are dated,—the latest being an allegory, long in the Ruhl
                    collection at Cologne, illustrating the kindred vices of drinking, smoking, and
                    dicing, in the year 1680.</p>
                <p>Mieris had numerous and distinguished patrons. He received valuable commissions
                    from Archduke Leopold, the elector-palatine, and Cosmo III., grand-duke of
                    Tuscany. His practice was large and lucrative, but never engendered in him
                    either carelessness or neglect. If there be a difference between the painter’s
                    earlier and later work, it is that the former was clearer and more delicate in
                    flesh, whilst the latter was often darker and more livid in the shadows. When he
                    died his clients naturally went over to his son Willem, who in turn bequeathed
                    his painting-room to his son Frans. But neither Willem nor Frans the younger
                    equalled Frans the elder.</p>
                <p>II. <hi rend="smallcaps">Willem van Mieris</hi> (1662-1747), son of Frans. His
                    works are extremely numerous, being partly imitations of the paternal subjects,
                    or mythological episodes, which Frans habitually avoided. In no case did he come
                    near the excellence of his sire.</p>
                <p>III. <hi rend="smallcaps">Frans van Mieris</hi> the younger (1689-1763) also
                    lived on the traditions of his grandfather’s painting-room.</p>
                <p>The pictures of all the generations of the Mieris family were successfully
                    imitated by A. D. Snaphaan, who lived at Leipsic and was patronized by the court
                    of Anhalt-Dessau. To those who would study his deceptive form of art a visit to
                    the collection of Worlitz near Dessau may afford instruction.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
