<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0916-0214-0205-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MEUSE (9th edition, volume 16, page 205)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93d6n">Bar</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sj19z78">Potatoes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f27h">Hemp</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210278">Belgium</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1073379">Potatoes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:955129">Hemp</term>
                    <term ref="fast:998853">Limes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:998827">Lime</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n214/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MEUSE</label>, a department in the north-east of France,
                    formed out of a part of Lorraine and portions of the Three Bishoprics, the
                    Clermontais, and Champagne, derives its name from the river by which it is
                    traversed from south to north. It lies between 4° 52' and 5° 50' E. long., and
                    between 48° 25' and 49° 38' N. lat., and is bounded on the N. by Belgium and the
                    department of Ardennes, on the E. by that of Meurthe-et-Moselle, on the S. by
                    those of Vosges and Haute-Marne, and on the W. by those of Marne and Ardennes.
                    Of its superficial area (2405 square miles), about one-half belongs to the basin
                    of the Meuse, which is enclosed to the east and west by the eastern and western
                    Argonnes. On the north-east it is watered by the Orne, a tributary of the
                    Moselle, and the Chiers, which runs by Montmédy, and joins the Meuse a little
                    beyond the northern limit of the department. The other half sends its waters to
                    the Seine through the Aire, a tributary of the Aisne, both of which take their
                    rise here, and by the Ornain, an affluent of the Saux, these two last being
                    tributary to the Marne. The Meuse receives no important river in its course
                    through this department. The highest elevation (1388 feet) occurs to the
                    south-west, on the line of the ridge which separates the basin of the Meuse from
                    that of the Seine. The heights gradually sink from south to north, but seldom
                    fall below 1000 feet. The hills of the western Argonne similarly sink rapidly
                    down to the valley of the Saux, where the lowest level of the department (377
                    feet) is reached. The climate of Meuse is transitional between the region of the
                    Soine and that of the Vosges; its winters are less severe than those of the
                    latter, but it is not so temperate as the former. The mean annual temperature is
                    52° Fahr. As at Paris, the maximum cold is 9° Fahr.; the greatest heat rarely
                    exceeds 95° Fahr.</p>
                <p>More than half the surface of the department consists of culturable lands,
                    one-fourth of forest, one-tenth of meadow land. The proportion of horses is
                    larger than in any other French department, except La Manche. There are 53,800
                    horses, 90,000 cattle, 145,000 sheep, 125,000 pigs, and nearly 30,000 beehives.
                    Cereals, potatoes, and beet-root are the chief crops (in 1877 465,966 quarters
                    of wheat, 104,660 quarters of barley, 585,355 quarters of oats, 7,677,374
                    bushels of potatoes, besides pulse, hemp, and colza). The vineyards produced
                    more than 6,600,000 gallons of wine of good quality. The forests, which are
                    principally of oak, are rich in game, as are the rivers in fish. The mineral
                    wealth of the department<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n215/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0916-0215-0206"/> includes iron ore, good freestone, and fossil
                    phosphates of lime. There are blast-furnaces, iron, copper, and bell foundries,
                    wireworks, and manufactories of files, hardware, and edge tools. The
                    cotton-spinning factories employ 15,000 spindles and 32,000 frames; the woollen
                    manufacture employs 5000 spindles, and some hundreds of persons are employed in
                    the spinning and weaving of hemp, flax, and jute. The glass-works (particularly
                    the manufactory of painted window-glass, transferred after the war of 1870 from
                    Metz to Bar-le-Duc), paper-mills, saw-mills, and flour-mills, as well as the
                    manufactures of lime, tiles, and fire-bricks, are worthy of mention. Hosiery and
                    embroidery also give occupation to a great number of workshops, and the
                    department is celebrated for its confectionery. Meuse contains more than 300
                    miles of railway,—the principal lines being that from Paris to Strasburg through
                    Bar-le-Duc and Commercy, that from Paris to Metz through Verdun, and the branch
                    line to the Meuse. The chief waterways are the canal connecting the Marne with
                    the Rhine, and the canal of the Meuse; the two together have a length of 146
                    miles. The population of the department in 1881 was 289,861,—a small number in
                    proportion to its extent, and with a tendency to decrease. Ecclesiastically it
                    forms the diocese of Verdun; it has its court of appeal at Nancy, and
                    constitutes part of the district of the army corps of Châlons-sur-Marne. There
                    are 4 arrondissements,—Bar-le-Duc, Commercy, Montmédy, and Verdun,—28 cantons,
                    and 586 communes. Bar-le-Duc (population in 1881, 17,485) is the capital;
                    Commercy has 5260 inhabitants and Montmédy 3000; St Mihiel (5915), on the Meuse,
                    has good churches and some remarkable rocks, and is the seat of the departmental
                    assize court.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
