<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0916-0207-0198-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">METSU, Gabriel (9th edition, volume 16, page
                    198)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s11w">Woman</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m6290g">Vice</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6j808">Gaming</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42r3nw89">Games</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94k2c">Painters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vt1gs41">Marketing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r22w">Markets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1050530">Painters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1010167">Marketing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1010316">Markets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1739388">Womanism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1895887">Womanizers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1166263">Vices</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1166236">Vice</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n207/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">METSU, <hi rend="smallcaps">Gabriel</hi></label>, a Dutch
                    painter of celebrity (born in 1630, died after 1667), is one of the few artists
                    of renown in Holland whose life has remained obscure. Houbraken, who eagerly
                    collected anecdotes of painters in the 18th century, was unable to gather more
                    from the gossip of his contemporaries than that, as early as 1658, Metsu, at the
                    age of forty-three, submitted to a dangerous surgical operation. The inference
                    drawn by superficial readers from this statement has been that death immediately
                    ensued. A more careful perusal would have shown that Houbraken knew that Metsu
                    had given lessons to De Musscher in 1665. Local records now reveal that Gabriel
                    was the son of Jacques Metsu, who lived most of his days at Leyden, where he was
                    three times married. The last of these marriages was celebrated in 1625, and
                    Jacomma Garnijers, herself the widow of a painter, gave birth to Gabriel in
                    1630. Connected by both his parents with art, Metsu was probably taught first by
                    his father and then by Gerard Dow. He probably finished his training under
                    Rembrandt. So far back as 1648, but a few days earlier than Jan Steen, who is
                    said to have painted his portrait, Metsu was registered in the painters’
                    corporation at Leyden; and the books of the guild also tell us that he remained
                    a member in 1649. In 1650 he ceased to subscribe, and works bearing his name and
                    the date of 1653 give countenance to the belief that he had then settled at
                    Amsterdam, where he continued his studies under Rembrandt. His companions at the
                    time would naturally be De Hooch and Van der Meer, whose example he soon
                    followed when it came to his turn to select the class of subjects for which his
                    genius fitted him. Under the influence of Rembrandt he produced the Woman Taken
                    in Adultery, a large picture with the date of 1653, in the Louvre, in which no
                    one would suspect the painter of high life or taverns were it not that his name
                    is written at full length on the canvas. The artist who thus repeated the gospel
                    subjects familiar to <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n208/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0916-0208-0199"/> Flinck and Eeckhout was also acquainted with
                    the Oriental wardrobe of Rembrandt, and ready to use it, like all his
                    contemporaries. But he probably observed that sacred art was ill suited to his
                    temper, or he found the field too strongly occupied, and happily for himself, as
                    well as for his admirers, he turned to other subjects for which he was better
                    fitted. We may doubt whether he tried the style of allegory as illustrated in a
                    picture of Justice Protecting Virtue and Chastising Vice in the gallery of the
                    Hague. There is every reason to think that this rough and frosty composition was
                    wrought by quite another master. What Metsu undertook and carried out from the
                    first with surprising success was the low life of the market and tavern,
                    contrasted with wonderful versatility by incidents of high life and the
                    drawing-room. In each of these spheres he combined humour with expression, a
                    keen appreciation of nature with feeling, and breadth with delicacy of touch,
                    unsurpassed by any of his contemporaries. In no single instance do the artistic
                    lessons of Rembrandt appear to have been lost upon him. The same principles of
                    light and shade which had marked his schoolwork in the Woman Taken in Adultery
                    were applied to subjects of quite a different kind. A group in a drawingroom, a
                    series of groups in the market-place, a single figure in the gloom of a tavern
                    or parlour, was treated with the utmost felicity by fit concentration and
                    gradation of light; a warm flush of tone pervaded every part, and, with that,
                    the study of texture in stuffs was carried as far as it had been by Terburg or
                    Dow, if not with the finish or the <hi rend="italic">brio</hi> of De Hooch.
                    Metsu’s pictures are all in such admirable keeping, and so warm and harmonious
                    in his middle or so cool and harmonious in his closing time, that they always
                    make a pleasing impression. They are more subtle in modulation than Dow’s, more
                    spirited and forcible in touch than Terburg’s; and, if Terburg may of right
                    claim to have first painted the true satin robe, he never painted it more softly
                    or with more judgment as to colour than Metsu.</p>
                <p>That Metsu married and became a citizen of Amsterdam in 1659 would only prove
                    that his residence in the commercial capital of the Netherlands was later than
                    historians have generally assumed. But there is no reason to think that Metsu
                    claimed his citizenship at once. The privileges of a burgess were given in
                    exchange for a payment of dues, and these painters had various ways of avoiding
                    unless they married. One of the best pictures of Metsu’s manhood is the
                    Market-place of Amsterdam, at the Louvre, respecting which it is difficult to
                    distribute praise in fair proportions, so excellent are the various parts, the
                    characteristic movement and action of the <hi rend="italic">dramatis</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">personae,</hi> the selection of faces, the expression and the
                    gesture, and the texture of the things depicted. A tin can in the arm of a cook
                    is a marvel of imitation, but the cook’s face is also a marvel of expression.
                    Equally fine, though earlier, are the Sportsman (dated 1661) and the Tavern
                    (also 1661) at the Hague and Dresden Museums, and the Game-Dealer’s Shop, also
                    at Dresden, with the painter’s signature and 1662.</p>
                <p>Metsu is one of the painters of whose skill Holland still preserves examples, yet
                    whose best pictures are either in England or in France or in the galleries of
                    Germany. The value of his works is large, and at the Pommersfelden sale in 1867
                    the Jealous Husband Dictating his Wife’s Letters, though but one of several
                    replicas, was bought by Lord Hertford for little short of £2000, while for the
                    Ride of the Prince of Orange, in the Gsell collection at Vienna, £3000 was paid
                    by Baron Rothschild in 1873. (J. A. C.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
