<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0916-0211-0202-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">METZ</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 16, page 202</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4pg1hs7w">Leather</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49s1kk48">Arm</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r39q">Franks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20f90">Carolingians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4nv99d8g">Huns</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:795379">Accounting</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:938081">Garrisons</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n211/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">METZ</label>, the capital of German Lorraine, and one of the
                    strongest fortresses in Europe, is situated at the confluence of the Moselle and
                    the Seille, 80 miles to the north-west of Strasburg, and 190 miles to the east
                    of Paris. It is the seat of a military governor, the judicial and administrative
                    authorities of Lorraine, a Roman Catholic bishop, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n212/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0916-0212-0203"/> Protestant and Jewish consistories, and a chamber
                    of commerce. The general appearance of the town is quaint and irregular, but
                    there are also many handsome modern streets. The Moselle flows through it in
                    several arms, crossed by fourteen or fifteen bridges. In the south-west corner
                    of the town is the esplanade, an extensive open space commanding a fine view of
                    the fertile “Pays Messin” around Metz. The most interesting of the ten city
                    gates is the Porte d’Allemagne or Deutsches Thor, a castellated structure
                    erected in 1445, and still bearing traces of the siege of Charles V. Metz
                    contains seven Roman Catholic churches, two Protestant churches, and a
                    synagogue. The cathedral, with huge pointed windows, slender columns, and
                    numerous flying buttresses, was begun in the 13th century, and finished in 1546,
                    and belongs to the decadence of the Gothic style. The Gothic churches of St
                    Vincent and St Eucharius, and the handsome garrison-church, completed in 1881,
                    also deserve mention. Among secular buildings the most important are the large
                    covered market, the town-hall, the palace of justice, the theatre, the
                    governor’s house, and the various buildings for military purposes. The public
                    library contains 35,000 volumes, including an extensive collection of works
                    relating to the history of Lorraine. In the same building is the museum, which
                    contains a picture gallery, a numismatic cabinet, and a collection of specimens
                    of natural history. Metz also possesses several learned societies and charitable
                    institutions, a gymnasium, three seminaries, and a military academy. The
                    cemetery of Chambière contains the graves of 8400 French soldiers who died here
                    in 1870.</p>
                <p>The commerce and industry of Metz have not yet entirely recovered from the blow
                    inflicted by the withdrawal of French capital in 1871. The principal articles of
                    manufacture are leather, coarse cloth and canvas, gunpowder, arms, needles,
                    billiard tables, hats, and artificial flowers. There are several large
                    iron-works in the neighbourhood. The trade of Metz is chiefly carried on in
                    leather, timber, wine, brandy, liqueurs, beer, preserved fruits, and hardwares.
                    A large annual fair is held here. The civil population of Metz, which in 1869
                    amounted to 48,066, sank in 1872 to 33,134. Since then it has steadily
                    increased, and in 1881 was 43,275, about half of whom were Germans. The garrison
                    of Metz consists of 10,000 men, or including the surrounding forts nearly
                    16,000. The total of 58,813 includes 17,000 Protestants and 1600 Jews.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n213/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0916-0213-0204"/>
                <p><hi rend="italic">History. —</hi> Metz, the Gallic Divodurum, was the chief town
                    of the Mediomatrici, and was also called by the Romans Mediomatrica, a name from
                    which the present form has been derived by contraction. Caesar describes it as
                    one of the oldest and most important towns in Gaul. The Romans, recognizing its
                    strategical importance, fortified it and supplied it with water by an imposing
                    aqueduct, the remains of which still exist. Under the Roman emperors Metz was
                    connected by military roads with Toul, Langres, Lyons, Strasburg, Verdun,
                    Rheims, and Treves. Christianity was introduced in the 3d century of our era. In
                    the middle of the 5th century the town was plundered by the Huns under Attila;
                    subsequently it came into the possession of the Franks; and in 512 it was made
                    the capital of Austrasia. On the partition of the Carolingian realms in 843 Metz
                    fell to the share of the western kingdom as the capital of Lorraine. Its
                    bishops, whose creation reaches back to the 4th century, now began to be very
                    powerful. Metz acquired the privileges of a free imperial town in the 12th
                    century, and attained great commercial prosperity. In 1552 it fell into the
                    hands of the French through treachery, and was heroically and successfully
                    defended against Charles V. by the young duke of Guise. It now sank to the level
                    of a French provincial town, and its population dwindled from 60,000 to 22,000
                    (1698). At the peace of Westphalia Metz, with Toul and Verdun, was formally
                    ceded to France, in whose possession it remained for upwards of two centuries.
                    In August 1870 the successes of the German troops compelled Marshal Bazaine and
                    the French army of the Rhine to seek shelter behind the fortifications of Metz,
                    which was forthwith subjected by the Germans to a rigorous blockade. After an
                    investment of ten weeks, during which not a single shot was fired at the town,
                    Bazaine capitulated, surrendering to the victors an army of nearly 180,000 men,
                    several hundred cannon, and an immense quantity of military stores of all kinds.
                    By the peace of Frankfort in 1871 Metz was again united to the German empire.
                    Marshal Fabert and Generals Custine and Kellermann were natives of Metz.</p>
                <p>As a fortress Metz has always been of the highest importance, and it now ranks
                    with Strasburg as one of the two great bulwarks of the west frontier of Germany.
                    The original town-walls were replaced by ramparts in 1550, and the citadel was
                    built in 1566. In 1674 the works were reconstructed by the celebrated military
                    engineer Vauban. Under Napoleon III. the fortress was strengthened to meet the
                    demands of modern warfare, and since 1871 the Germans have spared neither time
                    nor money in completing and supplementing his plans. The present fortifications
                    of Metz consist of two lines—an inner circle of bastions and ramparts enclosing
                    the city itself, and an outer circle of large detached forts on the surrounding
                    hills. The inner line is strengthened by two citadels, one of which is advanced
                    as a tête-de-pont on the left bank of the Moselle. The outer circle consists of
                    nine or ten large forts, connected with each other by smaller fortifications and
                    commanding all the approaches to the city. They form a large fortified camp with
                    a circumference of 15 miles, within which are twelve villages and numerous
                    country-houses and farms. The most distant of the outlying forts is about 3⅜
                    miles from the cathedral. Their names and positions may be seen on the annexed
                    plan. Previous to 1870 the fortress of Metz had never succumbed to an enemy.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Sources of Information.—Westphal,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Geschichte der Stadt</hi><hi rend="italic">Metz,</hi> 1875-78; Georg Lang, <hi
                    rend="italic">Metz und seine Umgebungen,</hi> 1883, and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Statistisch-topographisches Handbuch für Lothringen.</hi> The official German
                    account of the blockade.of Metz'in 1870 will be found in the history of the
                    Franco-German war issued by the general staff at Berlin, 1872 <hi rend="italic"
                    >sq.</hi> A succinct account is given by Georg Lang, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Die</hi><hi rend="italic">Kriegsoperationen um Metz im Jahr</hi> 1870, 2d ed.,
                    Metz, 1880.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
