<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0916-0299-0282-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">MIDDLETON, Thomas</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 16, page 282</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68967">Songs</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z196">Love</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tx6q">Play</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86p9b">Tricks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6j808">Gaming</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s11w">Woman</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9789n">Girls</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42r3nw89">Games</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1012869">Mayors</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1002769">Love</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1126120">Songs</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1176346">Witches</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942866">Girls</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1739388">Womanism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1895887">Womanizers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:937529">Games</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n299/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MIDDLETON, <hi rend="smallcaps">Thomas</hi></label> (<hi
                    rend="italic">c.</hi> 1570-1627), held a leading place among the dramatists of
                    the reign of James I. His <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n300/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0916-0300-0283"/> popularity would seem to have first come to a
                    height about 1607. This is a fair inference from the fact that in this and the
                    following year a whole swarm of comedies from his pen were licensed and
                    published— <hi rend="italic">A Trick to Catch the Old One, The Family of Love,
                    The Phoenix, Michaelmas Term, Your Five Gallants, A Mad World My Masters.</hi>
                    Only the first of these kept the stage after the author’s own generation, though
                    in point of wit and constructive skill it is not superior to <hi rend="italic"
                    >The Phoenix</hi> (a serious comedy) or <hi rend="italic">Your Five
                    Gallants</hi> (a bustling and gaily humorous farcical comedy). The plot of the
                    <hi rend="italic">Trick</hi> bears a family likeness to that of Massinger’s <hi
                    rend="italic">New Way to Pay Old Debts·,</hi> the titles in fact might be
                    interchanged. A ruined scapegrace outwits his creditors and a usurious uncle by
                    coming to town with a courtesan and passing her off as a widow with a fortune,
                    whom he treats with deferential friendship, but hardly dares to love, ruined and
                    hopeless as he is. His uncle lends him money that he may woo in proper state;
                    his creditors also intrigue to have the honour of supplying him with all the
                    needs of fashion; and the lady receives many costly presents from aspirants to
                    her hand and fortune. Though Middleton was apparently not in high popularity
                    till 1607, he had made his debut as a satirist ten years before; and if Malone
                    is right in his conjecture that the <hi rend="italic">Mayor of
                    Queensborough</hi> is identical with the <hi rend="italic">Randall Earle of
                    Chester</hi> mentioned by Henslowe in 1602, he had done dramatic work of a much
                    higher kind. Like <hi rend="italic">The Changeling,</hi> a later production, in
                    which Middleton had the assistance of Rowley, the tragedy of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Mayor</hi> is named after a character in the insignificant comic
                    underplot. Such a title scares away readers weary of half-intelligible
                    Elizabethan fun and satire; but Simon the comic mayor is a very subordinate
                    figure in the play, and the tragic portions alike in situation,
                    characterization, and language rank among the very noblest productions of the
                    Shakespearian age. There are scenes in the <hi rend="italic">Changeling</hi>
                    also which Mr Swinburne, with a judgment that will not be disputed, assigns to
                    Middleton, unsurpassed for intensity of passion and appalling surprises in the
                    whole range of Elizabethan literature. The execution of these scenes is far
                    beyond any power that Rowley showed in single-handed work, but well within the
                    scope of the author of the <hi rend="italic">Mayor of Queensborough</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Women Beware Women.</hi> This last play, in which every one of the
                    characters important enough to be honoured with a name perishes at the end in a
                    slaughter so rapid as to be somewhat confusing, was apparently one of
                    Middleton’s later works, and the simple and measured development of the plot In
                    the first acts seems to show traces of the influence of Massinger. Middleton’s
                    verse, when charged with the expression of impassioned love, contains many
                    echoes of the verse of <hi rend="italic">Romeo and Juliet,</hi> as if his ear
                    had been fascinated by it in his youth. His language generally proclaims him an
                    admiring disciple of Shakespeare’s; and in daring and happy concentration of
                    imagery, and a certain imperial confidence in the use of words, he of all the
                    dramatists of that time is the disciple that comes nearest the master. <hi
                    rend="italic">The Witch,</hi> by which Middleton’s name has of late been linked
                    with Shakespeare’s in groundless speculation as being part author of <hi
                    rend="italic">Macbeth,</hi> is by no means one of Middleton’s best plays. The
                    plot is both intricate and feeble, as if the play had been written with a view
                    to the half-comic spectacular exhibition of the witches, with their ribald
                    revelry, their cauldrons, hideous spells, and weird incantations. Charles Lamb’s
                    comparison of Middleton’s witches with Shakespeare’s is one of the most
                    exquisite morsels of criticism; but, when he says that Middleton’s witches are
                    “in a lesser degree fine creations,” he ought perhaps to have added that they
                    are merely embodiments of the vulgar superstition, put on the stage to excite
                    laughter rather than fear among a half-believing audience, an audience ready to
                    laugh at them in the light and in a crowded meeting, whatever each might do in
                    the dark alone. That Middleton had any share in <hi rend="italic">Macbeth</hi>
                    is a conjecture resting solely on the fact that the opening words of the song of
                    the witches about the cauldron in Shakespeare’s <hi rend="italic">Macbeth</hi>
                    occur also in the incantations about a cauldron in the last act of Middleton’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Witch,</hi> and that Middleton’s song was inserted by Davenant
                    in an “amended” reproduction of <hi rend="italic">Macbeth.</hi> If either
                    borrowed the words of this song from the other, that is no evidence of further
                    co-operation; besides all that is common to the two was probably as much public
                    property as a nursery rhyme. There is no evidence as to whether <hi
                    rend="italic">The Witch</hi> appeared before or after <hi rend="italic"
                    >Macbeth.</hi> Middleton co-operated with Dekker in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Roaring Girl</hi>; with Rowley in <hi rend="italic">A Fair Quarrel, The Spanish
                    Gipsy,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Changeling;</hi> and with Jonson and
                    Fletcher in <hi rend="italic">The Widow</hi> (one of the few of Middleton’s
                    plays reproduced after the Restoration). Towards the close of his life Middleton
                    got into difficulties with the privy council from writing a very clever
                    political play apropos of Prince Charles’s unsuccessful wooing of the Spanish
                    infanta in 1623. The chief personages in Spanish politics and their manoeuvres
                    were represented with most ingenious skill in the pieces and movements of <hi
                    rend="italic">A Game at Chess.</hi> This play was stopped by royal authority,
                    and the prosecution of the author was allowed quietly to drop. The few
                    unimportant facts known in Middleton’s private history are collected in Mr
                    Dyce’s admirable edition of his plays. He enjoyed the office of city
                    chronologer, and was often employed to write pageants and masques, in one case
                    at least contracting for the whole exhibition, besides furnishing the words. He
                    died in 1627, and was buried at Newington Butts.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
