<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0916-0789-0760-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MONROE, James (9th edition, volume 16, page
                    760)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w669c71">Views</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9q760">Jays</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795c7h">Republicanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46h4ct7t">Fox</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:945704">Governors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:874582">Conducting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1166896">Views</term>
                    <term ref="fast:982161">Jays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204597">Virginia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207035">Louisiana</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207034">Mississippi</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205150">Florida</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n789/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MONROE, <hi rend="smallcaps">James</hi></label> (1758-1831),
                    fifth president of the United States, was born 28th April 1758, in the county of
                    Westmoreland, Virginia. According to the family tradition, their ancestors are
                    traced back to a family of Scottish cavaliers descended from Hector Monroe, an
                    officer of Charles I. At the outbreak of the Revolutionary war, James Monroe was
                    a student at the College of William and Mary, but left his studies in 1776 to
                    join the continental army. He took part as lieutenant in the New Jersey campaign
                    of that year, and was wounded at the battle of Trenton. The next year he served
                    with the rank of captain on the staff of General William Alexander (“Lord
                    Stirling”), but, thus being out of the line of promotion, he soon found himself
                    without military employment. In 1780 he began the study of the law under the
                    direction of J efferson, then governor of Virginia. His intimacy with Jefferson
                    at this time had probably a controlling influence upon his subsequent political
                    career. He continued through all vicissitudes to possess the friendship and
                    support of both Jefferson and Madison.</p>
                <p>In 1782 Monroe was in the State legislature, and from 1783 to 1786 was a member
                    of Congress. On retiring from Congress he entered upon the practice of the law
                    at Fredericksburg, and was again elected to the legislature. In the Virginia
                    convention of 1788 for the ratification of the constitution, he was among the
                    opponents of that instrument; but his course was approved by the legislature of
                    his State, who elected him United States senator in 1790 to fill the vacancy
                    caused by the death of William Grayson. As senator he was a decided opponent of
                    the Federalist administration. Nevertheless he was selected by Washington in
                    1794 as minister to France in place of Gouverneur Morris, a Federalist, recalled
                    upon the request of the French Government. Being of the party who sympathized
                    with the revolutionary struggle in France, it was expected that his appointment
                    would be flattering to the Government of that country, and would also conciliate
                    the French party at home. The Government of the National Convention received
                    Monroe with open signs of favour, and on his part he expressed his own and his
                    country’s sympathy with the French Republic with so much enthusiasm that
                    Washington deemed his language not in keeping with the neutral policy which the
                    administration had recently proclaimed. At about the same time John Jay had
                    negotiated a treaty of amity and commerce with England which gave great umbrage
                    to France. It was alleged that the earlier treaty of 1778 with France was
                    violated by the stipulations of the Jay treaty; and the Directory seemed
                    disposed to make of this a <hi rend="italic">casus belli.</hi> In this emergency
                    it was believed by Washington and his advisers that Monroe failed to represent
                    properly the policy of the Government, and he was therefore recalled in 1796. In
                    justification of his diplomatic conduct, he published the next year his <hi
                        rend="italic">View,</hi> a pamphlet of 500 pages. In 1799 he became governor
                    of Virginia, and was twice re-elected. In the meantime the Republican party had
                    come into power, with Jefferson as president, and Monroe was again called upon
                    to fill an important diplomatic station. He was commissioned on 10th January
                    1803 to act with Livingston, resident minister at Paris, in negotiating the
                    purchase of New Orleans and the territory embracing the mouth of the
                    Mississippi, which formed a part of the province of Louisiana, recently ceded by
                    Spain to France. In view of the anticipated renewal of hostilities between
                    England and France in 1803, Napoleon was anxious, for a consideration, to part
                    with his new acquisition, which in the event of a war with England he would
                    probably lose by conquest. The American commissioners met therefore with little
                    difficulty in the accomplishment of their object. But, in the absence of
                    instructions, they assumed the responsibility of negotiating the purchase not
                    only of New Orleans but of the entire territory of Louisiana—an event that is
                    hardly second in importance to any in the history of the country. Monroe was
                    next commissioned as minister to England, <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n790/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0916-0790-0761"/> to succeed Rufus King, who had resigned. In
                    1804 he undertook a mission to Madrid, with the object of negotiating the
                    purchase of the Floridas; but in this he was unsuccessful, and returned to
                    London in 1805. The next year he was joined in a commission with William Pinkney
                    to negotiate a treaty with England to take the place of the Jay treaty, which
                    expired in that year. Lords Auckland and Howick having been appointed on the
                    part of England, a treaty was concluded on the last day of the year, which was
                    perhaps more favourable to the United States than the Jay treaty; but, like the
                    latter, it contained no provision against the impressment of American seamen.
                    For this reason President Jefferson refused to submit it to the Senate for
                    ratification, but sent it back for revision. In the meantime Canning had become
                    foreign secretary in place of Fox, and refused to reopen the negotiation. Monroe
                    returned to the United States in 1807, and, as in the case of his first French
                    mission, he drew up a defence of his diplomatic conduct in England. In 1808
                    certain disaffected Republicans attempted to put Monroe forward as the candidate
                    for the presidency, but as Virginia declared in favour of Madison Monroe
                    withdrew his name. In 1810 he was again in the legislature of his native State,
                    and the next year its governor. But in this year he was called from the state to
                    the national councils, superseding Robert Smith as secretary of state in
                    Madison’s cabinet, and took an active part in precipitating the war against
                    England in 1812. On the retirement of Armstrong, after the capture of Washington
                    in 1814, Monroe assumed the duties of the war department in addition to those of
                    the state department, and by his energy and decision infused something of vigour
                    into the conduct of the war. He was elected president in 1816, and was
                    re-elected in 1820 without opposition. The period of his administration
                    (1817-25) has been called “the era of good feeling,” for the reason that the
                    party issues of the past were mostly dead, and new issues had not yet arisen. In
                    the formation of his cabinet Monroe showed the soundness of his judgment,
                    selecting for the leading positions J. Q. Adams, J. C. Calhoun, W. H. Crawford,
                    and William Wirt. With these able advisers he devoted himself to the economic
                    development of the country, which had been so long retardèd by foreign
                    complications. As president, moreover, he was able to accomplish in 1819 the
                    acquisition of the Floridas, which as minister to Spain he had failed to do in
                    1804, and to define the boundary of Louisiana, which he had been the agent in
                    purchasing in 1803. But Monroe is best known to later generations as the author
                    of the so-called “Monroe doctrine,” a declaration inserted in his seventh annual
                    message, 2d December 1823. It was the formulation of the sentiment, then
                    beginning to prevail, that America was for Americans. One of the principles of
                    the neutral policy of the country, which had been established with much
                    difficulty, had been that the United States would not interfere in European
                    politics; and now this policy was held to include the converse as a necessary
                    corollary—that is, that Europe should not interfere in American politics,
                    whether in North America or South America. The occasion of proclaiming this
                    doctrine was the rumoured intervention of the Holy Alliance to aid Spain in the
                    reconquest of her American colonies. President Monroe believed that such a
                    policy entered upon by the allied continental powers of Europe would be
                    dangerous to the peace and safety of the United States; he therefore declared
                    that “we would not view any intervention for the purpose of oppressing them (the
                    Spanish American states) or controlling in any manner their destiny, by any
                    European power, in any other light than as the manifestation of an unfriendly
                    disposition towards the United States.” This declaration, together with the
                    known hostility of England to such a project, was sufficient to prevent further
                    action on the part of the Alliance.</p>
                <p>On the expiration of his presidential term Monroe retired to Oak Hill, his
                    residence in London county, Virginia; but at the time of his death, 4th July
                    1831, he was residing in New York. He was married about 1786, and left two
                    daughters. He was a man of spotless character; and, though not possessing
                    ability of the first order, he ranks high as a wise and prudent statesman. His
                        <hi rend="italic">Life</hi> has been written by D. C. Gilman. <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">(f. sn.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
