<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0916-0519-0498-04" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MIRANDA, Francesco (9th edition, volume 16, page
                    498)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1137041">Success</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1156290">Trials</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9785q">Success</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47s7hw9j">Girondists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46h4ct7t">Fox</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208963">Turkey</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204166">Venezuela</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205916">Colombia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n519/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MIRANDA, <hi rend="smallcaps">Francesco</hi></label>
                    (1754-1816), was born at Santa Fé in New Granada in 1754. He entered the army,
                    and served against the English in the American War of Independence. The success
                    of that war inspired him with a hope of being the Washington of his own country,
                    and a belief that the independence of Spanish America would increase its
                    material prosperity. With these views he began to scheme a revolution, but his
                    schemes were discovered and he had only just time to escape to the United
                    States. Thence he went to England, where he was introduced to Pitt, but chiefly
                    lived with the leading members of the opposition—Fox, Sheridan, and Romilly.
                    Finding no help in his revolutionary schemes, he travelled over the greater part
                    of Europe, notably through Austria and Turkey, till he arrived at the court of
                    Russia, where he was warmly received, but from which he was dismissed, though
                    with rich presents, at the demand of the Spanish ambassador, backed up by the
                    envoy of France. The news of the dispute between England and Spain about Nootka
                    Sound in 1790 recalled him to England, where he saw a good deal of Pitt, who had
                    determined to make use of him to “insurge” the Spanish colonies, but the
                    peaceful arrangement of the dispute again destroyed his hopes. In April 1792 he
                    went to Paris, with introductions to Pétion and the leading Girondists, hoping
                    that men who were working so hard for their own freedom might help his
                    countrymen in South America. France had too much to do in fighting for its own
                    freedom to help others; but Miranda’s friends sent him to the front with the
                    rank of general of brigade. He distinguished himself under Dumouriez, was
                    intrusted in February 1793 with the conduct of the siege of Maestricht, and
                    commanded the left wing of the French army at the disastrous battle of
                    Neerwinden. Although he had given notice of Dumouriez’s projected treachery, he
                    was put on his trial for treason on May 12. He was unanimously acquitted, but
                    was soon again thrown into prison, and not released till after the 9th
                    Thermidor. He again mingled in politics, and was sentenced to be deported after
                    the struggle of Vendémiaire. Yet he escaped, and continued in Paris til) the <hi
                        rend="italic">coup d’état</hi> of Fructidor caused him finally to take
                    refuge in England. He now found Pitt and Dundas once more ready to listen to
                    him, and the latter sent a special minute to Colonel Picton, the governor of
                    Trinidad, to assist General Miranda’s schemes in every possible way; but, as
                    neither of them would or could give him substantial help, he went to the United
                    States, where President Adams gave him fair words but nothing more. Once more he
                    returned to England, <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n520/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0916-0520-0499"/> where Addington might have done something for
                    him but for the signature of the peace of Amiens in 1802. At the peace, though
                    in no way amnestied, he returned to Paris, but was promptly expelled by the
                    First Consul, who was then eager to be on good terms with the court of Spain.
                    Disappointed in further efforts to get assistance from England and the United
                    States, he decided to make an attempt on his own responsibility and at his own
                    expense. Aided by two American citizens, Colonel Smith and Mr Ogden, he equipped
                    a small ship, the “Leander,” in 1806, and with the help of the English admiral
                    Sir A. Cochrane made a landing near Carâcas, and proclaimed the Colombian
                    republic. He had some success, and would have had more had not a false report of
                    peace between France and England caused the English admiral to withdraw his
                    support. At last in 1810 came his opportunity; the events in Spain which brought
                    about the Peninsular War had divided the authorities in Spanish America, some of
                    whom declared for Joseph Bonaparte, others for Ferdinand VII., while others
                    again held to Charles IV. At this moment Miranda again landed, and had no
                    difficulty in getting a large party together who declared a republic both in
                    Venezuela and New Granada or Colombia. But Miranda’s desire that all the South
                    American colonies should rise, and a federal republic be formed, awoke the
                    selfishness and pride of individual provincial administrations, and thus
                    weakened the cause, which further was believed to be hateful to heaven owing to
                    a great earthquake on March 26, 1812. The count of Monte Verde, the Bourbon
                    governor, had little difficulty in defeating the dispirited forces of Miranda,
                    and on July 26 the general capitulated on condition that he should be deported
                    to the United States. The condition was not observed; Miranda was moved from
                    dungeon to dungeon, and died in 1816 at Cadiz.</p>
                <p>There are allusions to Miranda’s early life in nearly all memoirs of the time,
                    but they are not generally very accurate. For his trial see Bûchez et Roux, <hi
                        rend="italic">Histoire Parlementaire,</hi> xxvii. 26-70. For his later life
                    see Biggs, <hi rend="italic">History of Miranda's Attempt in South America,</hi>
                    London, 1809; and Veggasi, <hi rend="italic">Revolucion de la Columbia.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
