<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0916-0239-0226-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">MICHAEL</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 16, page 226</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1150446">Thrones</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:841374">Bulgarians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:814767">Armenians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1004739">Macedonians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:812571">Arabism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4833n637">Rose</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b45717v01">Saracens</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s53t">Normans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kj57">Caesarism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n239/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MICHAEL</label>, the name of several Byzantine emperors.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Michael</hi> I. (Rhangabé) was an obscure nobleman who had
                    married Procopia, the daughter of Nicephorus I., and been made master of the
                    palace; his elevation to the throne was due to a revolutionary movement against
                    his brother-in-law Stauracius, who reigned only two months after the death of
                    Nicephorus on the battlefield (812). Elected as the tool of the bigoted orthodox
                    party in the church, Michael diligently persecuted the Iconoclasts on the
                    northern and eastern frontiers of the empire, but meanwhile allowed the
                    Bulgarians to ravage a great part of Macedonia and Thrace; having at last taken
                    the field in the spring of 813, he was defeated near Bersinikia, and Leo the
                    Armenian was saluted emperor in his stead in the following summer. Michael,
                    after having been compelled to become a monk, was permitted thenceforward to
                    live unmolested in the island of Prote, where he died in 845.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Michael</hi> II. (The Stammerer), a native of Amorium in
                    Phrygia, was of humble origin, and began life as a private soldier, but rose by
                    his talents and assiduity to the rank of general. He was one of those who had
                    favoured the election to the throne of his old companion in arms Leo the
                    Armenian in 813, but, detected in a conspiracy against the government of that
                    emperor, had been sentenced to death in December 820; his partisans, however,
                    succeeded in assassinating Leo on the morning of Christmas Day, and called
                    Michael from the prison to the throne. The principal features of his reign
                    (820-829) were a protracted struggle (of nearly three years) against his brother
                    general, Thomas, who aimed at the throne, the conquest of Crete by the Saracens
                    in 823, and the beginning of their attacks upon Sicily (827). Conciliatory on
                    the whole in his policy towards the image worshippers (his own sympathies were
                    iconoclastic), he incurred the wrath of the monks by entering into a second
                    marriage with Euphrosyne, daughter of Constantine VI., who had previously taken
                    the veil. He died in October 829, and was succeeded by Theophilus his son.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Michael</hi> III. (The Drunkard) was the grandson of Michael
                    the Stammerer, and succeeded his father Theophilus when only three years of age
                    (842). Until his majority at the age of eighteen the affairs of the empire were
                    managed by the empress-regent his mother Theodora; his education was shamefully
                    neglected, and it was during this period that Michael formed the disgraceful
                    personal habits which are indicated by his surname. In 861 Michael, together
                    with his uncle Bardas, undertook an expedition against the Bulgarians, which
                    resulted in the conversion of the Bulgarian king, who thenceforth bore the
                    Christian name of Michael. The emperor had been less successful in the campaign
                    which he led in person against Omar of Melitene in 860, but in 863 his uncle
                    Petronas gained an important victory over the Saracens in Asia Minor. The year
                    865 was marked by the first appearance of the Russians in the Bosphorus. Michael
                    was assassinated in his palace in 867 by Basilius the Macedonian, whom he had
                    associated with himself in the empire in the previous year.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Michael</hi> IV. (The Paphlagonian) owed his elevation to
                    Zoe, daughter of Constantine IX., the last of the Macedonian dynasty; this
                    princess was married to Romanus HL, but becoming enamoured of Michael, her
                    chamberlain, she poisoned her husband and married her attendant (1034). Michael,
                    however, being of a weak character and subject to epileptic fits, possessed the
                    supreme power only in name, and was a mere instrument in the hands of his
                    brother, John the Eunuch, who had been first minister both of Constantine and
                    Romanus. John’s diplomacy was successful in keeping the Arabs in the archipelago
                    and Egypt quiet for some time, and he was at last able to secure a victory for
                    the imperial arms at Edessa in 1037. The attempt to recover Sicily in the
                    following year with the help of the Normans was less prosperous, and in 1040 the
                    island wholly ceased to be a Byzantine province. About the same time, the
                    Bulgarians having overrun Macedonia and Thrace, and threatening Constantinople,
                    the indolent and infirm emperor, to the surprise alike of friends and foes, put
                    himself at the head of the army, and not only drove the enemy beyond the
                    frontier, but followed them into their own territory. He died, shortly after his
                    triumph, on December 10, 1041.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Michael</hi> V. (Calaphates or The Caulker), nephew and
                    successor of the preceding, derived his surname from his father Stephen, who had
                    originally followed the occupation of a caulker of ships. He owed his elevation
                    (December 1041) to his uncle John, whom along with Zoe he almost immediately
                    banished; this led to a popular tumult and his dethronement after a brief reign
                    of four months (April 1042). He lived for many years afterwards in the quiet
                    obscurity of a monastery.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Michael</hi> VI. (The Warlike) was already an old man when
                    chosen by the empress Theodora as her successor shortly before her death in
                    1056. His government was feeble in the extreme, and he was at last compelled to
                    abdicate by Isaac Comnenus, who had defeated his army in Phrygia (August 1057).
                    He also spent the rest of his life in a monastery.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Michael</hi> VII. (Ducas or Parapinaces) was the eldest son
                    of Constantine XI. Ducas, by whom along with his brothers Andronicus I. and
                    Constantine XII. he was invested with the title of Augustus; this joint
                    succession took place in 1067, but in 1071 it suited the policy of the uncle
                    Joannes Caesar to make Michael sole emperor. For <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n240/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0916-0240-0227"/> this position Michael, whose “character was
                    degraded, rather than ennobled, by the virtues of a monk and the learning of a
                    sophist,” was by no means fitted, and at length two generals of the name of
                    Nicephorus, surnamed Bryennius and Botaniates, simultaneously rebelled against
                    him in 1078; with hardly a struggle he resigned the purple and retired into a
                    monastery, where he afterwards received the title of archbishop of Ephesus.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Michael</hi> VIII. (Palaeologus), born in 1234, was the son
                    of Andronicus Palaeologus Comnenus and Irene Angela the granddaughter of Alexius
                    Angelus, emperor of Constantinople. At an early age he rose to distinction, and
                    ultimately became commander of the French mercenaries in the employment of the
                    emperors of Nicaea. A few days after the death of Theodore Lascaris II. in 1259,
                    Michael, by the assassination of Muzalon (which he is believed but not proved to
                    have encouraged), succeeded to the guardianship, shared with the patriarch
                    Arsenius, of the young emperor John Lascaris, then a lad of only eight years.
                    Afterwards invested with the title of “despot,” he was finally proclaimed
                    joint-emperor, and crowned alone at Nicaea on January 1, 1260. In the following
                    year (July 1261) Constantinople fell into the hands of the Caesar Alexius
                    Strategopulus, and Michael, having got himself crowned anew in the church of St
                    Sophia, caused his boy colleague to be blinded and sent into banishment. For
                    this last act he was excommunicated by Arsenius, and the ban was not removed
                    until six years afterwards (1268), on the accession of a new patriarch. In 1263
                    and 1264 respectively Michael, with the help of Urban IV., concluded peace with
                    Villehardouin, prince of Achaia, and Michael, despot of Epirus, who had
                    previously been incited by the pope to attack him; the friendly intervention had
                    been secured by a promise on the emperor’s part to help forward the reunion of
                    the Eastern and Western churches. In 1269 Charles of Sicily, aided by John of
                    Thessaly, again made war with the alleged purpose of restoring Baldwin to the
                    throne of Constantinople, and pressed Michael so hard that ultimately, yielding
                    to the importunities of Gregory X., he caused the deputies of the Eastern church
                    to attend the council of Lyons (1274) and there accept the “filioque” and papal
                    supremacy. The union thus brought about between the two churches was, however,
                    extremely distasteful to the Greeks, and the persecution of his “schismatic”
                    subjects to which the emperor was compelled to resort weakened his power so much
                    that Martin IV. was tempted to enter into alliance with Charles of Anjou and the
                    Venetians for the purpose of reconquering Constantinople. The invasion, however,
                    failed, and Michael so far had his revenge in the “Sicilian Vespers,” which he
                    helped to bring about. He died in Thrace in December 1282, and was succeeded by
                    his son Andronicus II.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Michael</hi> IX. (Palaeologus) was the son of Andronicus
                    II., and was associated with him on the throne from 1295, but predeceased him
                    (1320).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
