<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0916-0318-0301-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">MILK</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 16, page 301</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="103" ref="lcsh1910:b48w3881j">Milking</term>
                    <term n="103" ref="lcsh1910:b46688m79">Milk</term>
                    <term n="20" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term n="19" ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0mz69">Cream</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4q52fd7q">Butter</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4c24qn5t">Atlases</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b46w96h5f">Quadrumana</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204558">Denmark</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204556">Norway</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:843083">Butter</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="103" ref="fasttopic:1021745">Milking</term>
                    <term n="103" ref="fasttopic:1021615">Milk</term>
                    <term n="20" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term n="19" ref="fasttopic:882342">Cream</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n318/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MILK</label> is the fluid secreted by the mammary glands of
                    the division of vertebrate animals called <hi rend="italic">Mammalia.</hi> These
                    glands are in a rudimentary form in the Monotremes. In <hi rend="italic"
                    >Oτnitlιoτlιynclιus</hi> there is no nipple, but the mouth and tongue are
                    closely applied over the area on which the ducts open, and the fluid is
                    withdrawn by suction on the part of the young and compression of the gland by
                    the mother. In <hi rend="italic">Echidna</hi> the ducts of the gland open into a
                    small pouch, foreshadowing the larger pouches of marsupials. In Marsupials the
                    glands are more compact, and have a greater number of lobules. They are found
                    behind the marsupial depressions or those of the pouch; they are not fewer than
                    two on each side nor more than thirteen, six on each side and one midway. The
                    ducts, long and slender during lactation, open on a nipple which is covered by a
                    reflexion of the skin at the back of the pouch, thus forming a kind of hood or
                    sheath. The nipple is protruded beyond the hood during lactation, and is much
                    elongated. The number of these nipples bears a relation to the number of young
                    at a birth; thus the kangaroo, with one at a birth, has four nipples (two,
                    generally the anterior pair, being in use), whilst the Virginian opossum, which
                    produces six or more at a birth, has thirteen nipples. Rodents show a
                    corresponding provision for the nourishment of the young in the number of
                    nipples. A seeming exception is the common guinea-pig, which frequently has
                    eight, ten, or twelve young at intervals of two or three months, and yet the
                    mother has only two teats to serve them, turn and turn about; the original stock
                    of the domestic species breeds, however, only once annually, and has but one to
                    two young, so the domestic variety is a curious anomaly due to the artificial
                    circumstances of its life. In the porcupines there are two nipples, one midway
                    between the fore and hind leg, and the other midway between this and the base of
                    the fore leg. In the coypu, a creature often carrying its young on its back
                    whilst it swims across rivers, the teats project from the flanks near the
                    shoulders, and are of consideιable length, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n319/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0916-0319-0302"/> so that the young readily reach them. The <hi
                    rend="italic">Insectivora</hi> have, as a rule, more nipples than are found in
                    any other order. Thus in the tenrec <hi rend="italic">(Centetes')</hi> there are
                    as many as twenty-two, and they are rarely fewer than fourteen, spread out in
                    pairs from the pectoral to the inguinal regions. There are ten teats in the
                    common hedgehog, six to eight in moles and shrews, two in sloths and armadillos.
                    In <hi rend="italic">Cetacea</hi> there are two long, narrow, flat glands lying
                    between the dermal and abdominal muscles, with the subcutaneous blubber
                    separating them from the skin. The peculiarity of the arrangement in these
                    animals, where suckling is performed under water, is the large size of the
                    central duct, which acts as a kind of reservoir, so that the young may obtain a
                    considerable supply in a very short time. It would appear also that when
                    suckling takes place the nose of the young is above the surface of the water.
                    Among Ungulates, in the elephant the glands and teats are between the fore legs;
                    in the rhinoceros they are inguinal; in the mare and ass the glands are two in
                    number, and are found between the thighs, about 9 inches in front of the vulva;
                    the tapir has two inguinal nipples, the peccary two ventral and two inguinal,
                    the wild sow eight nipples, whilst in the domestic breeds there are at least
                    ten, extending from the pectoral to the inguinal regions. Ruminants have the
                    glands aggregated into a round mass in the inguinal region, pendulous in full
                    function, divisible into two glands, each of which has a large reservoir. When
                    in use the teats, one pair or two pairs being the number, in connexion with the
                    reservoirs become so large as to receive the special name of “udder.” All the
                    deer tribe, camels, the giraffe, and all kinds of cows have four teats; most
                    antelopes and the gazelles have two teats, whilst a few antelopes have four. As
                    to <hi rend="italic">Carnivora,</hi> the felines have usually six nipples; the
                    wolf, jackal, fox, dog have usually eight; the seals and the walrus have four,
                    the otters two, the weasels six, the bears six; and in the kinkajou <hi
                    rend="italic">(Cercoleptes)</hi> the number is reduced to two. Amongst <hi
                    rend="italic">Quadrumana,</hi> the aye-aye <hi rend="italic">(fJhiromys')</hi>
                    has only one pair of nipples, about an inch and a half in front of the vulva;
                    many lemurs have in addition to those a pectoral pair; in all the platyrhine and
                    catarhine <hi rend="italic">Quadrumana</hi> there is only one pair of glands,
                    restricted to the pectoral region. Here the teats are between the fore legs, and
                    the young clings to the mother’s breast in human fashion, but there is no
                    protrusion of the breast as in the human being. (For further details see Owen’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Anatomy of Vertebrates,</hi> vol. iii. p. 769.)</p>
                <p>In the human race the glands are two in number, forming, along with the skin and
                    fat, two rounded eminences, one on each side, on the front of the thorax. They
                    extend from the third to the sixth or seventh rib, and from the side of the
                    sternum to the axilla. In the centre projects a small conical body, the <hi
                    rend="italic">nipple.</hi> Around the nipple is a coloured circle, or <hi
                    rend="italic">areola,</hi> which is darker during pregnancy, and even in women
                    who have borne children than in the virgin state. The surface of the nipple is
                    wrinkled, and with a magnifying glass is seen to be covered with papillae. It is
                    perforated by numerous openings, the mouths of the milk ducts. The tissue of the
                    nipple contains numerous minute blood-vessels, and it has at the base muscular
                    fibres arranged in concentric circles and in radiating bands. It has much of the
                    character of erectile tissue, as in the <hi rend="italic">corpora cavernosa</hi>
                    of the penis, becoming turgid, firm, and prominent from excitement. The base of
                    the gland lies on the pectoral muscle, a thin layer of fascia intervening. The
                    surface is covered with fat, which gives it the smooth rounded outline. It is
                    amply supplied with blood by the long thoracic artery, some other minute
                    branches of the axillary artery, the internal intercostal artery, and the
                    subjacent intercostals. The nerves come from the anterior and middle intercostal
                    cutaneous branches, and the nipple is especially sensitive. The gland is
                    composed of numerous lobes bound together by connective and adipose tissue, and
                    each lobe is formed of smaller lobules. Each lobe has an excretory duct, and
                    these ducts, from fifteen to twenty in number, converge towards the areola,
                    beneath which they are dilated so as to form sinuses from ⅜th to ∣-th of an inch
                    in calibre. From these sinuses arise the ducts which open on the surface of the
                    nipple. The general structure will be understood by referring to the
                    accompanying figures, along with the description.</p>
                <p>When a duct is traced into the gland, it is found to subdivide into smaller
                    ducts, and these into still smaller, until the smallest ductlet is reached,
                    round the end of which are clustered several <hi rend="italic">alveoli</hi> or
                    pouches. Each alveolus has a wall, lined with epithelium cells. In the wall of
                    the alveolus there are capillary blood-vessels which bring the blood near the
                    cells. By this blood the cells are nourished. There is a minute cavity in the
                    centre of each alveolus into which cells or their products can accumulate. There
                    can be no doubt that the formation of the milk globule takes place in these
                    cells. Whilst milk is not being formed the cells have a granular appearance, and
                    the lumen or central cavity of the alveolus is small; but during secretion the
                    cavity is enlarged and shows a few milk globules, whilst one or more milk
                    globules can be seen in the interior of the cell. If the milk globule in the
                    cell be very large, the nucleus of the cell is pressed outwards and the
                    protoplasm of the cell is reduced to a thin covering, over the globule, at this
                    stage presenting a striking resemblance to a fat cell containing an oil globule.
                    Thus each milk globule is formed in the protoplasm of the epithelium cell, and
                    even at an early stage each milk globule consists of a minute drop of fat or oil
                    surrounded by a thin albuminous envelope. It has not been clearly ascertained
                    whether epithelial cells, after having secreted milk globules, degenerate and
                    fall off, or whether they have the power of ejecting the milk globules. The
                    fluid constituents of milk (water holding <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n320/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0916-0320-0303"/> salts in solution) may be separated from the
                    blood by a kind of filtration under blood pressure, as is the case in other
                    secretory processes. The origin of the sugar of milk and of the casein is
                    unknown. (For a description of the minute structure of the milk gland, see
                    Klein’s <hi rend="italic">Atlas of Histology,</hi> p.</p>
                <p>300, and references.) At the beginning of lactation the milk is rich in large
                    irregularly-f or med cor puscles ( fig. 3, <hi rend="italic">a, a, a)</hi>
                    called <hi rend="italic">colostrum</hi> corpuscles. These are contractile
                    bodies, slowly changing their form and squeezing out the oily particles. At
                    first they are the only bodies present, but they are soon replaced by the
                    ordinary milk globules. Such globules have bright refractive edges, the surface
                    is smooth, they vary in size from κτ⅛τytlι to <hi rend="subscript"> π7</hi> ⅛
                    <hi rend="subscript"> π</hi> th of an inch in diameter, and each consists of a
                    drop of fatty matter surrounded by a layer of albumen (“Ascherson’s
                    membrane”).</p>
                <p>A secretion of milk takes place in newly-born children, from the fourth to the
                    eighth day, and also in rare cases in men (Hermann’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Physiology,</hi> p. 158). During gestation in the human being the mammary
                    glands increase in size; immediately after the birth of the child active
                    secretion commences; and usually it is on the stoppage of the secretion, ten
                    months afterwards, that the process of menstruation, which has been arrested by
                    impregnation, again is re-established.</p>
                <p>The secretion of milk is undoubtedly affected by the nervous system, as is shown
                    by fear or mental distress arresting or injuring the quality of the secretion,
                    and by the “rush” or feeling of fulness in the breast experienced by the mother
                    when the child’s mouth touches the nipple, or even when she sees her offspring.
                    The nervous mechanism, however, is unknown, as it has been observed that
                    secretion may continue even after section of all the nerves known to pass to the
                    gland. The nature of the diet has a marked influence on the quality of the
                    secretion. Thus the amount of casein and of fat is greater during an animal than
                    during a vegetable diet. Fatty foods do not seem to increase the amount of fat
                    or butter; an ample supply of carbo-hydrates (starches and sugars) increases the
                    amount of sugar. These facts indicate that most if not all of the constituents
                    of milk are formed from changes in the protoplasm of the epithelial cells. In
                    some women the milk is deficient in fat and casein, and consequently is less
                    nutritious. Prolonged lactation diminishes the amount of fat and sugar without
                    materially affecting the amount of albuminous matter; but the milk is less
                    nutritious and is unfit for the child. The occurrence of menstruation during
                    lactation also deteriorates the milk. (j. <hi rend="smallcaps">g. μ.)</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Milk as Food.</hi></p>
                <p>The milk of various domesticated animals is more or less used by man for food.
                    The milk of the cow, which may be taken as typical of all others, and is indeed
                    by far the most important and valuable of all, is, when newly drawn, an opaque
                    white fluid, with a yellowish tinge, soft, bland, and sweetish to the taste, and
                    possessed of a faintly animal odour. This odour, according to Schreiner, is due
                    to the presence of sulphuretted hydrogen, and disappears after a short exposure.
                    The specific gravity of milk ordinarily ranges from 1Ό29 to 1Ό33, very seldom
                    reaching 1Ό35 or falling so low as 1Ό27. In chemical constitution it consists of
                    an emulsion of fatty globules (cream) in a watery alkaline solution of casein,
                    and a variety of sugar, peculiar to milk, called lactose. The fat (which when
                    separated we know as butter) and the lactose constitute the carbonaceous portion
                    of the milk regarded as food. The casein, which forms the principal constituent
                    of cheese, and a certain proportion of albumen which is present, form the
                    nitrogenous, while the complex saline substances and water are the mineral
                    constituents. These various substances are present in the proportions which
                    render milk a perfect and typical food suitable to the wants of the young of the
                    various animals for whom it is provided by nature. The milk of all animals, so
                    far as is’ known, contains them, although they are present in somewhat different
                    proportions. It is probable that the milk of ruminants possesses certain
                    physical and physiological distinctions from that of non-ruminant animals, which
                    will account for the virtues attributed to the milk of the ass and mare. The
                    following table exhibits the chemical constitution of the kinds of milk most
                    frequently used by man :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>Cow.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Goat.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Ewe.<note anchored="true"
                            place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Ewe’s milk is exceedingly variable,
                            especially in its percentage of fat. The above analysis is one of nine
                            by Dr Voelcker, in which the fat was found to range from about 2 to 12f
                            per cent.</p></note></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Mare.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Ass.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Human</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Winter Blyth.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Cameron.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1 Voelcker.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Voelcker.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Cameron.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Chevallier and</p><p>Henry</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Gerber.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Water</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>86 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi>
                            87</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>87’00</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>84’48</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>83’70</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>90’310</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>91’65</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>88’02</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Fat</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3’50</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4’00</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6’11</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4’45</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’055</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’11</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2’90</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Casein and albumin...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>j 4’75</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4’10</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3’94</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5Ί6</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’953</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’82</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Γ60</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Sugar</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4Ό0</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4’28</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4’68</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5’73</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6’285</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6Ό8</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7’03</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Ash</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’70</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’62</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’79</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’96</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’369</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’34</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’31</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>In addition to these constituents milk contains small proportions of the gases
                    carbonic acid, sulphuretted hydrogen, nitrogen, and oxygen, and minute
                    quantities of other principles, the constant presence and essential conditions
                    of which have not been determined. These consist of galactin and lactochrome,
                    substances peculiar to milk, discovered by Winter Blyth, with certain animal
                    principles such as leucin, pepton, kreatin, tyrosin, &amp;c. The salts in milk
                    consist, according to the average of numerous analyses by Fleischmann, of the
                    following constituents :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Phosphoric acid</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>28’31</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Potash</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>17’34</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Chlorine</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>16’34</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Magnesia</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4Ό7</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Lime</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>27’00</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Ferric oxide</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’62</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Soda</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>10’00</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Milk thus is not to be regarded as a definite chemical compound nor even as a
                    mixture of bodies in fixed and invariable proportions. Not only does the milk of
                    different races and breeds of cows vary within comparatively wide limits; the
                    milk of the same animal is subject to extensive fluctuation. The principal
                    causes of variation in the individual are age, period of lactation, nature and
                    amount of food, state of health, and treatment, such as frequency of milking,
                    &amp;c. The following table indicates the range of normal variations:—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Water</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>90’00 to</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>83’65</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Fat</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2’80 „</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4’50</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Casein and albumin</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3’30 „</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5’55</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Sugar</p><p>Ash</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3’00 „</p><p><hi rend="italic"
                            >0’70</hi><hi rend="italic">„</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5’50</p><p>0’80</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The average quantity of milk yielded by cows is also highly variable, both in
                    individuals and breeds. As a rule the smaller breeds of cows yield a small
                    amount of milk rich in cream (butter fat), while the yield of the larger breed
                    is greater in quantity, but comparatively deficient in cream. A good milch cow
                    should yield in a milk-giving period of from eight to nine months about <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n321/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0916-0321-0304"/> 500 gallons of milk, from which nearly 500 B⅛ of
                    cheese or 200 lb of butter would be obtainable.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Dairy Treatment.—</hi> Cows are commonly milked by hand two or
                    three times a day. A milking machine of American origin, which was introduced
                    about the year 1862, has been entirely abandoned. The milk should be drawn from
                    the animals in as clean a condition as possible, but notwithstanding every
                    precaution some amount of hair and epithelial and other animal débris invariably
                    enters the milk-pail. It has therefore to be immediately strained through a
                    sieve with fine wire-cloth or hair strainer. As milk is peculiarly susceptible
                    of taint, and absorbs odours of all kinds with great avidity, it is of the
                    utmost consequence that all vessels in which it is placed or kept should be so
                    made as to be easily purified and that they should be kept scrupulously clean.
                    In Switzerland milk is strained with most beneficial effect through sprigs of
                    washed fir tops, which inserted loosely and uprightly into the hole of a funnel
                    arrest all hair, skin, clots, and slimy matter on the acicular leaves. The milk
                    drains through in a clean condition with a fresh slightly aromatized flavour
                    favourable to its keeping. A fresh sprig is used on each occasion of straining
                    milk, so that there is freedom from the risk of taint which arises through the
                    use of imperfectly cleaned wire gauze. The milk must be removed from the
                    cow-house as quickly as possible; and, if intended for use as new milk and for
                    sale in the neighbourhood of the dairy, it may at once be put up for delivery.
                    But if it has to travel a distance, or if it is to be kept for creaming or
                    cheese-making, it should be rapidly cooled down, and kept in a cool airy
                    milk-room if practicable, surrounded with fresh cold water.</p>
                <p>The ordinary method of separating cream either for direct use or for butter
                    making is by allowing it to form on the surface and skimming it off with a broad
                    flat spoon; but ingenious adaptations of centrifugal machines—of which Laval’s
                    separator is one of the best known—have been introduced for the purpose of
                    effecting the rapid and complete separation of the cream. The centrifugal force
                    of such machines throws the denser portions of the fluid towards the sides of a
                    rapidly revolving cylinder, collecting the cream on an inner layer, which is
                    carried off by one channel while the impoverished milk escapes by another. The
                    Laval separator gives very rich cream, as will be seen from the following
                    analyses by Voelcker:—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Ordinary Cream.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Cream by Separator.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Skimmed Milk by Laval
                            Separator.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Ordinary Skimmed Milk.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Water</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>77’30</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>66’12</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>90 ’82</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>89’25</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Butter fat</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>15’45</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>27’69</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’31</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’12</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Casein</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3’40</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2’69</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3’31</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3’69</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Milk sugar</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3T5</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3’03</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4’77</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5Ί6</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Mineral matter</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’70</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’47</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>O∙79</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’78</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>After being kept some time, depending principally on the temperature at which it
                    is maintained, milk begins to turn sour owing to the formation of lactic acid,
                    by a process of fermentation, at the expense of the lactose or milk sugar. The
                    acid so developed causes a coagulation of the casein, and the milk separates
                    into a solid white curd, and a thin transparent yellow milk serum or whey. These
                    changes can to a certain extent be artificially produced, hindered, and
                    controlled. The following are the results of analyses by Fleischmann :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="3" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">Constituents
                            of</hi> 100 <hi rend="italic">Parts of Sweet Milk.</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>. 3’56</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>butter.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>20’00 cream &lt;</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>16’30</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>buttermilk.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi>
                            0Ί4</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>loss.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>i 7’93</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>curd.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>79’70 skimmed milk &lt;</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>71’45</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>whey.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>’ 0’32</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>loss.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’30 loss</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’30</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>loss.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="7" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">Relative
                            Composition of Milk and its Products.</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Water.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Fat.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Casein.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Albumin.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Milk Sugar.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Ash.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Whole milk</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>87’60</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3’98</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3’02</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’40</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4’30</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’70</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Cream</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>77’30</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>15’45</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3’20</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’20</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3’15</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi>
                            70</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Skim-milk</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>90’34</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1Ό0</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2’87</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’45</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4’63</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0 ’ 71</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Butter</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>14’89</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>82Ό2</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’97</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’28</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’28</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’56</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Buttermilk</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>91’00</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’80</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3’50</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’20</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3’80</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’70</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Curd</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>59’30</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6’43</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>24’22</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3’53</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5Ό1</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’51</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Whey</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>94’00</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’35</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’40</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’40</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4’55</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’60</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The simplest and most advantageous form in which milk can be disposed of as a
                    commercial product is by its sale as sweet or new milk, and it is in this manner
                    that the greater proportion of the milk produced within the reach of large
                    centres of population is disposed of. New milk, cream, and skimmed milk are the
                    only primary forms in which milk is sent into the market. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Cheese</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Butter</hi> have been dealt with in
                    separate articles (⅛.v.). Whey, the yellow liquid remaining after the separation
                    of the curd in cheese making, is a source of milk sugar, employed to a limited
                    extent in pharmacy; but it is principally used for feeding pigs. The buttermilk
                    which remains after separating butter is a most wholesome and nutritious article
                    of food.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Preservation of Milk.-</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    r</hi><hi rend="italic">ι</hi><hi rend="italic">∖∖</hi><hi rend="italic">e</hi>
                    numerous methods which have been proposed for the preservation of milk in a
                    condition fit for use over a lengthened period resolve themselves into (1)
                    chemical treatment with alkaline salts and antiseptic bodies, (2) physical
                    treatment, such as cooling or icing, boiling, and aeration, and (3) condensation
                    with or without the addition of a preservative agent. All systems of
                    preservation, however, are subject to serious disadvantages either from their
                    serving their purpose for too limited a time, or their interfering with the
                    natural constitution and properties of the milk. Of all preservatives cold is
                    the most efficient and least objectionable. It has been shown by Soxhlet <hi
                    rend="italic">(Dingier's Polytech. Journal,</hi> ccxxiii. 329) that milk cooled
                    by ice-water remains sweet and unaltered for fourteen days, but after that time
                    acquires a rancid taste. After twenty-eight days it coagulates on boiling owing
                    to the presence of acids resulting from the oxidation of the cream, and in
                    thirty-four days it coagulates even in the ice-water. It is also found that milk
                    which has undergone aeration with atmospheric air has its keeping properties
                    much improved. The aeration is effected by allowing the milk to fall from some
                    height in a state of fine division by passing it through the meshes of a sieve.
                    By another method air cooled by passing over ice is blown through the milk.</p>
                <p>Milk keeps sweet for a longer time when boiled, but the smell, taste, and other
                    properties are affected, partly owing to the escape of gases mixed with it when
                    fresh. The unpleasant flavour communicated by boiling can be avoided if the
                    action takes place in a closed vessel and the milk is immediately cooled down in
                    a refrigerator connected therewith. In the case of any suspicion of taint in
                    milk either from disease in the cow, contamination from unhealthy persons, or
                    the use of infected water in cleaning vessels, boiling is also strongly to be
                    recommended, as it effectually destroys the germs of disease, in the carrying
                    and spreading of which milk is a most active agent. It is with the utmost
                    difficulty that boiled milk can be coagulated by means of rennet; but by
                    treatment with acid it coagulates more rapidly and freely than if unboiled.</p>
                <p>Of the various chemical compounds which have been suggested and more or less used
                    for preserving milk, the most successful hitherto has been salicylic acid, which
                    has the advantage of being tasteless and inodorous. By briskly stirring in
                    rather less than 2 grains to a pint of milk, it can be kept liquid and sweet in
                    a temperature of from 65° to 68° Fahr, for twelve hours, and at 55° Fahr, for a
                    whole day. If 4 grains be used to a pint, coagulation in the higher temperature
                    is delayed from two or three days, and at the lower temperature the milk may be
                    kept good from three to five days. Boracic acid and borax are also employed by
                    dairymen, the former being known as glacialine salt. The presence of any
                    chemical antiseptic in milk is, however, at best a matter of doubtful
                    advantage.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Condensation. —</hi> Milk is now treated on a large scale by a
                    process of concentration, the product of which comes into the market in two
                    forms—as “plain condensed milk” and as “preserved milk.” The credit of
                    originating the industry is due to Mr Gail Borden of White Plains, New York, who
                    began his experiments about 1849. In 1851 he introduced his plain condensed
                    milk, which is simply milk from which between three-fourths and four-fifths of
                    the water has been removed, and in 1861 he rendered important services to the
                    army in the field by supplying preserved milk which was in <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n322/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0916-0322-0305"/> effect milk similarly concentrated, with a
                    proportion of sugar added, and hermetically sealed in tin cans. The manufacture
                    was transplanted to Switzerland in 1865, after which condensing factories were
                    established in England, Ireland, Denmark, Bavaria, Norway, and elsewhere. With
                    the introduction of the condensing trade there has also been associated the
                    factory system of dealing with dairy products, by which the milk of many dairies
                    is carried to one centre and dealt with either for condensing or for cheese or
                    butter making. The following epitome of the process of condensing milk is irom a
                    paper by Mr Willard of Cornell university, New York <hi rend="italic">{Jour.
                    Roy. Agric. Soc.,</hi> 2d series, vol. viii., 1872). The milk when received at
                    the factory is first passed, he says, “through a strainer to the receiving vat;
                    from this it is conducted eff, going through another strainer into the heating
                    cans, each holding about 20 gallons; these cans are set in hot water, and the
                    milk is held in them till it reaches a temperature of 150° to 175° Fahr.; it
                    then goes through another strainer into a large vat, at the bottom of which is a
                    coil of copper pipe, through which steam is conducted, and here the milk is
                    heated up to the boiling point. Then the best quality of white granulated sugar
                    is added, in the proportion of 1∣ lb of sugar to the gallon of milk, when it is
                    drawn into the vacuum-pan having a capacity of condensing 3000 quarts or more at
                    a time. The milk remains in the vacuum-pan subjected to steam for about three
                    hours, during which time about 75 per cent, of its bulk in water is removed,
                    when it is drawn off into cans, holding 40 quarts each. The cans are only
                    partially filled, and are then set in a large vat containing cold water, the
                    water being of a height equal to that of the milk in the cans. Here it is
                    stirred until the temperature of the condensed fluid is reduced to a little
                    below 70°; it is then turned into large drawing-cans with faucets, in order to
                    facilitate the filling of the small cans, .... holding 1 lb each, which are
                    immediately soldered to exclude the air.”</p>
                <p>In the case of plain condensed milk the concentration is usually carried farther
                    than is practised in preparing the preserved milk, it being evaporated down to
                    between one-fourth and one-fifth of the original bulk. It is not put up in
                    sealed tins, being intended for immediate use, and keeps sweet only for a few
                    days, varying with the state of the weather, whereas the sugared milk in sealed
                    cans keeps for years. The large amount, however, of cane sugar added to
                    preserved milk seriously disturbs its balance of proportion as a perfect food,
                    and renders it unfit to be used alone in a dilute state as a substitute for
                    mother’s milk by infants, a purpose for which it is largely employed. It should
                    also be observed that the relative proportion of fat is small, the milk being
                    partially skimmed before it is operated on, so that the statement that preserved
                    milk diluted with a small proportion of water is equal to cream is not to be
                    relied on. Preserved milk, rich in cream, has always a more or less rancid oily
                    taste, and cannot be obtained so sweet and even in flavour as that largely
                    deprived of fat. According to a German patent of E. Klebs in Prague, plain
                    condensed milk may be preserved by adding to every 100 litres of the original
                    milk a solution of 50 grains of benzoate of magnesium in one litre of water.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Adulteration.—</hi> Practically the invariable mode of
                    sophisticating milk for sale consists in the addition of water and in the
                    subtraction of cream,—in other words, passing off skimmed or partly skimmed as
                    new milk. Now and again there are found certain little refinements on these
                    simple frauds, such as adding a quantity of sugar to correct the specific
                    gravity, flour or starch to increase opacity, and a touch of colouring matter to
                    cover the bluish tinge which would betray skimmed milk. In the United Kingdom no
                    official standard of what constitutes pure milk has been promulgated, but the
                    so-called Somerset House standard has been generally recognized in law courts.
                    According to this, new milk should contain as a minimum of solids not fat 8 ’6
                    per cent, and of fat 2 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 5 per cent., and of water
                    a maximum of 88‘9 per cent. The most satisfactory manner of discovering the
                    probable genuineness of a sample of milk is by chemical analysis carried
                    sufficiently far to determine the amount of fat and of other solids present.
                    Numerous attempts have been made to place in the hands of dairymen, dealers, and
                    consumers of milk a trustworthy method of estimating the condition and value of
                    the article by simple quantitive tests for cream or fat—at once the most
                    valuable constituent and one the presence of which in average proportion is
                    indicative of the quality of the whole. The simplest but at the same time the
                    least trustworthy and efficient method is by means of the so-called
                    “creamometer,” which consists merely of a graduated glass tube in which a
                    measured amount of milk is placed and the amount of cream it throws up is read
                    off by means of the scale. Specific gravity determinations have by themselves no
                    significance, seeing milk deprived of its cream can by dilution with water be
                    brought to correspond exactly with the original milk. But by a combination of
                    two methods,—first taking the specific gravity, next observing the yield of
                    cream by the “creamometer,” and finally taking the specific gravity of the milk
                    deprived of cream, regard being had to the temperature of the milk in these
                    observations, an approximately accurate idea of the value of a sample may be
                    obtained. Among so-called “lactoscopes,” the operations of which are based on
                    the fact that milk rich in cream is a much more opaque fluid than that from
                    which cream has been taken or to which water is added, that invented by
                    Professor Feser of Munich is one of the simplest and most useful. It consists of
                    a glass tube open at the upper end and attenuated at its lower extremity. Into
                    this narrower portion is fused a small cylindrical rod of opaque milk glass on
                    which black lines are marked. These lines are invisible when the lower portion
                    of the tube is filled with a measured quantity of milk, but on addition ol water
                    they become visible. When the black lines become by the gradual admixture of
                    water perfectly distinct, the richness of the milk in cream globules is
                    indicated by the height to which the mixture of milk and water has risen in the
                    wide portion of the tube, which has engraved on it a scale showing on one side
                    the amount of water added and on the other the proportion of cream equivalent to
                    the transparency resulting from such addition.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Statistics.—</hi> In the year 1878 it was calculated by Mr J.
                    C. Morton that the total yield of milk from the 2,250,000 cows and heifers in
                    milk or in calf in England and Scotland amounted to about 1,000,000,000 gallons
                    yearly. He assumed that about one-sixth of that quantity (167,000,000 gallons)
                    went to feed calves, and that the daily consumption of the population was
                    1,000,000 gallons, being rather more than a quarter of a pint per head, which
                    accounts for 365,000,000, still leaving 468,000,000 gallons to be used for
                    butter and cheese making. Two-thirds of this quantity, or 312,000,000 gallons,
                    Mr Morton assumes was usedfor cheese-making, yielding 2,800,000 cwts. of cheese
                    (rather less than 1 tb per gallon of milk), and the remainder, 156,000,000
                    gallons, of milk devoted to butter-making would yield 530,000 lb of butter, or 1
                    lb of butter for every 21 pints of milk. In these figures no account is taken of
                    Ireland, whence at that period there were sent to England alone yearly 3,500,000
                    lb of salted butter. In June 1882 the number of cows and heifers in milk and in
                    calf in Great Britain did not vary greatly from the number on which Mr Morton’s
                    estimate for 1878 was based, being 2,267,175, whilst in Ireland the number was
                    1,398,905, making the total for the United Kingdom 3,682,317. If we take
                    approximately Mr Morton’s data as the basis of calculation, the 3,682,317 milk
                    cows and heifers in the United Kingdom would yield, at 440 gallons per head,
                    1,620,219,480 gallons of milk. Further, assuming that one-sixth of this is
                    consumed by calves, one-third consumed by population, one-third used for
                    cheese-making, and one-sixth used for butter-making, we have as the yield of
                    cheese 4,846,000 cwts. and as the yield of butter 920,000 cwts. As Ireland is
                    much more a butter-producing than a cheese-yielding country, the quantity of
                    cheese made is probably overestimated in these figures, and the amount of butter
                    made is correspondingly understated. To bring out the consumption of dairy
                    products for the year the following imports must be added:—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Cwts.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Value.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Cheese</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1,692,495</p><p>2,167,428</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"
                            ><p>£4,742,368</p><p>11,339,226</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Butter (including
                            butterine)</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Thus we find the total supply of cheese to the United Kingdom in 1882 was
                    6,538,495 cwts., and of butter the supply was 3,087,428 cwts. Estimating the
                    home produce of both articles at the same value as the imports, the cheese
                    supply cost £18,320,000, and the butter £16,150,000. Adding to these the
                    probable cost of the milk consumed as such (say 550,000,000 gallons at Is. per
                    gallon = £27,500,000), we have for the year 1882 in round numbers £62,000,000
                    expended on dairy produce within the United Kingdom.</p>
                <p>The total number of milch cows at present (1883) in the United States is stated
                    at 15,000,000, which, taking the 440 gallons basis, yield annually 6,600,000,000
                    gallons, or nearly 30,000,000 tons of milk. In America the factory system of
                    treating milk has attained much greater dimensions than in Europe, and that
                    perfection of treatment, combined with the cheapness of raising and feeding
                    stock, enables the American companies to enter the European markets with large
                    quantities of cheese and other dairy products of uniformly good quality which
                    find a ready and remunerative sale.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Koumiss.—</hi> Under this name is properly understood a
                    fermented drink prepared from mare’s milk by the Tartar tribes of the Russian
                    empire and by all the nomad races of the northern parts of Asia. It is made by
                    diluting mare’s milk with about one-sixth part of its quantity of water, and
                    adding as a ferment about one-eighth part of very sour milk or of old koumiss.
                    This mixture is placed in a wooden vessel which is covered over with a thick
                    cloth, and so left for about twenty-four hours in a moderately warm situation.
                    During that time a thick coagulum rises to the surface, which is thoroughly
                    reincorporated by churning. After standing for another day, the whole mass is
                    again thoroughly churned and mixed up, and in this state it forms new koumiss,
                    having an agreeable subacid taste. The liquor is mostly stored and preserved by
                    the Tartars in skin bottles, in which the fermentation continues developing its
                    alcoholic qualities, and mellowing and improving its taste. Genuine Tartar
                    koumiss has the following composition :—alcohol 3’21, lactic <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n323/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0916-0323-0306"/> acid 0Ί9, sugar 2Ί0, albuminoids Γ86, fat l <hi
                    rend="superscript"> -</hi> 78, salts 0'509, carbonic acid 0'177, and water
                    93'46. A distilled spirit is prepared from koumiss, which is drunk among the
                    Tartars under the name of araca or arsa. Koumiss has of late years come into
                    prominent notice as a remedial agent in cases of pulmonary consumption, and
                    generally as a nutritious form of food easily assimilated by delicate stomachs.
                    It is probable that all its virtues reside in the original milk from which it is
                    prepared, in which case the koumiss can only be regarded as valuable in so far
                    that it is a convenient form under which the essential properties of the milk
                    can be preserved for use. Under the name of koumiss a preparation of cow’s milk
                    is now very generally sold. It is made by adding to each quart of new milk about
                    a tablespoonful of common sugar and brewer’s yeast, allowing the fermentation to
                    proceed a sufficient length, then bottling and corking as in the case of aerated
                    waters. Such a preparation contains about the same proportion of alcohol as
                    genuine koumiss, but a nou-alcoholic variety can also be obtained, made, by a
                    process of natural fermentation, which continuing after bottling develops a
                    large amount of carbonic acid and renders the liquor highly effervescent. (J.
                    PA. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
