<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0916-0784-0755-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">MONMOUTH, James, Duke of</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 16, page 755</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:869839">Commons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0399k">Towers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k224">Baths</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n784/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MONMOUTH, <hi rend="smallcaps">James, Duke of</hi></label>
                    (1649-1685), was the son of Lucy Walters, “a brown, beautiful, bold, but insipid
                    creature,” who became the mistress of Charles II. during his exile at the Hague.
                    He was born at Rotterdam on 9th April 1649. That Charles was his father is more
                    than doubtful, for Lucy Walters had previously lived with Robert Sidney, brother
                    of Algernon, and the boy resembled him very closely. Charles, however, always
                    recognized him as his son, and lavished on him an almost doting affection. Until
                    the Restoration he was placed under the care, first of Lord Crofts, and then of
                    the queen-dowager, receiving his education to the age of nine from Roman
                    Catholics, but thenceforward from Protestant tutors. In July 1662 he was sent
                    for by Charles, and at thirteen was placed under the protection of Lady
                    Castlemaine and in the full tide of the worst influences of the court. No formal
                    acknowledgment of his relation to the king was made until his betrothal to Anne
                    Scott, daughter of the earl of Buccleuch, and the wealthiest heiress of
                    Scotland, whom he married in 1665. During 1663 he was made duke of Orkney, duke
                    of Monmouth, and knight of the Garter, and received honorary degrees at both
                    universities. At court he was treated as a prince of the blood. In 1665 he
                    served with credit under the duke of York in the sanguinary naval battle off
                    Lowestoft. A captaincy in the Life Guards was given him, and in 1670, on the
                    death of Monk, he was made captain-general of the king’s forces. Offices of
                    wealth also were showered upon him, and he was admitted to the privy council. In
                    1670 Monmouth was with the court at Dover, and it is affirmed by Reresby that
                    the mysterious death of Charles’s sister, the duchess of Orleans, was due to her
                    husband’s revenge on the discovery of her intrigue with the duke. It is certain,
                    from an entry by Pepys, that as early as 1666 he had established a character for
                    vice and profligacy. He was the direct author of the attack in December 1670 on
                    Sir John Coventry, and only a few months later received the royal pardon for his
                    share in the wanton murder of a street watchman. De Gramont, in his vivid sketch
                    of Monmouth, after describing the beauty and bodily prowess for which he was
                    celebrated, notices the fatal emptiness and poverty of his mind: “Tous les
                    avantages du corps par-loient pour lui; mais son esprit ne disait pas un petit
                    mot en sa faveur. Il n’avait de sentimens que ce qu’on lui en inspirait.”</p>
                <p>Hitherto Monmouth had been but the spoiled child of a wicked court. Now, however,
                    by no act or will of his own, he began to be a person politically important. As
                    early as 1662 the king’s excessive fondness for him had caused anxiety. Even
                    then the fear of a “difference” between Monmouth and James, duke of York,
                    exercised men’s minds; and every caress or promotion kept the fear alive. Who
                    could tell but that, in default of legitimate issue from his queen, Charles
                    might declare Monmouth himself his lawful son? A civil war would be the certain
                    consequence. Soon after 1670 the matter took a more serious aspect. The
                    anti-popery spirit was rapidly becoming a frenzy, and the succession of James a
                    probability and a terror. Charles was urged to legitimize Monmouth by a
                    declaration of his marriage with Lucy Walters. He returned answer that, much as
                    he loved the duke, he would rather see him hanged at Tyburn than own him for his
                    legitimate son. Every attempt, however, was henceforth made, especially by
                    Shaftesbury, to accustom people to this idea. He was taught to regard himself as
                    the representative of the Protestant interest, and his position was emphasized
                    by James’s second marriage with the Roman Catholic princess Mary of Modena. From
                    this time his popular title was “the Protestant duke.” Charles was induced to
                    confer many prominent employments upon him. The influence of James, however, was
                    strong enough to prevent his obtaining the lord-lieutenancy of Ireland; but he
                    received the command of the 6000 troops who assisted the French in the second
                    Dutch war, and, though without any claims to generalship, behaved with courage
                    in the field. In 1674 he was made “commander-in-chief;” and, in connexion with
                    this, another unsuccessful attempt, graphically described in Clarke’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Life of James,</hi> was made to gain from Charles a tacit
                    admission of his legitimacy. At Shaftesbury’s instance he was placed in command
                    of the army employed in 1675 against the Scottish Covenanters, and was present
                    at Bothwell Bridge (22d June 1679). He was also, at the king’s request, elected
                    chancellor of the university of Cambridge. In 1678, when Charles was driven into
                    war with Louis, Monmouth took the command of the English contingent, and again
                    gained credit for personal courage at the battle of St Denis. On his return to
                    London England was in the throes of the popish terror. The idea of securing the
                    Protestant succession by legitimizing Monmouth again took shape and was eagerly
                    pressed on by Shaftesbury; at the time it seemed possible that success would
                    wait on the audacity.</p>
                <p>The Pensionary parliament was dissolved in January 1678-79, and was succeeded by
                    one still more determined in its anti-popery spirit. To avoid the storm, and to
                    save, if possible, his brother’s interests, Charles instructed him to leave the
                    country. James retired to Brussels, the king having previously signed a
                    declaration that he “never was married, nor gave contract to any woman
                    whatsoever but to my wife Queen Catherine.” In spite of this, Monmouth might
                    naturally now nourish ambitious views. His rival was off the stage; Shaftesbury,
                    his chief supporter, was president of the remodelled privy council; and he
                    himself was the favourite of the city. In the summer of 1679 the king suddenly
                    fell ill, and the dangers of a disputed succession became terribly apparent. The
                    party opposed to Monmouth, or rather to Shaftesbury, easily prevailed upon
                    Charles to consent to his brother’s temporary return. When, after the king’s
                    recovery, James went back to Brussels, he received a promise that Monmouth too
                    should be removed from favour and ordered to leave the country. Accordingly, in
                    September 1679, the latter repaired to Utrecht, while shortly afterwards James’s
                    friends so far gained ground as to obtain for him permission to reside at
                    Edinburgh instead of at Brussels. Within two months of his arrival at Utrecht,
                    Monmouth secretly returned to England, arriving in London on 27th <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n785/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0916-0785-0756"/> November. Shaftesbury had assiduously kept alive
                    the anti-popery agitation, and Monmouth, as the champion of Protestantism, was
                    received with every sign of popular delight. The king appeared to be greatly
                    incensed, deprived him of all his offices, and ordered him to leave the kingdom
                    at once. This he refused to do, and the only notice taken of the disobedience
                    was that Charles forbade him to appear at court.</p>
                <p>It was at this time that the <hi rend="italic">Appeal from the Country to the
                    City,</hi> written by Ferguson, was published, in which the legitimacy was
                    tacitly given up, and in which it was urged that “he that hath the worst title
                    will make the best king.” Now it was too that the exclusionists, who, in the
                    absence of parliament, were deprived of their best basis for agitation,
                    developed the system of petitioning. So promptly and successfully was this
                    answered by the “abhorrers” that Charles, feeling the ground safer under him,
                    recalled James to London,—a step immediately followed by the resignation of the
                    chief Whigs in the council.</p>
                <p>Once more, however, a desperate attempt was made, by the fable of the “black
                    box,” to establish Monmouth’s claims; and once more these claims were met by
                    Charles’s public declarations in the <hi rend="italic">Gazette</hi> that he had
                    never been married but to the queen. Still acting under Shaftesbury’s advice,
                    Monmouth now went upon the first of his progresses in the west of England,
                    visiting the chief members of the country party, and gaining by his open and
                    engaging manner much popularity among the people. In August 1680 James returned
                    to Edinburgh, his right to the succession being again formally acknowledged by
                    Charles. Monmouth at once threw himself more vehemently than ever into the plans
                    of the exclusionists. He spoke and voted for exclusion in the House of Lords,
                    and used language not likely to be forgotten by James when an opportunity should
                    come for resenting it. He was ostentatiously feasted by the city, the stronghold
                    of Shaftesbury’s influence; and it was observed as he drove to dinner that the
                    mark of illegitimacy had been removed from the arms on his coach.</p>
                <p>The year 1681 seemed likely to witness another civil war. The parliament finished
                    a session of hysterical passion by passing a series of resolutions of extreme
                    violence, of which one was that Monmouth should be restored to all his offices
                    and commands; and when Charles summoned a fresh parliament to meet at Oxford the
                    leaders of the exclusionists went thither with troops of armed men. Not until
                    the dissolution of this last parliament on 27th March 1681 did the weakness of
                    Monmouth’s cause appear. In a moment the ground was cut from under the feet of
                    his supporters; their basis for agitation was gone; pamphlets and broadsheets
                    could ill supply the place of a determined and unscrupulous majority of the
                    House of Commons. The deep-seated respect for legitimate descent asserted
                    itself, and a great reaction took place. In November Dryden published <hi
                    rend="italic">Absalom and Achitophel.</hi> Shaftesbury was attacked, but was
                    saved for the time by a favouring jury. Monmouth himself did not escape insult
                    in the street and from the pulpit. He thought it wise to try to make his peace
                    with the king, but he did so in terms which incensed Charles the more. He was
                    forbidden to hold communication with the court; and, when he went in September
                    1682 on a second progress through the western and north-western counties, his
                    proceedings were narrowly watched, and he was at length arrested at Stafford.
                    Severity and extreme lenity were strangely mingled in the treatment he received.
                    He was released on bail, and in February 1683, after the flight and death of
                    Shaftesbury, he openly broke the implied conditions of his bail by paying a
                    third visit to Chichester with Lord Grey and others on pretence of a hunting
                    expedition.</p>
                <p>It is probable that Monmouth never went so far as to think of armed rebellion;
                    but there is little doubt that he had talked over schemes likely to lead to
                    this, and that Shaftesbury had gone further still. The Rye House plot gave an
                    excuse for arresting the Whig leaders; Russell and Sidney were judicially
                    murdered; Monmouth retired to Toddington in Bedfordshire, and was left
                    untouched. Court intrigue favouring him, he succeeded, by the betrayal of his
                    comrades and by two submissive letters, in reconciling himself with the help of
                    Halifax both to the king and to James, though he had the humiliation of seeing
                    his confessions and declarations of penitence published at length in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Gazette.</hi> His character for pettishness and folly was now
                    amply illustrated. He denied that he had given evidence; he then wrote a
                    recantation of the denial. He managed by importunity to get from the king the
                    paper of recantation; and lastly, by the advice of his wife, he offered again to
                    sign the paper which he had withdrawn. Charles heartily despised him, and yet
                    appears to have retained affection for him. His partial return to favour raised
                    the hopes of his partisans; to check these, Algernon Sidney was executed.
                    Monmouth was now subpoenaed to give evidence at the trial of young Hampden. To
                    escape from the difficulties thus opened before him he fled to Holland, probably
                    with Charles’s connivance, and though he once more, in November 1684, visited
                    England, it is doubtful whether he ever again saw the king. From that time till
                    the king’s death he lived with Henrietta Wentworth, his mistress, in Holland and
                    at Brussels.</p>
                <p>The quiet accession of James II. soon brought Monmouth to the crisis of his fate.
                    Though at first desirous of retirement, his character was too weak to withstand
                    the urgency of more determined men. Within two months of Charles’s death he had
                    yielded to the impetuosity of Argyll and others of the exiles, and to vague
                    invitations from England. It is curious, as showing the light in which his
                    claims were viewed by his fellow-conspirators, that one of the terms of the
                    compact between them was that, though Monmouth should lead the expedition, he
                    should not assume the title of king without their consent, and should, if the
                    rebellion were successful, resign it and accept whatever rank the nation might
                    offer. Now, as always, he was but a puppet in other men’s hands.</p>
                <p>On the 2d of May Argyll sailed with three ships to raise the west of Scotland;
                    and three weeks later, with a following of only eighty-two persons, of whom Lord
                    Grey, Fletcher of Saltoun, Wade, and Ferguson, the author of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Appeal from the Country to the City,</hi> were the chief, Monmouth
                    himself set out for the west of England, where, as the stronghold of Protestant
                    dissent and as the scene of his former progresses, he could alone hope for
                    immediate support. Even here, however, there was no movement; and when on 11th
                    June Monmouth’s three ships, having eluded the royal fleet, arrived off Lyme
                    Regis, he landed amid the curiosity rather than the sympathy of the inhabitants.
                    In the market-place his “declaration,” drawn up by Ferguson, was read aloud. In
                    this document James was painted in the blackest colours. Not only was he
                    declared to be the murderer of Essex, but he was directly charged with having
                    poisoned Charles to obtain his crown. Monmouth soon collected an undisciplined
                    body of some 1500 men, with whom he seized Axminster, and entered Taunton.
                    Meanwhile the parliament had declared it treason to assert Monmouth’s
                    legitimacy, or his title to the crown; a reward of £5000 was offered for him
                    dead or alive, and an act of attainder was passed in unusual haste. Troops had
                    been hurriedly sent to meet him, and when he reached Bridgwater Albemarle was
                    already in his rear. From Bridgwater the army marched through Glastonbury to
                    attack Bristol, into which Lord Feversham had hastily thrown a regiment of
                    footguards<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n786/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0916-0786-0757"/>. The attempt, however, miscarried; and, after
                    summoning Bath in vain, Monmouth, with a disordered force, began his retrograde
                    march through Philips-Norton and Frome, continually harassed by Feversham’s
                    soldiers. At the latter place he heard of Argyll’s total rout in the western
                    Highlands. He was now anxious to give up the enterprise, but was overruled by
                    Grey, Wade, and others. On the 3d of July he reached Bridgwater again, with an
                    army little better than a rabble, living at free quarters and behaving with
                    reckless violence. On Sunday the 5th Feversham entered Sedgemoor in pursuit;
                    Monmouth the same night attempted a surprise, but his troops were hopelessly
                    routed. He himself, with Grey and a few others, fled over the Mendip Hills to
                    the New Forest, hoping to reach the coast and escape by sea. The whole country,
                    however, was on the alert, and at midnight on the 8th, within a month of their
                    landing, James heard that the revolt, desperate from the first, was over, and
                    that his rival had been captured close to Ringwood, in Hampshire.</p>
                <p>The poor strain in Monmouth’s character was now shown. On the day of his capture
                    he wrote to James in terms of the most unmanly contrition, ascribing his
                    wrongdoings to the action of others, and imploring an interview. On the 13 th
                    the prisoners reached the Tower, and on the next day Monmouth was allowed to see
                    James. The accounts of this interview are difficult to reconcile in some points,
                    but all agree that Monmouth’s behaviour was unmanly in the extreme. No mercy was
                    shown him, nor did he in the least deserve mercy; he had wantonly attacked the
                    peace of the country, and had cruelly libelled James. The king had not, even in
                    his own mind, any family tie to restrain him from exercising just severity, for
                    he had never believed Monmouth to be the son of any one but Robert Sidney. Two
                    painful interviews followed with the wife for whom he bore no love, and who for
                    him could feel no respect; another imploring letter was sent to the king, and
                    abject protestations and beseechings were made to all whom he saw. He offered,
                    as the last hope, to become a Roman Catholic, and this might possibly have
                    proved successful, but the priests sent by James to ascertain the sincerity of
                    his “conversion” declared that he cared only for his life and not for his
                    soul.</p>
                <p>He met his death on the scaffold with calmness and dignity. In the paper which he
                    left signed, and to which he referred in answer to the questions wherewith the
                    busy bishops plied him, he expressed his sorrow for having assumed the royal
                    style, and at the last moment confessed that Charles had denied to him
                    privately, as he had publicly, that he was ever married to Lucy Walters. He died
                    at the age of thirty-six, on the 15th of July 1685. “Thus ended,” says Evelyn,
                    “this quondam duke, darling of his father and the ladies, being extremely
                    handsome and adroit; an excellent souldier and dancer, a favourite of the
                    people, of an easy nature, debauched by lusts, seduced by crafty knaves, who
                    would have set him up only to make a property, and took the opportunity of the
                    king being of another religion to gather a party of discontented men. He failed
                    and perished.”</p>
                <p>Authorities for Monmouth’s career are, besides the known modern histories,
                    Roberts’s <hi rend="italic">Life</hi> (1844), Evelyn’s and Pepys’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Diaries,</hi> Oldmixon’s <hi rend="italic">History</hi> (1724),
                    James II. ’s <hi rend="italic">Memoirs,</hi> Clarke’s <hi rend="italic">Life of
                    James,</hi> Reresby’s <hi rend="italic">Memoirs,</hi> Sidney’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Diary</hi> (1843), Scott’s notes to <hi rend="italic">Absalom and
                    Achitophel,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Heroic Life,</hi> &amp;c. (1683). For
                    the rebellion, Lord Grey’s <hi rend="italic">Secret History</hi> should be
                    consulted. (0. A. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
