<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0916-0021-0012-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MENSHIKOFF, Alexander Danilovich (9th edition, volume
                    16, page 12)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k06x23n">Cake</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zv9m">Streets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz5d">Youth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vt81">Swedes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:908898">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term ref="fast:843972">Cake</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1139996">Swedes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n21/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MENSHIKOFF, <hi rend="smallcaps">Alexander
                        Danilovich</hi></label> (1672-1729), born at Moscow on the 17th of November
                    (o.s.) 1672, was the son of a poor man, who employed him to sell cakes about the
                    streets of that city. In this humble occupation he attracted the attention of
                    Lefort, one of Peter the Great’s most active co-operators, who was pleased with
                    his sprightliness, and took him into his service. Peter, soon afterwards <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n22/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0916-0022-0013"/> seeing the youth at Lefort’s, was also
                    delighted with him, and took him to be his page. Menshikoff soon became
                    indispensable to the czar, assisting him in his workshop, and displaying signal
                    bravery in the company of his master at the siege of Azoff. He formed one of the
                    suite of Peter during his travels, and worked with him at Saardam and Deptford.
                    Throughout his wars with the Swedes, Menshikoff was the companion of the czar,
                    and greatly distinguished himself. For his gallantry at the battle of the Neva,
                    on the 7th of May (o.s.) 1703, he received the order of St Andrew. In 1704 he
                    was made general, and at the request of the czar created a prince of the Holy
                    Roman Empire. His house on the Vasilii-Ostroff was magnificent; there
                    ambassadors were received, and banquets were given gorgeous with gold and silver
                    plate. Unfortunately there is a dark side to the picture, and the favourite was
                    guilty of extortion to such an extent as to bring him under his master’s
                    censure. On the death of Peter the position of Menshikoff became very perilous;
                    his successes had raised about him a host of enemies eager for his downfall. The
                    Golitzins, Dolgoroukis, and all those who formed what may be called the Old
                    Russian party, wished to proclaim the son of Alexis emperor. Those, however,
                    whose aggrandizement was bound up with Peter’s reforms—Menshikoff, Apraksin,
                    Bontourlin, Goloff kin, and others—were in favour of giving the crown to Peter’s
                    widow, who accordingly ascended the throne as Catherine I. During her reign the
                    influence of Menshikoff was unbounded, and he virtually governed the country;
                    but the empress died in 1727, after a reign of two years. She had made a will,
                    no doubt at the instigation of the favourite, to the effect that Peter, her
                    grandson, was to be czar under the guardianship of Menshikoff, whose daughter
                    Mary was to be married to the youthful sovereign. Under pretence of taking care
                    of the young czar, Menshikoff caused him to be removed to his house and
                    surrounded him with his creatures. He was now at the height of his power;
                    foreign ambassadors remarked that even the great Peter himself was never feared
                    so much. The young czar, however, showed no affection for Mary Menshikoff, and
                    the girl was equally apathetic towards her betrothed, being in love with a
                    member of the family of Sapieha at the time her father had forced her into the
                    engagement. The Dolgoroukis used the aversion of the young prince to his <hi
                        rend="italic">fiancee</hi> as a means of creating dislike to the father. A
                    chain of events was gradually leading to the downfall of the favourite. He was
                    soon refused admittance to the summer palace, whither the young czar had
                    retired. Next he was arrested, and so overpowered was he at his disgrace that he
                    had an apoplectic stroke. In vain did he address letters both to the emperor and
                    his sister. Shortly after, by order of the czar, the fallen magnate departed
                    from St Petersburg, but more like a nobleman retiring to his estate than a
                    culprit going into exile. The people regarded him with dislike, and most of them
                    rejoiced over his fall. On his way a courier arrived with orders to take the
                    czar’s ring of betrothal from his daughter Mary and give her back her own, which
                    had been worn by Peter ∏. Menshikoff was not permitted to pass through Moscow,
                    but was conducted to Oranienburg, in the government of Riazan, and there placed
                    under strict surveillance. Soon afterwards the whole family was banished to
                    Siberia, and arrived at Berezoff towards the end of 1727. Menshikoff’s wife died
                    on the journey, and was buried near Kazan. On the arrival of the prisoners they
                    were lodged in a wooden house, consisting of four rooms. But Menshikoff did not
                    long endure the horrors of exile in this inclement region. According to
                    Mannstein, he died (November 12, o.s., 1729) of an apoplectic stroke, because
                    there was no one at Berezoff, as he himself remarked, who understood how to open
                    a vein. The young czar ordered the release from exile of the two remaining
                    children of Menshikoff,—his daughter Mary had died at Berezoff in the same year
                    as her father,—and restored some of their property to them.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
