<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0367-0350-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">REID (9th edition, volume 20, page 350)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:915437">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198491">Essay</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1075567">Presbyterians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1075562">Presbyterianism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198483">Brown</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1042815">Objectivity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795379">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795510">Accounts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4348gn83">Mind</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r20rx5q">Presbyterianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n367/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">REID</label><hi rend="smallcaps">Thomas</hi> (1710-1796), the
                    chief founder of what is generally designated the Scottish school of philosophy,
                    was born at Strachan in Kincardineshire, about 20 miles from Aberdeen, on the
                    26th April 1710. His father was minister of the place for fifty years, and
                    traced his descent from a long line of Presbyterian ministers on Deeside. His
                    mother belonged to the brilliant family of the Gregorys, which gave so many
                    representatives to literature and science in Scotland last century. After two
                    years at the parish school of Kincardine, Thomas Reid entered Marischal College,
                    Aberdeen, in 1722. He was instructed in philosophy by Dr George Turnbull, in his
                    day a voluminous and versatile writer, but now almost entirely forgotten.
                    Turnbull’s teaching would appear, from the account given of it by M‘Cosh, to
                    have anticipated and suggested certain characteristics of Reid’s subsequent
                    theory. Reid graduated in 1726 at the early age of sixteen, but remained in
                    Aberdeen as librarian to the university for ten years longer. This may be looked
                    upon as his real student-time, and it seems to have been largely devoted to
                    mathematical reading. In 1737 he was presented to the living of Newmachar near
                    Aberdeen. The parishioners, being violently excited at the time about the law of
                    patronage, received Reid with open hostility; and tradition asserts that, during
                    the preaching of his first sermon, an uncle who lived near defended him on the
                    pulpit stair with a drawn sword. But before he left the parish he was completely
                    successful in winning the affections of his people. He was, however, nowise
                    distinguished as a preacher, being accustomed <hi rend="italic">“</hi> from a
                    distrust in his own powers,” as Stewart puts it, “to preach the sermons of Dr
                    Tillotson and of Dr Evans.” The greater part of his time was given to study;
                    and, instigated by the publication of Hume’s treatise, he now turned his chief
                    attention to philosophy, and in particular to the theory of external perception.
                    His first publication, however, which dealt with a question of philosophical
                    method suggested by the reading of Hutcheson, was more nearly allied to his
                    mathematical studies. The “Essay on Quantity, occasioned by reading a Treatise
                    in which Simple and Compound Ratios are applied to Virtue and Merit,” denies
                    that a mathematical treatment of moral subjects is possible. The essay appeared
                    in the <hi rend="italic">Transactions</hi> of the Royal Society for the year
                    1748. Before this, in 1740, Reid had married a cousin of his own, the daughter
                    of a London physician. In 1752 the professors of King’s College, Aberdeen,
                    elected him to the chair of philosophy, which he held for the next twelve years.
                    The foundation of the Aberdeen Philosophical Society, which numbered among its
                    members Campbell, Beattie, Gerard, and Dr John Gregory, was mainly owing to the
                    exertions of Reid, who was secretary for the first year (1758). Many of the
                    subjects of discussion were drawn from Hume’s speculations; and during the last
                    years of his stay in Aberdeen Reid propounded his new point of view in several
                    papers read before the society. Thus we find from the minutes that on the 13th
                    and 26th of July 1758 Mr Reid “handled” the following questions:— “Are the
                    objects of the human mind properly divided into impressions and ideas <hi
                    rend="italic">1</hi> And must every idea be a copy of a preceding impression <hi
                    rend="italic">1</hi>” The reply to Hume which these titles foreshadow was
                    embodied by Reid in his <hi rend="italic">Enquiry into the Human Mind on the
                    Principles of Common Sense,</hi> published in 1764. The <hi rend="italic"
                    >Enquiry</hi> does not go beyond an analysis of sense perception, and is
                    therefore more limited in its scope than the later <hi rend="italic"
                    >Essays·,</hi> but if the latter are sometimes more mature, there is more
                    freshness about the earlier work. The same year saw Reid’s removal from Aberdeen
                    to the professorship of moral philosophy in the university of Glasgow, where he
                    succeeded Adam Smith. This position he continued to hold till 1781, when he
                    resigned his chair in order to give his undivided energies to completing a
                    systematic exposition of his philosophy. As a public teacher, Reid did not
                    possess the eloquence and charm of manner which afterwards characterized both
                    Stewart and Brown. Stewart’s account of his lecturing, which may be presumed to
                    be favourable, mentions only the “silent and respectful attention” which was
                    accorded to “the simplicity and perspicuity of his style” and “the gravity and
                    authority of his character.” Reid’s philosophical influence was mainly exerted
                    through his writings, and, at second hand, through the eloquent treatment which
                    his doctrines received at the hands of Dugald Stewart, and the learning which
                    Hamilton subsequently devoted to their elucidation. The <hi rend="italic">Essays
                    on the Intellectual Powers of Man</hi> appeared in 1785, and their ethical
                    complement, the <hi rend="italic">Essays on the Active Powers of the Human
                    Mind,</hi> in 1788. These, with an account of Aristotle’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Logic</hi> appended to Lord Karnes’s <hi rend="italic">Sketches of the History
                    of Man</hi> (1774), conclude the list of Avorks published in Reid’s lifetime.
                    Hamilton’s edition of Reid also contains an account of the university of Glasgow
                    and a selection of Reid’s letters, chiefly addressed to his Aberdeen friends the
                    Skenes, to Lord Karnes, and to Dr James Gregory. With the two last-named he
                    discusses the materialism of Priestley and the theory of necessitarianism. He
                    reverted in his old age to the mathematical pursuits of his earlier years, and
                    his ardour for knowledge of every kind remained fresh to the last. But in 1792
                    the serenity which marked the concluding years of his life AA <hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> as clouded by the death of his Avife. All the children
                    of their marriage except one daughter had died many years before. In other
                    respects Reid’s life pursued its equable and uneventful course till within a few
                    weeks of his death, which took place on the 7th October 1796.</p>
                <p>The kev to Reid’s whole philosophy is to be found in <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n368/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0368-0351"/>his revulsion from the sceptical conclusions of
                    Hume. In several passages of his writings he expressly dates his philosophical
                    awakening from the appearance of the <hi rend="italic">Treatise of Human
                    Nature.</hi> “I acknowledge,” he says in the dedication of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Enquiry,</hi> “that I never thought of calling in question the principles
                    commonly received with regard to the human understanding until the <hi
                    rend="italic">Treatise of Human Nature</hi> was published in the year 1739. The
                    ingenious author of that treatise upon the principles of Locke—who was no
                    sceptic—hath built a system of scepticism which leaves no ground to believe any
                    one thing rather than its contrary. His reasoning appeared to me to be just;
                    there was, therefore, a necessity to call in question the principles upon which
                    it was founded, or to admit the conclusion.” Reid thus takes Hume’s scepticism
                    as, on its own showing, a <hi rend="italic">reductio ad impossibile</hi> of
                    accepted philosophical principles, and refuses, accordingly, to separate Hume
                    from his intellectual progenitors. From its origin in Descartes and onwards
                    through Locke and Berkeley, modern philosophy carried with it, Reid contends,
                    the germ of scepticism. That scepticism, “inlaid in it and reared along with
                    it,” Hume did but bring to light. Embracing the whole philosophic movement under
                    the name of “the Cartesian system,” Reid detects its <hi rend="italic"
                    >-n-pwrov</hi> i/reDSos in the unproved assumption shared by these thinkers
                    “that all the objects of my knowledge are ideas in my own mind.” This doctrine
                    or hypothesis he usually speaks of as “the ideal system” or “the theory of
                    ideas”; and to it he opposes his own analysis of the act of perception. In view
                    of the results of this analysis, Reid’s theory (and the theory of Scottish
                    philosophy generally) has been dubbed natural realism or natural dualism in
                    contrast to theories like subjective idealism and materialism or to the
                    cosmothetic idealism or hypothetical dualism of the majority of philosophers.
                    But this is unduly to narrow the scope of Scottish philosophy, which does not
                    exhaust itself, as it is sometimes supposed to do, in uncritically reasserting
                    the independent existence of matter and its immediate presence to mind. The real
                    significance of Reid’s doctrine lies in its attack upon the principles which
                    Hume explicitly lays down as the alpha and the omega of his system, viz., the
                    principles that all our perceptions are distinct existences, and that the mind
                    never perceives any real connexion among distinct existences <hi rend="italic"
                    >(cf.</hi> Appendix to the third volume of the <hi rend="italic">Treatise,</hi>
                    1740). It is here that the danger of “the ideal system” really lies — in its
                    reduction of reality to “particular perceptions,” momentary or “perishing”
                    existences essentially unconnected with each other. If the ultimate elements of
                    experience are unrelated units or sense-atoms, called impressions, then it only
                    remains to be shown, as Hume attempts to show, how the <hi rend="italic"
                    >illusion</hi> of supposed necessary connexion arises. But Reid meets this
                    scepticism by combating the principle on which it is based. In logical language,
                    he denies the actuality of the abstract particular: unrelated impressions and
                    ideas nowhere exist. The unit of knowledge is not an isolated impression but a
                    judgment; and in such a judgment is contained, even initially, the reference
                    both to a permanent subject and to a permanent world of thought, and, implied in
                    these, such judgments, for example, as those of existence, substance, cause and
                    effect. Such principles are not derived from sensation, bujb are “suggested” on
                    occasion of sensation, in such a way as to constitute the necessary conditions
                    of our having perceptive experience at all. Thus we do not start with “ideas,”
                    and afterwards refer them to objects; we are never restricted to our own minds,
                    but are from the first immediately related to a permanent world. Reid has a
                    variety of names for the principles which, by their presence, lift us out of
                    subjec tivity into perception. He calls them “natural judgments,” “natural
                    suggestions,” “judgments of nature,” “judgments immediately inspired by our
                    constitution,” “principles of our nature,” “first principles,” “principles of
                    common sense.” The last designation, which became the current one, was
                    undoubtedly unfortunate, and has conveyed to many a false impression of Scottish
                    philosophy. It has been understood as if Reid had merely appealed from the
                    reasoned conclusions of philosophers to the unreasoned beliefs of common life.
                    The tirades of men like Beattie and Oswald, and many unguarded utterances of
                    Reid himself, lent countenance to this notion. But Reid’s actions are better
                    than his words; his real mode of procedure is to redargue Hume’s conclusions by
                    a refutation of the premises inherited by him from his predecessors. For the
                    rest, as regards the question of nomenclature, Reid everywhere unites common
                    sense and reason, making the former “only another name for one branch or degree
                    of reason.” Reason, as judging of things self-evident, is called common-sense to
                    distinguish it from ratiocination or reasoning. And in regard to Reid’s
                    favourite proof of the principles in question by reference to “the consent of
                    ages and nations, of the learned and unlearned,” it is only fair to observe that
                    this argument assumes a much more scientific form in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Essays,</hi> where it is almost identified with an appeal to “the structure and
                    grammar of all languages.” “The structure of all languages,” he says, “is
                    grounded upon common sense.” To take but one example, “the distinction between
                    sensible qualities and the substance to which they belong, and between thought
                    and the mind that thinks, is not the invention of philosophers; it is found in
                    the structure of all languages, and therefore must be common to all men who
                    speak with understanding” (Hamilton’s <hi rend="italic">Reid,</hi> pp. 229 and
                    454).</p>
                <p>The principles which Reid insists upon as everywhere present in experience
                    evidently correspond pretty closely to the Kantian categories and the unity of
                    apperception. Similarly, Reid’s assertion of the essential distinction between
                    space or extension and feeling or any succession of feelings may be compared
                    with Kant’s doctrine in the <hi rend="italic">¿Esthetic.</hi> “Space,” he says,
                    “whether tangible or visible, is not so properly an object [Kant’s “matter”] as
                    a necessary concomitant of the objects both of sight and touch.” Like Kant, too,
                    Reid finds in space the source of a necessity which sense, as sense, cannot give
                    (Hamilton’s <hi rend="italic">Reid,</hi> 323). In the substance of their answer
                    to Hume, the two philosophers have therefore much in common. But Reid lacked the
                    art to give due impressiveness to the important advance which his positions
                    really contain. Although at times he states his principles with a wonderful
                    degree of breadth and insight, he mars the total effect by frequent looseness of
                    statement, and by the amount of irrelevant psychological matter with which they
                    are overlaid. And, if Kant was overridden by - a love of formal completeness and
                    symmetry, Reid’s extreme indifference to form and system is an even more
                    dangerous defect in a philosopher. It has also to be admitted that the
                    principles frequently appear in Reid more as matter of assertion than as
                    demonstrated necessities for the constitution of experience. The transcendental
                    deduction, or proof from the possibility of experience in general, which forms
                    the vital centre of the Kantian scheme, is wanting in Reid; or, at all events,
                    if the spirit of the proof is occasionally present, it is nowhere adequately
                    stated and emphasized. But, when these defects are acknowledged, Reid’s
                    insistence on judgment as the unit of knowledge and his sharp distinction
                    between sensation and perception must still be recognized as philosophical
                    results of the highest importance. They embody the only possible answer to <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n369/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0369-0352"/>Hume’s sceptical dissolution of knowledge. Reid’s
                    theory of sensation, indeed, deserves more attention than has been generally
                    bestowed upon it. According to this theory, sensations are not the objects of
                    our perception, not even, as Kant maintained, the “matter” of our perceptions on
                    which the “form” is superinduced; they are merely the “signs” which introduce us
                    to the knowledge of real objects. The latter “are presented to the mind” by
                    means of, or on occasion of, certain corresponding sensations; but the sensation
                    and the perception “appear upon accurate reflexion not only to be different
                    things, but as unlike as pain is to the point of a sword” (Hamilton’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Reid,</hi> 122). Sensation, it might be expressed, is the
                    condition of perception, but there is no sort of community between the two. They
                    are distinct in kind, and therefore the possibility of deriving the one from the
                    other— of melting down the real world into subjective sensations —is once for
                    all shut out. Reid’s position here enables him to escape also from the
                    phenomenalism of the Kantian theory. Inasmuch as the permanent objects presented
                    to us in perception are not in any sense a manipulation of subjective
                    sensations, there is not even an apparent warrant for branding them as “merely”
                    phenomenal. They are real in the full sense of the word; we know the world as it
                    really exists.</p>
                <p>The relativism or phenomenalism which Hamilton afterwards adopted from Kant and
                    sought to engraft upon Scottish philosophy is thus wholly absent from the
                    original Scottish doctrine. One or two passages may certainly be quoted from
                    Reid in which he asserts that we know only properties of things and are ignorant
                    of their essence. But the exact meaning which he attaches to such expressions is
                    not quite clear; and they occur, moreover, only incidentally and with the air of
                    current phrases mechanically repeated. In Dugald Stewart, however, the merely
                    qualitative nature of our knowledge is consciously emphasized, and made the
                    foundation of philosophical arguments; so that Stewart in this respect paves the
                    way for the more thoroughgoing philosophy of nescience elaborated by Hamilton.
                    But since Hamilton’s time the most typical Scottish thinkers have repudiated his
                    relativistic doctrine, and returned to the original tradition of the school.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Authorities</hi> .—For the life, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Memoir</hi> by Dugald Stewart, prefixed to Hamilton’s edition of Reid’s works,
                    may be consulted, along with the account given by Dr M'Cosh in his <hi
                    rend="italic">Scottish Philosophy</hi> (1875). The complete edition of the works
                    by Sir William Hamilton, published in two volumes with notes and supplementary
                    dissertations by the editor (6th ed. 1863), has superseded all others. (A.
                    SE.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
