<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0893-0860-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ROSSINI (9th edition, volume 20, page 860)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2ch0v">Music</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90251t">Opera</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9785q">Success</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1030269">Music</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1030814">Musicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1046191">Operas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1046145">Opera</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1137041">Success</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n893/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ROSSINI</label><hi rend="smallcaps">Gioachino Antonio</hi>
                    (1792-1868), Italian dramatic composer, was born at Pesaro, February 29, 1792.
                    He first studied music under Angelo Tesei, and that so successfully that he was
                    able to sing solos in church when only ten years old, and three years later to
                    appear at the opera house as Adolfo, in Paer’s <hi rend="italic">Camilla.</hi>
                    He was next placed under a retired tenor, named Babbini, and on the breaking of
                    his voice he entered the Liceo at Bologna for the purpose of studying
                    counterpoint under Mattel. On his departure from the school, Mattei, who was not
                    pleased with his progress, told him that he knew enough counterpoint to enable
                    him to write in the free style, but that he was quite unfit for the composition
                    of church music. “Do I know enough to write operas?” asked Rossini. “Quite
                    enough,” was the reply. “Then,” said the boy, “Icare to know no more.” But in
                    truth his wonderful instinct had taught him a great deal more than either he or
                    Mattei suspected. Rossini’s first opera, <hi rend="italic">La Cambiale di
                    Matri-</hi></p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n894/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0894-0861"/>
                <p><hi rend="italic">monio,</hi> was produced with success at the Teatro San Mosè at
                    Venice in 1810. In 1811 he produced <hi rend="italic">HEquivoco
                    Stravagante,</hi> at Bologna; but his first real triumph was achieved at Venice
                    in 1812, in <hi rend="italic">HInganno felice,</hi> a work in which his genius
                    unmistakably asserted itself. In the same year he produced <hi rend="italic">La
                    Pietra del Paragone,</hi> with equal applause, at Milan, besides four other
                    operas in other places. These pieces were all successful, but <hi rend="italic"
                    >Tancredi,</hi> written for the Teatro San Fenice at Venice, in 1813, produced a
                    veritable <hi rend="italic">furore.</hi> The name of the young <hi rend="italic"
                    >maestro</hi> was now famous; yet, strange to say, his greatest comic opera was
                    hissed on its first performance at Rome in 1816. This delightful inspiration,
                    first entitled <hi rend="italic">Alma-viva,</hi> but now known as <hi
                    rend="italic">Il Barbiere di Siviglia,</hi> was founded on a libretto which
                    Paisiello had already treated with success, and hence the refusal of the Roman
                    audience to tolerate it. But the beauty of the music overcame the scruples of
                    the most prejudiced listeners, and, by the time the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Barbixre</hi> reached its third representation, Rossini was openly accepted as
                    the greatest dramatic composer in Italy. Between 1815 and 1823 Rossini composed
                    no less than twenty operas, including his masterpieces <hi rend="italic"
                    >Elisabetta</hi> (1815), <hi rend="italic">Il Barbiere</hi> (1816), <hi
                    rend="italic">Otello</hi> (1816), <hi rend="italic">La Cenerentola</hi> (1817),
                    <hi rend="italic">La Gazza LaRra</hi> (1817), <hi rend="italic">Mosè in
                    Egitto</hi> (1818), <hi rend="italic">Le Donna del Lago</hi> (1819), and <hi
                    rend="italic">Semiramide</hi> (1823), the last of which has lately been revived,
                    with so great success, by Madame Adelina Patti.</p>
                <p>Rossini visited England in 1823, and in 1824 accepted an engagement as musical
                    director of the Théâtre Italien in Paris, where, in 1829, he produced his last
                    great masterpiece, <hi rend="italic">Guillaume TeU.</hi> After completing this
                    beautiful work, he composed no more until 1832, when he wrote the first six
                    movements of the <hi rend="italic">Stabat Mater</hi> for private performance
                    only. He completed this lovely composition in 1839, and it was first publicly
                    performed at the Salle Ventadour in 1842. In 1855 he settled permanently in
                    Paris, at 2 Rue Chaussée d’Antin, where he composed his last work, the <hi
                    rend="italic">Petite Messe Solennelle,</hi> which was first privately performed
                    at the house of M. Pillet Will, March 16, 1864, and posthumously produced at the
                    Théâtre Italien February 28, 1869. Rossini was twice married—to Isabella Colbran
                    in 1821, and in 1847 to Olympe Pelissier. After his final return to Paris he
                    spent a part of every year in a suburban villa in the Avenue Ingres, at Passy,
                    and here he died of a very painful illness, November 13, 1868. He was buried at
                    the church of the Trinité, November 21, with every possible honour. He was a
                    foreign associate of the Institute, “grand officer of the Legion of Honour,” the
                    recipient of innumerable orders, and a member of innumerable musical
                    institutions. Honour was justly lavished upon him; and, though his career was
                    not free from temporary misfortunes, probably no man of genius ever lived a
                    happier life, or enjoyed more fully the appreciation both of brother artists and
                    the general public.</p>
                <p>Rossini effected a complete revolution in the style of Italian opera. His
                    accompaniments were richer than any that had ever been previously heard in
                    Italy, and in their masterly instrumentation rivalled some of the most notable
                    achievements of German art. His use of the crescendo and the “cabaletta,” though
                    sometimes carried to excess, gave a brilliancy to his music which added greatly
                    to the excellence of its effect. He first accompanied his recitatives with the
                    stringed orchestra in <hi rend="italic">ElisabeUa,</hi> and with stringed and
                    wind instruments combined in <hi rend="italic">Otetta</hi> And his overtures are
                    by far the most masterly and complete compositions of the kind that the Italian
                    school has ever produced.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
