<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0395-0378-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">REMIGIUS (or Remedius (9th edition, volume 20, page
                    378)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:896108">Documentation</term>
                    <term ref="fast:825070">Back</term>
                    <term ref="fast:837146">Bouquets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1167847">Visigoths</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:939002">Gauls</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hq83">Visigoths</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c72h">Gauls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50fz6v">Carlovingians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hx15x22">Merovingians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49z90c2b">Avars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fx74153">Documents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n395/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">REMIGIUS (or <hi rend="smallcaps">Remedius</hi></label>, as
                    the name is spelt in Fredegarius and elseAA-fiere), or <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Remi,</hi> Avas born of noble parents and, according to a later tradition, in
                    the district of Laon. In one of his OAvn letters, Avritten apparently about 512
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.,</hi> Remigius speaks of himself as having been a
                    bishop for fifty-three years. This throws back his election to about 459; and,
                    as all his earlier biographers agree in making him twenty-one years of age on
                    his appointment to this office, the date of his birth may be fixed at somewhere
                    about the year 438. The bishopric was forced upon the young recluse by the
                    townspeople of Rheims, who in this century had not yet lost the right of
                    electing their own pastor. For the next thirty-seven years of Remigius’s life
                    A\־e have no clue excepting one, or at most two, allusions in the letters of
                    Sidonius Apollin-aris <hi rend="italic">(Ep.</hi> viii. 14; ix. 7,8),—both of
                    which epistles M. Baret has assigned to from 472 to 474. It is true that
                    Fredegarius (Du Cliesne, i. 728), Avriting about 658, and the later biographers
                    associate the name of Remigius Avith that of Clovis in the story of the famous
                    vase of Sois-sons. But the earlier account of Gregory ( <hi rend="italic">c</hi>
                    . 590) lends no sanction to this association; and it is not till 496 that
                    Remigius figures definitely in history. On the Christmas day of this year he
                    baptized Clovis at Rheims Avith the greatest pomp. “Bow thy head meekly, O
                    Sicambrian,” Avere his Avords to the royal convert; “adore Avhat thou hast burnt
                    and burn Avhat thou hast adored.” Two of the king’s sisters Avere baptized about
                    the same time; and on the death of one of these, Albofledis, Remigius Avrote
                    Clovis a letter of consolation that is still preserved (Dom. Bouq. iv. 51). The
                    traditions and perhaps the documents of Hincmar’s time enumerated the immense
                    possessions conferred by Clovis upon his favourite ])relate. Remigius, in his
                    turn, does not seem to have been slack in urging the orthodox king to undertake
                    the deliverance of his fellow believers who in southern Gaul reluctantly
                    submitted to the yoke of the Aryan Burgundians and Visigoths. His intrigues with
                    the discontented bishops of Burgundy are said to have paved the Avay for
                    Clovis’s invasion (500). Hincmar has preserved the tradition that Remigius
                    blessed Clovis before he set out <hi rend="superscript">1</hi> on his Avar
                    against the Visigoths (507); r.nd Ave still ha\ <hi rend="superscript">r</hi> e
                    the letter in which he recommends the king to be merciful in his neAv conquests
                    (Bouquet, iv. 52; see, however,</p>
                <p>' Junghans’s remarks on the probable date of this letter).</p>
                <p>It is not, hoAvever, solely as a statesman or as the mentor of a barbarian king
                    that Remigius claims attention. In Hincmar’s time he Avas recognized as the
                    second founder of the church of Rheims, to whose influence that see OAved the
                    greater ])art of its possessions; and in such a matter the popular tradition can
                    hardly have been entirely Avrong. One of his feAv remaining letters is directed
                    in the most vigorous terms against the encroachments of a neighbouring bishop,
                    Falco of Maestriclit (Bouq., iv. 53). He is said to have established a bishopric
                    at Laon, his native place. So great Avas his fame that it reached the ears of
                    Alaric and his Gothic counsellors at Toulouse, and that, at last, Pope Hormisdas
                    or one of his immediate predecessors appointed him his vicar throughout the
                    Frankish domains. Of Remigius’s writ-ings only a feAv verses and the letters
                    alluded to above have been preserved; but his credit for learning and eloquence
                    is amply attested by Sidonius Apollinaris and Gregory of Tours. The former,
                    writing to Remigius (c. 472), declares him to be unsurpassed by any living
                    orator.</p>
                <p>Gregory has also preserved the tradition that Remigius Avas bishop of Rheims for
                    more than seventy years (De Gloria Conf., 89), a fact Avhicli inclines us to lay
                    some confidence on the more detailed statement of Hincmar that he died on
                    January 13, in the ninety-sixth year of his age, after an episcopate of
                    seventy-four years. Hence Ave may fix upon 533 as the date of his decease, more
                    especially as this conclusion coincides Avell enough Avith the little that is
                    known as to the chronology of his îavo immediate successors (Ste Marthe, ix.
                    10-13). In 882, Avhen the Northmen AA־ere threatening a descent upon the un-AA
                    <hi rend="superscript">r</hi> allecl city of Rheims, Hincmar had the body of St
                    Remi ' removed from its first resting-place in the little church of! St
                    Christopher to Epernay. Next year it aa־us brought back to Rheims, but it Avas
                    not restored to its original home till some years later. We learn from Gregory
                    of Tours that, even so early as the reign of Childebert II. (575-596) the first
                    of October AA <hi rend="superscript">7</hi> as held sacred to the memory of the
                    saint. During the Carlovingian times this day became <hi rend="superscript"
                    >;</hi> one of the great feasts of the year, its observance being <hi
                    rend="superscript">:</hi> sanctioned by the council of Mainz in 813 and a
                    capitulary of Louis le Débonnaire in 821 (Dessailly). In 1049 Pope Leo IX.
                    assisted at the removal of the relics and issued a decree for the observation of
                    the fête.</p>
                <p>The authorities for the life of St Remi are very meagre. An almost contemporary
                    Vita Rcmigii, written in the popular j Latin of the period (cothurno Gallicano),
                    and known to Gregory of Tours, Avas, according to Hincmar, almost entirely
                    destroyed in the I troubled times of Charles Martel, but not before it had been!
                    abbreviated and stripped of nearly all historic value by Fortunatus j between
                    the years 565 and 590. This abridgment, which still exists, formed the basis of
                    the Vita Rcmigii Avritten by Hincmar, archbishop of Rheims from 845 to 882, who,
                    however, professes to incorporate with his work some fragments of the original
                    Vita and other ancient documents, as he has most certainly incorporated the
                    living traditions of his own age. In the course of the next century Flodoard, a
                    canon of Rheims {oh. 966), compiled his account of St Remi, by making a very
                    free use of his predecessors’ labours, with, however, some traditional
                    information of his own. The above works are all in Mignc’s Patrologia, vols,
                    lxxxviii., exxv., kc. See also Fredegarius and Gregory of Tours, whose authority
                    is only second to that of Fortunatus. The scattered documents of the Merovingian
                    period are to be found in the great collections of A. I)u Cliesne, Bouquet, and
                    Labbé. Le Cointe’s Annales Ecclesiastici, vol. i.; Mabillon’s Annales Ordinis
                    Bened., vol. i.; Ste Marthe’s Gallia Christiana, \ <hi rend="superscript">T</hi>
                    ol. ix.; and the Ada Sanctorum (October 1), which contains the best modern life
                    of St Remi, may be consulted with advantage. Of French lives see that by the
                    prior Armand. The so-called Testamenlum Rcmigii, which has been preserved in a
                    longer and shorter form by Flodoard and <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n396/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0396-0379"/>Hincmar, has lately found an able champion of its
                    authenticity in the Abbe Dessailly. For Remigius’s connexion with Vedastus (who
                    assisted in the conversion of Clovis), St Medard, St Eleutherius, &amp;c., see
                    the Bollandist <hi rend="italic">Vita Jtemigii</hi> alluded to above and the <hi
                    rend="italic">Acta Sanctorum</hi> for Feburary 6, June 8, and February 20.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
