<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0275-0258-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">RAISINS (9th edition, volume 20, page 258)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1120047">Skin</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1089594">Raisins</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1137272">Sugar</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1137549">Sugars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:946524">Grapes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cv3f">Skins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45d8nd6f">Skin</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42z12x62">Raisins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zn7v">Sugar</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43x83n13">Sugars</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n275/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">RAISINS</label> are the dried fruits of certain varieties of
                    the grape vine, <hi rend="italic">Vit is vinifera,</hi> which groAv principally
                    in the warm climate of the Mediterranean coasts and are comparatively rich in
                    sugar. The use of dried grapes or raisins as food is of great antiquity (Numb.
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">a</hi> 1; 3 .¡־ Sam. xxv. 18, xxx. 12). In mediaeval times
                    raisins imported from Spain Avere a prized luxury in England, and to the present
                    day Great Britain continues to be the best customer of the raisin-producing
                    regions. “Raisins of the sun” are obtained by letting the fruit continue on the
                    vines after it has come to maturity, Avhere there is sufficient sunshine and
                    heat in the autumn, till the clusters dry on the stocks. Another plan is
                    partially to sever the stalk before the grapes are quite ripe, thus stopping the
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Aoav</hi> of the sap, and in that condition to leave them
                    on the vines till they are .sufficiently dry. The more usual process, liOAvever,
                    is to cut off the fully ripe clusters and expose them, spread out, for several
                    days to the rays of the sun, taking care that they are not injured by rain. In
                    unfavourable weather they may be dried in a heated chamber, but are then
                    inferior in quality. In some parts of Spain and France it is common to dip the
                    gathered clusters in boiling Avater, or in a strong potash lye, a practice which
                    softens the skin, favours drying, and gives the raisins a clear glossy
                    appearance. Again, in Asia Minor the fruit is dipped into hot Avater on the
                    surface of which swims a layer of olive oil, which communicates a bright lustre
                    and softness to the skin. Some superior A־arieties are treated with very great
                    care, retained on their stalks, and sent into the market as clusters for table
                    use; but the greater part are separated from the stalks in the process of drying
                    and the stalks AvinnoAved out of the fruit. Raisins come from numerous
                    Mediterranean localities, and present at least three distinct varieties,—(1)
                    ordinary or large raisins, (2) sultana seedless raisins, and (3) currants or
                    Corinthian raisins (see vol. vi. p. 715). The greater proportion of the common
                    large raisins of English commerce comes from the provinces of Malaga, Valencia,
                    and Alicante in Spain; these are knoAvn by the common name of Malaga raisins.
                    Those of the finest quality, called Malaga clusters, are prepared from a variety
                    of muscatel grape, and preserved on the stalks for table use. This variety, as
                    Avell as Malaga layers, so called from the manner of packing, are exclusively
                    used as dessert fruit. Raisins of a somewhat inferior quality, knoAvn as
                    “lexias,” from the same provinces, are used for cooking and baking purposes.
                    Smyrna raisins also come to some extent into the English market. The best
                    quality, knoAvn as Elemé, is a large fruit, having a reddish yelloAv skin with a
                    sweet pleasant flavour. Large-seeded dark-coloured raisins are produced in some
                    of the islands of the Greek Archipelago and in Crete, but they are little seen
                    in the British markets. In Italy the finest raisins are produced in Calabria,
                    inferior qualities in central Italy and in Sicily. From the Lipari Islands a
                    certain quantity of cluster raisins of good quality is sent to England. In the
                    south of France raisins of high excellence—Provence raisins in clusters—are
                    obtained at RoqueA <hi rend="superscript">r</hi> aire, Lunel, and Frontignan.
                    Sultana seedless raisins are the produce of a small variety of yellow grape,
                    cultivated exclusively in the neighbourhood of Smyrna. The vines are groAvn on a
                    soil of decomposed hippurite limestone, on sloping ground rising to a height of
                    400 feet <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n276/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0276-0259"/>above the sea, and all attempts to cultivate
                    sultanas in other raisin-growing localities have failed, the grapes quickly
                    reverting to a seed-bearing character. The dried fruit has a fine golden-yellow
                    colour, with a thin, delicate, translucent skin and a sweet aromatic flavour. A
                    very fine seedless oblong raisin of the sultana type with a brownish skin is
                    cultivated in the neighbourhood of Damascus, but it is rarely seen in the
                    Western markets.</p>
                <p>Raisins are chiefly valuable on account of the large proportion of grape sugar
                    and cream of tartar which they contain. In old dry raisins these substances are
                    found in hard nodular masses. The seeds contain from 15 to 18 per cent, of a
                    bland fixed oil and about 5 per cent, of tannin. The imports into the United
                    Kingdom average in value about £1,000,000 yearly, the quantity imported in 1883
                    having been 588,309 cwt., valued at £1,057,934.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
