<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0521-0504-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">RHAeTIA (9th edition, volume 20, page 504)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zs2kn9v">Tracts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mc8rm1n">Plains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c72h">Gauls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz36">Inns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4736m682">Lakes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1151043">Time</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1153794">Tracts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1156484">Tribes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1048190">Originality</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1065075">Plains</term>
                    <term ref="fast:939002">Gauls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821579">Austrians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916316">Etruscans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239717">Alps</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n521/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">RHAeTIA</label> was the name given in ancient times to a
                    province of the Roman empire, which included a considerable tract of the Alpine
                    regions that separated the great valleys of the Po and the Danube, comprising
                    the districts occupied in modern times by the Grisons and the Austrian province
                    of Tyrol. Before their subjugation by Rome the Rhaetians are described as one of
                    the most powerful and warlike of the Alpine tribes; but little or nothing is
                    known as to their origin and history. It is indeed stated distinctly by Livy (v.
                    33) that they were of Etruscan origin, and a tradition reported by Justin (xx.
                    5) and Pliny (∕∕.A <hi rend="superscript">r</hi> ., iii. 24, 133) affirmed that
                    they were a portion of that people who had been settled in the plains of the Po
                    and were driven into the mountains by the irruption of the Gauls, when they
                    assumed the name of Rhaetians from a leader of the name of Rhaetus. Very little
                    value can, however, be attached to such traditions, and the attempts of some
                    modern writers to support them by philological researches have led to no
                    satisfactory result. But the ethnical connexion of the Rhaetians with the
                    Etruscans has been accepted by Niebuhr, and its general reception by the Romans
                    would seem to prove that they were a distinct race from their neighbours the
                    Ligurians as well as from the Gauls and Germans.</p>
                <p>The name of the Rhaetians is first mentioned by Polybius, but merely
                    incidentally, and they played no part in Roman history till after the fall of
                    the republic. It is certain, however, that they continued virtually independent
                    until Augustus undertook their subjugation, in common with that of the
                    neighbouring Alpine tribes bordering upon Italy. The importance he attached to
                    this task is shown by his having deputed its execution to his two step-sons,
                    Drusus and Tiberius, who in a single campaign reduced them all to subjection (15
                    B.c.), so that their territory was shortly after incorporated as a province in
                    the Roman empire and their name never again appears in history. The exploits of
                    the imperial youths on this occasion have been immortalized in two well-known
                    odes of Horace <hi rend="italic">(Od.,</hi> iv. 4 and 14). In the time of Strabo
                    their territory was considered as extending from the Lakes of Como and Garda to
                    that of Constance (the Lacus Brigantinus), while the allied people of the
                    Vindelici, who had shared in their <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n522/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0522-0505"/>contest against the Roman arms, as well as in
                    their final subjugation, extended down the northern slope of the Alps as far as
                    the Danube. By far the greater part of this extensive region was occupied by
                    rugged mountains, the inhabitants of which, when compelled to abandon their
                    predatory habits, subsisted principally upon the produce of their flocks. Some
                    of the valleys, however, which extended on the south side down to the plains of
                    Italy, were rich and fertile, and produced excellent wine, which was considered
                    equal to any of those grown in Italy itself. The most important of these valleys
                    λvas that of the Adige, which descends from the high Alps adjoining the Brenner
                    to Verona; of this the upper portions were held by the Breuni, whose name is
                    still perpetuated in that of the Brenner, while the lower and more fertile
                    region was occupied by the Tridentini, whose chief town of Tridentum was the
                    same as the now celebrated city of Trent. The next people towards the west were
                    the Triumpilini, in the valley still known as Val Trompia; the Camuni in Val
                    Camonica; the Orobii, who appear to have occupied the Val Tellina and adjoining
                    districts; and the Lepontii, between the Lago Maggiore and the Pennine Alps. The
                    tribes in the interior and heart of the mountain ranges cannot be for the most
                    part assigned to definite localities. The Genauni, mentioned by Horace as well
                    as by Strabo, are supposed to have occupied the Val di Non, and the Vennones or
                    Venostes the lofty ranges near the source of the Adige.</p>
                <p>The boundaries of the Roman province were repeatedly changed. At first it appears
                    to have comprised all Vinde-licia, so as to have extended to the Danube from its
                    sources to its confluence with the Inn, which constituted its eastern boundary
                    on the side of Noricum. But at a later period this northern tract was separated
                    from the central mountain region, and the two were named Rhaetia Prima and
                    Rhaetia Secunda, in which form they appear in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Notitia.</hi> At the same time the southern valleys were gradually incorporated
                    with Italy and assigned to the territory of the neighbouring municipal towns.
                    Thus Tridentum, which was originally a Rhaetian town, came to be included in
                    Venetia, and is ass.igned by Pliny to the tenth region of Italy. The only
                    important town in the northern part of the province was the Roman colony of
                    Augusta Vindelicorum, which still retains the name of Augsburg. The same is the
                    case with Curia, now Chur or Coire, the capital of the Grisons, and Brigantia
                    (Bregenz), which gave name in ancient times to the lake now called the Lake of
                    Constance.</p>
                <p>The province of Rhaetia was traversed by two great lines of Roman roads,—the one
                    leading from Verona and Tridentum (Trent) across the pass of the Brenner to
                    Innsbruck (Pons Oeni), and thence to Augsburg (Augusta Vindelicorum), and the
                    other from Bregenz on the Lake of Constance, by Coire and Chiavenna, to Como and
                    Milan.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
