<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0276-0259-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">RAJA (9th edition, volume 20, page 259)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dn40316">Ornament</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4959c725">Alterants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45d8nd8d">Alteratives</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:806112">Alteratives</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1151043">Time</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1156484">Tribes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1119311">Singing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1092062">Red</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950823">Hand</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n276/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">RAJA</label> (English form <hi rend="smallcaps">Rajah),</hi>
                    Sanskrit nom. sing, of the stem <hi rend="italic">rdjan</hi> (in modern Indian
                    vernaculars <hi rend="italic">raja, rajah, raja, rajan, rdzu, irdsen,</hi> also
                    the forms <hi rend="italic">red, rdo, rdna</hi> are traceable to the same stem)
                    = king, prince, chief, from the root <hi rend="italic">raj,</hi> to be
                    resplendent. In the oldest times the headman of any petty tribe was called rhjh
                    from the fact of his being conspicuous for the number of golden ornaments with
                    which he was decked out. Then raja became the common designation for a king,
                    whether of a small tribe or of a large state. The constitution of all states was
                    monarchical, mostly hereditary, occasionally also electoral, but in no case
                    absolute, for the people had a voice in the government. On the other hand, the
                    king was greatly hampered in his action by his duties towards the priestly
                    caste. Even in that later stage of Indian civilization which we find portrayed
                    in the code of Manu the king appears as subordinate to the priest, though his
                    prerogative is in all other respects paramount, especially in the matter of
                    revenue. Theoretically this system has been continued ever since; but
                    practically the rdj d’s powers have been gradually extended, some of them being
                    distributed by him at his pleasure among various officials, who were rewarded,
                    not by regular salaries, but by grants and the profits of oppression. <note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See for the Vedic period, H.
                    Zimmer, <hi rend="italic">Altindisches Leben,</hi> Berlin, 1879, p. 162 <hi
                    rend="italic">sq.</hi>; for later times, M. Duncker, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Geschichte des Alter-thuins,</hi> iii. 152 <hi rend="italic">sq.,</hi> and
                    Tod’s <hi rend="italic">Antiquities of Rajasthan,</hi> passim. </p></note> It
                    thus appears that the title is, strictly speaking, only applicable to Hindu
                    potentates, but in practice it is not unfrequently used to indicate a ruling
                    chief irrespective of his nationality or creed.</p>
                <p>The rights and privileges assigned to rfijfis by treaty and usage are manifold
                    and varied. But all rAjfis are precluded from waging war against an external foe
                    save with the permission of the British Government, and so none can be said to
                    be independent in the fullest sense of the word. At the same time there are
                    several princes in India who titularly hold that status, in so far, that is, as
                    they possess the right to administer their kingdom according to their own
                    notions of justice and equity; but even in these instances, and they are few,
                    British residents are attached to the various courts, charged to advise in the
                    interests of good government and righteous dealing. Such officers seldom fail to
                    secure a powerful influence, and it is not often that their counsel is
                    disregarded or their representations pass unheeded. More than this, when
                    flagrant injustice occurs the British Government is occasionally compelled to
                    interfere, and instances are not wanting when a raja has been deposed,
                    notwithstanding a clause in his treaty forbidding the intervention of the
                    British Government in the affairs of his state. Such cases, which are not
                    frequent, are justified by political necessity. In many instances native chiefs
                    are allowed by treaty to maintain a military force, but at the present time the
                    troops principally serve to gratify the cravings of Eastern potentates for the
                    outward and visible signs of power.</p>
                <p>Rdj4s of lesser note retain a semblance of power so far as concerns questions of
                    minor importance, but in grave cases involving issues of life and death the
                    officer attached to the court reviews and, should it be necessary, modifies or
                    reverses the decrees which may be passed. Chieftains in this category do not
                    even enjoy the appearance of independence, though in many instances they are
                    allowed to keep a body of military retainers.</p>
                <p>Other r&amp;jds are merely large and wealthy landholders with no sovereign rights
                    or privileges, resembling in many respects the territorial magnates of Great
                    Britain; while in some instances the term is simply a title of distinction
                    unconnected with the possession of land or power.</p>
                <p>Scarcely less complex and varied are the conditions which regulate succession to
                    the rAj ships of India: in some instances adoption is admitted, in other cases
                    collateral succession is accepted, while again there are occasions when the
                    customs of the family are a potent factor in the choice of an heir. It might
                    have been supposed perhaps that the salute could be fairly taken as indicative
                    of the status of the chief to whom it is assigned; but in reality such an
                    assumption would be most misleading, for not unfrequently the number of guns was
                    fixed in bygone years, and the lapse of time has made numerous and essential
                    changes in the status of the various chieftains. So much is this the case that
                    it has never been settled authoritatively what chiefs are entitled to claim the
                    Western prefix of “highness.”</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
