<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0879-0846-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ROSA (9th edition, volume 20, page 846)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w08wh24">Portraits</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bn9x31n">Tombs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4df6k36b">Earth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p84454w">Wheels</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1152439">Tombs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1174522">Wheels</term>
                    <term ref="fast:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:815177">Art</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1072324">Portraits</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n879/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ROSA</label><hi rend="smallcaps">Salvator</hi> (1615-1673), a
                    renowned painter of the Neapolitan school, was born in Arenella, in the
                    outskirts of Naples, in 1615: the precise day is given as 20th June, and also as
                    21st July. His father, Vito Antonio de Rosa, a land surveyor, was bent upon
                    making the youth a lawyer, and sent him to study in the convent of the Somaschi
                    fathers. Here Salvator began showing a turn for art: he went in secret to his
                    maternal uncle Paolo Greco to learn the practice of painting, but soon found
                    that Greco had little pictorial lore to impart, so he transferred himself to his
                    own brother-in-law Francesco Fracan-zaro, a pupil of Ribera, and afterwards had
                    some practiçe under Ribera himself. Above all he went to nature, frequenting the
                    Neapolitan coast, and keeping his eyes open and his hand busy. At the age of
                    seventeen he lost his father; the widow was left unprovided for, with at least
                    five children, and Salvator found himself immersed in a sea of troubles and
                    perplexities, with nothing for the while to stem them except a buoyant and
                    adventurous temperament. He obtained some instruction under the battle-painter
                    Aniello Falcone, but chiefly painted in solitude, haunting romantic and desolate
                    spots, beaches, mountains, caverns, verdure-clad recesses. Hence he became in
                    process of time the initiator of romantic landscape, with a special turn for
                    scenes of strange or picturesque aspect—often turbulent and rugged, at times
                    grand, and with suggestions of the sublime. He picked up scanty doles when he
                    could get them, and his early landscapes sold for a few pence to petty dealers.
                    The first person to discover that Rosa’s work was not as trumpery as it was
                    cheap was the painter Iianfranco, who bought some of the paintings, and advised
                    the youth to go to Rome. Hither in 1635, at the age of twenty, Rosa betook
                    himself; he studied with enthusiasm, but, catching fever, he returned to Naples
                    and Falcone, and for a while painted nothing but battle-pieces, and these
                    without exciting any attention. This class of work was succeeded by the
                    landscape art peculiarly characteristic of him—wild scenes wildly peopled with
                    shepherds, seamen, or especially soldiers. He then revisited Rome, and was
                    housed by Cardinal Brancaccio; this prelate being made bishop of Viterbo, Rosa
                    painted for the Chiesa della Morte a large and noticeable picture of the
                    Incredulity of Thomas—the first work of sacred art which we find recorded from
                    his hand. At Viterbo he made acquaintance with a mediocre poet named Abati, and
                    was hence incited to try his own faculty in verse. He then returned to Naples.
                    Here the monopolizing triumvirate—Ribera, Caracciolo, and Corenzio— were still
                    powerful. Rosa was as yet too obscure to suffer from their machinations; but,
                    having painted a picture of Tityus Torn by the Vulture, which went to Rome and
                    there produced a great sensation, he found it politic to follow in the footsteps
                    of his fame, and once more, in 1638, resought the papal city.</p>
                <p>Rosa was a man of facile and versatile genius, and had by this time several
                    strings to his bow. It is said that, still keeping painting steadily in view as
                    his real objective, he resolved to secure attention first as a musician, poet,
                    improvisatore, and actor—his mother-wit and broad Neapolitan dialect (which
                    appears to have stuck to him through life) standing him powerfully in stead. In
                    the carnival he masqued as Formica and Capitan Coviello, and bustled about Rome
                    distributing satirical prescriptions for diseases of the body and more
                    particularly of the mind. As Formica he inveighed against the farcical comedies
                    acted in the Trastevere under the direction of the celebrated Bernini. Some of
                    the actors, in one of their performances, retaliated by insulting Rosa, but the
                    public was with him, and he now enjoyed every form of <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n880/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0880-0847"/>success,—social prestige, abundant commissions,
                    and any amount of money, which he was wont to throw about broadcast to the
                    populace. In 1646 he returned to Naples, and is said to have taken an active
                    part in the insurrection of Masaniello; certain it is that he sympathized with
                    and admired the fisherman autocrat, for a passage in one of his satires proves
                    this. His actual share in the insurrection is, however, dubious; it appears only
                    in recent narratives, and the same is the case with the well-known story that at
                    one time he herded with a band of brigands in the Abruzzi—an incident which
                    cannot be conveniently dove-tailed into any of the known dates of his career. As
                    regards the popular revolt against Spanish tyranny, it is alleged that Rosa,
                    along with other painters —Coppola, Porpora, Micco Spadaro, Dal Po, Masturzo,
                    the two Vaccari, and Cadogna—all under the captaincy of Aniello Falcone, formed
                    the Compagnia della Morte, whose mission it was to hunt up Spaniards in the
                    streets and despatch them, not sparing even those who had sought some place of
                    religious asylum. He painted a portrait of Masaniello—probably from reminiscence
                    rather than from life: indeed it is said that he painted him several times over
                    in less than life size. On the approach of Don John of Austria the blood-stained
                    Compagnia dispersed, Rosa escaping or at ' any rate returning to Rome. Here he
                    painted some important subjects, showing the uncommon bent of his mind as it
                    passed from landscape into history —Democritus amid Tombs, the Death of
                    Socrates, Regulus in the Spiked Cask (these two are now in England), Justice
                    Quitting the Earth, and the Wheel of Fortune. This last work, the tendency of
                    which was bitingly satirical, raised a storm of ire and remonstrance. Rosa,
                    endeavouring at conciliation, published a description of its meaning (probably
                    softened down not a little from the real facts); none the less an order for his
                    imprisonment was issued, but ultimately withheld at the instance of some
                    powerful friends. It was about this time that Rosa wrote his satire named <hi
                    rend="italic">Babylon,</hi> under which name Rome was of course indicated.</p>
                <p>Cardinal Giancarlo de’ Medici now invited the painter to leave Rome—which had
                    indeed become too hot to hold him—for Florence. Salvator gladly assented, and
                    remained in the Tuscan capital for the better part of nine years, introducing
                    there the new style of landscape; he had no pupils, but various imitators.
                    Lorenzo Lippi the painter poet, Baldovini, and other <hi rend="italic">beaux
                    esprits</hi> shared with Rosa the hospitalities of the cardinal, and they formed
                    an academy named I Percossi (the Stricken), indulging in a deal of ingenious
                    jollity—Rosa being alike applauded as painter, poet, and musician. His chief
                    intimate at this time was Lippi, whom he encouraged to proceed with the poem <hi
                    rend="italic">Il Malmantile Racpuistato.</hi> He was well acquainted also with
                    Ugo and Giulio Maffei, and housed with them more than once in Volterra, where he
                    wrote other four satires— <hi rend="italic">Music, Poetry, Painting,</hi> and
                    <hi rend="italic">War.</hi> About the same time he painted his own portrait, now
                    in the Uffizi Gallery of Florence. Finally he reverted once more to Rome, and
                    hardly left that city again. Much enmity still brooded there against him, taking
                    the form more especially of an allegation that the satires which he zealously
                    read and diffused in MS. were not his own production, but filched from some one
                    else. Rosa indignantly repelled this charge, which remains indeed quite
                    unsubstantiated, although it is true that the satires deal so extensively and
                    with such ready manipulation in classical names, allusions, and anecdotes that
                    one is rather at a loss to fix upon the period of his busy career at which Rosa
                    could possibly have imbued his mind with such a multitude of semi-erudite
                    details. It may perhaps be legitimate to suppose that his literary friends in
                    Florence and Volterra had coached him up to a large extent—the satires, as
                    compositions, remaining none the less strictly and fully his own. To confute his
                    detractors he now wrote the last of the series, entitled <hi rend="italic"
                    >Envy.</hi> Among the pictures of his closing years were the admired Battlepiece
                    now in the Louvre, painted in the short space of forty days, full of long-drawn
                    carnage, with ships burning in the offing; Pythagoras and the Fishermen; the
                    Oath of Catiline (Pitti Gallery); and the very celebrated Saul and the Witch of
                    Endor (Louvre), which is perhaps his latest work. He undertook a series of
                    satirical portraits, to be closed by one of himself, but while occupied with
                    this project he was assailed by dropsy, which, after lasting fully half a year,
                    brought his life to a close on loth March 1673. In his last moments he married a
                    Florentine named Lucrezia, who kept his house and had borne him two sons, one of
                    them surviving him, and he died in a contrite frame of mind. He lies buried in
                    the Chiesa degli Angeli, where a portrait of him has been set up. Salvator Rosa,
                    after .the hard struggles of his early youth, had always been a successful man,
                    and he left a handsome fortune.</p>
                <p>Rosa λvas indisputably a great leader in that modern tendency of fine art towards
                    the romantic and picturesque which, developing in various directions and by
                    diversified processes, has at last almost totally differentiated modern from
                    olden art. He saw appearances with a new eye, and presented new images of them
                    on his canvases, and deserves therefore all the credit due to a vigorous
                    innovator, even if we contest the absolute value of his product. He himself
                    courted reputation for his historical works, laying comparatively little stress
                    on his landscapes; in portraits he was forcible. In chiaroscuro he is simple and
                    effective; his design has energy and a certain grandeur, without any high type
                    of form or any superior measure of correctness. His colour is too constantly of
                    a sandy or yellowish-grey tone. Personally he was a man of high spirit, and he
                    sold his pictures at large prices, more (it is said) to assert the honour of his
                    art than from love of money; rather than sell them cheap he destroyed them. In
                    his later Florentine period he etched several of his works, subjects of
                    mythology, soldiering, &amp;c. He was choleric, but kind and generous. Though a
                    man of gaiety and pleasure, and a jovial boon companion, he does not appear to
                    have been vicious in any serious degree. He was talkative, very sharp-tongued,
                    and an unblushing encomiast of his own performances. Among his pictures not
                    already mentioned we may name, in the London National Galleiy, Mercury and the
                    Dishonest Woodman, and two others; in Raynham Hall, Belisarius; in the Grosvenor
                    Gallery, Diogenes; in the Pitti Gallery, a grand portrait of a man in armour,
                    and the Temptation of St Anthony, which contains his own portrait. This last
                    subject appears also in St Petersburg, and in the Berlin Gallery.</p>
                <p>The satires of Salvator Rosa deserve more attention than they have generally
                    received. Though considerably spread abroad during his lifetime, they were not
                    published until 1719. They are all in terza rima, written without much literary
                    correctness, but remarkably spirited, pointed, and even brilliant. They are
                    slashingly denunciatory, and from this point of view too monotonous in
                    treatment. Rosa here appears as a very severe castigator of all ranks and
                    conditions of men, not sparing the highest, and as a champion of the poor and
                    down-trodden, and of moral virtue and Catholic faith. It seems odd that a man
                    who took so free a part in the pleasures and diversions of life should be so
                    ruthless to the ministers of these. The satire on <hi rend="italic">Music</hi>
                    exposes the insolence and profligacy of musicians, and the shame of courts and
                    churches in encouraging them. <hi rend="italic">-Poetry</hi> dwells on the
                    pedantry, imitativeness, adulation, affectation, and indecency of poets— also
                    their poverty, and the neglect with which they were treated; and there is a very
                    vigorous sortie against oppressive governors and aristocrats. Tasso’s glory is
                    upheld; Dante is spoken of as obsolete, and Ariosto a£ corrupting. <hi
                    rend="italic">Painting</hi> inveighs against the pictorial treatment of squalid
                    subjects, such as beggars (though Rosa must surely himself have been partly
                    responsible for this misdirection of the art), against the ignorance and
                    Iewdness of painters, and their tricks of trade, and the gross indecorum of
                    painting sprawling half-naked saints of both sexes. <hi rend="italic">IVar</hi>
                    (which contains the eulogy of Masaniello) derides the folly of hireling
                    soldiers, who fight and perish while kings stay at home; the vile morals of
                    kings and lords, heresy, and unbelief also come in for a flagellation. In <hi
                    rend="italic">Babylon</hi> Rosa represents himself as a fisherman, Tirreno,
                    constantly unlucky in his net-hauls on the Euphrates; he converses with a native
                    of the country, Ergasto. Babylon (Rome) is very severely treated, and Naples
                    much the same. <hi rend="italic">Envy</hi> (the last of the satires, and
                    generally accounted the best, although without strong apparent reason)
                    represents Rosa <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n881/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0881-0848"/>dreaming that, as he is about to inscribe in all
                    modesty his name upon the threshold of the temple of glory, the goddess or fiend
                    of Envy obstructs him, and a long interchange of reciprocal objurgations ensues.
                    Here occurs the highly-charged portrait of the chief Roman detractor of Salvator
                    (we are not aware that he has ever been identified by name); and the painter
                    protests that he would never condescend to do any of the lascivious work in
                    painting so shamefully in vogue.</p>
                <p>As authorities for the life of Salvator Rosa, Passeri, <hi rend="italic">Vite
                    drPitlori,</hi> may he consulted, and Salvini, <hi rend="italic">Safire e Vila
                    di Salrator Rosa;</hi> also Baldinucei and Dominiei. The <hi rend="italic"
                    >Life</hi> by Lady Morgan is a romantic treatment, mingling tradition or mere
                    Action with fact. (W. M. R.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
