<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0334-0317-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">REDSHANK (9th edition, volume 20, page 317)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1092276">Redshank</term>
                    <term ref="fast:833880">Blacks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:833576">Black</term>
                    <term ref="fast:995621">Leggings</term>
                    <term ref="fast:995328">Leg</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1109037">Scolopax</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vd0k">Leg</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j96094w">Seasons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fn10z9f">Nests</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45x25p07">Winter</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210572">Iceland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n334/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">REDSHANK</label> the usual name of a bird—the <hi
                    rend="italic">Scolopax calidris</hi> of Linnaeus and <hi rend="italic">Totanus
                    calidris</hi> of modern authors —so called in English from the colour of the
                    bare part of its legs, which, being also long, are conspicuous as it flies over
                    its marshy haunts or runs nimbly beside the waters it affects. In suitable
                    localities it is abundant throughout the greater part of Europe and Asia, from
                    Iceland to China, mostly retiring to the southward for the winter, though a
                    considerable number remain during that season along the coasts and estuaries of
                    some of the more northern countries. Before the great changes effected by
                    drainage in England it was a common species in many districts, but at the
                    present day there are very few to which it can resort for the purpose of
                    reproduction. In such of them as remain, its lively actions, both on the ground
                    and in the air, as well as its loud notes render the Redshank, during the
                    breeding-season, one of the most observable inhabitants of what without its
                    presence would often be a desolate spot, and invest it with a charm for the
                    lover of wild nature. At other times the cries of this bird may be thought too
                    shrill, but in spring the love-notes of the male form what may fairly be called
                    a song, the constantly repeated refrain of which— <hi rend="italic">leero,
                    leero</hi> , <hi rend="italic">leero</hi> (for so it may be syllabled)— rings
                    musically around, as with many gesticulations he hovers in attendance on the
                    flight of his mate; or, with a slight change to a different key, engages with a
                    rival; or again, half angrily and half piteously complains of a human intruder
                    on his chosen ground. The body of the Redshank is almost as big as a Snipe’s,
                    but its longer neck, wings, and legs make it appear a much larger bird. Above,
                    the general colour is greyish-drab, freckled with black, except the lower part
                    of the back and a conspicuous band on each wing, which are white, while the
                    flight-quills are black, thus producing a very harmonious effect. In the
                    breeding-season the back and breast are mottled with dark brown, but in winter
                    the latter is white. The nest is generally concealed in a tuft of rushes or
                    grass, a little removed from the wettest parts of the swamp whence the bird gets
                    its sustenance, and contains four eggs, usually of a rather warmly tinted brown
                    with blackish spots or blotches; but no brief description can be given that
                    would point out their differences from the eggs of other birds, more or less
                    akin, among which, those of the <hi rend="smallcaps">Lapwing</hi> (vol. xiv. p.
                    308) especially, they are taken and find a ready sale.</p>
                <p>The name Redshank, prefixed by some epithet as Black, Dusky, or Spotted, has also
                    been applied to a larger but allied species— the <hi rend="italic">Totanus
                    fuscus</hi> of ornithologists. This is a much less common bird, and in Great
                    Britain as well as the greater part of Europe it only occurs on its passage to
                    or from its breeding-grounds, which are usually found south of the Arctic
                    Circle, and differ much from those of its congeners—the spot ־ chosen for the
                    nest being nearly always in the midst of forests and, though not in the thickest
                    part of them, often with trees on all sides, generally where a fire has cleared
                    the undergrowth, and mostly at some distance from water. This peculiar habit was
                    first ascertained by Wolley in Lapland in 1853 and the following year. The
                    breeding-dress this bird assumes is also very remarkable, and seems (as is
                    suggested) to have some correlation with the burnt and blackened surface
                    interspersed with white stones or tufts of lichen on which its nest is made—for
                    the head, neck, shoulders, and lower parts are of a deep black, contrasting
                    vividly with the pure white of the back and rump, while the legs become of an
                    intense crimson. At other times of the year the plumage is very similar to that
                    of the common Redshank, and the legs are of the same light orange-red. (A.
                    N.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
