<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0883-0850-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ROSE (9th edition, volume 20, page 850)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4833n637">Rose</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sj19s90">Students</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9qc3b">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68d53">Tubes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18t15">Seeds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w37kw6x">Flowers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6pc2x">Planting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1100524">Roses</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1158581">Tubes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1111109">Seeds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:927866">Flowers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1065823">Plants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821579">Austrians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1136041">Students</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n883/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ROSE</label><hi rend="italic">(Rosa).</hi> The rose has for
                    all ages been the favourite flower, and as such it has a place in general
                    literature that no other plant can rival. In most cases the rose of the poets
                    and the rose of the botanist are one and the same in kind, but popular usage has
                    attached the name rose to a variety of plants whose kinship to the true plant no
                    botanist would for a moment admit. In this place we shall employ the word in its
                    strict botanical significance, and in commenting on it treat it solely from the
                    botanical point of view (see also <hi rend="smallcaps">Horticulture,</hi> vol.
                    xii. p. 260). The rose gives its name to the order <hi rend="italic"
                    >Rosaceae,</hi> of which it may be considered the type. The genus consists of
                    species varying in number, according to the diverse opinions of botanists of
                    opposite schools, from thirty to one hundred and eighty, or even two hundred and
                    fifty, exclusive of the many hundreds of mere garden varieties. While the lowest
                    estimate is doubtless too low, the highest is enormously too large, but in any
                    case the wide discrepancies above alluded to illustrate very forcibly the
                    extreme variability of the plants, their adaptibility to various conditions, and
                    consequently their wide dispersion over the globe, the facility with which they
                    are cultivated, and the readiness with which new varieties are continually being
                    produced in gardens by the art of the hybridizer or the careful selection of the
                    raiser. The species are natives of all parts of the northern hemisphere, but are
                    scantily represented in the tropics unless at considerable elevations.</p>
                <p>They are erect or climbing shrubs, never herbs or trees, generally more or less
                    copiously provided with thorns of various shapes and with glandular hairs, as in
                    the sweet brier or in the moss rose of gardens. The thorns serve the purpose of
                    enabling the shrub to sustain itself amid other vegetation, and perhaps in some
                    sort serve as a protection against marauders. The viscid hairs which are
                    specially frequent on the flower stalks or in the neighbourhood of the flower
                    serve to arrest the progress of undesirable visitants, while the perfume emitted
                    by the glands in question may co-operate with the fragrance and colour of the
                    flower to attract those insects whose presence is desirable. The leaves are
                    invariably alternate, provided with stipules, and unequally pinnate, the
                    stipules themselves being in this case perhaps merely the lowest pair of ‘ <hi
                    rend="superscript">,</hi> pinnae” or leaflets less perfectly developed than the
                    others. The flowers are solitary or in loose cymes (cluster-roses) produced on
                    the ends of the shoots. The flower-stalk expands into a vase-or urn-shaped
                    dilatation, called the receptacle or rcceρtacular tube, which ultimately becomes
                    fleshy and encloses in its cavity the numerous carpels or fruits. From the edge
                    of the urn or “hip” proceed five sepals, often more or less compounded like the
                    leaves and overlapping in the bud. AVitbin the sepals are five petals, generally
                    <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n884/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0884-0851"/>broad or roundish in outline, with a very short
                    stalk or none at all, and of all hues except blue. The very numerous stamens
                    originate from about the same spot as the sepals and petals; each has a slender
                    filament and a small two-celled anther. The inner portion of the receptacular
                    tube whence the stamens spring is thick and fleshy, and is occasionally spoken
                    of as the “disk”; but, as in this case it does not represent any separate organ,
                    it is better to avoid the use of the term. The carpels are very numerous,
                    ultimately hard in texture, covered with hairs, and each provided with a long
                    style and button-like stigma. The carpels are concealed within the receptacular
                    tube and only the stigmas as a rule protrude from its mouth. Each carpel
                    contains one ovule without perisperm. The so-called fruit is merely the
                    receptacular tube, which, as previously mentioned, becomes fleshy and brightly
                    coloured as an attraction to birds, which devour the hips and thus secure the
                    dispersion of the seed. The stamens are in whorls, and, according to Payer, they
                    originate in pairs one on each side of the base of each petal (parapetalous), so
                    that there are ten in each row; a second row of ten alternates with the first, a
                    third with the second, and so on. By repeated radial and tangential branching a
                    vast number of stamens are ultimately produced, and when these stamens assume a
                    petaloid aspect we have as a consequence the double flowers which are so much
                    admired. The carpels are much less subject to this petaloid change, and, as it
                    generally happens in the most double of roses that some few at least of the
                    anthers are formed with pollen, the production of seed and the possibility of
                    cross-breeding become intelligible. Under natural circumstances rose flowers do
                    not secrete honey, the attraction for insects being provided, according to
                    Müller, by the colour and perfume and the abundance of pollen for food. The
                    stigmas and anthers come to maturity at the same time, and thus, while
                    cross-fertilization by insect agency is doubtless most common, close
                    fertilization is not prevented.</p>
                <p>In <hi rend="italic">The Student's Flora</hi> Sir Joseph Hooker recognizes seven
                    species of <hi rend="italic">Rosa</hi> as British. Among them may be mentioned
                    <hi rend="italic">B SqAnosissima,</hi> the Scotch Rose, much less variable than
                    the others, A. <hi rend="italic">rubigiηosa,</hi> the Sweet Brier, represented
                    by several varieties, <hi rend="italic">R. canina,</hi> the DogRose, of which no
                    fewer than twenty-nine varieties are described, and <hi rend="italic">R.
                    arvensis.</hi> Cultivated roses are frequently “budded” or worked upon the stems
                    of the brier or <hi rend="italic">R. canina,</hi> or upon young seedling plants
                    of the same species. Other species also are used for stocks (see Horticulture).
                    Roses have been grown for so many centuries and have been crossed and recrossed
                    so often that it is difficult to refer the cultivated forms to their wild
                    prototypes. The older roses doubtless originated from <hi rend="italic">R.
                    galliea,</hi> a native of central and southern Europe. <hi rend="italic">R.
                    Centifolia</hi> (the Cabbage Rose), a native of the Caucasus, contributed its
                    share. A cross between the two species named may have been the source whence
                    originated the Bourbon Roses. The yellow-flowered Austrian and Persian Brier
                    originated from <hi rend="italic">R. Cglanteria,</hi> a native of Austria. The
                    Monthly or China Roses sprang from the Chinese <hi rend="italic">R. iηdicα,</hi>
                    and these crossed with others of the <hi rend="italic">R. Centifolia οτ
                    galliea</hi> type are the source of the hybrid perpétuais so commonly grown
                    nowadays, because, in addition to their other attractions, their blooming season
                    is relatively prolonged, and, moreover, is repeated in the autumn. Tea Roses and
                    Noisettes, it is to be presumed, also acknowledge <hi rend="italic">Rosa
                    indiea</hi> as one of their progenitors. The Banksian Rose is a Chinese
                    Climbingspecies, with small white or fawn-coloured flowers of great beauty; the
                    Macartney Rose (A. <hi rend="italic">bracteata)</hi> is also of Chinese origin.
                    Its nearly evergreen deep green leaves and large white flowers are very
                    striking. The Japanese A. <hi rend="italic">rugosa</hi> is also a remarkable
                    species, notable for its bold rugose foliage, its large white or pink flowers,
                    and its conspicuous globular fruit. A. <hi rend="italic">damascena</hi> is
                    cultivated in some parts of Roumelia for the purpose of making attar of roses
                    (see Oils and Perfumery). According to Hanbury, the flowers are gathered before
                    sunrise and distilled the same day. The distilled liquid is allowed to remain
                    for a day or two, by which time most of the oil will have risen to the surface,
                    from which it <hi rend="superscript">1</hi> is skimmed off. The percentage
                    yielded is very small, not more than O <hi rend="superscript">-</hi> O 4.</p>
                <p>In India A. <hi rend="italic">damascena</hi> is grown largely near Ghazipur for
                    the purpose of procuring attar of roses and rose water. The roses are distilled
                    with double their weight of water. The attar is skimmed off in the Turkish
                    method. Colonel Drury mentions that it takes 200,000 roses to yield the weight
                    of a rupee in attar. This quantity sells on the spot for 100 rupees.</p>
                <p>Rose water is chiefly produced in Europe from the Provence or cabbage rose, A.
                    <hi rend="italic">Centifolia,</hi> grown for the purpose at Mitcham and much
                    more abundantly in the south of France. Conserve of roses and infusion of roses,
                    two medicinal preparations retained for their agreeable qualities rather than
                    for any special virtue, are prepared from the petals of <hi rend="italic">Rosa
                    galliea,</hi> one variety of which was formerly grown for the purpose near the
                    town of Provins. Conserve of dog rose is made from the ripe hips of the dog
                    rose, <hi rend="italic">Rosa canina.</hi> Its only use is in the manufacture of
                    pills.</p>
                <p>The name Rose of Jericho is popularly applied to a small Cruciferous weed, <hi
                    rend="italic">Anastatiea Iiierochuntina,</hi> a native of the desert regions of
                    Egypt, !Arabia, Palestine, and Persia. In the dry season the dead branches are
                    strongly incurved, and thus serve to protect the still living seed in the pods.
                    In the wet season the branches absorb the moisture to a large extent, unfold,
                    resume the direction they had in life, and facilitate the dispersion of the seed
                    under circumstances favourable to germination. The plant is frequently carried
                    off as a curiosity, inasmuch as immersion in a basin of water enables it to
                    resume the original form and to create the impression that the plant “comes to
                    life again,” but the process is purely a physical one.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
