<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0621-0598-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ROBERTSON (9th edition, volume 20, page 598)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1066938">Play</term>
                    <term ref="fast:897549">Dramatists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:796296">Actors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1037627">Night</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1115061">Shafting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198490">Dreams</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4f18sp5w">Shafting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tx6q">Play</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xg38">Dreams</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vp7r">Home</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zv9m">Streets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vs7f">Dramatists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m5h">Actors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zh9p">Stage</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w922">Writers</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n621/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ROBERTSON</label> Thomas William (1829-1871), English
                    dramatist, was born on 9th January 1829. As a dramatist he had a brief but very
                    brilliant career. It is not too much to say that he was the most successful and
                    distinguished writer of plays in his generation. The son of a provincial actor
                    and manager, chief of a “circuit” that ranged from Bristol to Cambridge,
                    Robertson was familiar with the stage from his childhood; but it was not till
                    the last seven years of his life that he made his mark. He was never, as he
                    admitted himself, very successful as an actor. He tried his hand also at writing
                    plays, and a farcical comedy by him, <hi rend="italic">A Night's Adventure,</hi>
                    was produced at the Olympic under Farren’s management as early as 1851. But this
                    did not make good his footing, and he remained for some years longer in the
                    provinces, varying, his work as an actor with miscellaneous contributions to
                    newspapers. In 1860 he went to London with the intention, it is said, of making
                    his living by journalism and light literature. He edited a mining journal and
                    contributed to it a novel afterwards dramatized with the title <hi rend="italic"
                    >Shadow Tree Shaft.</hi> He wrote a farce entitled <hi rend="italic">A
                    Cantab,</hi> which was played at the Strand in 1861. Then, in 1864, came his
                    first marked success, <hi rend="italic">David Garrick,</hi> produced at the
                    Haymarket with Sothern in the principal character.. It was not, however, till
                    the production of <hi rend="italic">Society</hi> at the Prince of Wales Theatre
                    in 1865, under the management of Miss Marie Wilton, afterwards Mrs Bancroft,
                    that the originality and cleverness of the dramatist were fully recognized.
                    Play-writer and company were exactly suited one to another; the plays and the
                    acting together—the small size of the playhouse being also in their favour—were
                    at once recognized as a new thing, and, while some critics sneered at the
                    “cup-and-saucer comedy,” voted it absurdly realistic, said there was nothing in
                    it but commonplace life represented without a trace of Sheridanian wit and
                    sparkle, all London flocked to the little house in Tottenham Street, and the
                    stage was at once inundated with imitations of the new style of acting and the
                    new kind of play.</p>
                <p>Robertson, although his health was already undermined, followed up <hi
                    rend="italic">Society</hi> in quick succession with the series of characteristic
                    plays which made the reputation of himself, the company, and the theatre. <hi
                    rend="italic">Ours</hi> was produced in 1866, <hi rend="italic">Caste</hi> in
                    1867, <hi rend="italic">Play</hi> in 1868, <hi rend="italic">School</hi> in
                    1869, <hi rend="italic">M.P.</hi> in 1870. For twenty years there probably has
                    not been a week, hardly a night, in which some one of Robertson’s plays has not
                    been produced somewhere in Great Britain,.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n622/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0622-0599"/>
                <p>and still they show no sign of abating popularity. The masterly stage-craft is
                    undoubtedly one of the elements in this remarkable conquest of the play-going
                    public; the purity and generous morality of the plays another; the
                    dialogue—which is always bright and clever, without any straining after or
                    indeed much attaining to wit—a third; the humour, distinctness, and typical
                    representativeness of the characters a fourth. That there is more art and
                    individuality in the plays than critics at first were willing to admit is clear
                    from the fact that none of Robertson’s numerous imitators have succeeded in
                    catching his happy knack. Another proof of something like genius—dramatic genius
                    if not literary genius—is the skill with which he repeats the same idea with
                    such variations that each time it is as fresh as if it were new. Again and again
                    his situations owe their point to the contrast between generous kindness of
                    heart and sordid worldliness, or between the ardent trustful affections of youth
                    and the cynicism of disenchanted middle age. Pleasant sunny brightness and
                    ingenuity within a narrow range constitute Robertson’s distinction rather than
                    breadth or fertility or striking brilliancy of wit. He knew his powers and
                    worked steadily within them, not striving to go beyond. With the exception of
                    <hi rend="italic">David Garrick</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Home,</hi> written
                    for the Haymarket, and <hi rend="italic">Dreams</hi> for the Gaiety, all his
                    well-known plays were written for the Prince of Wales Theatre, with which his
                    distinctive style of comedy is identified. Unhappily he did not live long to
                    enjoy his success, but died in London in February 1871.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
