<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0235-0218-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">RAEBURN (9th edition, volume 20, page 218)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1072324">Portraits</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944605">Goldsmiths</term>
                    <term ref="fast:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:815177">Art</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:864129">Clerks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:830184">Bells</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198483">Brown</term>
                    <term ref="fast:961111">Hospitalers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w08wh24">Portraits</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r76k">Martins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2td33">Goldsmithing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47659k3h">Goldsmiths</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dz7j">Clerks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gm81p0j">Bells</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vp7r">Home</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4154dp40">Artists</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n235/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">RAEBURN</label><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Henry</hi>
                    (1756-1823), portrait-painter, was born at Stockbridge, a suburb of Edinburgh,
                    on the 4th of March 1756, the son of a manufacturer of the city. He was early
                    left an orphan. Being placed in Heriot’s Hospital, he received there the
                    elements of a sound education, and at the age of fifteen was apprenticed to a
                    goldsmith in Edinburgh. Here he had some little opportunity for the practice of
                    the humbler kinds of art, and various pieces of jewellery, mourning rings and
                    the like, adorned with minute drawings on ivory by his hand, are still extant.
                    Soon he took to the production of carefully finished miniatures; and, meeting
                    with success and patronage, he extended his practice to oil-painting, being all
                    the while quite self-taught. The worthy goldsmith his master watched the
                    progress of his pupil with interest, gave him every encouragement, and
                    introduced him to David Martin, who had been the favourite assistant of Allan
                    Ramsay junior, and was now the leading portrait-painter in Edinburgh. Raeburn
                    received considerable assistance from Martin, and was especially aided by the
                    loan of portraits to copy. Soon the young painter had gained sufficient skill to
                    render it advisable that he should devote himself exclusively to art. When in
                    his twenty-second year he was asked to paint the portrait of a young lady whom
                    he had previously observed and admired when he was sketching from nature in the
                    fields. She was the daughter of Peter Edgar of Bridgelands and widow of Count
                    Leslie. The lady was speedily fascinated by the handsome and intellectual young
                    artist, and in a month she became his wife, bringing him an ample fortune. After
                    the approved fashion of artists of the time, it was resolved that Raeburn should
                    visit Italy, and he accordingly started with his wife. In London he was kindly
                    received by Sir Joshua Reynolds, who gave him excellent advice as to his study
                    in Rome, especially recommending to his attention the works of Michelangelo. He
                    also offered him more substantial pecuniary aid, which was declined as unneeded;
                    but Raeburn carried with him to Italy many valuable introductions from the
                    president of the Academy. In Rome he made the acquaintance of Gavin Hamilton, of
                    Batoni, and of Byers. For the advice of the last-named he used to acknowledge
                    himself greatly indebted, and particularly for the recommendation that “he
                    should never copy an object from memory, but, from the principal figure to the
                    minutest accessory, have it placed before him.” After two years of study in
                    Italy he returned to Edinburgh in 1787, where he began a most successful career
                    as a portrait-painter. In that year he executed an admirable seated portrait of
                    the second Lord President Dundas.</p>
                <p>Of his earlier portraiture we have interesting examples in the bust-likeness of
                    Mrs Johnstone of Baldovie and in the three-quarter-length of Dr James Hutton,
                    works which, if they are somewhat timid and tentative in handling and wanting in
                    the trenchant brush-work and assured mastery of subsequent productions, are full
                    of delicacy and character. The portraits of John Clerk, Lord Eldin, and of
                    Principal Hill of St Andrews belong to a somewhat later period. Raeburn was
                    fortunate in the time in which he practised portraiture. Sir Walter Scott,
                    Blair, Mackenzie,</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n236/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0236-0219"/>
                <p>Woodhouselee, Robertson, Home, Ferguson, and Dugald Stewart were resident in
                    Edinburgh, and they were all, along with a host of others less celebrated,
                    immortalized on the painter’s canvas. Of his fully matured manner we could have
                    no finer examples than his own portrait and that of the Rev. Sir Henry Moncreiff
                    Wellwood, the bust of Dr Wardrop of Torbane Hill, the two full-lengths of Adam
                    Rolland of Gask and that of William Macdonald of St Martin’s. It was commonly
                    believed that Raeburn was less successful in his female than in his male
                    portraits, but the exquisite full-length of his wife, the smaller likeness of
                    Mrs R. Scott Moncrieff in the Scottish National Gallery, and that of Mrs Robert
                    Bell are sufficient to prove that he could on occasion portray all the grace and
                    beauty of the gentler sex.</p>
                <p>Raeburn spent his life in Edinburgh, rarely visiting the metropolis, and then
                    only for brief periods, thus preserving his own sturdy individuality, if he
                    missed the opportunity of engrafting on it some of the fuller refinement and
                    delicacy of the London portraitists. His leisure was employed in athletic
                    sports, in his garden, and in architectural and mechanical pursuits, and so
                    varied were the interests that filled his life that his sitters used to say of
                    him, “You would never take him for a painter till he seizes the brush and
                    palette.” Professional honours fell thick upon him. In 1812 he was elected
                    president of the Society of Artists in Edinburgh, in 1814 associate, and in the
                    following year full member of the Royal Academy. In 1822 he was knighted by
                    George IV. and appointed His Majesty’s limner for Scotland. He died at Edinburgh
                    on the 8th of July 1823.</p>
                <p>In his own day the portraits of Raeburn were excellently and voluminously
                    engraved, especially by the last members of the great school of English
                    mezzotint. In 1876 a collection of over 300 of his works was brought together in
                    the Royal Scottish Academy galleries; in the following year a series of twelve
                    of his iinest portraits was included in the winter exhibition of the Royal
                    Academy, London; and a volume of photographs from his paintings has been edited
                    by Dr John Brown.</p>
                <p>Raeburn possessed all the necessary requirements of a popular and successful
                    portrait-painter. He had the power of producing a telling and forcible likeness;
                    his productions are distinguished by breadth of effect, by admirable force of
                    handling, by execution of the swiftest and most resolute sort. Wilkie has
                    recorded that, while travelling in Spain and studying the works of Velazquez,
                    the brash-work of that master reminded him constantly of the “square touch” of
                    Raeburn. But the portraits of Velazquez are unsurpassable examples of tone as
                    well as of handling, and it is in the former quality that Raeburn is distinctly
                    wanting. The colour of his portraits is sometimes crude and out of relation,
                    inclining to the use of positive and definite local pigments, and too little
                    perceptive of the changeful subtilties and modifications of atmospheric effect.
                    His draperies frequently consist of little more than two colours—the local hue
                    of the fabric and the black which, more or less graduated, expresses its shadows
                    and modelling. In his flesh, too, he wants—in all but his very best productions—
                    the delicate refinements of colouring which distinguish the works of the great
                    English portrait-painters. His faces, with all their excellent truth of form and
                    splendid vigour of handling, are often hard and bricky in hue.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
