<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0219-0202-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">RABUTIN (9th edition, volume 20, page 202)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:844959">Camps</term>
                    <term ref="fast:844926">Camping</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649t8s">Camping</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n219/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">RABUTIN</label><hi rend="smallcaps">Roger de, Comte de
                    Bussy</hi> (1618-1693), commonly known as <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Bussy-Rabutin</hi> (and for shortness <hi rend="smallcaps">Bussy),</hi> is
                    perhaps the most characteristic figure among the lesser noblesse of France in
                    the 17th century, as La Rochefoucauld is among the greater. Bussy, however,
                    except in point of gallantry and literary power, chiefly illustrated the evil
                    sides of the character. He represented a family of distinction and age in
                    Burgundy (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Sevign¿,</hi> Madame de), and his father was
                    L6onor de Rabutin, a soldier of merit and a man of position, holding the
                    lieutenant-generalship of the province of Nivernais. Bussy-Rabutin (it is
                    perhaps advisable to add the family name to distinguish him from the hardly less
                    famous Bussy d’Amboise) was born in 1618. He was the third son, but by the death
                    of his elder brothers became the representative of the family. He entered the
                    army when he was only sixteen and fought through several campaigns, succeeding
                    his father in the office of “mestre de camp.” But he very early distinguished
                    himself in other ways than that of military service, and in 1641 was sent to the
                    Bastille by Richelieu for some months as a punishment for neglect of his duties
                    in running after his ladyloves. In 1643 he married a cousin, Gabrielle de
                    Toulongeon, who seems to have been fond of him, and for a short time he left the
                    army. But in 1644 he again bought a commission and for some years was closely
                    connected with the great CondA His wife died, and he became more famous, or at
                    least more notorious, than ever by an attempt to abduct Madame de Miramion, a
                    rich widow. This affair was with some difficulty made up and Bussy afterwards
                    married Louise de</p>
                <p>Rouville. When the Fronde broke out he, like others, went from party to party,
                    but finally passed to the royal side. He fought with some distinction both in
                    the civil war and on foreign service, and in 1655 he went to serve under Turenne
                    in Flanders. He served there for several campaigns and distinguished himself at
                    the battle of the Dunes and elsewhere; but he did not get on well with his
                    general, and his quarrelsome disposition, his overweening vanity, and his habit
                    of composing libellous <hi rend="italic">chansons</hi> by degrees made him the
                    enemy of most persons of position both in the army and at court. In the year
                    1659 he fell into disgrace for having taken part in an orgy or series of orgies
                    at Roissy near Paris during Holy Week, which caused great scandal, and shortly
                    afterwards he began to compose for the amusement of his mistress, Madame de
                    Montglas, his famous <hi rend="italic">Histoire Amoureuse des Gaules.</hi> This
                    book—a series of sketches of the chief ladies of the court, not without wit, but
                    much less remarkable for wit than for ill nature and licence—circulated freely
                    in manuscript and had numerous spurious sequels. One of these stung the king,
                    and Bussy was in 1665 sent to the Bastille, where he remained for more than a
                    year, and from which he was only liberated on condition of retiring to his
                    estates. Here he abode in what was then called exile for seventeen years. He was
                    then restored to a modified degree of royal favour, but never received any great
                    mark of it, and died in 1693.</p>
                <p>Although a man of considerable abilities, Bussy had very little in his character
                    that was either amiable or estimable. Despite his extravagant pride of birth and
                    rank, there is much reason for acquiescing in the verdict pronounced on him (by
                    an anonymous contemporary apparently), that he was “a coxcomb, who never, either
                    at court or in camp, lost the taste for bad company and the air of a rustic”;
                    his bravery was undoubted, but he seems to have much overrated his own military
                    ability. He libelled friends and foes alike, and any toleration which might be
                    extended to his innumerable gallantries is lessened by his incorrigible habit of
                    telling tales and his spiteful scandal - mongering against women who had left
                    him or whom he had left. He was, however, possessed of much literary power. The
                    <hi rend="italic">Histoire Amoureuse</hi> is in its most striking passages
                    merely adapted from Petronius, and, except in a few portraits, its attractions
                    are chiefly those of the scandalous chronicle. But his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Mémoires,</hi> published after his death, are extremely lively and
                    characteristic, and his voluminous correspondence yields in variety and interest
                    to few collections of the kind, except Madame de Sévigné’s, who indeed is
                    represented in it to a great extent, and whose letters first appeared in it. The
                    literary and historical student, therefore, owes Bussy some thanks. But it is
                    impossible not to see that he united some of the worst characteristics of an
                    aristocracy on the way to decadence—relaxed morals, a glaring indifference to
                    duty and to all motives but self-interest, insolence in prosperity, servility in
                    adverse circumstances, jealousy of others more favoured than himself.</p>
                <p>The best edition of the <hi rend="italic">Histoire Amoureuse des Gaules</hi> is
                    that of Boiteau and Livet in the Bibliothèque Elzévirienne (4 vols., Paris,
                    1856-76), of the <hi rend="italic">Mémoires</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Correspondance</hi> that of Lalanne (8 vols., Paris, 1857-59). Bussy wrote
                    other things, of which the most important, his <hi rend="italic">Genealogy of
                    the Rabutin Family,</hi> remained in M8. till 1867.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
