<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0709-0731-0421-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">EUSEBIUS (7th edition, volume 9, page 421)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xp6v36q">Arianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1163799">Valentinians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193750731?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">EUSEBIUS</label>, surnamed <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Pamphilus,</hi> a celebrated bishop of Caesarea, in Palestine, and onc of the
                    most illustrious men of the Christian church, was born in Palestine, towards the
                    close of the reign of Gallienus, about the year 267 of our era. He was the
                    intimate friend of Pamphilus, who suffered martyrdom under Diocletian in 309,
                    and, after his death, took his name in honour of his memory. He was ordained
                    bishop of Caesarea in 313. He had a considerable share in the contest relating
                    to Arius, whose cause he, as well as several other bishops of Palestine,
                    defended, being persuaded that Arius had been unjustly persecuted by Alexander,
                    bishop of Alexandria. He assisted at the council of Nice in 325, when he made a
                    speech to the emperor Constantine on his coming to the council, and was placed
                    next to him on his right hand. In 330 he was present at the council of Antioch,
                    in which Eustathius, bishop of that city, was unjustly deposed; but though he
                    was chosen by the bishop and people of Antioch to succeed that prelate, he
                    absolutely refused. In 334 hc assisted at the councils of Caesarea and of Tyre,
                    by which Athanasius was condemned; and he was present at the assembly of bishops
                    at Jerusalem during the dedication of the church in that city. By these bishops
                    he was sent to the emperor Constantine to defend what they had done against
                    Athanasius; when he pronounced the panegyric composed on. that emperor during
                    the public rejoicings in the beginning of the thirtieth year of his reign.
                    Eusebius survived the emperor but a short time, and died in 338. Ecclesiastical
                    writers, ancient and modern, are much divided in opinion respecting Eusebius.
                    Several have defended him with warmth, in which number are Sozomenes, Socrates,
                    Victorius, and some others. St Jerome, on the other hand, calls him the prince
                    of Arians, Photius accuses him, the seventh council condemns him, and this
                    opinion is generally followed by the moderns. The successor of Eusebius was
                    Acacius, surnamed the One-eyed, a man not less learned or less eloquent, and
                    more enterprising, than his master. Eusebius composed in Greek a multitude of
                    works filled with eloquence and erudition; and those which have reached us,
                    whilst they justify the high reputation of the author, cannot fail to occasion
                    regret that so many have perished. He wrote, 1. the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Apology</hi> or Defence <hi rend="italic">of Origen,</hi> in six books; 2. a
                    <hi rend="italic">Treatise against</hi><hi rend="italic">Hierocles</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> 3. Fifteen books of <hi rend="italic">Preparationes
                    Evangelicae,</hi> and twenty <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Demonstratione</hi><hi rend="italic">Evamgelica</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> 4.
                    A <hi rend="italic">Chronicle</hi> from the beginning of the world till the
                    twentieth year of Constantine; 5. An <hi rend="italic">Ecclesiastical
                    History,</hi> of which Valetius published a good edition in Greek and Latin; 6.
                    A <hi rend="italic">Paschal Cycle</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> 7. A work against
                    Marcellus of Ancyra, who was condemned at the council of Constantinople in 335
                    and 336; 8. Four books of the <hi rend="italic">Life of Constantine</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi></p>
                <p>9. Five books on the <hi rend="italic">Incarnation</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi>
                    İ0. Ten books of Commentaries on Isaiah; 11. Thirty books against Porphyry; 12.
                    a book of <hi rend="italic">Topics;</hi> 13. A <hi rend="italic">Nomenclature of
                    Peoples and Nations,</hi> according to the books of the Hebrews; 14. A <hi
                    rend="italic">Topography of Judaea and the Temple</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi>
                    15. Three books of the <hi rend="italic">Life of</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Pamphilus</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> 16. <hi rend="italic">Opuscula</hi> on
                    the Martyrs; 17. <hi rend="italic">Commentaries on the Psalms',</hi> 18. A <hi
                    rend="italic">Letter to Caspianus,</hi> and a <hi rend="italic">Concordance of
                    the Four Evangelists.</hi> It appears also that he wrote a <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cornmėntary on the first Epistle to the Corinthians,</hi> and a <hi
                    rend="italic">Treatise on the Accomplishment of the Predictions of Jesus
                    Christ.</hi> The greater number of his works, however, is only known by the
                    testimony of St Jerome, who makes frequent mention of them, cites fragments of
                    them, and appears to have used them very freely in the composition of his own
                    works. Of those which have come down to us, the most considerable is the <hi
                    rend="italic">Ecclesiastical History,</hi> which has been translated into Latin
                    by Rufinus, by Musculus, and by Christopherson. The version of the
                    last-mentioned translator, printed opposite the Greek text, appeared in 1612.
                    This work of Eusebius is of the greatest utility in reference to the history of
                    the Christian church during the first three centuries, and it has earned for its
                    author the honourable title of Father of Ecclesiastical History. In his <hi
                    rend="italic">Chronicle,</hi> which contains the principal actions of great men,
                    and the history of discovery in the arts, Eusebius is supposed to have availed
                    himself of the Chronology composed a century before by Julius Africanus. St
                    Jerome translated the Chronicle into Latin, and continued it till the sixth
                    consulate of Valens and Valentinian. The four books of the Life of Constantine
                    have been printed with the Ecclesiastical History, and translated into French by
                    Cousin. The ten books which remain of the <hi rend="italic">Preparatio
                    Evαngelica</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Demonstratio</hi> were published at
                    Paris in 1627, with the versions of Donatus and Vigerus, to which was subjoined
                    the Treatise against Hierocles. It is in the <hi rend="italic">Demonstratio</hi>
                    that the invaluable fragment on Sanctification is contained. The Topography of
                    the Holy Land, which St Jerome translated into Latin, was published in Greek by
                    Bonfrère in 1631: it is also found in several editions of the works of St
                    Jerome. The Commentary on the Psalms was published by Montfaucon; the <hi
                    rend="italic">Opuscula</hi> in Latin by Sirmond; the Letter to Caspianus and the
                    Canons for a Concordance <pb break="no" facs="nls:193750744?mode=fullsize"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0709-0744-0422"/> of the Gospels in the edition of the Greek New
                    Testament, by Robert Estienne, 1550; the Notes on the Canticles by Meursius; and
                    the fragments on the Lives of the Prophets by Curlerius, in his <hi
                    rend="italic">Commentaries of Procopius on Isaiah-</hi> EUSTATHIANS, a name
                    given to the Catholics of Antioch in the fourth century, on occasion of their
                    refusal to acknowledge any other bishop except Eustathius, who had been deposed
                    by the Arians. This denomination was given them during the episcopate of
                    Paulinus, whom the Arians substituted instead of Eustathius, about the year 330,
                    when they began to hold their assemblies apart. About the year 350, Leontius of
                    Phrygia, surnamed the Eunuch, who was an Arian, and was put in the see of
                    Antioch, desired the Eustathians to perform their service in his church; which
                    offer they accepted, and the church of Antioch served indifferently both Arians
                    and Catholics. This, we are told, gave occasion to two institutions, which have
                    ever since subsisted in the church; the first, psalmody in two choirs; and the
                    second, the doxology.</p>
                <p>This conduct, which seemed to imply a kind of communion with the Arians, gave
                    great offence to many of the Catholics, who began to hold separate meetings; and
                    hence arose the schism of Antioch. Upon this, the rest, who continued to meet in
                    the church, ceased to be called Eustathians, and that appellation was restricted
                    to the dissenting party. Flavianus, bishop of Antioch, in 381, and one of his
                    successors, Alexander, in 481, brought about a coalition or reunion between the
                    Eustathians and the body of the church of Antioch, which is described with much
                    solemnity by Theodoret <hi rend="italic">(Eccl.</hi> lib. iii. c. 2.)</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Eustathians</hi> were also a sect of heretics in the fourth
                    century, who derived their name from their founder Eustathius, a monk, who w as
                    so foolishly fond of his own profession, that he condemned all other conditions
                    of life. But whether this Eustathius was the same with the bishop of Sebastia
                    and the chief of the Semi-Arians, is not easy to determine.</p>
                <p>Eustathius excluded married people from salvation, prohibited his followers from
                    praying in their houses, and obliged them to quit all they had, as incompatible
                    with the hopes of heaven. He drew them out of the other assemblies of
                    Christians, to hold secret meetings with him, and made them wear a particular
                    habit; he ordained them to fast on Sundays; and he taught them, that the
                    ordinary fasts of the church were needless, after they had attained to a certain
                    degree of purity which he pretended to. He evinced great horror of chapels built
                    in honour of martyrs, and of the assemblies held therein. Several women, seduced
                    by his reasoning, forsook their husbands, and abundance of slaves deserted their
                    masters’ houses. He was condemned at the council of Gaugra in Paphlagonia, which
                    was held between the years 326 and 341.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
