<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0174-0163-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LA BADIE, LABADISTS (9th edition, volume 14, page
                    163)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xp6v395">Congregationalism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w669c71">Views</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2th4x">Resultants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bw6x">Spirits</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gb1xr6p">Spirit</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z892p9k">Spiritism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44b2x59s">Calvinism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130061">Spirits</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130040">Spirit</term>
                    <term ref="fast:844591">Calvinism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:875210">Congregationalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1166896">Views</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1047359">Order</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n174/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LA BADIE, LABADISTS</label>. Jean de la Badie, a noted
                    Pietist leader in the 17th century, was the son of Jean Charles de la Badie,
                    governor of Guyenne; he was born in the town of Bourg not far from Bordeaux, on
                    the 13th of February 1610, and died in Altona, on the 13th of February 1674. He
                    was sent along with two brothers to the Jesuit school at Bordeaux, where his
                    talents attracted the attention of bis teachers, and they secured him for their
                    order against the wishes of his parents. In 1626 he began to study philosophy
                    and theology, and in due time made his profession. From a study of the Bible, of
                    Augustine, Bernard, and the mystics, he was led to hold somewhat extreme views
                    about the efficacy of prayer and the direct influence of the Holy Spirit upon
                    believers, and adopted Augustinian views about grace, free will, and
                    predestination, which brought him into collision with his order. The result was
                    that he resigned and was separated from the Jesuits on the plea of ill health.
                    He then became a preacher to the people, and was encouraged by his bishop to
                    devote himself to this work. The study of Calvin’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Institutes,</hi> however, taught him that he had more in common with the
                    Reformed than with the Roman Catholic Church, and after various adventures he
                    joined the Reformed Church of France at Montauban in 1650. His fame had preceded
                    him, and his accession to the ranks of the Protestants was deemed a great
                    triumph; no such man since Calvin himself, it was said, had left the Roman
                    Catholic Church. He was called to the pastorate of the church at Orange on the
                    Rhone, and at once became noted for the severity of the discipline he exercised.
                    He set his face zealously against dancing, card-playing, and worldly
                    entertainments. The unsettled state of the country, recently annexed to France,
                    compelled him to leave Orange. He accepted a call to the French church in
                    London, but did not stay there long; and after various wanderings he at length
                    settled at Middelburg, where he was called to be pastor to the French-speaking
                    congregation. His peculiar opinions were by this time (1666) well known, and his
                    congregation and himself at once found themselves in conflict with the
                    ecclesiastical authorities. Various “classes” and synods met and discussed the
                    “seditious sermons and new and erroneous doctrine which De la Badie had preached
                    in various of our churches before he had been inducted at Middelburg,” and the
                    result was the establishment of a separate church by De la Badie and his
                    followers. He had gathered round him some enthusiastic disciples, Peter Yvon at
                    Montauban, Peter Dulignon, Francis Menuret, and more important than any Anna
                    Maria v. Schiirman, whose book <hi rend="italic">Eucleιia</hi> is perhaps the
                    best exposition of the tenets of her master. At Middelburg, at the head of his
                    separatist congregation, De la Badie developed his views for a reformation of
                    the Reformed Churches :—the church is a communion of holy people who have been
                    bom again from sin; baptism is the sign and seal of this regeneration, and is to
                    be administered only to believers; the Holy Spirit guides the regenerate into
                    all truth, and the church possesses throughout all time those gifts of prophecy
                    which it had in the ancient days; the community at Jerusalem is the continual
                    type of every Christian congregation, therefore there should be a community of
                    goods, the disciples should live together, eat together, dance together;
                    marriage is a holy ordinance between two believers, and the children of the
                    regenerate are born without original sin; marriage with an unregenerate person
                    is not binding. The life and separatism of the community brought them into
                    frequent collision with their neighbours and with the magistrates of Middelburg,
                    and in 1670 they accepted the invitation of the princess Elizabeth, abbess of
                    Herford in Westphalia, to take up their abode within her territories, and
                    settled down in Herford to the number of about fifty. Not finding the rest they
                    expected, however, they migrated to Altona in 1672, where they were dispersed on
                    the death of the leaders. Small communities also existed in the Rhineland, and a
                    missionary settlement was established in New York.</p>
                <p>See H. van Berkum, De Lαbαdic eη de Labadisten, Sneek, 1851; Goebel, Geseh. d.
                    Christi. Lebens in der rheinisdi-westphälischen Kirche, Coblentz, 1852; Heppe,
                    Geschichte des Pietismus, Leyden, 1879; Ritschi, Geschichte des Pietismus, vol.
                    i., Bonn, 1880; and especially Peter Yvon, Abrégé précis de la vie et de la
                    conduite et des vrais sentiments de feu Mr de Labadie, and Anna Maria v.
                    Schiirman, Eucleria, Altona, 1673, 1678.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n175/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0175-0164"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
