<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0831-0808-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LOIRET (9th edition, volume 14, page 808)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tv2w">Canals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20h7x">Valleys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48w3845p">Corn</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bz61762">Leveling</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:845230">Canals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1163841">Valleys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:878993">Corn</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996970">Levellers</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n831/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LOIRET</label>, a department of central France, made up of
                    three districts of the ancient province of Orléanais,— Orléanais proper,
                    Gâtinais, and Dunois,—together with portions of the Isle of France and Berri,
                    lies between.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n832/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0832-0809"/>
                <p>47° 30' and 48° 20' N. lat. and between 1° 30' and 3° 8' E. long., and is bounded
                    on the N. by Seine·et-0ise, on the N.E. by Seine-et-Marne, on the E. by Yonne,
                    on the S. by Nièvre and Cher, on the S.W. by Loir-et-Cher, and on the N.W. by
                    Eure-et-Loir; its greatest length, from north-west to south-east, is 75 miles,
                    its greatest breadth, from north to south along the meridian of Paris, 50 miles,
                    and its area 2614 square miles. The name is derived from the Loiret, a stream
                    which issues from the ground some miles to the south of Orleans, and after a
                    course of about 7 miles falls into the Loire; its large volume gives rise to the
                    belief that it is a subterranean branch of that river. The Loire traverses the
                    department by a broad valley which, though frequently devastated by disastrous
                    floods, is famed for its rich tilled lands, its castles, its towns, and its
                    vineclad slopes. To the right of the Loire are Gâtinais (capital Montargis) and
                    Beauce; the former district is so named from its <hi rend="italic">gatines</hi>
                    or wildernesses, of which saffron is, along with honey, the most noteworthy
                    product; Beauce, on the other hand, a monotonous tract of corn-fields without
                    either tree or river, has been called the granary of France. Between Beauce and
                    the Loire is the extensive forest of Orleans, which is slowly disappearing
                    before the advances of agriculture. South of the Loire is Sologne, long barren
                    and unhealthy from the impermeability of its subsoil, but undergoing gradual
                    improvement in both respects by means of pine plantation and draining and
                    manuring operations. The surface of the department presents little variation of
                    level; the highest point (on the borders of Cher) is 900 feet above the level of
                    the sea, and the lowest (ou the borders of Seine-et-Marne) is 220 feet. The
                    watershed on the plateau of Orleans between the basins of the Seine and Loire,
                    which divide Loiret almost equally between them, is almost imperceptible. The
                    lateral canal of the Loire from Roanne stops at Briare; from the latter town a
                    canal connects with the Seine by the Loing valley, which is joined by the
                    Orleans canal at Montargis. The only important tributary of the Loire within the
                    department is the Loiret; the Loing, a tributary of the Seine, has a course of
                    40 miles from south to north, and is accompanied throughout first by the Briare
                    canal and afterwards by that of Loing. The Essonne, another important affluent
                    of the Seine, entering Loiret at Malesherbes, takes its rise on the plateau of
                    Orleans, as also does its tributary the Juine. The department has the climate of
                    the Sequanian region, the mean temperature being almost the same as that of
                    Paris; the number of rainy days is one hundred and twenty, and the rainfall
                    varies from 18 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 5 to 27 ’ 5 inches according to
                    the district, that of the exposed Beauce being smaller than that of the woody
                    Sologne. Two-thirds of the entire area is cultivable; between one-sixth and
                    one-seventh is under wood; vineyards occupy one-twentieth; and the remainder is
                    taken up by meadows, heath, and marsh.</p>
                <p>A large number of sheep, cattle, horses, asses, pigs, and goats are reared;
                    poultry, especially geese, and bees are plentiful. The yield of wheat and oats
                    is much in excess of the consumption; the crops of rye, barley, meslin,
                    potatoes, beetroot, colza, and hemp are also very important. Wine is abundant,
                    but of inferior quality. Buckwheat supports bees by its flowers, and poultry by
                    its seeds. Saffron is another source of wealth. The woods consist of oak, elm,
                    birch, and pine; fruit trees thrive in the department, and Orleans is a great
                    centre of nursery gardens. The industries are brick and tile making, and the
                    manufacture of faience, for which Gien is one of the most important centres in
                    France. The Briare manufacture of porcelain buttons and pearls employs 1500
                    workmen. Flourmills are very numerous. There are iron and brass foundries,
                    which, along with agricultural implement making, bell-founding, and the
                    manufacture of pins, nails, and files, represent the chief metalworking
                    industries. The production of hosiery, wool-spinning, and various forms of wool
                    manufacture are also engaged in. A large quantity of the wine grown is made into
                    vinegar (vinaigre d’Orléans). The tanneries produce excellent leather; and
                    paper-making, sugar-refining, wax-bleaching, and the manufacture of caoutchouc
                    (in one factory) complete the list of industries. The exports are principally
                    corn, flour, wine, vinegar, live-stock, and wood. The four arrondissements are
                    those of Orleans, Gien, Montargis, and Pithiviers. The capital is Orleans. The
                    population in 1876 was 360,903 an increase of 70,764 since 1801.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
