<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0297-0282-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LANE, Edward William (9th edition, volume 14, page
                    282)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rp3w">Health</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42f7k049">Scholarship</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ht2gf4t">Scholarships</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:952743">Health</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1432095">Scholarships</term>
                    <term ref="fast:903991">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812574">Arabists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812576">Arabs</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n297/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LANE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Edward William</hi></label>
                    (1801-1876), one of the greatest of European Arabists, was the son of Dr
                    Theophilus Lane, a prebendary of Hereford. He lost his father in boyhood, and
                    his character was mainly formed by the influence of his mother, a woman of
                    strong and beautiful nature He was designed for Cambridge and the church, and
                    became proficient in mathematics, but, abandoning the purpose of proceeding to
                    the university, gave himself for some time to the study of engraving. Weak
                    health, aggravated by intense application to Eastern study, compelled him to
                    throw aside the burin, and in 1825 he started for Egypt, where he spent three
                    years, twice ascended the Nile, proceeding as far as the second cataract, and
                    composed a complete description of Egypt, with a portfolio of one hundred and
                    one drawings. This work was never published, but the account of the modern
                    Egyptians, which formed a part of it, was accepted for separate publication by
                    the Society for the Diffusion of Useful Knowledge. To perfect this work Lane
                    again visited Egypt in 1833-35, residing mainly in Cairo, but retiring to Luxor
                    during the plague of 1835. An interesting journal of this visit to Egypt is
                    included in the memoir by his grand-nephew prefixed to the sixth part of his
                    great <hi rend="italic">Lexicon.</hi> Perfected by the additional observations
                    collected during these years, the <hi rend="italic">Modern Egyptians</hi>
                    appeared in 1836, and at once took the place which it has never lost as the best
                    description of Eastern life and an Eastern country ever written. In accuracy,
                    completeness, and graphic simplicity of description the book approaches ideal
                    perfection. It was followed from 1838 to 1840 by a translation of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Arabian Nights,</hi> with a mass of valuable notes and
                    illustrations, designed to make the book a sort of encyclopaedia of Eastern
                    manners, and rivalling the merit of his first work. The translation itself is an
                    admirable proof of scholarship, but is characterized by a somewhat stilted
                    mannerism, which is not equally appropriate to all parts of the motley-coloured
                    original. The character of some of the tales, and the tedious repetitions of the
                    same theme which are found in the Arabic collection, induced Lane to leave
                    considerable parts of the work untranslated. In 1840 Lane married a Greek lady.
                    A useful volume of <hi rend="italic">Selectionsfrom the Kur-dn</hi> was
                    published in 1843, but before it passed through the press the indefatigable
                    author was again in Egypt, where he spent seven years (1842-49) collecting
                    materials for a great Arabic lexicon, which the munificence of Lord Prudhoe
                    (afterwards duke of Northumberland) enabled him to undertake. The most important
                    of the materials amassed during this sojourn (in which he was accompanied by his
                    wife and by his sister, Mrs Poole, authoress of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Englishwoman in Egypt,</hi> with her two sons, afterwards well known in Eastern
                    letters) was a copy in 24 thick quarto volumes of Sheikh Murtadâ’s great
                    lexicon, the <hi rend="italic">Taj</hi><hi rend="italic">et ‘Artes,</hi> which,
                    though itself a compilation, is so extensive and exact that it formed the main
                    basis of Lane’s subsequent work. The author, who lived in Egypt in last century,
                    used more than a hundred sources, interweaving what he learned from them with
                    the <hi rend="italic">Kdmus</hi> of Firuzabâdy in the form of a commentary. By
                    far the larger part of this commentary was derived from the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Lisän</hi><hi rend="italic">el ‘Arab</hi> of Ibn Mokarram, a work of the 13th
                    century, which Lane was also able to use while in Cairo.</p>
                <p>Returning to England in the year 1849, Lane devoted the whole remainder of his
                    life to the task of digesting and translating his Arabic material in the form of
                    a great thesaurus of the lexicographical knowledge of the Arabs. In spite of
                    weak health he continued this arduous task with unflagging diligence till a few
                    days before his death, which took place at Worthing 10th August 1876. The work
                    remains unfinished; five parts appeared during his lifetime (1863-1874), and two
                    smaller parts have since been published from his papers. Even in its imperfect
                    state the <hi rend="italic">Lexicon</hi> is an enduring monument, the
                    completeness and finished scholarship with which it is executed making each
                    article an exhaustive monograph. All Lane’s work has the stamp of masterly
                    perfection. He produced no occasional writings, and two essays contributed to
                    the magazine of the German Oriental Society complete the record of his
                    publications. Lane was not an original mind; his powers were those of
                    observation, industry, and sound judgment. He had singular tact in accommodating
                    himself to the Eastern character; he lived in the East as an Oriental; and his
                    familiarity with Eastern life and ways of thought was unique. His personal
                    character was elevated and pure, his strong sense of religious and moral duty
                    being of the type that characterized the best circles of English evangelicalism
                    in the early part of this century.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
