<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0485-0466-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LEOPOLD I (9th edition, volume 14, page 466)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:908898">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1159574">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:964057">Hungarians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208963">Turkey</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206891">Poland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n485/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LEOPOLD I</label>. (1G 40-1705), Holy Roman emperor, the
                    second son of the emperor Ferdinand HI. and Maria Anna of Spain, was born June
                    9,1640. He became king of Hungary in 1655, and king of Bohemia in 1658, in which
                    year he also received the imperial crown, the electors having chosen him in
                    preference to Louis XIV. of France. Leopold had been educated for the church,
                    and throughout life he had the tastes and sympathies of a churchman rather than
                    those of a secular ruler. He secluded himself as much as possible from the
                    world, and would have preferred to live in peace, yet his long reign was
                    destined to be one of the most agitated periods in German history. It happened
                    that he had in Louis XIV. a rival of extraordinary power, and Leopold was in no
                    respect a match for his craft, ambition, and audacity. The serious difficulties
                    of Leopold’s career began in 1662, when the mismanagement of his ministers in
                    regard to Transylvania made war with Turkey inevitable. The Turks invaded
                    Hungary, and, having seized Grosswardein and Neuhäusel, broke into Moravia and
                    Silesia. The princes of the empire, who had been made virtually independent by
                    the results of the Thirty Years’ War, watched the progress of the struggle with
                    indifference; but in 1663, Leopold having made a personal appeal to them in the
                    diet at Ratisbon, they were induced to grant him aid. On the 1st of August 1664
                    Montecuculi defeated the Turks at St Gotthard on the Raab, and had the war been
                    prosecuted with energy much future disaster would probably have been prevented.
                    The emperor, however, made no further use of his victory than to induce the
                    Turks to accept an armistice for twenty years. He allowed them to retain
                    Grosswardein and Neuhäusel, and their candidate for the principality of
                    Transylvania was formally recognized. In 1672 Leopold came for the first time
                    into direct collision with Louis XIV. As it seemed highly probable that the
                    French king would not be content with the conquest of Holland, Leopold, as head
                    of his hereditary territories and as emperor, associated himself with
                    Brandenburg and Spain for the support of the Dutch. For some time, in
                    consequence of the intrigues of Prince Lobkowitz, the emperor’s minister, the
                    war was conducted indolently by the Germans; and early in 1675 Turenne gained a
                    series of brilliant victories in Alsace. Later in the same year Turenne was
                    slain, and his army defeated at Sassbach; and Montecuculi forced his way across
                    the French frontier. The treaty of Nimeguen having been signed by the Dutch in
                    1678, the emperor concluded peace in 1679. The French retained Freiburg in
                    Breisgau; and soon afterwards Louis XIV., instead of giving up towns which he
                    had undertaken to resign, seized many new cities and districts. To these acts of
                    robbery he gave an appearance of legality by instituting so-called “Chambers of
                    Reunion.” The German people bitterly resented his aggression, but the princes
                    declined to interfere, and the energies of the emperor were fully occupied
                    elsewhere. His system of government in Hungary was arbitrary and tyrannical, and
                    in 1682 the Hungarians, headed by Emeric Tökölyi, broke into open revolt. They
                    were encouraged by Louis XIV., who stirred up the Turks to join them in
                    attacking Austria. In 1683 a Turkish army of 200,000 men, led by the grand
                    vizier Kara Mustapha, entered Hungary, and pushed on to Vienna, which they
                    besieged from the 14th of July till the 12th of September. The German princes
                    were unwilling to act even in such an emergency as this, but at last an imperial
                    army under the electors of Bavaria and Saxony marched towards Vienna, and they
                    were joined by John Sobieski of Poland with a corps of 26,000 men. These troops,
                    in association with the emperor’s army under Duke Charles of Lorraine, attacked
                    the Turks on the 12th of September 1683, at the Kalenberg, near Vienna. The
                    Turks were so effectually defeated that they were soon driven from Hungary.
                    Another great victory was gained over them at Mohacz in 1687; and in 1697 they
                    were defeated by Prince Eugene at Zenta. In 1699 the treaty of Carlowitz was
                    signed, whereby the emperor became complete master of the districts which the
                    Turks had conquered in Hungary. Twelve years before (1687), the Hungarians, worn
                    out by the struggle, had submitted to the emperor at the diet of Pressburg, the
                    monarchy being made hereditary in the house of Hapsburg instead of elective.
                    This settlement had scarcely been concluded when the emperor was involved in new
                    troubles by the French invasion of the Palatinate in 1688. On this occasion
                    Louis XIV. had to account with an antagonist of a very different character from
                    the emperor Leopold. William of Orange, when raised to the throne of England,
                    made it the object of his life to break the supremacy of France; and through his
                    efforts was formed the Grand Alliance, which for more than eight years carried
                    on war by sea and land. The emperor did not approve of the treaty of Ryswick
                    (1697), but after the withdrawal of his allies he had no alternative but to
                    consent to the establishment of peace. Louis was compelled to cede most of the
                    acquisitions he had made after the treaty of Nimeguen, but retained Strasburg.
                    In 1701 began the war of the Spanish succession, waged by Leopold in defence of
                    the claims of his second son Charles against those of Philip of Anjou, grandson
                    of Louis XIV. In this war Leopold was supported by the empire, and by England,
                    Holland, and Prussia. It opened with several victories gained by Prince Eugene;
                    but afterwards King Joseph and the margrave of Baden were repeatedly defeated,
                    and the emperor was weakened by a renewal of the movement for national
                    independence in Hungary. His confidence was revived by the battle of Blenheim,
                    but he did not live to see the full results of that great victory. On the 5th of
                    May 1705 he died of dropsy in the chest. He was a man of ungainly appearance,
                    the most prominent feature of his face being his large hanging under-lip. The
                    life of his court <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n486/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0486-0467"/> was regulated in accordance with the strictest
                    rules of Spanish etiquette, but in his relations to his family a naturally kind
                    disposition often broke through the crust of rigid conventions. Although one of
                    the most intolerant sovereigns of his age, he gave considerable attention to
                    science, and took a prominent part in the establishment of the universities of
                    Innsbruck, Olmütz, Halle, and Breslau. Early in his reign he allowed his
                    judgment to be controlled by his cabinet, but he never placed implicit trust in
                    any minister after the discovery that Lobkowitz had been in communication with
                    the French. He was married three times, and two of his sons became
                    emperors—Joseph L and Charles VI. <hi rend="smallcaps">(j.</hi> si.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
