<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0633-0614-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LIGHTFOOT, John (9th edition, volume 14, page
                    614)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86q1x">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vr13">Stone</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tx35664">Baptism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:880858">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1133812">Stone</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1133955">Stoning</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1043068">Occasionalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:827229">Baptism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n633/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LIGHTFOOT, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi></label>
                    (1602-1675), an eminent rabbinical scholar, was the son of Thomas Lightfoot,
                    vicar of Uttoxeter, Staffordshire, and was born at Stoke-upon-Trent in that
                    county, on March 29, 1602. His school education was received at Morton Green
                    near Congleton, Cheshire, and in June 1617 he entered Christ’s College,
                    Cambridge, where he made great progress in Latin and Greek, and was reckoned the
                    best orator among the undergraduates. After taking his bachelor’s degree, he
                    became for some time assistant master at Repton in Derbyshire; at the canonical
                    age he received ordination, and shortly afterwards was appointed curate of
                    Norton-under-Hales in Shropshire. There he attracted the notice of Sir Rowland
                    Cotton, an amateur Hebraist of some attainments it would seem, who made him his
                    domestic chaplain at Bellaport, and was the first to awaken his taste for
                    rabbinical learning. Shortly after the removal of Sir Rowland with his family to
                    London, Lightfoot followed him thither, but for some unexplained reason soon
                    left the capital again, and, visiting his parents at Uttoxeter, took a solemn
                    leave of them, having resolved “to travel beyond the seas.” An unexpected and
                    pressing invitation induced him to change his determination, and to accept a
                    charge at Stone in Staffordshire, where he continued for about two years, and
                    where, on May 21, 1628, he married Joyce, daughter of William Crompton of Stone
                    Park, and widow of George Copwood of Delverne, Staffordshire. From Stone he
                    removed to Hornsey near London, for the sake of the library of Sion College,
                    which he often had occasion to consult; his first published work, entitled <hi
                    rend="italic">Erubhin, or Miscellanies, Christian and Judaical, penned for
                    recreation at vacant hours,</hi> and dedicated to Sir R. Cotton, appeared at
                    London in 1629. During the summer and autumn of 1630 he lived at Uttoxeter, and
                    in September of that year he was presented by Sir R. Cotton to the rectory of
                    Ashley in Staffordshire, where he continued to discharge his pastoral duties,
                    and to prosecute his rabbinical studies, for the next twelve years. For the more
                    uninterrupted pursuit of the latter he is said to have bought a small piece of
                    land near his parsonage, and to have built upon it a small house “containing a
                    study and withdrawing room below, and a lodging chamber above.” “Here he closely
                    followed his said studies with great delight and unwearied diligence, and did
                    choose to lodge here very often, though it were so near to his family and
                    parsonage house.” In June 1642 he left Ashley for London; the precise occasion
                    of the removal is not known, but probably it arose out of the necessity for
                    personal superintendence of the publication of his next work, <hi rend="italic"
                    >A few and new Observations upon the Book of Genesis: the most of them certain;
                    the rest, probable; all, harmless, strange, and rarely heard of before,</hi>
                    which appeared at London in that year with a dedication to “my dear and loving
                    countrymen of the county of Stafford, and other my friends residing in the city
                    of London.” Soon after his arrival in the capital he became minister of St
                    Bartholomew’s church, near the Exchange; and in 1643 he was appointed to preach
                    the sermon before the House of Commons on occasion of the public fast of March
                    29. It was afterwards published under the title of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Elias</hi><hi rend="italic">Redivivus,</hi> the text being Luke i. 17; in it a
                    parallel is drawn between the Baptist’s ministry and the work of reformation
                    which in the preacher’s judgment was incumbent on the parliament of his own day.
                    Lightfoot was also one of the original members of the Westminster Assembly,
                    which held its first formal meeting<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n634/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0634-0615"/> on Saturday, July 1, 1643; his “Journal of the
                    Proceedings of the Assembly of Divines from January 1, 1643 to December 31,
                    1644,” now printed in the thirteenth volume of the 8vo edition of his <hi
                    rend="italic">Works,</hi> is a valuable historical source for the too brief
                    period to which it relates. He was assiduous in his attendance from the first,
                    and, though frequently standing almost or even quite alone, especially in the
                    Erastian controversy, exercised a material influence on the result of the
                    discussions of the Assembly. In 1643 Lightfoot published <hi rend="italic">A
                    Handful of Gleanings out of the Book of Exodus,</hi> dedicated to the
                    inhabitants of Bartholomew Exchange, and in the same year he was made master of
                    Catherine Hall by the parliamentary visitors of Cambridge, and also, on the
                    recommendation of the Assembly, was promoted to the rectory of Much Munden in
                    Hertfordshire; both appointments he retained until his death. In 1644 was
                    published in London the first instalment of the laborious but never completed
                    work of which the full title runs <hi rend="italic">The Harmony of the Four
                    Evangelists among themselves, and with the Old Testament, with an explanation of
                    the chiefest difficulties both in Language and Sense: Part I. From the beginning
                    of the Gospels to the Baptism of our Saviour.</hi> The second part <hi
                    rend="italic">From the Baptism of our Saviour to the first Passover after</hi>
                    followed in 1647, and the third <hi rend="italic">From the first Passover after
                    our Saviour’s Baptism to the second</hi> in 1650. On August 26, 1645, he again
                    had the honour of preaching before the House of Commons on the day of their
                    monthly fast; in the discourse, which was afterwards published <hi rend="italic"
                    >(A Fast Sermon,</hi> on Rev. xx. 1, 2), after controverting as erroneous and
                    false the doctrine of the Millenaries, he goes on to urge upon the parliament
                    various practical suggestions for the repression with a strong hand of current
                    blasphemies (“I do hold it a truer point in divinity that ‘ errans conscientia
                    liganda ’ than ‘ ligat ’ ”), for a thorough revision of the authorized version
                    of the Scriptures, for the encouragement of a learned ministry, and for a speedy
                    settlement of the church. “I rejoice to see what you have done in platforming
                    classes and presbyteries, and I verily and cordially believe it is according to
                    the pattern in the mount.” In the same year appeared <hi rend="italic">A
                    Commentary upon</hi><hi rend="italic">the Acts of the Apostles, chronical and
                    critical; the Difficulties of the text explained, and the times of the Story
                    east into annals. From the beginning of the Book to the end of the Twelfth
                    Chapter. With α brief survey of the contemporary Stary of the Jews and
                    Bomans</hi> (down to the third year of Claudius); and in 1647 he published <hi
                    rend="italic">The Harmony, Chronicle, and Order of the Old Testament,</hi> which
                    was followed in 1655 by <hi rend="italic">The Harmony, Chronicle, and Order of
                    the New Testament,</hi> inscribed to Cromwell, with an epistle dedicatory to his
                    highness’s honourable council. In the last-named year Lightfoot, who in 1652 had
                    commenced doctor of divinity, was chosen vice-chancellor of the university of
                    Cambridge, but continued to reside by preference at Munden, in the rectory of
                    which, as well as in the mastership of Catherine Hall, he was confirmed, through
                    the influence of friends, at the Restoration. The remainder of his life was
                    principally devoted to the production of the work by which his name now chiefly
                    lives, the <hi rend="italic">Horae Hebraicae et Talmudicae,</hi> in which the
                    volume relating to Matthew appeared in 1658, that relating to Mark in 1663, and
                    those relating to 1 Corinthians, John, and Luke, in 1664, 1671, and 1674
                    respectively. Towards the close of 1675, while travelling from Cambridge to Ely
                    (where he had been collated by Sir Orlando Bridgman to a prebendal stall), he
                    caught a severe cold, upon which, by an indiscretion in diet it is said, fever
                    supervened; falling afterwards into a lethargy w hich continued for about a
                    fortnight, he died at Ely on December 6, 1675. The <hi rend="italic"
                    >Horse</hi><hi rend="italic">Hebraicae et Talmudicae impenses</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">in</hi><hi rend="italic">Acta</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Apostolorum</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">in Ep. S.
                    Pauli</hi><hi rend="italic">ad</hi><hi rend="italic">Bomanos</hi> were published
                    posthumously.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> of Lightfoot were first edited, in 2 vols, fol.,
                    by Bright and Strype in 1684; the <hi rend="italic">Opera Omnia,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">cura</hi><hi rend="italic">Τexelii,</hi> appeared at Rotterdam in
                    1686 (2 vols, fol.), and again, edited by Leusden, at Franeker in 1699 (3 vols.
                    fol.). A volume of <hi rend="italic">Remains</hi> was published at London in
                    1700. The <hi rend="italic">Ηor. Hebr.</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Talm.</hi> were also edited in Latin by Carpzov (Leipsic,
                    1675-79), and again, in English, by Gandell (Oxford, 1859). The most complete
                    edition is that of the <hi rend="italic">Whole Works,</hi> in 13 vols. 8vo,
                    edited by Pitman (London, 1822-25). It includes, besides the works already
                    noticed, numerous sermons, letters, and miscellaneous writings; and also <hi
                    rend="italic">The Temple, especially as it stood in the Lays of our Saviour</hi>
                    (London, 1650).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
