<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0707-0684-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LIPPI (9th edition, volume 14, page 684)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1050530">Painters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1747280">Virgins</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1167649">Virginity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1167852">Vision</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1167909">Visions</term>
                    <term ref="fast:852215">Chapels</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94k2c">Painters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g68c">Virginal</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44m91m0x">Virginity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z892g7x">Chapels</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93k3f">Madonna</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47w67561">Visions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20q1q">Vision</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n707/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LIPPI</label>, the name of three celebrated Italian
                    painters.</p>
                <p>I. <hi rend="smallcaps">Fra Filippo Lippi</hi> (1412-1469), commonly called Lippo
                    Lippi, one of the most celebrated painters of the Italian quatrocento, was born
                    in Florence,- <hi rend="superscript"> j</hi>-his father, Tommaso, being a
                    butcher. His mother died in his earliest infancy, and his father two years
                    later. His aunt, a poor woman named Monna Lapaccia, then took charge of him; and
                    in 1420, when only eight years of age, he was registered in the community of the
                    Carmelite friars of the Carmine in Florence. Here he remained till 1432, and his
                    early faculty for fine art was probably developed by studying from the works of
                    Masaccio in the neighbouring chapel of the Brancacci. Between 1430 and 1432 he
                    executed some works in the monastery, which were destroyed by a fire in 1771;
                    they are specified by Vasari, and one of them was particularly marked by its
                    resemblance to Masaccio’s style. Eventually Fra Filippo quitted his convent, but
                    it appears that he was not relieved from some sort of religious vow; there is a
                    letter of his, dated in 1439, in which he speaks of himself as the poorest friar
                    of Florence, and says he is charged with the maintenance of six marriageable
                    nieces. In 1452 he was appointed chaplain to the convent of S. Giovannino in
                    Florence, and in 1457 rector <hi rend="italic">(Rettore Commendatarw)</hi> of S.
                    Quirico at Legnaia,and his gains were considerable,and even uncommonly large
                    from time to time; but his poverty seems to have been chronic none the less, the
                    money being spent, according to one account, in frequently recurring amours.</p>
                <p>Vasari relates some curious and romantic adventures of Fra Filippo, which modern
                    biographers are not inclined to believe. Except through Vasari, nothing whatever
                    is known of his visits to Ancona and Naples, and his intermediate capture by
                    Barbary pirates and enslavement in Barbary, whence his skill in
                    portrait-sketching availed to release him. The doubts thrown upon his
                    semi-marital relations with a Florentine lady appear, however, to be somewhat
                    arbitrary; Vasari’s account is circumstantial, and in itself not greatly
                    improbable, and to say that he is the sole authority for the facts goes but a
                    small way towards invalidating them. Towards June 1456 Fra Filippo was settled
                    in Prato (near Florence) for the purpose of fulfilling an important commission
                    which had been given him to paint frescos in the choir of the cathedral. Before
                    actually undertaking this work he set about painting, in 1458, a picture for the
                    convent chapel of St Margaret of Prato, and there saw Lucrezia Buti, the
                    beautiful daughter of a Florentine, Francesco Buti; she was either a novice or a
                    young lady placed under the nuns’ guardianship. Lippi asked that she might be
                    permitted to sit to him for the figure of the Madonna; he made passionate love
                    to her, abducted her to his own house, and kept her there spite of the utmost
                    efforts the nuns could make to reclaim her. The fruit of their loves was a boy,
                    who became the painter, not less celebrated than his father, Filippino Lippi
                    (noticed below). Such is substantially Vasari s narrative, published less than a
                    century after the alleged events; it is not refuted by saying, more than three
                    centuries later, that perhaps Lippo had nothing to do with any such Lucrezia,
                    and perhaps Lippino was his adopted son, or only an ordinary relative and
                    scholar. The argument that two reputed portraits of Lucrezia in paintings by
                    Lippo, one as a Madonna in a very fine picture in the Pitti gallery, and the
                    other in the same character in a Nativity in the Louvre, are not alike comes to
                    very little; and it is reduced to nothing when the disputant adds that the
                    Louvre painting is probably not done by Lippi at all. This painting comes,
                    however, from St Margaret’s at Prato, and is generally considered to be the very
                    one on which Vasari’s story hinges.</p>
                <p>The frescos in the choir of Prato cathedral, being the stories of the Baptist and
                    of St Stephen, represented on the two opposite wall spaces, are the most
                    important and monumental works which Fra Filippo has left, more especially the
                    last of the series, showing the ceremonial mourning over Stephen’s corpse. This
                    contains a portrait of the painter, but which is the proper figure is a question
                    that has raised some diversity of opinion. Some of the subjects are legendary,
                    as, for instance, the attempt of the devil to substitute a changeling for the
                    infant protomartyr. At the end wall of the choir are S. Giovanni Gualberto and
                    S. Albert, and on the ceiling the four evangelists.</p>
                <p>The close of Lippi’s life was spent at Spoleto, where he had been commissioned to
                    paint, for the apse of the cathedral, some scenes from the life of the Virgin.
                    In the semidome of the apse is Christ crowning the Madonna, with angels, sibyls,
                    and prophets. This series, which is not wholly equal to the one at Prato, was
                    completed by Fra Diamante after Lippi’s death.</p>
                <p>That Lippi died in Spoleto, on or about 8th October 1469, is an undoubted fact;
                    the mode of his death is again a matter of dispute. It has been said that the
                    pope granted Lippi a dispensation for marrying Lucrezia, but that, before the
                    permission arrived, he had been poisoned by the indignant relatives either of
                    Lucrezia herself, or of some lady who had replaced her in the inconstant
                    painter’s affections. This is now generally regarded as a fable; and it may very
                    well be such, although the incident does not present any intrinsic improbability
                    in relation to the Italy of the 15th century. Fra Filippo lies buried in
                    Spoleto, with a monument erected to him by Lorenzo the Magnificent; he had
                    always been zealously patronized by the Medici family, beginning with Cosmo
                    Pater Patriae. Francesco di Pesello (called Pesellino) and Sandro Botticelli
                    were among his most distinguished pupils.</p>
                <p>Some leading pictures by Lippi not already mentioned are the following. In 1441
                    he painted an altarpiece for the nuns of S. Ambrogio which is now a prominent
                    attraction in the Accademia of Florence, and has been celebrated in Browning’s
                    well-known poem. It represents the Coronation of the Virgin among angels and
                    saints, of whom many are Bernardine monks. One of these, placed to the right, is
                    a half-length portrait of Lippo, pointed out by an inscription upon an angers
                    scroll “Is perfecit opus.” The price paid for this work in 1447 was 1200
                    Florentine lire, which seems surprisingly or even unaccountably large. For
                    Geminiano Inghirami of Prato he painted the death of St Bernard, a fine specimen
                    still extant. His principal altarpiece in this city is a Nativity in the
                    refectory of S. Domenico,—the Infant on the ground adored by the Virgin and
                    Joseph, between Sts George and Dominic, in a rocky landscape, with the shepherds
                    playing and six angels in the sky. In the Uffizi is a fine Virgin adoring the
                    infant Christ, who is held by two angels; in the London National Gallery, a
                    Vision of St Bernard. The picture of the Virgin and Infant with an Angel, in
                    this same gallery, also ascribed to Lippi, is disputable.</p>
                <p>Few pictures are so thoroughly enjoyable as those of Lippo Lippi; they show the
                    naïveté of a strong rich nature, redundant in lively and somewhat whimsical
                    observation. He approaches religious art from its human side, and is not
                    pietistic though true to a phase of Catholic devotion. He was perhaps the
                    greatest colourist and technical adept of his time, with good draughtsmanship,—a
                    naturalist, with less vulgar realism than some of his contemporaries, and with
                    much genuine episodical animation, including semi-humorous incidents and low
                    characters. He made little effort after perspective and none for
                    foreshortenings, was fond of ornamenting pilasters and other architectural
                    features. Vasari says that Lippi was wont to hide the extremities in drapery, to
                    evade difficulties. His career was one of continual development, without
                    fundamental variation in style or in colouring. In his great works the
                    projκ&gt;rtions are larger than life.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n708/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0708-0685"/>
                <p>II. <hi rend="smallcaps">Filippino</hi> or <hi rend="smallcaps">Lippino
                    Lippi</hi> (1460-1505) was the natural son of Fra Lippo Lippi and Lucrezia Buti,
                    born in Florence and educated at Prato. Losing his father before he had
                    completed his tenth year, the boy took up his avocation as a painter, studying
                    under Sandro Botticelli, and probably under Fra Diamante. The style which he
                    formed was to a great extent original, but it bears clear traces of the manner
                    both of Lippo and of Botticelli,—more ornamental than the first, more realistic
                    and less poetical than the second. His powers developed early; for we find him
                    an accomplished artist by 1480, when he painted an altarpiece, the Vision of St
                    Bernard, now in the Badia of Florence; it is in tempera, with almost the same
                    force as oil painting. Soon afterwards, probably from 1482 to 1490, he began to
                    work upon the frescos which completed the decoration of the famous Brancacci
                    chapel in the Carmine, commenced by Masolino and Masaccio many years before. He
                    finished Masaccio’s subject of the Resurrection of the King’s Son, and was the
                    sole author of Paul’s Interview with Peter in Prison, the Liberation of Peter,
                    the Two Saints before the Proconsul, and the Crucifixion of Peter. These works,
                    were none others extant from his hand, are sufficient to prove that Lippino
                    stood in the front rank of the artists of his time. The dignified and expressive
                    figure of St Paul in the second-named subject has always been particularly
                    admired, and appears to have furnished a suggestion to Raphael for his Paul at
                    Athens. Portraits of Luigi Pulci, Antonio Pollaiuolo, Lippino himself, and
                    various others are to be found in this series. In 1485 he executed the great
                    altarpiece of the Virgin and Saints, with several other figures, now in the
                    Uffizi Gallery. Another of his leading works is the altarpiece for the Nerli
                    Chapel in S. Spirito—the Virgin Enthroned, with splendidly living portraits of
                    Nerli and his wife, and a thronged distance. In 1489 Lippino was in Rome,
                    painting in the church of the Minerva, having first passed through Spoleto to
                    design the monument for his father in the cathedral of that city. Some of his
                    principal frescos in the Minerva are still extant, the subjects being in
                    celebration of St Thomas Aquinas. In one picture the saint is miraculously
                    commended by a crucifix; in another, triumphing over heretics. In 1496 Lippino
                    painted the Adoration of the Magi now in the Uffizi, a very striking picture,
                    with numerous figures. This was succeeded by his last important undertaking, the
                    frescos in the Strozzi Chapel, in the church of S. Maria Novella in Florence—
                    Drusiana Restored to Life by St John the Evangelist, St John in the Cauldron of
                    Boiling Oil, and two subjects from the legend of St Philip. These are
                    conspicuous and attractive works, yet somewhat grotesqueand exaggerated,— full
                    of ornate architecture, showy colour, and the distinctive peculiarities of the
                    master. Filippino, who had married in 1497, died in 1505 of an attack of throat
                    disease and fever, aged only forty-five. His character for amiability and
                    courtesy is described in very laudatory terms by Vasari. The best-reputed of his
                    scholars was Raffaellino del Garbo.</p>
                <p>Like his father, Filippino had a most marked original genius for painting, and he
                    was hardly less a chief among the artists of his time than Fra Filippo had been
                    in his; it may be said that in all the annals of the art a rival instance is not
                    to be found of a father and son each of whom had such pre-eminent natural gifts
                    and leadership. The father displayed more of sentiment, and candid sweetness of
                    motive; the son more of richness, variety, and lively pictorial combination. He
                    was admirable in all matters of decorative adjunct and presentment, such as
                    draperies, landscape backgrounds, and accessories; and he was the first
                    Florentine to introduce a taste for antique details of costume, &amp;c. He
                    formed a large collection of objects of this kind, and left his designs of them
                    to his son. In his later works there is a tendency to a mannered development of
                    the extremities, and generally to facile overdoing. The London National Gallery
                    ]&gt;ossesses a good and characteristic though not exactly a first-rate specimen
                    of Lippino, the Virgin and Child between Sts Jerome and Dominic.</p>
                <p>III. <hi rend="smallcaps">Lorenzo Lippi</hi> (1606—1664), a painter and poet, was
                    born in Florence. He studied painting under Matteo Rosselli, the influence of
                    whose style, and more especially of that of Santi di Tito, is to be traced in
                    Lippi’s works, which are marked by taste, delicacy, and a strong turn for
                    portrait-like naturalism. His maxim was “to poetize as he spoke, and to paint as
                    he saw.” After exercising his art for some time in Florence, and having married
                    at the age of forty the daughter of a rich sculptor named Susini, Lippi went as
                    court painter to Innsbruck, where he has left many excellent portraits. There he
                    wrote his humorous poem named <hi rend="italic">Malmantile Racquistato,</hi>
                    which was published under the anagrammatic pseudonym of “Pcrlone Zipoli.” Lippi
                    was a friend of Salvator Rosa, and was a man of pleasant and generous temper,
                    and very polite. He was, however, somewhat self-sufficient, and, when visiting
                    Parma, would not look at the famous Correggios there, saying that they could
                    teach him nothing. He died of pleurisy in 1664.</p>
                <p>The most esteemed works of Lippi as a painter are a Crucifixion in the gallery at
                    Florence, and a Triumph of David which he executed for the saloon of Angiolo
                    Galli, introducing into it portraits of the seventeen children of the owner. His
                    poem the <hi rend="italic">Mαlmαrdilc Racquistato</hi> is a burlesque romance,
                    mostly compounded out of a variety of popular tales; its principal
                    subject-matter is an expedition for the recovery of a fortress and territory
                    whose queen had been expelled by a female usurper. It is full of graceful or
                    racy Florentine idioms, and is counted by Italians as a “testo di lingua.” Lippi
                    is more generally or more advantageously remembered by this poem than by
                    anything which he has left in the art of painting. It was not published until
                    1688, several years after his death. (W. Μ. R.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
