<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0668-0647-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LIME (9th edition, volume 14, page 647)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r72g">Gypsum</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40z7110r">Lime</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fj5w">Calcium</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cf9j625">Ammonia</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04032">Alcohol</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41z41s37">Alcoholates</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:998853">Limes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:998827">Lime</term>
                    <term ref="fast:844035">Calcium</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807737">Ammonia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:804631">Alcohols</term>
                    <term ref="fast:939255">Gays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931557">Foraminifera</term>
                    <term ref="fast:949721">Gypsum</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210572">Iceland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n668/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LIME</label> is the name of the strongly basic monoxide CaO
                    of the metal calcium. This base is widely diffused throughout the three kingdoms
                    of nature in the form of salts, of which the carbonate CaCO <hi rend="subscript"
                    > 3</hi> and the hydrated sulphate CaSO <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>.2H <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O are by far the most abundant. Both are found in the
                    mineral kingdom in a variety of forms. Of native carbonates of lime, <hi
                    rend="italic">calcspar</hi> (Iceland spar), though comparatively rare, may be
                    mentioned first as representing the purest native form of the compound. It
                    generally presents itself in the form of well-developed transparent colourless
                    rhombohedra, which possess to a remarkable degree the property of producing
                    double refraction of light, whereupon is founded its application in the
                    construction of certain optical instruments. Of the varieties of massive or
                    crystalline carbonate of lime, those which, through the fineness of their grain
                    and other qualities, lend themselves for the purposes of the sculptor go by the
                    name of marble, while the remainder are embraced under the generic term of
                    limestone. This name, however, is understood to exclude chalk, a soft, amorphous
                    variety which, according to Ehrenberg, consists mainly of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Foraminifera</hi> shells. All limestones contain at least traces of magnesia.
                    When this foreign base is present in considerable proportion the rock is termed
                    “dolomite” (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Magnesium).</hi> Among the native forms of
                    (hydrated) sulphate of lime the mineral “selenite” (glacies Mariae) corresponds
                    to Iceland spar among the carbonates. It forms colourless transparent
                    clino-rhombic prisms, generally united into “twins,” and flattened down into
                    plates readily cleavable along planes parallel to the surface. Hardness ranges
                    from 1 ’ 5 to 2; the specific gravity is 2 <hi rend="superscript"> ,</hi> 3. Far
                    more common than selenite are the massive varieties known as <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Alabaster</hi> (see vol. i. p. 439) and ordinary <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Gypsum</hi> (vol. xi. p. 337).</p>
                <p>Both sulphate and carbonate of lime, apart from their occurrence as independent
                    minerals, are almost universally diffused throughout the earth’s crust, and in
                    the waters of the ocean. Now the sulphate is appreciably soluble in even pure
                    water, while the carbonate, though practically insoluble in pure, is quite
                    decidedly soluble in carbonic acid water. As all atmospheric water must
                    necessarily hold carbonic acid gas in absorption, most natural waters, and
                    certainly all deep-well waters, are contaminated with more or less of
                    bicarbonate or sulphate of lime, or with both. When such a water is being
                    boiled, there is an escape of the free and the loosely combined carbonic acid,
                    and the carbonate of lime comes down as a loose precipitate or as a “crust”;
                    and, when the water is sufficiently concentrated by evaporation, the sulphate
                    likewise is partly deposited. The decomposition of the “bicarbonate” in fact
                    takes place, though slowly, even at ordinary temperatures, when the water in
                    which it is held in solution is exposed to the atmosphere. It is in this manner
                    that stalagmites and stalactites frequently seen within rock-caverns are
                    produced, and there is no difficulty in accounting for the grotesque and
                    fantastic forms which the latter often exhibit.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Quicklime.—</hi> The native carbonate always serves as the
                    starting-point in the preparation of calcium compounds. From it the oxide CaO,
                    known as quicklime or caustic lime, is produced industrially by heating
                    limestone or marble in kilns, between layers of fuel, which in the United
                    Kingdom is generally coal. The carbonic acid goes away with the gaseous products
                    of combustion, and the oxide remains in unfused lumps of the form of the
                    original stones. Lime, when pure, is an amorphous white solid, which is
                    absolutely infusible and non volatile; and on this account, when raised to high
                    temperatures, it emits a brilliant white light (“lime-light”). The commercial
                    article is generally grey or otherwise discoloured by the presence of foreign
                    metallic oxides.</p>
                <p>The decomposition that goes on in a limekiln is not brought about by the effect
                    of heat alone. Gay-Lussac found long ago that carbonate of lime, when heated to
                    intense redness in a closely covered crucible, loses its carbonic acid only very
                    slowly, while the acid goes off readily even at somewhat lower temperatures when
                    a current of steam is passed over the heated limestone. This may be accounted
                    for by assuming that the steam, in the first instance, produces hydrate—from the
                    carbonate—of lime, which latter then at once breaks up into its two components.
                    More probably, however, the steam acts only by producing a <hi rend="italic"
                    >quasi</hi> vacuum, that is, by clearing out the carbonic acid which, if allowed
                    to stagnate even at high temperatures, would react on the quicklime produced,
                    thus preventing the decomposition of a portion of the carbonate.</p>
                <p>Quicklime acts readily and energetically on water, with evolution of much heat
                    (269 units per unit weight of lime, Berthelot) and formation of a bulky white
                    powder of the hydrate CaOH <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O or Ca(OH) <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> ∙ This powder readily mixes with water into a smooth
                    paste, which may be diluted to a milky liquid—milk of lime. This, when filtered
                    through paper, yields “lime-water,” a strongly alkaline liquid containing about
                    <hi rend="subscript"> τ</hi> ⅜ <hi rend="subscript"> π</hi> th of its weight of
                    lime (calculated as CaO). When boiled it deposits a part of its dissolved lime
                    as such, and when exposed to ordinary air it quickly draws a skin of carbonate
                    of lime. Hence its application as a reagent for carbonic acid, and the extensive
                    use of mille of lime (whitewash) as a cheap white pigment in wall-painting. Lime
                    paste, as every one knows, is most extensively used as a mortar or cement for
                    bricks and stones in building. For this purpose it is always mixed with a
                    certain proportion of sand. This admixture in all probability was originally
                    intended only to save lime and prevent shrinking. But it is now generally
                    assumed to have a chemical function, causing the formation of a hard silicate of
                    lime pervading and thus strengthening the mortar. Some chemists deny the
                    practical importance though not the occurrence of this silication; what admits
                    of no doubt is that the hardening of mortar involves the very gradual conversion
                    of the original hydrate into carbonate of lime. Under the name of plaster, a
                    fine smooth paste of lime and sand, with short hair to increase the tenacity of
                    the mixture, is a most important material for coating the internal walls and
                    roofs of ordinary buildings.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Hydraulic Cements.—</hi> Ordinary mortar, on account of the
                    solubility of lime in water, is unfit for aquatic mascnry; for this purpose
                    hydraulic cements must be used. Of these there are a great variety, which,
                    however, mostly agree in this that they consist of calcined mixtures of
                    limestone and clay (preferably alkaliferous clay) and other silicates. By
                    calcining such mixtures at temperatures short of that at which a glass would be
                    produced, the lime becomes caustic, and part of the caustic lime, by uniting
                    with the clay (and silicate generally), forms a silicate sufficiently basic to
                    be disintegrable by acids and even by water. When such cement, as a powder, is
                    mixed with water, the lime acts upon the silicate of alkali and the gelatinous
                    silica-hydrate transitorily produced, and with the silica and alumina and oxide
                    of iron unites into a hard, waterproof, very complex, silicate mixture.</p>
                <p>H. Ste Claire Deville having found that magnesia has hydraulic properties,
                    hydraulic cements have been made by calcining dolomites of the proper
                    composition so far as to decompose only the carbonate of magnesia (into MgO and
                    CO <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>). See <hi rend="smallcaps">Cement,</hi> vol. v.
                    p. 328.</p>
                <p>Lime, being the cheapest of powerful bases, is largely used in chemical
                    manufacturing. It serves for the causticizing of soda, for the preparation of
                    ammonia from ammonia salts, and for the manufacture of bleaching powder. It also
                    enters into the composition of certain kinds of glass, and is used (as lime or
                    as carbonate), in the making of soda ash.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Lime Salts. —</hi> These can in general be prepared by the
                    saturation of the respeotive acids with lime hydrate. Thus the (pure) <hi
                    rend="italic">ear·</hi><pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n669/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0669-0648"/><hi rend="italic">bonate</hi> CaCO <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 3</hi> may be prepared by passing carbonic acid into
                    limewater. But a more convenient method is to decompose a solution of pure
                    chloride of calcium with excess of carbonate of ammonia, preferably at 70-80°
                    C., when the carbonate assumes the form of a crystalline precipitate which
                    settles readily and is easily washed with hot water. The <hi rend="italic"
                    >sulphate</hi> (artificial gypsum) appears as a voluminous white precipitate,
                    consisting of minute colourless needles, when sulphuric acid is added to a not
                    too dilute solution of chloride of calcium or other lime salt. The precipitate
                    CaSO <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>.2H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O is
                    appreciably soluble in water, 1000 parts of which at 0°, 35°, and 100° C.
                    dissolve 2‘05, 2 ’ 54, and a little over 2 parts respectively of gypsum. The
                    hydrated sulphate at temperatures exceeding 110“ C. loses its water. The
                    anhydrous sulphate, if formed below about 200° C., readily recombines with water
                    into compact gypsum (plaster of Paris). By exposure to high temperatures (500°
                    C. and upwards) sulphate of lime loses its power of recombining with water; at
                    very high temperatures it fuses. A naturally anhydrous sulphate of lime
                    (anhydrite) occurs in association with rock salt, and otherwise, as a not very
                    common mineral.</p>
                <p>The well-known favourable action of gypsum as a manure, more especially for
                    clover (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Agriculture),</hi> has lately been explained by
                    Déherain on the strength of analyses and vegetation experiments of his own, by
                    assuming that it converts the carbonate of potash of the soil into sulphate,
                    which, being less obstinately retained by the soil, more readily finds its way
                    into the roots of the plants.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Chloride of Calcium</hi> (muriatie of lime), CaCl <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, is prepared by dissolving marble or limestone in
                    aqueous muriatic acid. The iron and manganese generally present as impurities
                    can be eliminated, after peroxidation by chlorine water, by digestion with
                    hydrate of lime, which also, if allowed sufficient time, removes the magnesia.
                    The filtrate is acidified with hydrochloric acid and concentrated by
                    evaporation, so far that, on cooling, it deposits part of the dissolved salt as
                    crystals. These have the composition CaCl <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>.6H <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O. They are very easily soluble in water and alcohol,
                    and highly hygroscopic. Hence the salt is used occasionally to keep textile
                    fibres moist and in a fit state for being woven. The crystals when kept in a
                    basin at about 200° lose about two-thirds of their water, and leave that porous
                    kind of chloride of calcium which analytical chemi⅛ts prefer for the drying of
                    gases. This substance, when heated to redness— which must be done in platinum to
                    prevent contamination—loses the rest of the λvater and (at 723° C., Carnelley)
                    fuses into the anhydrous salt CaCl <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, which on
                    cooling hardens into a stone-like mass. In this final process of dehydration,
                    however, part of the chlorine goes off as hydrochloric acid, so that the product
                    obtained is contaminated with some oxychloride. This can be prevented by
                    igniting the salt with sal-ammoniac or—more surely—by effecting the dehydration
                    in a current of anhydrous hydrochloric acid gas. Anhydrous chloride of calcium
                    is much used in laboratories as a powerful dehydrating agent. It combines with
                    ammonia gas into a solid compound. It dissolves in methyl alcohol and in ethyl
                    alcohol, forming crystallizable “alcoholates” (Graham), compounds of CaCl <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> with “crystal alcohol.”</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Nitrate of Calcium,</hi> Ca(NO <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>)
                    <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, crystallizing with 4H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>
                    O, is a very hygroscopic salt, soluble in even absolute alcohol. It is mentioned
                    here as a material for the convenient preparation of <hi rend="italic">pure</hi>
                    lime—by simple ignition of the salt in a platinum crucible. Regarding <hi
                    rend="italic">bleaching powder,</hi> a double salt of hypochlorite and chloride
                    of calcium Cl-Ca-(C1O), see <hi rend="smallcaps">Chlorine,</hi> vol. v. p.
                    678.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Fluoride of Calcium,</hi> CaF <hi rend="subscript"> a</hi>,
                    obtainable by precipitation of chloride of calcium with an alkaline fluoride,
                    occurs in nature as <hi rend="smallcaps">Fluorspar</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >(q.v.).</hi> Fluoride of calcium is widely disseminated throughout the mineral
                    kingdom aβ an admixture with other minerals. All native forms of phosphate of
                    lime contain it; some in considerable quantity. Traces of it are found in bones
                    and in the ashes of most plants.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Metallic Calcium</hi> cannot be prepared by the reduction of
                    the oxide with charcoal. It may be produced, however, by the electrolysis of the
                    fused chloride or—more conveniently—by heating the iodide Cal <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> (seven parts) with sodium (one part) in an iron
                    crucible. The metal has a yellow colour; it is somewhat harder than lead, and
                    very malleable and ductile (Liès-Bodart and Jobin). The specific gravity is 1 ’
                    578 (Bunsen and Matthicson). It does not tarnish in <hi rend="italic">dry</hi>
                    air, but readily decomposes water, with evolution of hydrogen and formation of
                    hydrate of lime. It is practically non-volatile. When heated in air or oxygen it
                    burns with a most brilliant light into oxide, CaO.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Tests.</hi> —Solutions of ordinary calcium salts are not
                    affected visibly by sulphuretted hydrogen, sulphide of ammonium, or pure
                    ammonia. Carbonate of ammonia, even in the presence of sal-ammoniac,
                    precipitates the carbonate. So far calcium behaves like barium and strontium.
                    From the former it is distinguished by its not being precipitated by either
                    hydrofluosilicic acid or bichromate of potash, and from both by its spectrum and
                    the relatively large solubility of its sulphate in water. The latter is obtained
                    from any calcium solution by addition of sulphuric acid and alcohol. The
                    sulphate is washed with alcohol on a filter. When then boiled with water it
                    yields a solution which, dilute as it is, gives a very distinct precipitate with
                    oxalate of ammonia (barium and strontium sulphates in these circumstances give
                    negative results). Oxalate of ammonia is the most delicate precipitant for
                    calcium; the precipitate is insoluble in water, in ammonia and ammonia salts,
                    and in acetic acid. From solutions (in acids) of phosphate or oxalate of calcium
                    ammonia and likewise sulphide of ammonium precipitate the metal as phosphate or
                    oxalate. To detect it in such a precipitate, dissolve in hydrochloric acid and
                    add sulphuric acid and alcohol. The calcium is precipitated as sulphate, which
                    can be identified as just explained.</p>
                <p>For the phosphates of lime, see <hi rend="smallcaps">Phosphates.</hi> (W. D.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
