<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0311-0294-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LAOS, or Lawa (9th edition, volume 14, page
                    294)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bg2hh25">Mongols</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zf6b">Malays</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r724">Presents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42n4zk6c">Complexion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bn9x40m">Buffaloes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1156484">Tribes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1033832">Nationalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:840456">Buffaloes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950823">Hand</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1086604">Racing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:970716">Indos</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1025421">Mongols</term>
                    <term ref="fast:840320">Buddhists</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210322">Laos</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205406">Afghanistan</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n311/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LAOS, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Lawa</hi></label>, a large
                    Indo-Chinese nation, occupying the northern and eastern provinces of Siam known
                    as the Laos states, mainly between 15° and 24° N. lat., 98° and 106° E. long.
                    There are two main divisions—the Lau-pang-kah, or “White Paunch” Laos, and the
                    Lau-pang-dun, or “Black Paunch” Laos, the former between the Deng-Phya-Phai
                    range and the river Mekong, the latter about the middle and upper course of the
                    river Menam, and so called from the habit of tattooing a black pattern about the
                    navel. The Laos are closely related in physique and speech to the Siamese
                    proper, and are by some writers regarded as the primitive stock of that race.
                    They are an historical people who were formerly constituted in an ancient and
                    powerful kingdom, whose capital Vinh-khianh (Vien-shan) was taken and destroyed
                    by the Siamese about the year 1828. Since then they have been entirely subject
                    to Siam, and are governed partly by khiao, or native hereditary princes, partly
                    by mandarins or governors directly nominated by the Bangkok authorities. The
                    present khiao of the province of Bassak north of Camboja is the last surviving
                    descendant of the ancient Lao dynasty. The khiao are invested by means of the
                    gold dish, betel-box, spittoon, and teapot which are sent from Bangkok, and
                    returned at their death or deposition. Of all the khiao the most powerful is the
                    prince of Ubon (15° N., 105° E.), whose jurisdiction extends nearly from Bassak
                    on the Mekong northwards to the great southern bend of that river.</p>
                <p>The many contradictory accounts of the Laos that have been published by
                    travellers are due to the fact that quite three-fourths of the race have become
                    mixed with the surrounding Khas or aboriginal inhabitants of the peninsula. The
                    half-castes that have thus sprung from alliances with the Bolovens, Thêhs,
                    Redehs, Sui, and other wild tribes of Caucasie stock present every variety
                    between that type and the Mongolian. But those that have preserved the purity of
                    their blood are still distinguished by the high cheek bones, small flat nose,
                    oblique eyes, wide mouth, black lank hair, sparse beard, and yellow complexion
                    of the Tai and other branches of the Mongol family. These are also a
                    semi-civilized people with a knowledge of letters, followers of the Buddhist
                    teachings, settled in small towns and villages, and engaged chiefly in
                    agriculture. They have domesticated the elephant and buffalo, and are peaceful
                    and industrious, being skilled in the production of lacquered wares, and silk
                    and cotton fabrics for local use. Trading relations have also long been
                    established .with China, Siam, Burmah, and Camboja, with which countries their
                    ivory, gold dust, tin, gums, lac, benzoin, raw silk, skins, and sapanwood are
                    bartered for cotton cloth, chintzes, silks, opium, hardware, and porcelain. At
                    present a large portion of this trade is in the hands of itinerant Burmese
                    dealers and hawkers, who are met everywhere between the Irawadi and Mekong
                    valleys, organized in small caravans with a headman and porters all well armed,
                    like the Povindahs of Afghanistan.</p>
                <p>The civilized Laos have long been addicted to slave hunting, not only with the
                    sanction but even with the cooperation of the authorities. When times are hard
                    and tribute cannot otherwise be raised, “the Lao mandarins organize regular
                    expeditions against the wild tribes. On some slight pretext a favourable camping
                    ground is chosen, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n312/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0312-0295"/> whence attacks are made in all directions on
                    villages, which they hope to surround or surprise. The savages live only in
                    small hamlets consisting of a few huts, and they are powerless to resist the
                    attacks of men armed with guns. These razzias are usually made only against the
                    independent savages who reject the authority of the Lao princes and refuse to
                    pay tribute. But I have noticed that the compact by which the savages consent to
                    surrender a part of their independence, in order to preserve their wives,
                    children, and themselves, is far from being always respected; and the
                    unfortunate Gnia-heuns, for example, who dwell within a few leagues of Bassak,
                    are in the greatest terror of the prince, refusing on any consideration to leave
                    their forests or inaccessible villages.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Dr Harmaud, Τοur du Monde, July 5, 1879.</p></note> The
                    convoys of slaves, purchased chiefly by Chinese and Malay dealers from Camboja,
                    are forwarded mainly to Bangkok, Korat, and Phnom-penh, the present capital of
                    Camboja. This organized slave trade is the great curse of the nation, and tends
                    more than all other causes combined to retard the natural development of the Lao
                    country.</p>
                <p>The mixed Lao peoples are distinguished from the pure stock chiefly by their more
                    regular features, tall stature, lighter complexion, sub-dolichocephalic crania,
                    and generally lower social condition. Most of them, although nominal Buddhists,
                    are in reality still nature-worshippers, who make offerings of sticks and stones
                    to the local genii, and guard their homes against evil spirits by means of
                    brooms, cotton threads, bunches of herbage, and other curious devices. Some of
                    them are quite as savage as the wild tribes, and, although acquainted with the
                    use of firearms, still use the characteristic crossbow, a formidable weapon,
                    which in skilled hands will kill a buffalo with a simple bamboo arrow at
                    considerable distances. In some parts the confusion of types and usages is so
                    great that the true Khas can be distinguished from the Laos only by the lobe of
                    the ear, which is pierced for the insertion of large bone, ivory, or wooden
                    ornaments like those worn by many of the Oceanic races.</p>
                <p>Apart from the passions associated with the infamous slave trade, encouraged by
                    their rulers, the Laos are an inoffensive, unwarlike, and peace-loving race,
                    fond of music, and living chiefly on a diet of rice, vegetables, fruits, fish,
                    and poultry. Pure and mixed, they number altogether perhaps some 1,500,000.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
