<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0719-0696-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LITHGOW, William (9th edition, volume 14, page
                    696)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cv4br3k">Ambassadors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vp7r">Home</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40p0ww6s">Journeys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h708258">Surveying</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zd00">Surveys</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795379">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795510">Accounts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:806713">Ambassadors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150276">Thoughtfulness</term>
                    <term ref="fast:959074">Home</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239717">Alps</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1226682">Albania</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205592">Morocco</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206891">Poland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n719/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LITHGOW, <hi rend="smallcaps">William</hi></label> (c.
                    1583-c. 1660), a noted Scottish traveller, was born in Lanark, where his father
                    was a burgess, possessed of considerable heritable property. The date generally
                    assigned to his birth is 1583; and he was educated at the grammar school of his
                    native town, then celebrated as a seminary of learning. His natural disposition
                    was probably active and restless, as even in his boyhood he tells us that he
                    made voyages to both the Orkneys and the Shetlands, and somewhat later travelled
                    through the Low Countries, Germany, Bohemia, and Switzerland. The final
                    impelling cause of his leaving Scotland, however, appears to have been some
                    savage outrage committed either upon himself or on one nearly connected with
                    him, arising, it is thought, from some love affair, which gave him an
                    intolerable disgust to home. He left his native country about 1608 or 1609, and
                    proceeded to Paris, where he remained ten months, and then crossed the Alps to
                    Rome and Naples; after which he wandered through Istria, Dalmatia, Albania,
                    Greece, Asia Minor, Syria, Mesopotamia, Palestine, and Egypt, most of his
                    journey having been performed on foot. In the course of his travels he escaped
                    innumerable dangers from robbers, and hardships from exposure to inclement
                    weather. He returned to England by Sicily and Paris. Another tour which he made
                    lay through Morocco, Algiers, Tunis, Tripoli, Hungary, Germany, and Poland. On
                    his arrival in London he became an object of interest to King James, who, on the
                    spirit of travel again returning upon him, furnished him with commendatory
                    letters to all kings, princes, dukes, &lt;fcc., whose territories he might
                    desire to visit. In 1619, accordingly, he went over to France, and thence passed
                    through Portugal and Spain as far as Malaga. There he was apprehended as a spy,
                    and after suffering the most excruciating tortures, first in prison and
                    afterwards in the Inquisition, he was at length released on the interference of
                    the English consul, and allowed to return to England in 1621. The minute
                    description which he gives of the terrible torture to which he was subjected is
                    almost unequalled for horror, and, when he arrived in London, he had the
                    appearance of a man more dead than alive. He was carried on a feather bed to
                    Theobald’s in order that King James might be an eyewitness of what he called his
                    “martyred anatomy.” The whole court crowded to see him. The king commanded that
                    the greatest care should be taken of him, and he was twice sent to Bath at his
                    Majesty’s expense. On recovering his health, he was desired by James to apply to
                    Gondomar, the Spanish ambassador, for recovery of the money and other valuables
                    of which he had been plundered by the governor of Malaga, and for a thousand
                    pounds in reparation of his injuries. Gondomar gave fair promises that all his
                    demands should be granted, but nothing was done. Whereupon, having met the
                    ambassador at the royal levee, and reproached him with his perfidy, after high
                    words on both sides, Lithgow furiously assailed him with his fists, in the
                    presence of the king, the imperial ambassador, and the knights and gentlemen of
                    the court. This, of course, was an offence which could not be passed over, and,
                    though his boldness was generally commended, he had to suffer an imprisonment of
                    nine weeks in the Marshalsea. His latter years are understood to have been spent
                    in his native town, and he is said to have died somewhere about 1660.</p>
                <p>A portion of his travels appeared in a small volume in London in 1614, but the
                    complete work was not published till 1632. It has been repeatedly reprinted. It
                    was also translated into Dutch and published at Amsterdam in his lifetime. His
                    other works are <hi rend="italic">—An Account of the Siege of Breda</hi> (1637)
                    at which he had been <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n720/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0720-0697"/> present; <hi rend="italic">A Survey of London and
                    England’s State,</hi> 1643; <hi rend="italic">Relation of the Siege of
                    Newcastle,</hi> 1645. His poetical remains, collected, by James Maidment, were
                    published at Edinburgh in 1863.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
