<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0208-0197-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LADÁK and BALTÍ (9th edition, volume 14, page
                    197)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206102">Nepal</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205406">Afghanistan</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sf2mc0b">Aryans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4804xr51">Mohammedans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v698h77">Mohammedanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48s4jt2v">Heights</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20h7x">Valleys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1163841">Valleys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1938968">Aryans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:818281">Aryanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150682">Tibetans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n208/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LADÁK <hi rend="smallcaps">and</hi> BALTÍ</label>. The name
                    Ladâk (pronounced in Tibet in Lata) belongs primarily to the broad valley of the
                    upper Indus in West Tibet, but includes several surrounding districts in
                    political connexion with it; the present limits are between 75° 40' and 80° 30'
                    E. long., and between 32° 25' and 36° N. lat. It is bounded N. by the Kuenlun
                    range and the slopes of the Karakorum, N.W. and W. by the Mussulman, state of
                    Balti or Little Tibet, S.W. by Kashmir, S. by British Himalayan territory, and
                    E. by the Chinese Tibetan provinces of Ngari and Rudék. <hi rend="superscript">
                    1</hi> The whole region lies very high, the valleys of Rukshu in the south-east
                    being 15,000 feet, and the Indus near Lé 11,000 feet, while the average height
                    of the surrounding ranges is 19,000 feet. The proportion of arable and even
                    possible pasture land to barren rock and gravel is very small.</p>
                <p>The natural features of the country may be best explained by reference to two
                    native terms, under one or other of which every part is included, viz., <hi
                    rend="italic">changtang, i.e.,</hi> “northern, or high plain,” where the amount
                    of level ground is considerable, and the hills proportionally further apart; and
                    <hi rend="italic">rong, i.e.,</hi> “deep valley,” where the contrary condition
                    prevails. The former predominates in the east, diminishing gradually westwards.
                    There, although the vast alluvial deposits which once filled the valley to a
                    remarkably uniform height of about 15,000 feet have left their traces on the
                    mountain sides, they have undergone immense denudation, and their débris now
                    forms secondary deposits, flat bottoms, or shelving slopes, the only spots
                    available for cultivation or pasture. These masses of alluvium are often found
                    either metamorphosed to a subcrystalline rock still showing the composition of
                    the strata, or simply consolidated by lime.</p>
                <p>Grand scenery is exceptional, for the valleys are confined, and from the higher
                    points the view is generally of a confused mass of brown or yellow absolutely
                    barren hills, of no great apparent height. The parallelism characteristic of the
                    Himalayan ranges continues here, the direction being north-west and south-east.
                    A central range divides the Indus valley, here 4 to 8 miles wide, from that of
                    its north branch the Shayok, which with its fertile tributary valley of Nubra is
                    again bounded on the north by the Karakorum. This central ridge is mostly
                    syenitic gneiss, and north-east from it are found, successively, Silurian
                    slates, Carboniferous shales, and Triassic limestones, the gneiss recurring at
                    the Turkestan frontier. The Indus lies along the line which separates the
                    crystalline rocks from the Eocene sandstones and shales of the lower range of
                    hills on the left bank, the lofty mountains behind them consisting of parallel
                    bands of rocks from Silurian to Cretaceous. <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi></p>
                <p>There are several lakes in the east districts at about 14,000 feet. They have
                    evidently been of much greater extent, and connected with the river systems of
                    the country, but they are now mostly without outlet, saline, and in process of
                    desiccation.</p>
                <p>The climate is intensely dry, practically rainless, the little snow which falls
                    soon disappearing; <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> above a certain height no dew
                    is deposited. The alternations of temperature are great; the sun’s direct rays
                    are hotter than in the Indian plains, <hi rend="superscript"> 4</hi> while the
                    afternoon winds are piercingly cold; except in summer it freezes every night,
                    even in the lower districts, and nightly throughout the year at 15,000 feet.</p>
                <p>Vegetation therefore is confined to valleys and sheltered spots, where a stunted
                    growth of tamarisk and <hi rend="italic">Hyricαriα, Hippophae</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Plaeagnus,</hi> furze, and the roots of <hi rend="italic"
                    >burtsi,</hi> a salsolaceous plant, supply the traveller with much-needed
                    firewood. The trees are the pencil cedar <hi rend="italic">(Juniperus</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">ejccelsa),</hi> the poplar and willow (both extensively planted,
                    the latter sometimes wild), apple, mulberry, apricot, and walnut. Agriculture
                    depends on irrigation, which is skilfully managed, the principal products being
                    wheat, common and naked barley (from which the returns are usually small),
                    millet, buckwheat, pease, beans, and turnips. Lucerne and prangos (an
                    umbelliferous plant) are used as fodder.</p>
                <p>Among domestic animals are the famous shawl goat, two kinds of sheep, of which
                    the larger <hi rend="italic">(huniya)</hi> is used for carrying burthens, and is
                    a principal source of wealth, the yak, and the dso, a valuable hybrid between
                    the yak and common cow. Among wild animals are the kyang or wild ass, ibex,
                    markhor, antelope, <hi rend="italic">Ovis Poli,</hi> marmot, hare, and other
                    Tibetan fauna.</p>
                <p>The capital, Lé (population 4000), lies 4 miles from the river on the right bank,
                    11,540 feet above the sea, at the southern base of a spur from the central
                    range,— a terraced slope, with scattered hamlets, extending thence to the Indus.
                    It contains the palace of the old gyalpos, an imposing structure seven stories
                    high, and a wide bazaar where polo is played. It is surrounded by poplar
                    plantations, with manis <hi rend="superscript"> 5</hi> and ch <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi> hordtens <hi rend="superscript"> 6</hi> beyond. The
                    houses <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> Geographically the east boundary is a
                    mountain ridge some way within Chinese territory, which, running north, is the
                    watershed between East and West Tibet, and from the north part of which the
                    Indus, from the south the Sutlej, take their rise.</p>
                <p><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> Here, in the Zanskar, as the name implies, copper
                    is found.</p>
                <p><hi rend="superscript"> 8</hi> The average height of the snow-line is about
                    19,000 feet.</p>
                <p><hi rend="superscript"> 4</hi> Geranl records 158° in Ruρshu, i.e., only 27°
                    below boiling point at that altitude.</p>
                <p><hi rend="superscript"> s</hi> “Mani,” a long stone wall, several ftet wide,
                    running along tieroadside, covered with loose stones deposited by the
                    passers-by, inscribed with the prayer or ejaculation, “Om mani padme horn.”</p>
                <p><hi rend="superscript"> 6</hi> “Ch’hordten,” the monumental tomb of a lama.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n209/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0209-0198"/>
                <p>are usually two-storied, with flat roofs and balconies to the south or west, the
                    doors and shutters striped red and white.</p>
                <p>The numerous monasteries are built (as the houses used to be, for defence) in
                    lofty and picturesque situations, and would be strategically strong but for the
                    absence of water. They are supported partly by their own lands, but chiefly by
                    liberal gifts from the peasantry, with whose interests the lamas identify
                    themselves. The latter are hospitable, and their superiors often refined,
                    intelligent, and genial.</p>
                <p>The religion is Buddhist, chiefly of the Dukpa or Red sect, but traces of an
                    older faith linger, to which the masked dances of the monks may possibly be
                    referred. Mohammedanism, previously on the increase, is discouraged by the
                    Kashmir Government, its Hindu influence tending, as Hinduism has done in Nepal,
                    to introduce caste ideas.</p>
                <p>Polyandry is general, except among the rich.</p>
                <p>The home trade is worth little over £4000; the chief exports are wool, dried
                    fruits, salt, and small quantities of gold, borax, and sulphur; the chief
                    imports, provisions, hardware, and tea; but the transit trade is relatively very
                    important, the chief routes from the Punjab, Afghanistan, and Kashmir into
                    Eastern Turkestan and Chinese Tibet all passing through Lé.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The trade registered at Lé, chiefly between
                    India and Eastern Turkestan, averages £134,000, the principal exports from India
                    being cotton goods, value £29,200; silk ditto, £6000; skins, £3600; and tea,
                    £3500; and from Eastern Turkestan—raw silk, £14,100; silver, £29,700; gold,
                    £7000; charas, £6400; horses, £3200.</p></note> It is carried by coolies, or on
                    ponies, sheep, or yaks, over difficult passes often 18,000 feet high, and is
                    further hampered by the exclusive policy of China and Russia. The mechanical and
                    political obstacles have long engaged the attention of the Indian
                    Government.</p>
                <p>History. —The earliest notice of Ladâk is by the Chinese pilgrim Fa-hian, 400
                    A.n., who, travelling in search of a purer fftith, found Buddhism flourishing
                    there, the only novelty to him being the prayer-cylinder, the efficacy of which
                    he declares is incredible. Ladâk formed part of the Tibetan empire until its
                    disruption in the 10th century, and since then has continued ecclesiastically
                    subject, and sometimes tributary, to Lhasa. Its inaccessibility saved it from
                    any Mussulman invasion until 1531, when Sultan Said of Kashgar marched an army
                    across the Karakorum, one division fighting its way into Kashmir and wintering
                    there. Next year they invaded eastern Tibet, where nearly all perished from the
                    effects of the climate.</p>
                <p>Early in the 17th century Ladâk was invaded by its Mohammedan neighbours of
                    Balti, who plundered and destroyed the temples and monasteries; and again, in
                    1685-88, by the Sokpa or Calmucks, who were expelled only by the aid of the
                    lieutenant of Aurangzeb in Kashmir, Ladâk thereafter becoming tributary. The
                    gyalpo or king then made a nominal profession of Islam, and allowed a mosque to
                    be founded at Lé, and the Kashmiris have ever since addressed his successors by
                    a Mohammedan title. When the Sikhs took Kashmir, Ladâk, dreading their approach,
                    offered allegiance to Great Britain. It was, however, conquered and annexed in
                    1834-41 by Ghulab Singh of Jamu—the unwarlike Ladâkis, even with nature fighting
                    on their side, and against indifferent generalship, being no match for the Dogra
                    troops. These next turned their arms successfully against the Baltis (who in the
                    18th century were subject to the Mogul), and were then tempted to revive the
                    claims of Ladâk to the Chinese provinces of Rudok and Ngari. This, however,
                    brought dowp an army from Lhasa, and after a three days’ fight the Indian force
                    was almost annihilated—chiefly indeed by frostbite and other sufferings, for the
                    battle was fought in mid-winter, 15,000 feet above the sea. The Chinese then
                    marched on Lé, but were soon driven out again, and peace was finally made on the
                    basis of the old frontier. The widespread prestige of China is curiously
                    illustrated by the fact that tribute, though disguised as a present, is paid to
                    her, for Ladâk, by the maharaja of Kashmir.</p>
                <p>The adjoining territory of Balti—possibly the Byltae of Ptolemy—forms the west
                    extremity of the vast region known as Tibet, whose natural limits here are the
                    Indus from its abrupt southward bend in 74° 45' E. long., and the mountains to
                    the north and west, separating a comparatively peaceful Tibetan population from
                    the fiercer</p>
                <p>Aryan tribes beyond. Mohammedan writers about the 16th century speak of Balti as
                    “Little Tibet,” and of Ladâk as “Great Tibet,” thus ignoring the really Great
                    Tibet altogether. The Balti people call Gilghit “a Tibet,” and Dr Leitner says
                    that the Chilasi, a Dard people west of the Indus, call themselves Boté, or
                    Tibetans;<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>This, however,
                    it has been said, is only taken from the name of a former ruling
                    family.</p></note> but, although these districts may have been, like Kashmir,
                    overrun by the Tibetans, or have received rulers of that race, the ethnological
                    frontier coincides with the geographical one here given. Balti is a mass of
                    lofty mountains, the prevailing formation being gneiss. In the north is the
                    Baltoro glacier, the largest out of the arctic regions, 35 miles long, contained
                    between two ridges whose highest peaks to the south are 25,000 and to the north
                    28,265 feet. The Indus, as in Lower Ladâk, runs in a narrow gorge, widening for
                    nearly 20 miles after receiving the Shayok. The capital, Skardo, a scattered
                    collection of houses, stands here, perched on a rock 7740 feet above the sea.
                    The house roofs are flat, occupied only in part by a second story, the remaining
                    space being devoted to drying apricots, the chief staple of the main valley,
                    which supports little cultivation. But the rapid slope westwards is seen
                    generally in the vegetation. Birch, plane, spruce, and <hi rend="italic">Pinus
                    excelsa</hi> appear; the fruits are finer, including pomegranate, pear, peach,
                    vine, and melon, and where irrigation is available, as in the North Shigar, and
                    at the deltas of the tributary valleys, the crops are more luxuriant and
                    varied.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Population.—</hi> The Ladâkis, numbering about 21,000, are
                    Tibetan, with a slight Caucasian admixture, and there are numerous Baltis and
                    Dards (the latter superficially Buddhist) in the western districts. The Changpa,
                    <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> “mountaineers,” in the east are also Tibetan. They
                    are singularly hardy, good-humoured, not stupid though simple and clumsy, dirty
                    (washing, it is said, once a year, but not regularly), fond of social
                    gatherings. The national drink, chang, is a sort of beer made from barley. The
                    Balti type contains a much larger Aryan element, the isolated Dard (or Shin)
                    communities being probably relics of an early Aryan population, subsequently
                    overlaid by a Tibetan. The cross is a good one, the Baltis being more
                    intelligent, if less genial, than the Ladâkis, and equally industrious. They are
                    taller, less beardless, and their noses less flat. They eschew pigtails. Polo is
                    played more generally, and with more spirit, than in Ladâk. The two languages
                    are mutually intelligible. Like many Tajik and other mountain tribes westwards,
                    the Baltis are Shiah Mohammedans. The women are thus more secluded than in
                    Ladâk, where they are particularly independent. They have abandoned polyandry,
                    and (possibly in consequence) their numbers— some 58,000 in Baltl·and western
                    Ladâk—are larger than the country can support. Many emigrate to Kashmir and to
                    British territory, where they do well. In the west the Dards are numerous, and a
                    Dard element is especially observable in the families of the chiefs, some of
                    whom, as in Ladâk, were semi-independent before the annexation.</p>
                <p>The principal works consulted have been Mr F. Drew’s excellent book on The Jummoo
                    and Kashmir Territories·, a valuable paper by General H. Strachey “On the
                    Physical Geography of Western Tibet,” in the Roy. Geog. Soc. Journ., vol.
                    xxiii.; Cunningham’s Ladak∙, The Tribes of the Hindoo Koosh, by Major J.
                    Biddulph; the travels of Vigne, and of Moorcroft and Trebeck; papers by R.
                    Lydekker, in Records of the Geological Survey of India, vols, xiii. and xiv.,
                    and by Dr F. Stolicza, in Report of Sir T. D. Forsyth’s mission to Yarkand. (C.
                    T.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
