<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0487-0468-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LEPROSY (9th edition, volume 14, page 468)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cv3f">Skins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45d8nd6f">Skin</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pk07518">Face</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46q1sk44">Deltas</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40k26h3v">Lombards</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:848002">Carters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1120047">Skin</term>
                    <term ref="fast:919522">Face</term>
                    <term ref="fast:890004">Deltas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:961111">Hospitalers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204556">Norway</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204082">Japan</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n487/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LEPROSY</label><hi rend="italic">(Lepra</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Arabum,</hi><hi rend="italic">Elephantiasis</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Graecorum,</hi><hi rend="italic">Aussatz,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Spedalskhecι),</hi> the greatest disease of rnediaeval Christendom, is
                    identified, on the one hand, with a disease endemic from the earliest historical
                    times (1500 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.)</hi> in the delta and valley of the Nile,
                    and on the other hand with a disease now common in Asia, Africa, South America,
                    the West Indies, and certain isolated localities of Europe. An authentic
                    representation of the leprosy of the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n488/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0488-0469"/> Middle Ages exists iu a picture at Munich by
                    Holbein, painted at Augsburg in 1516; St Elizabeth gives bread and wine to a
                    prostrate group of lepers, including a bearded man whose face is covered with
                    large round reddish knobs, an old woman whose arm is covered with brown
                    blotches, the leg swathed in bandages through which matter oozes, the bare knee
                    also marked with discoloured spots, and on the head a white rag or plaster, and,
                    thirdly, a young man whose neck and face (especially round the somewhat hairless
                    eyebrows) are spotted with brown patches of various size. It is conjectured by
                    Virchow that the painter had made studies of lepers from the leper-houses then
                    existing at Augsburg. These external characters of mediaeval leprosy agree with
                    the descriptions of it by the ancients, and with the pictures of modern leprosy
                    given by Danielssen and Boeck for Norway, by various authors for sporadic
                    European cases, by Anderson for Malacca, by Carter for India, by Wolff for
                    Madeira, and by Hillis for British Guiana. There has been some confusion in the
                    technical naming of the disease; it is called <hi rend="italic">Elephantiasis
                    (Leontiasis, Satyriasis)</hi> by the Greek writers, and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Lepra</hi> by the Arabians. The latter term has been generally adopted in
                    modern books, but in England the name of <hi rend="italic">Lepra</hi> is applied
                    (after Willan) to an entirely different disease of the skin.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">History.—</hi> Egypt was regarded by the ancients (positively
                    by Lucretius) as the country whence leprosy came. It was probably endemic among
                    the Hebrews when they migrated from Egypt. The minute diagnostic indications
                    given in Lev. xiii. appear to relate to true leprosy and to other diseases that
                    might be mistaken for it, and the frequently recurring word Sara*ath (translated
                    “leprosy”) is best taken in a generic sense; those cases in which progress would
                    show itself at so short intervals as seven days, and those cases for which the
                    ceremonial of cleansing was provided, could hardly have been cases of leprosy, a
                    disease always incurable, and with stages reckoned rather by months or years
                    than by weeks. Herodotus knew of leprosy as existing in Persia. The earlier
                    Greek and Latin writers speak of it as a foreign disease, but it became
                    established in Greece and Italy in the 1st century n.c.; Pliny implies that it
                    was introduced by the army of Pompey returning from Syria. The disease soon
                    appeared in the Roman colonies of Spain, Gaul, and Britain. The Lombard king
                    Rothar (7th century) made laws regulating the marriage of lepers, and similar
                    laws were made by Pippin and Charlemagne. Leper-houses existed at Verdun, Metz,
                    and Maestricht in the 7th century, at St Gall in the 8th, and at Canterbury in
                    the 11 th. It was amidst the stir and movement of the crusades that leprosy grew
                    to be epidemic in western Europe; it attacked the people in great numbers and in
                    all ranks (including members of royal families). Leper-houses (mostly religious
                    and dedicated to St Lazarus, but in northern Europe more secular and dedicated
                    to St George) were founded in every considerable town; the total number of these
                    in Europe was loosely estimated by Matthew Paris at 19,000, the number in France
                    is independently estimated at 2000, and (according to Sir J. Y. Simpson) there
                    were 95 houses of the first class in England (of these 7 at Norwich and 5 at
                    Lynn), and several in Ireland and Scotland. The isolation of lepers was strictly
                    enforced by law and popular sentiment. They wore a special costume, usually a
                    long grey gown with hood drawn over the face, and carried a wooden clapper to
                    give warning of their approach. They were forbidden to enter inns, churches,
                    mills, or bakehouses, to touch healthy persons or eat with them, to wash in the
                    streams, or to walk in narrow footpaths. Their outcast state was signified by
                    the German name <hi rend="italic">(Aussatz)</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> the
                    Chronicle of Limburg (under the year 1374) speaksofa famous monkish poet, whose
                    songs all Germany was singing, as one “<hi rend="italic">der</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">ward</hi><hi rend="italic">von den Leuten aussätzig, und</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">war</hi><hi rend="italic">nicht</hi><hi rend="italic">reiny</hi>
                    The disease began to decline (first in Italy) in the 15th century, and had
                    mostly disappeared in the 17th. A leper-house was founded in Edinburgh (at
                    Greenside) as late as 1591, and it was not till 1741 (others give 1798) that the
                    last known leper died in Shetland.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Present Geographical Distribution.—</hi> Survivals of the great
                    mediaeval outbreak are found on the west coast of Norway (about two thousand
                    lepers; leper hospital at Bergen founded 1277, now added to), in the Baltic
                    provinces of Russia (leper hospitals founded at Riga in 1220 and Revel 1237, not
                    now in use), on the Riviera (a small and diminishing number), on the Sicilian
                    coasts, and in certain coast provinces of Spain and Portugal (leper hospital at
                    Lisbon since the 13th century). Sporadic cases of home origin have also been
                    described for Hungary and Rouιnania; the cases occurring in England and France
                    are in persons who have been born or have lived in the East or West Indies. The
                    disease is met with also in Iceland, along the Caspian and delta of the Volga,
                    along the Black Sea, and in islands of the Levant (especially Scio and Crete).
                    It is common all over the East from Syria to Japan and Kamchatka, in Egypt and
                    North African states, in "West Africa from the Senegal to the Congo, in Cape
                    Colony, Madagascar, Mauritius, Isle de Bourbon, St Helena, Madeira, Canaries and
                    Azores, Brazil, Central America, the West Indies, Mexico, New Brunswick (small
                    isolated French colony), and especially in the Hawaiian Islands. Leprosy has
                    been found among Chinese immigrants in the United States as far east as Chicago,
                    and in Queensland. Leper hospitals (with inmates numbering from two hundred
                    downwards) are kept up in several of the West Indian colonies, at Tracadie (New
                    Brunswick), at Cape Town, in Mauritius, at Malacca and Singapore, at Colombo, at
                    Madras, Cochin, and Bangalore, at Bombay and Rajkot, and at Calcutta, Benares,
                    and Agra. There are also leper hospitals at Bergen (3), Molde, and Trondlιjem,
                    at San Remo, at Oporto, Coimbra, and Lisbon, at Terceira (Azores), Las Palmas
                    (Grand Canary) since 15th century, and Funchal (Madeira) since about 1500, at
                    Pernambuco, Bahia, and Rio, at Honolulu, at Macao (for two hundred years) and
                    Canton, in Java (several) and in Amboyna, at Scio (since 1445), Scutari,
                    Damascus, and Jerusalem. A ruined convent at Ramleh accommodates thirty lepers
                    or more, and a mosque at Nablus is occupied by about seventy. In several of the
                    above instances the leper hospital is built upon an outlying island. Leper
                    villages occur in China and Japan, and in Persia. Leper communities exist in
                    Crete, but the largest of them is now mostly occupied by a non-leprous
                    population. Throughout the East, including British India, the hospital
                    accommodation for lepers is only casual, and isolation is not carried out to the
                    same extent as during the prevalence of the disease in Europe.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Definition, Characters, Pathology, and Causation —</hi> Leprosy
                    is an incurable constitutional disease, marked externally by discoloured patches
                    and nodules on the skin, and deeply implicating the structure and function of
                    the peripheral nervous system. Like the infections, it has a prodromal stage,
                    which is uncertain in its character, and is measured rather by months or years
                    than by days or weeks; the chief premonitory symptoms are unaccountable
                    lassitude and mental depression, pains in the limbs and joints, febrile periods
                    (cold and hot fits), loss of appetite, and nausea. That stage is followed by the
                    “periodically eruptive stage,” during which blotches on the skin come and go;
                    sooner or later these erythematous congestions and exudations leave either
                    permanent spots, brown or blanched, which are often without feeling, or they
                    leave nodules. The disease diverges into two main <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n489/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0489-0470"/> varieties, the spotted <hi rend="italic">(Lepra
                    maculosa')</hi> and the nodular <hi rend="italic">(Lepra tuberculosa).</hi> The
                    two kinds are found side by side in the same population, and sometimes in the
                    same person. The maculae arise in the place of former recurrent spots, and are
                    often raised indurations; when the pigmentation deepens, the disease is <hi
                    rend="italic">L. maculosa nigra</hi>; when the spots become blanched, it is <hi
                    rend="italic">L. maculosa alba</hi> or white leprosy. Anaesthesia, which very
                    generally goes with the leprous process, is especially marked in the blanched
                    spots, hence the name <hi rend="italic">L. anaesthetica.</hi> Anaesthetic spots
                    are apt to have bullae forming on them <hi rend="italic">(pemphigus</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">leprosus),</hi> their periodical eruption being attended with
                    fever. The nodules (characteristic of the other form) generally arise also in
                    the situation of old blotches; they are at first small scattered points, but
                    they grow and coalesce to the size of lentils, hazel nuts, or walnuts. While the
                    maculae of leprosy may occur in any part, the nodules are most apt to form on
                    the face (brows, eyelids, ears, wings of the nose, lips, cheeks), causing
                    thickening of all the features <hi rend="italic">(Leontiasis, Satyriasis)',</hi>
                    but they often occur on the hands and feet, and sometimes over the whole body.
                    The nodules, from being exposed to the weather and to injuries, often ulcerate,
                    and the ulcers, like those of syphilis and lupus, tend to spread. Maculae,
                    especially on the limbs, are liable to slighter ulcerations followed by
                    incrustation. Deep ulceration and necrosis occur at the joints of the fingers
                    and toes, which may drop off joint by joint, leaving a well-healed stump <hi
                    rend="italic">(L. mutilans).</hi> Certain mucous membranes thicken, become
                    nodulated, and ulcerate, viz., the conjunctiva corneae (causing <hi
                    rend="italic">pannus</hi><hi rend="italic">leprosus),</hi> and the lining of the
                    mouth, nose, throat, and larynx (causing hoarseness). The external groups of
                    lymphatic glands enlarge; leprous affections of the viscera also are described.
                    The peripheral nerves are the subject of thickenings and degenerations like
                    those in the skin. The new-formed tissue in all situations is granulation-like,
                    as in syphilis and lupus; and leprosy, with those two diseases, is treated of by
                    Virchow under the head of granuloma. By some the nervous lesions (including an
                    alleged affection of the spinal cord) are taken to be primary, while the changes
                    in the skin and other parts (with anaesthesia) are held to be secondary and due
                    to disordered innervation. Leprosy has been claimed as one of the diseases
                    caused by parasites, on several occasions by old writers in the gross sense, and
                    recently by observers who have found innumerable minute bacillus-rods within the
                    cells of the leprous new growth. The essential cause of leprosy is unknown. It
                    probably arose in the Delta and valley of the Nile in prehistoric times, and
                    under similar climatic and telluric conditions in other (chiefly intertropical)
                    countries; and the most memorable fact in its history is its rise and subsidence
                    as an epidemic disease in Europe. It is now endemic (chiefly but not
                    exclusively) among peoples who inhabit the sea-coast or the estuaries of rivers,
                    who live much on fish (often putrid), and who intermarry closely. The old
                    opinion that leprosy is contagious is now generally discredited.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Lilcrαture.</hi> —-For history and geographical distribution,
                    see Hirsch, <hi rend="italic">Handbuch der historisch-geographischen</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Pathologic,</hi> 1st ed., Erlangen, 1860 (with exhaustive
                    literature). For pathology, Virchow, <hi rend="italic">Die</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >krankhaften Geschwülste,</hi> Berlin, 1863-67, vol. ii. For clinical histories,
                    R. Liveing, <hi rend="italic">Elephantiasis</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Graecorurn</hi><hi rend="italic">or True Leprosy,</hi> London, 1873, chap. iv.
                    For mediaeval leprosy—in Germany, Virchow, in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Virchow’s</hi><hi rend="italic">Archiv,</hi> five articles, vols, xviii.-xx.,
                    1860-61; in the Netherlands, Israels, in <hi rend="italic">Ncderl. Tijdschr.
                    νoor Genccskunde,</hi> vol. i., 1857; in Britain, J. Y. Simpson, <hi
                    rend="italic">Edin. Med. and Surg. Journ.,</hi> three articles, vols, lxvi. and
                    lxvii., 1846-47. Treatises on modern leprosy in particular localities:
                    Danielssen and Boeck (Norway), <hi rend="italic">Traité delà Spédalskhed,</hi>
                    with atlas of twenty-four coloured plates, Paris, 1848; A. F. Anderson, <hi
                    rend="italic">Leprosy as met with in the Straits Settlements,</hi> coloured
                    photographs with explanatory notes, London, 1872; H. Vandyke Carter (Bombay),
                    <hi rend="italic">On Leprosy and Elephantiasis,</hi> with coloured plates,
                    London, 1874; Hillis, <hi rend="italic">Leprosy in British Guiana,</hi> an
                    account of West Indian leprosy, with twenty-</p>
                <p>two coloured plates, London, 1882. See also the dermatological works of Hebra,
                    Erasmus Wilson, Bazin, and Hutchinson. An important early work is that of P. G.
                    Hensler, <hi rend="italic">Vom abendländischen Aussatze im Mittelalter,</hi>
                    Hamburg, 1790. (G. C.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
