<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0527-0508-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LIBERIA (9th edition, volume 14, page 508)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:997231">Liberians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1744651">Dollarization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:896433">Dollar</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1137272">Sugar</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vp1v">Dollar</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zn7v">Sugar</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94f0m">Negroes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48911q68">Baptists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205331">Liberia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204739">Maryland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210278">Belgium</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206005">Guinea</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206830">Brazil</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n527/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LIBERIA</label>, a Negro republic on the Grain Coast of West
                    Africa. Founded in 1822 by American philanthropists for the settlement of
                    freedmen who wished to return to their native land, or to enjoy political and
                    social privileges then denied them in the United States, it remained for
                    twenty-five years under the tutelage of the mother country, but on the 26th July
                    1847 it was declared independent. In 1848 it was recognized as a sovereign state
                    by Great Britain, which aided it in various ways, and by other Continental
                    powers, and finally in 1861 by the United States. Its nominal boundaries are
                    from the river Jong, a tributary of the Sherbar, in 7° 35' N. lat., 12° 20' W.
                    long., and the river San Pedro, in 4° 45' N. lat., 6 <hi rend="superscript">
                    3</hi> 40' W. long., a distance of 380 miles, the limits of the state in the
                    interior being usually stated at from 80 to 100 miles eastward, though this is
                    unsettled, and the entire area of the country at 24,000 square miles, or 1000
                    miles less than Holland and Belgium combined. Like that of northern Guinea
                    generally, the Liberian shore is low, but the country rises towards the
                    interior, and is well-wooded and watered by numerous streams. The climate is,
                    however, hot and unhealthy for Europeans, though of late years it has been
                    improved by drainage, and is considered superior to that of any part of the
                    neighbouring coast. The soil is fertile and well suited for the growth of
                    tropical crops, such as cotton, rice, sugar, indigo, yams, groundnuts, bananas,
                    ginger, cassava,pine-apples, cocoa-nuts, limes, oranges, tamarinds, and the
                    Liberian variety of coffee<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Liberian coffee (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Coffee,</hi> vol. vi. p. 110) has
                    been introduced into Brazil, Ceylon, the Dutch Indies, &amp;c. The quantity
                    actually exported from Liberia is comparatively small.</p></note> held in such
                    high esteem. These products, in addition to palm oil, form the main support of
                    the inhabitants, who in return import arms, ammunition, tobacco, salt
                    provisions, implements of husbandry, cutlery, British cottons, and other
                    manufactured goods. Coffee, palm oil, palm-kernels, rubber, ivory, dye woods,
                    hides, ivory, arrowroot, sugar, cocoa, ginger, and rice form the principal
                    articles of its commerce, which is carried on chiefly with Great Britain,
                    Holland, Hamburg, and America. Copper, gold, iron, and deposits of gum-copal
                    exist, but they are not worked; and all the large wild animals have long since
                    been killed or driven out of the woods. Stock can be kept in the higher lands.
                    The government is modelled on that of the United States, and consists of a
                    president, and a congress composed of a senate of eight members elected for four
                    years, and of a house of representatives of thirteen members elected for three
                    years, in addition to a supreme court, and a cabinet of the American type. One
                    additional representative is given for each additional 10,000 inhabitants by
                    which the population may increase. Military service in the militia is obligatory
                    on every male citizen between the ages of sixteen and fifty, but there is no
                    standing army. There is no established church, and all faiths are equally
                    tolerated. The state is divided into four counties (Mezurada, Grand Bassa,
                    Sinoe, and Maryland<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Maryland was originally a separate colony, founded in 1831; it became an
                    independent republic in 1854, and about 1860 was incorporated with its older
                    neighbour.</p></note>), and these again into townships, each 64 square miles in
                    area. There are a number of little villages, but the only place of any
                    consequence is Monrovia, the capital, containing 13,000 inhabitants, and in
                    appearance very like a town in the southern United States, but in no way
                    remarkable except for the large number of churches within its bounds. Besides
                    Monrovia the chief ports are Robertsport, Marshall, Edina or Buchanan,
                    Greenville, Sesters River, Sasstown, and Harper, and in 1881 foreigners were
                    further permitted to trade at any point to the north of Robertsport. The present
                    population of the republic (1882) comprises 18,000 civilized negroes, chiefly of
                    American origin, and 1,050,000 half-wild natives, some of whom are adopting a
                    settled life, and conforming to the habits of their tamed countrymen. Among the
                    more interesting tribes are the Veis, the Bassas, the Krus, and the Mandingoes.
                    The American Methodist Episcopal mission dates from 1833, the American Episcopal
                    from 1834, and that of the American Baptists from 1835. The revenue of the state
                    was returned at September 30, 1875, as 111,457 dollars, chiefly derived from
                    customs, the national debt being 500,000 dollars, contracted in England in 1871.
                    Of this neither principal nor interest has been paid. Socially and politically
                    the state cannot be pronounced a marked success. The negroes in America display
                    little desire to throw in their fortunes with it, now that they are free to go
                    whither they list, nor do the barbarous tribes on the border of the republic
                    seem to admire the black parody on a white man’s government, which for sixty
                    years has been presented to them. There is now and again a small immigration
                    from the United States, but the Liberian civilization, cut off from the benefit
                    of intercourse with a higher and broader culture, is apt to deteriorate, while
                    neither the climate nor the laws and social surroundings are ever likely to
                    attract many white men to its shores. It is, however, only fair to add that,
                    though internal disorder is too often the rule, the state shows an appreciation
                    of education and religion, and a keen desire to stand well in the good opinion
                    of the powers with which it has relations by accredited representatives. It has
                    formed treaties with most of the European countries, and with Hayti and the
                    United States; and, though it has not paid its debts, successive Governments are
                    in the habit of registering vows to meet this first obligation of a nation
                    towards its neighbours. British coin and an irredeemable <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n528/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0528-0509"/> paper currency are the money chiefly in
                    circulation, but all accounts are kept in United States dollars and cents. The
                    weights employed are also British, except that gold from the interior is bought
                    and sold by the usano = 16 akis = 16,000 cowries = 314 ’ 76 grains troy. The
                    gondar-ardeb (7 ’ 74 imperial pints), the massuah-ardeb (2 ’ 32 imp. gals.), and
                    the kuba (1 ’ 788 imp. pints) are also in common use.</p>
                <p>See Gurley’s <hi rend="italic">Life of Jehudi Ashman,</hi> 1835; Stockwell, <hi
                    rend="italic">The Republic of Liberia,</hi> 1868; Wilson, <hi rend="italic"
                    >JVcst Africa,</hi> 1856; Hutchinson, <hi rend="italic">Impressions of JVcst
                    Africa,</hi> 1858; Bitter, in <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">far</hi><hi rend="italic">allgemeine Erdkunde,</hi> vol. i., 1853;
                    Brown, <hi rend="italic">Countries of the JVorld,</hi> vol. vi. pp. 123-127,
                    1881; Bowen, <hi rend="italic">Central Africa,</hi> 1857; Themas, <hi
                    rend="italic">JVcst Coast of Africa,</hi> 1860; “Die Negerrepublik Liberia,” in
                    <hi rend="italic">Unsere Zeit,</hi> vol. iii., 1858; U.S. Consular Reports,
                    1881.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
