<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0706-8758-0135-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CARD (7th edition, volume 6, page 135)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r47q">Cuttings</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mg7fz12">Cutting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j09wd22">Teething</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hh6c56c">Teeth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vb0p">Caesars</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:885683">Cutting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1145710">Teeth</term>
                    <term ref="fast:995089">Leather</term>
                    <term ref="fast:864940">Clubs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193348758?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CARD</label>, among artificers, an instrument consisting of a
                    block of wood set with sharp teeth, serving to arrange the hairs of wool, flax,
                    hemp, and the like. There are different kinds of them, as hand-cards,
                    stock-eards, &amp;e. They are made as follows:</p>
                <p>A pieee of thiek leather, of the size intended for the card, is strained in a
                    frame for that purpose, and then pricked full of holes, into which the teeth or
                    pieces of iron wire are inserted; after whieh the leather is nailed by the edges
                    to a flat piece of wood, in the form of an oblong square, about a foot in length
                    and half a foot in breadth, with a handle plaeed in the middle of one of the
                    longer sides.</p>
                <p>The teeth are made in the following manner. The wire being drawn of the size
                    intended, a skain or number of wires are eut into proper lengths by means of a
                    gauge, and then doubled in a tool contrived for the purpose; after which they
                    are bent into the proper direction by means of another tool, and then plaeed in
                    the leather, as above mentioned. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Woollen
                    Manufacture.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Cards,</hi> in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Gaming,</hi> little pieees of fine thin pasteboard, of an oblong figure, of
                    several sizes, but most eommonly, in Britain, three inches and a half long and
                    two and a half broad, on whieh are painted several points and figures.</p>
                <p>The moulds and bloeks for making cards are exactly like those that were used for
                    the first printed books. , A sheet of wet or moist paper is laid on the block,
                    whieh is very slightly done over with a sort of ink made of lampblack diluted in
                    water, and mixed with some stareh to give it a body. This is afterwards rubbed
                    off with a round list. The eourt-eards are coloured by means of several
                    patterns, styled <hi rend="italic">stane-files.</hi> These consist of papers eut
                    through with a penknife; řìnd in the apertures the various colours, as red,
                    black, &amp;e. are severally applied. These patterns are painted with
                    oil-colours, that the brushes may not wear them out; and when the pattern is
                    laid on the pasteboard, a brush full of colour is slightly passed over it, and,
                    leaving the eolour within the openings, forms the faee or figure of the
                    eard.</p>
                <p>Among sharpers, divers sorts of false and fraudulent earđs have been eontrived;
                    as, 1. <hi rend="italic">Marked</hi> eards, where the aces, kings, queens,
                    knaves, are marked on the eorners of the backs with spots of different number
                    and order, either with clear water or water tinged with pale Indian ink, that
                    those in the seeret may distinguish them. AEes are marked with single spots on
                    two eorners opposite diagonally; kings with two spots at the same eorners;
                    knaves with the same number transversed. 2. <hi rend="italic">Breef</hi> eards,
                    those which are longer or broader than the rest, ehiefly used at whist and
                    piquet. The broad eards are usually for kings, queens, knaves, and aces; the
                    long for .the rest. Their design is to direct the cuttings, to enable him in the
                    secret to cut the cards disadvantageously to his adversary, and draw the person
                    unacquainted with the fraud to eut them favourably for the sharper. As the pack
                    is placed either endwise or sidewise to him that is to cut, the long or broad
                    cards naturally lead him to cut them. Breef eards are sometimes made thus by the
                    manufacturer; but, in defeet of these, sharpers pare all but the breefs with a
                    penknife or razor. 3. <hi rend="italic">Corner bend</hi> denotes four eards
                    turned down finely at one corner, to serve as a signal to cut by. 4. <hi
                    rend="italic">Middle bend,</hi> or Kingston-bridge, is where the trieks are bent
                    two different ways, which eauses an opening or arch in the middle, to direet
                    likewise the cutting.</p>
                <p>Cards were invented about the year 1390, to divert Charles VI. of France, who had
                    fallen into a melancholy disposition. The inventor proposed, by the figures of
                    the four suits or eolours, as the French call them, to represent the four
                    elasses of men in the kingdom. By the <hi rend="italic">coeurs</hi> (hearts) are
                    meant the <hi rend="italic">gens de choeur,</hi> choir-men, or eeelesiastics;
                    and therefore the Spaniards, who eertainly received the use of cards from the
                    French, have <hi rend="italic">copas,</hi> or chalices, instead of hearts. The
                    nobility, or prime mili.- tary part of the kingdom, are represented by the ends
                    or points of lanees or pikes; and our ignorance of the meaning or the
                    resemblanee of the figure induced us to call them <hi rend="italic">spades.</hi>
                    The Spaniards have <hi rend="italic">espadαs,</hi> swords, in lieu of pikes,
                    whieh are of similar import. By diamonds are designed the order of eitizens,
                    merchants, or tradesmen, <hi rend="italic">carreaux,</hi> square stones, tiles,
                    or the like. The Spaniards have a eoin, <hi rend="italic">dincros,</hi> which
                    answers to it; and the Dutch eall the Freneh word <hi rend="italic"
                    >carreaux,</hi><hi rend="italic">streηeeη,</hi> stones and diamonds, from the
                    form. <hi rend="italic">Trefle,</hi> the trefoil-leaf, or elovergrass, eorrnptly
                    called <hi rend="italic">clubs,</hi> alludes to the husbandmen and peasants. But
                    how this suit came to be called <hi rend="italic">clubs</hi> is not easily
                    explained; unless, borrowing the game from the Spaniards, who have <hi
                    rend="italic">bastos</hi> (staves or clubs) instead of the trefoil, we gave the
                    Spanish signification to the French figure.</p>
                <p>The history of the four kings, whieh the Freneh, in drollery, sometimes call the
                    cards, are David, Alexander, Caesar, and Charles; which names were then, and
                    still are, on the Freneh eards. Those respeetable names represent the four
                    celebrated monarchies of the Jews, Greeks, Romans, and Franks under Charlemagne.
                    By the queens are intended Argine, Esther, Judith, and Pallas (names retained in
                    the French cards), typical of birth, piety, fortitude, and wisdom, the
                    qualifications residing in each person. <hi rend="italic">Argine</hi> is an
                    anagram for <hi rend="italic">regina,</hi> queen by descent. By the knaves were
                    designed the servants to knights, for <hi rend="italic">knave</hi> originally
                    meant only <hi rend="italic">servant</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> but Freneh
                    pages and valets, now indiscriminately used by various orders of persons, were
                    formerly only allowed to persons of quality, esquires <hi rend="italic"
                    >(pscmres),</hi> shield or armour-bearers. Others faney that the knights
                    themselves were designed by those eards, because Hogier and Labire, two names on
                    the Freneh eards, were famous knights at the time when eards were supposed to
                    have been invented.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
