<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0706-8095-0084-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CANNON (7th edition, volume 6, page 84)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pg1hs5x">Gun</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ng4gw65">Gunning</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z02z952">Cannon</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4125q963">Dominicans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tm72270">Metals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zz70">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ft8dp2t">Sand</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1017914">Metallizing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1018047">Metals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:979089">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1104803">Sand</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1024369">Modeling</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193348095?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CANNON</label>, a military engine for throwing balls, &amp;c.
                    by the help of <hi rend="smallcaps">Gunpowder.</hi></p>
                <p>The invention of brass cannon is by Laney ascribed to J. Owen. He says that they
                    were first known in England in the year 1535; but he yet acknowledges that, in
                    1346, there were four pieces of cannon in the English army at the battle of
                    Cressy, and that these were the first that were known in France. And Mezeray
                    relates, that by means of five or six pieces of cannon, King Edward struck
                    terror into the French army, it being the first time they had seen any of these
                    thundering machines; though others affirm that cannon were known also in France
                    at the same time, but that the French king, in his hurry to attack, the English,
                    and in confidence of victory, left all his cannon behind him as useless
                    encumbrances. The Germans carry the invention farther back, and attribute it to
                    Albertus Magnus, a Dominican monk, about the year 1250. Vossius rejects all
                    these opinions, and finds cannon in China almost 1700 years ago. According to
                    him, they were invented by the Emperor Kitey in the year of Christ 85. See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Artillery</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Gunnery.</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Cannon,</hi><hi rend="italic">the Art of Casting.</hi> Formerly
                    the mould for casting cannon was of loam, but now it is usually made of dry
                    sand. Loam for making moulds is a composition consisting principally of an earth
                    that contains a good deal of clay. This earth is passed through sieves, and then
                    mixed, whilst wet, with horse dung, cow’s hair, chopped straw, or tow cut short;
                    the loam being mixed up with one of these substances, they are well beaten up
                    together on a wooden board with an iron bar. By this addition the loam becomes
                    susceptible of being dried rapidly without cracking. The most attenuated loam is
                    used for the surface of the mould that is to come in contact with the metal, to
                    the end that the surface may come oft' smooth. The loam moulders are a
                    particular class of workmen, different from the common sand moulders. The
                    business to which they are bred consists in making, of loam and of dry sand, the
                    moulds for steam-engine cylinders, pipes for conveying water, boilers, guns, and
                    other large articles.</p>
                <p>Formerly on a tapering wooden spindle, entwined with straw ropes, a model was
                    made of loam, copied exactly from the pattern gun. This model was painted over
                    with a coat of wood ashes mixed with water. By means of this coat no adhesion
                    took place between the convex model and the loam which was afterwards applied.
                    Over this coat of ashes successive coats of loam were applied, each being dried
                    by fire before the next was laid on; and the whole was bound externally with
                    longitudinal iron bars, and with hoops transversely. Over this carcass of iron a
                    coat of plaster of Paris was applied. This was dried, and then the spindle and
                    its envelope of straw was taken out. The interior convex model being thus
                    deprived of its core and support, fell to pieces and was picked out; and then a
                    hollow mould of the gun remained. In this way the mould for the body of the
                    piece was formed; the moulds for the breech and head were made separately; and
                    these three parts were joined together so as to form a complete mould. This
                    method of moulding guns required the construction of a new convex model for
                    every gun that was moulded; and it was used in the French government founderies
                    of Douai, Ruelle near Paris, and Strasburg, in 1794.</p>
                <p>The following method of constructing the loam-mould is an improvement on that
                    just mentioned. A model of wood, or, to prevent change of form by moisture, a
                    model of brass or pewter, is made and formed on the turning lathe, with its
                    exterior surface exactly resembling that of the gun, with its head and the
                    square piece at the cascabel; if the model is of metal, it is made hollow for
                    the sake of lightness. This model is laid with its longitudinal axis horizonal,
                    and one half immersed in a bed of sand. Upon that part of the model which
                    projects above the sand successive coats of loam are applied and pressed on the
                    model. When the first layer is dried by fire, a second layer is applied and
                    dried, and so on till the model is covered with a coat of loam four or five
                    inches thick. Over this an iron carcass is applied, and over the carcass another
                    coat of loam. The mould with the model in it is now turned, so that the half
                    already covered with loam shall be lowermost. The plain surface of the loam
                    which had been in contact with the sand is painted over with a coat of blacking,
                    composed of finely powdered charcoal mixed with clayed water; this prevents the
                    adhesion of the flat surface with the loam that is to be laid on it. A layer of
                    <pb break="no" facs="nls:193348108?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0706-8108-0085"/>
                    loam is applied upon the naked half of the model. - This is dried, and several
                    more layers are applied successively. A carcass is put over the loam
                    corresponding to the carcass of the first half, so that these two carcasses can
                    be bound together with bolts and wedge-formed keys, with screw-bolts and nuts,
                    or tied with iron-wire.’ When the loam is dry, the upper half of the mould is
                    lifted off, the model is taken out, and the interior surfaces of both parts of
                    the mould are painted over with blacking; this prevents the loam from being
                    melted, and from adhering to the hot metal. The two halves of the mould are then
                    put together, and the carcasses are firmly connected by their bolts; the whole
                    is thoroughly dried by fire. When dried, the mould is placed vertically in the
                    pit of the casting house, with the breech lowermost; sand is beat round it for
                    support, and the metal is poured in at the top of the head. This method was
                    practised in the Arsenal of Paris in 1794.</p>
                <p>The most approved method of constructing the mould of a gun is in dry sand, and
                    this is the method now practised in Britain. Guns cast in loam do not come from
                    the mould with a surface so correctly resembling that of the model as those cast
                    in dry sand; and in order to render the surface correct, and to remedy defects,
                    it was always necessary to subject them to the process of turning. In guns
                    carefully cast in dry sand, the process of turning might be dispensed with; the
                    gun would then be strengthened by the outer skin of metal, which, having cooled
                    more rapidly than the other parts, is the hardest. This outer skin is also less
                    liable to rust than the surface laid bare by turning. The mould of a gun in dry
                    sand, at the same time that it is more accurate, is also sooner made and dried,
                    than a loam-mould. Dry sand moulding is a part of the business of the
                    loam-moulder.</p>
                <p>The sand for dry sand mouldings is made by mixing a quantity of sharp refractory
                    sand with water in which clay has been diluted. After the mixture is thoroughly
                    made, if a handful is grasped, and on opening the hand the sand retains the form
                    given it, then the consistence of the mixture is good. The sand should have the
                    following qualities :— <hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">st,</hi> It
                    should not be fusible by the heat of melted cast-iron; if it were, it would
                    adhere to the metal, and make the surface of the gun rough. <hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic">2,dly,</hi> It must be sharp, and composed
                    of angular particles; if the particles of the sand were round, it would not hold
                    together on taking out the model. 3&lt;√7τ∕, It must not contain too much clay,
                    for in that case it would crack in drying, <hi rend="italic">⅛thly,</hi> It must
                    contain a certain proportion of clay, to retain the form that the model
                    impresses on it.</p>
                <p>I. For dry sand moulding, a pattern of wood may be used, turned exactly to the
                    form of the gun; or, to avoid expansion from humidity, the model, or pattern as
                    it is termed in the founderies, may be of metal. Brass or pewter arc preferable
                    to iron for making patterns, as a smooth surface may be more easily given them,
                    so that they may leave a correct impression, and may come out well from the
                    sand. The metallic pattern is hollow, that it may be lighter and more easily
                    handled: it is also in different pieces; and each piece fits into the adjacent
                    piece by a rabbet.</p>
                <p>The length of each piece of the model should be a very little greater than the
                    given length of the corresponding part of the gun, because the length of the
                    mould is the length of the gun whilst hot, and this is longer than the length of
                    the gun when it comes to the temperature of the atmosphere, at which temperature
                    the dimensions of the guns are given. It has been estimated that some kinds of
                    cast iron contract six hundredths of an inch in a foot in passing from the
                    liquid state to the temperature of the atmosphere. This contraction is not
                    considerable enough to be taken into consideration in the diameter of the
                    pattern. The shrinking of the sand in drying, though not considerable, tends
                    likewise to make the piece shorter, and is another motive for making the pattern
                    a little longer than the dimensions taken from a gun at the usual temperature.
                    The patterns of the trunions are attached to the pattern of the second reinforce
                    by screws, so as to be unscrewed and separated when the pattern is to be lifted
                    out of the sand.</p>
                <p>The gun-box, in which the dry sand mould is to be formed, is of cast iron, and
                    cast in sand. It consists of several portions; each of these portions has
                    flanges, by which it is fixed to the others, and the whole, when connected
                    together, form the gun-box. In the flanges are holes through which bolts are
                    passed; the bolts are secured by wedge-formed keys; thus the different parts of
                    the box are firmly held together. The two portions of the gun-box which contain
                    the brecch-ring and cascabel are single, not being divided longitudinally. Each
                    of the other five transverse portions is divided longitudinally into two. A
                    handle is fixed to each portion of the box, for the purpose of moving it. The
                    upper transverse portion A A contains the gun-head. In each of the two portions
                    BB, which contain the second reinforce, there is a lateral projection for the
                    trunnions. The figure represents the gun-box with the breech lowermost, in the
                    position in which it is placed when the metal is poured in.</p>
                <p>To make the mould, the pattern of the breech is first placed on a board, and the
                    corresponding portion of the gun-box is put over it, and sand is rammed between
                    the pattern and the box. The flat exposed surface of the sand is painted over
                    with blacking, which consists of charcoal and clayed water, that there may be no
                    adhesion with the sand of the next portion of the mould. The pattern of the
                    first reinforce is now fitted into the pattern of the breech, and the
                    corresponding portions of the first reinforce box adjusted on the flange of the
                    breech box. Sand is well ramified, in small quantities at a time, between the
                    pattern and the box; and the upper flat surface of the sand is painted over with
                    blacking. The mould is completed by adding the remaining pieces of the model and
                    of the box, one above another, ramming the sand, and painting the transverse
                    surface of the sand at the top of each division of the box with blacking. The
                    sand must be strongly and equably rammed, that every part of its surface may be
                    able to resist the pressure of the liquid metal. Three little wedges are
                    interposed between the two adjacent transverse portions of the box, that the
                    sand may project a little, so that after it is dry it may be flush with the box;
                    if this were not done, there would be an interval between the adjacent surfaces
                    of the sand, through which the metal would pass and form a fin.</p>
                <p>When every part is moulded, the box is taken to pieces, and the parts of the
                    pattern are carefully taken out of the sand, for which purpose they are first
                    struck with a wooden mallet. Each part of the mould is then carried separately
                    to the stove to dry. The stove is a room twelve or’ fifteen feet square, with
                    large iron doors on one side; the <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193348121?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0706-8121-0086"/> fire is made
                    in a large conical grate placed on the middle of the floor; the smoke issues by
                    an aperture in the brick ceiling. The heat in this stove is considerable, but it
                    must not be so great as to make the boxes red hot; for then, by the expansion of
                    the iron, the mould would be injured; the moulds take about fifteen hours to dry
                    in this situation. When the moulds are taken out of the stove, their interior
                    surface is painted over with a coat of blacking, that there may be no adhesion
                    between the mould and the metal.</p>
                <p>The pieces of the gun-box containing the mould are then taken to the pit, and
                    being carefully placed the one upon the other by the crane, they are put
                    together, and secured by their bolts. The mould is placed with the breech
                    undermost; the axis of the mould is made perpendicular to the horizon by a
                    plumb-line, that the weight of melted metal may press equably, and not more on
                    one side of the mould than on another. It is not necessary that sand should be
                    rammed round the mould, the box being strong, and its parts firmly bound
                    together, so as to require no additional support. The mould is now in a position
                    for the metal to flow into it through its open end, which is the extremity of
                    the head. Whether the gun is to be of cast iron or brass, the construction of
                    the mould is the same.</p>
                <p>The pig-iron from which the gun is to be made is melted in a furnace, called an
                    air-furnace in the iron founderies, and termed by some authors a reverberatory
                    furnace. The flame of pit-coal is carried by a current of, air so as to play
                    upon the pig-iron. The stack of the chimney is forty feet high. By the pressure
                    of the unrarefied external air on the lower part of the rarefied column of air
                    in the furnace and chimney, the current of air through the furnace is produced.
                    The grate G is larger than any other transverse section of the furnace. (See
                    figure next column.) The furnace has three openings, one, C, for introducing the
                    coals; the second, P, which has a sliding brick door, with a counterpoise,
                    serves for introducing the pig-iron. The third, I, is for the purpose of
                    stirring the metal, and taking out the melted iron for small castings by iron
                    ladles coated with clay, and made red hot. This third opening has a door of
                    fire-brick; the joints between the door and the door-frame are luted. In the
                    middle of the door is a hole, through which the state of the melted metal may be
                    seen. There is likewise a smaller opening, T, for letting out the melted
                    metal.</p>
                <p>The furnace and stack are of brick. The, interior of the furnace is a coating of
                    fire-brick, nine inches thick, detached and separate from the outer, coat and
                    the other parts of the building, in order that the heat may not melt the common
                    brick of which the outer, parts are composed. The fire-brick is made of
                    refractory clay, which, containing little, iron, and little, or no calcareous,
                    master, burns white, and sustains a great heat without melting. These bricks are
                    made of S,tourbridge clay, or of a light bluish gray strątified clay found in
                    the strata that accompany coal in some of the collieries in Scotland. The clay
                    is first ground, the pieces of ironstone, picked out, and then made into bricks.
                    In making the interior coating of the furnace, the bricks must be built with
                    moistened fire-clay, and not with lime mortar. The quantity of metal put into
                    the furnace should be equal to the weight of the solid unbored gun with, its
                    head, and something more in case of need. It requires a large air-furnace to
                    contain metal enough for one large gun.</p>
                <p>The pig-iron for guns should be gray, that kind having most tenacity; white
                    pig-iron is too brittle, and so hard that the head cannot be cut off, nor the
                    gun bored.</p>
                <p>A bed of sand, N, is made in the furpace, on which the pig-iron is to be laid.
                    The furnace is heated to a white heat, til the sand is vitrified, which is known
                    to have taken place by touching the surface of the sand with an iron ringard.
                    The brick door is then lifted up, and the pig-iron is laid on the bed of sand.
                    The heat should be applied so as to produce a speedy fusion; for if the iron is
                    long exposed to heaţ before melting, a portion of its carbonaceous matter is
                    burnt, and it passes from the state of gray cast iron to that of white. In
                    situations where pit-coal cannot be had, wood may be used in the air-furnace;
                    but the heat given by wood is not so great as that produced by pit-coal. To
                    obtain the utmost heat that the wood is capable of affording, it should be well
                    dried, cut into small logs, and the logs should be placed with their end upon
                    the grate.</p>
                <p>The pig-iron melted by the flame playing on it, flows down into a cavity, L,
                    which has a hole, T, opening outwardly, and stopped with clay. When the hole is
                    forced open by a workman, the metal issues and is conveyed by a gutter formed of
                    sand to the gun-mould, into which the melted metal falls through the open end of
                    the head. The sand forming the gutter should be in a proper state of moisture.
                    If it is too dry, some pieces of it will be carried away tíy the metal. Across
                    the gutter is a dam composed of an iron plate luted, and dipping a little below
                    the surface of the metal to retain the scoriae. This dam is driven down to stop
                    the current of metal when the mould is full. The metal is also skimmed, as it
                    passes along, by a skimmer, composed of a rod of iron, terminated by a flat
                    semi-elliptical piece luted and made red hot. It is sometimes the practice to
                    plunge a piece of green wood for a short time into the head whilst liquid. This
                    is with a view to prevent honeycombs, and its action may be to metallize any
                    oxidated particles of the metal, and that the vapour from the.green wood, rising
                    to the surface of the metal, may, carry with it small air bubbles, or other
                    extraneous bodies that would, if they remained, occasion cavities in the
                    metal.</p>
                <p>The figure is a transverse section of the air-furnace. C is the opening through
                    which the coals are introduced. P, the opening at which the pig-iron is thrown
                    in. T, the hole through which the metal is let out. The metal flows into the
                    casting-house. 0, the floor of the casting-house. In this floor is the pit in
                    which the moulds of large goods are sunk, that the metal may flow down into
                    them. I, the door, with a hole in it, for seeing the state of the melted
                    metal.</p>
                <p>G, the grate. L, the lower part of the cavity of the furnace, into which the
                    metal, as it is melted, flows. S, steps <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193348134?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0706-8134-0087"/> leading to A,
                    the ash-pit. N, bottom of the furnace, lined with sand. H, chimney; the height
                    of the stack if forty feet from the surface of the ground. Tħe stack is
                    strengthened in different places by iron bars, X. F is the mass of building
                    which forms the foundation built below the surface óf the ground to support thé
                    weight of the furnace and stack. R, the surface of the ground out of doors. C P
                    N L H is the course that the flame takes.</p>
                <p>It is better to cast thg guns from the air-furnace than from the blast-furnace;
                    for in the blast-furnace, where the ironstone is smelted, the quality of the
                    metal is uncertain, and it may vary from one cast to another, by causès either
                    unknown, or not under the cóhtrol of the iron-master. On the other hand, in the
                    air-furnace, pig-iron of a quality proper for making guns is put in, and the
                    quality of the iron is not materially altered by the process of melting.</p>
                <p>The head of the gun is like the jet (gate or geet of the workmen) of any other
                    casting. Whilst the whole is liquid, the head is a column of liquid metal that
                    acts by its height, exerting pressure on the metal that forms the body of the
                    gun. The metal subjected to this pressure whilst liquid is less subject to
                    porosity when cooled. The head also furnishes metal to fill up the cavities that
                    occur in the piece by the contraction and crystallization of the metal whilst it
                    is passing to the solid state. All the great contractions and crystallizations
                    are thus transferred to the surface of the head, which is found to be composed
                    of large cavities, sometimes containing cast iron crystallized in a fern-leafed
                    shape. The head also serves to receive any impurities that may have escaped the
                    attention of those appointed to skim the iron as it flows along the gutter.</p>
                <p>In ten or twelve hours, the piece is sufficiently cool to be removed. It is then
                    stripped of the mould and taken to the boring-mill, to undergo the operations
                    described under our article <hi rend="smallcaps">Boring of Cannon.</hi> Mortars,
                    howitzers, and carronades are moulded, cast, and bored in the same way as long
                    guns.</p>
                <p>The English Board of Ordnance is supplied with iroπ guns by contract. The
                    contractors ärc those iron-masters who offer the guns at the lowest price, and
                    the guns are cast at their works in the country. The guns are sent to Woolwich
                    to be examined in respect to their dimensions, the coincidence of the axis of
                    the bore with that of the piece, the position of the touch-hole, and to undergo
                    a proof by powder. It is also tried whether water can be forced through the
                    substance of the gun. If any cavities called honey-combs be found in the bore,
                    the piece is rejected. The proofs are at the risk of the contractors, who
                    generally examine and prove the guns at their works before sending them to
                    Woolwich. Unserviceable guns are taken to the triangle, where a large mass of
                    cast iron is let fall upon the gun, from a height of forty or fifty feet. The
                    gun is thus broken into pieces of a size fit for being introduced into the air
                    furnace to be re-cast. Some brass guns are cast and bored in the foundery of the
                    Board of Ordnance at Woolwich.</p>
                <p>Cast-iron guns have the advantage of not suffering any injurious alteration from
                    the beat.of repeated firing. Brass guns when fired rapidly in succession droop
                    at the muzzle. Cast-iron guns alone are used on board British ships; brass guns
                    are now principally used for field pieces. Brass guns, in strict and precise
                    language, might be called bronze guns, as the word brass is most commonly used
                    to denote a composition of copper and zinc, whereas, in gun-metal, there is
                    generally little zinc, and often none. Copper alone is too soft, so that the
                    guns that have been made of it were cut and furrowed by the ball in firing. Use
                    is made, therefore, of a mixture of copper and tin, this composition being
                    harder than copper. Copper and tin separately are soft and malleable; when
                    combined they form a composition that is hard and brittle; and these two
                    qualities are increased by augmenting the relative quantity of tin. Different
                    proportions have been employed for guns; ten parts by weight, of copper, and one
                    of tin, is a proportion that is found to give the requisite hardness, and not
                    too much, nor too great brittleness. The copper is first melted; and the tin is
                    added. If the tin were melted first, and the copper added, much of the tin would
                    be oxidated before the combination took place; the metal, during the process, is
                    stirred with a rod of green wood.</p>
                <p>Bell-metal is a combination of copper and tin in other proportions,. It is made
                    hard by means of tin, in order that it may be sonorous. It contains twenty-five
                    per cent. of tin, and is too brittle and too hard for making guns. In the year
                    1794 the revolutionary government of France obtained gun-metal by depriving
                    bell-metal of a part of its tin. Bell-metal was heated with the contact of air,
                    and stirréd to oxidate the tin; the bell-metal was thus reduced to the state of
                    a coarse powder; this powder was thrown iηto another quantity of bell-metal in
                    fusion; the metallic and oxidated copper in the powder melted, and was mixed
                    with the already fused bell-metal; the oxide of tin of the powder remained on
                    the surface. A melted mass was thus obtained, containing a larger proportion of
                    copper than the bell-metal, and fit for making guns.</p>
                <p>The mould for brass guns is formed of dry sand, in the same way as the mould for
                    cast-iron guns already described. The furnace for melting brass for guns is a
                    reverberatory furnace, the metal being exposed to the flame. It has no high
                    chimney like the air-furnace for melting iron, the heat required not being so
                    great as that for melting cast iron.</p>
                <p>Brass guns are subject to melt at the interior extremity of the touch-hole, by
                    the heàa of quick firing; and the melted parts are driven out by the explosion,
                    so as to render the touch-hole too wide. To prevent this, there is sometimes a
                    bush of copper inserted, and in this bush the toucħ-hole is drilled. The copper
                    being less fusible than the brass, is not melted by the heat of firing the
                    piece. To form the bush, a cylindrical piece of copper is hammered cold, and
                    made into the form of a male screw. A hole is then bored, reaching from the
                    surface of the gun into its bore; the diameter of this cylindrical hole is equal
                    to the diameter of the cylinder of copper measured from the bottom of the
                    threads of the screw. The piece of copper is then screwed into the cylindrical
                    hole, and the touchhole is drilled in it.</p>
                <p>The improvements in casting cannon, as in other arts, have been gradual. Formerly
                    cannon were cast with a core, and this was practised in some founderiës in
                    Flanders, even in the year 1794; but they are now always cast solid, experience
                    having shown that guns cast solid are stronger, and lefeš liable to burst, and
                    the bore is freer from honeycombs, and more likely to haVe. the same axis with
                    the piece. The second of these qualities is still more certainly attained by the
                    practice now in use Of making the gun itself revolve whilst boring; in this way,
                    as long as the boring bar remains unmoved, the axis is right; but if the boring
                    bar has a conical motion, then the point of the bit is out of the axis; when the
                    boring bar was made to revolve, the bore might deviate greatly from the axis.
                    The improvements in the casting of cannon have kept pace with the improvements
                    in the manufacture of cast iron.</p>
                <p>The art of casting iron was known to the ancients, as appears from a small
                    antique statute of Hercules, of cast iron, dug up at Rome. In China it appears
                    to be practised with a dexterity visible in the Chinese specimens of many other
                    arts. In modern Europe it has grown with <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193348147?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0706-8147-0088"/> the general
                    advancement of society, and has latterly attained to a high degree of
                    improvement in this island, where individuals having the command <hi
                    rend="italic">of</hi> capital, and the power of making advances for the salaries
                    of workmen and the construction of buildings, were induced to form large
                    establishments for the smelting of ironstone, and for the manufacture of cast
                    iron. In France cast iron is little used; many of the articles which in England
                    are of cast iron being there of wrought iron, copper, earthenware, or wood. In
                    the Prussian dominions the art of casting statues and small medals in cast iron
                    is successfully practised. But in none of the other countries of Europe is cast
                    iron so generally used, and nowhere is it manufactured on so large a scale, and
                    with the employment of so much capital, as in Britain.</p>
                <p>Pit-coal has been the main instrument in this extensive manufacture. As it gives
                    a better heat for the melting of cast iron, and saves the great extent of ground
                    required for rearing wood, the greater part of the cast iron in Britain is now
                    extracted from the ironstone, and made into castings by pit-coal. Pit-coal began
                    to be used in the smelting of ironstone in 1619. This first operation was
                    performed in Worcestershire by Dudley, who describes his process in a book
                    entitled <hi rend="italic">Metallum</hi><hi rend="italic">Martis.</hi> The
                    manufacture of cast iron was not much advanced one hundred years afterwards; for
                    in the first half of the eighteenth century cast-iron goods were imported into
                    some part of Britain from Holland; and the Dutch chimney-backs, with the figure
                    of a parrot, are to be seen in old country houses in Scotland to this day.</p>
                <p>Two kinds of mineral are smelted· for iron in Britain. The first is the
                    haematites of Ulverstone and the neighbourhood of Whitehaven, which, as it
                    contains much iron (60 per cent.), is carried by sea to smelting furnaces in
                    different parts of Britain. The second is the argillaceous ironstone, which
                    constitutes some of the strata that accompany pit-coal. This is more generally
                    used than the haematites. And it is in the vicinity of the masses of stratified
                    minerals which yield coal and ironstone that the principal iron-works in Britain
                    arc set down. These strata are found in various parts of the island, and arc
                    portions of tlιat class of depositions called by geologists the coal formation.
                    A stratum of coal or of ironstone of considerable extent is termed by the coal
                    and iron masters a coal field, or an ironstone field.</p>
                <p>Pit-coal cannot be employed entire in the blast-furnace; the bituminous part
                    would be conglutinatcd by the heat, and the furnace would be choked, and the
                    materials would no longer descend gradually as they ought to do. The coal is
                    therefore burnt to drive off its bitumen, and it is then in a state of cinder,
                    and called coak. It requires a larger mass of coak than of charcoal to smelt
                    ironstone. Hence the coak blast-furnaces are large, and the machines employed to
                    blow them are more powerful than the wooden spring bellows invented in Germany
                    in 1620, and which continue to be employed in the charcoal iron furnaces in
                    Germany and France. Bellows connected by leather, and worked by water, were used
                    to blow the blast-furnaces at Carron at the commencement of that establishment
                    in 1760. Some time after, these bellows gave place to blowing machines, composed
                    of pistons working in iron cylinders, constructed by the celebrated Smeaton, and
                    described in his reports. The blowing machines of the blastfurnaces in Britain
                    are now always composed of pistons moving in iron cylinders. The improvements in
                    the steamengine have rendered practicable the working of blastfurnaces in
                    situations where there is no fall of water; and, on the other hand, the
                    manufacture of the various parts of numerous steam-engines has called forth the
                    abilities and ingenuity of the iron founder.</p>
                <p>In consequence of the advanced state of the English cast-iron manufacture,
                    several foreign nations have been desirous of introducing the English method,
                    and have procured English workmen for that purpose. In this way iron-works on
                    the English plan were erected in Russia about 1780, in Silesia in 1790; and in
                    France, at Creusot, twelve miles south of Autun, there were three English coak
                    blast-furnaces begun about 1790, under the direction of William Wilkinson.</p>
                <p>The strength of guns depends on the strength of the metal of which the gun is
                    composed, and on the quantity of metal and the manner in which it is disposed.
                    This subject will be considered in the article <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Gunnery.</hi> The nature of the subject does not admit of determining with
                    precision the best weight and length that can be given to a gun fitted for
                    exploding a ball of a given weight. Guns of the same caliber are consequently
                    made of different dimensions even in the same country. The four tables that
                    follow contain the weight, length, and other dimensions of British and of French
                    guns.</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>I</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="9" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi
                            rend="italic">Table of the Length, Weight, Caliber, and Charges of
                            British Government Iron Guns.</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>42 Pounder gun</p><p>32 Pounder gun
                            ,24 Pounder gun</p><p>18 Pounder gun</p><p>12 Pounder gun</p><p>9
                            Pounder gun</p><p>6 Pounder gun</p><p>4 Pounder gun</p><p>3 Pounder
                            guu</p><p>2 Pounder gun</p><p>1 Pounder gun ⅜ Pounder gun</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Length.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Weight.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Diameter of the Bore.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Diameter of the Shot.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Diameter of the Shot
                            Gauge.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>Charge.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>F. In.</p><p>10 0</p><p>10 0</p><p>10
                            0</p><p>9 6</p><p>9 6</p><p>9 6</p><p>9 0</p><p>6 0</p><p>4 6</p><p>3
                            9</p><p>3 0</p><p>3 0</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Cwt. lb. oz.</p><p>67 0 0</p><p>58 0
                            0</p><p>52 0 0</p><p>42 0 0</p><p>34 0 0</p><p>30 1 0</p><p>24 0
                            0</p><p>12 1 0</p><p>7 1 0</p><p>4 2 0</p><p>2 2 0</p><p>1 2
                            0</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"
                            ><p>Inches.</p><p>7-018</p><p>6∙410</p><p>5∙824</p><p>5∙292</p><p>4∙623</p><p>4∙20</p><p>3
                            ’
                            668</p><p>3∙204</p><p>2∙913</p><p>2∙544</p><p>2∙019</p><p>1∙602</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"
                            ><p>Inches.</p><p>6∙684</p><p>6∙105</p><p>.5∙547</p><p>5∙040</p><p>4∙403</p><p>4∙000</p><p>3∙498</p><p>3*053</p><p>2∙775</p><p>2∙423</p><p>1∙293</p><p>1∙526</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Inches.</p><p>6∙795 6∙207 5∙639 5∙124
                            4∙476 4∙066 3∙552 3∙104 2∙820 2∙463 1∙955</p><p>1∙551</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Proof, lb.</p><p>25∙0 21∙8
                            18-0</p><p>150
                            12∙0</p><p>9∙0</p><p>6∙0</p><p>4∙0</p><p>3∙0</p><p>2∙0</p><p>1∙0</p><p>0∙8</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Service,
                            lb.</p><p>14∙0</p><p>10∙11</p><p>8∙0</p><p>6∙0</p><p>4∙0</p><p>30</p><p>2∙0</p><p>1∙5</p><p>1∙0</p><p>0∙11</p><p>0∙6</p><p>0∙3</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193348160?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0706-8160-0089"/>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="4" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">∏∙</hi><hi
                            rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">Table of the Length, Weight, and
                            Caliber of Iron Ordnance used on Board British Merchant Ships in</hi>
                            1811.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>9 Pounder gun..</p><p>6 Pounder
                            gun..</p><p>4 Pounder gun..</p><p>12 Pounder carronade</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Length from Base-ring to
                            Muzzle-end.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Weight.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Diameter of</p><p>Bore.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Feet. In.</p><p>5 0</p><p>4 6</p><p>4
                            0</p><p>4 0</p><p>4 0</p><p>1 3⅜</p><p>3 6</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Cwt. lb. oz.</p><p>14 2 0</p><p>9 1
                            17</p><p>6 3 21</p><p>10 1 0</p><p>8 1 23</p><p>6 2 21</p><p>6 0
                            8</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Inches. 4∙2 3∙668
                            3∙204</p><p>4∙52</p><p>4∙11</p><p>4∙11</p><p>3∙6</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>9 Pounder carronade</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>9 Pounder car-ronađe light.</p><p>6
                            Pounder carronade</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="4" role="data" rows="1"><p>III.— <hi rend="italic">Table of the
                            Length and Weight of Iron Guns used in the French Navy in</hi>
                            1794.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>36 Pounder gun..</p><p>24 Pounder
                            gun..</p><p>18 Pounder gun..</p><p>12 Pounder gun..</p><p>8 Pounder gun,
                            long</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Length from the extremity of the
                            Pommel to extremity of Muzzle.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Length of the Head with which the Gun
                            is cast.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Weight of the Gun.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Pieds. Pouces.</p><p>10 0</p><p>9
                            5⅛</p><p><hi rend="italic">'</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">'12</hi></p><p>8
                            10 <hi rend="subscript"> τ</hi> ⅜</p><p>8 2⅛⅛</p><p>8 7⅜⅛</p><p>7
                            5⅛</p><p>7 7 <hi rend="subscript"> τ</hi> ⅛</p><p>6 0⅛</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Pieds. Ponces.</p><p>3 0</p><p>3
                            0</p><p>2 6</p><p>2 6</p><p>2 0</p><p>2 0 ,</p><p>2 0</p><p>2
                            0</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"
                            ><p>Lbs.</p><p>7190</p><p>5116</p><p>4212</p><p>2995</p><p>2382</p><p>2056</p><p>1733</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>8 Pounder gun, short</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6 Pounder gun, long</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4 Pounder</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="5" role="data" rows="1"><p>IV.— <hi rend="italic">Table of the
                            Weight of Brass Guns used in the French Land Service in</hi> 1794, <hi
                            rend="italic">and the Weight of the llead with which they are
                            Cast.</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Length from the extremity of Pommel
                            to extremity of Muzzle.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Weight of the Gun.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Weight of the Head.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>24 Pounder"</p><p>16 Pounder</p><p>12
                            Pounder</p><p>8 Pounder</p><p>12 Rounder"</p><p>8 Pounder</p><p>4
                            Pounder</p><p>1 Pounder</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Battering guns Garrison guns Field
                            pieces</p><p>∣ For light ſ troops</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Pieds. Pouces, í 10 ]θ⅛ 1 lθ ¾⅛ ∫ 0
                            θτ <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>- ↑ θ θ⅛ (
                            7 0⅛ i 6 1⅛ į 4 10 <hi rend="subscript"> τ</hi> ¾ -ļ 3 10</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"
                            ><p>Lbs.</p><p>5628</p><p>4111</p><p>3184</p><p>2175</p><p>1808</p><p>1186</p><p>590</p><p>266</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"
                            ><p>Lbs.</p><p>3100</p><p>2600</p><p>1800</p><p>1200</p><p>1235</p><p>950</p><p>550</p><p>250</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">(b. b.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
