<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0706-8420-0109-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CAPELL, Edward (7th edition, volume 6, page
                    109)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921321">Farmers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:915437">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198491">Essay</term>
                    <term ref="fast:883769">Critics</term>
                    <term ref="fast:883735">Criticism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x05xf77">Criticism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16x10">Plans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4nv99d9z">Extracts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193348420?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CAPELL, <hi rend="smallcaps">Edward</hi></label>, a gentleman
                    well known by his indefatigable attention to the works of Shakspeare, was a
                    native of the county of Suffolk, and received his education at the school of St
                    Edmund's Bury. In the dedication of his edition of Shakspeare, in 1768, to the
                    Dųke of Grafton, he observes that “bis father and the grandfather of his grace
                    were friends, and to the patronage of the deceased nobleman he owed the leisure
                    which enabled him to bestow the attention of twenty years on that work.” The
                    office which his grace bestowed on Mr Capell was that of deputy-inspector of the
                    plays, to which a salary was annexed of L.200 a year. As early as the year 1745,
                    Mr Capell, shocked at the licentiousness of Han-mer’s plan, first projected an
                    edition of Shakspeare, of the strictest accuracy, to be collated and published
                    in due time, <hi rend="italic">ex fide</hi><hi rend="italic">codicum.</hi>
                    Accordingly, he proceeded to collect and compare the oldest and scarcest copies,
                    noting the original excellencies and defects of the rarest quartos, and
                    distinguishing the improvements or variations of the first, second, and third
                    folios; and after many years labour produced a very beautiful small octavo in
                    ten volumes, with an “Introduction.” There is not, as the authors of a monthly
                    periodical have observed, a more singular literary composition than that
                    “Introduction.” In style and manner it is more obsolete and antique than the age
                    of which he treats. It is Lord Herbert of Cherbury walking the new pavement in
                    all the trappings of romance; but, like Lord Herbert, it displays many valuable
                    qualities accompanying this air of extravagance, much sound sense, and
                    appropriate erudition. In the title-page of “Mr W <hi rend="superscript"> τ</hi>
                    illiam Shakspeare, his Comedies, Histories, and Tragedies,” it was announced
                    “Whereunto will be added, in some other volumes, notes critical and explanatory,
                    and a body of various readings entire.” “The Introduction” likewise declared
                    that these “notes and various readings” would be accompanied with another work,
                    disclosing the sources from which Shakspeare “drew the greater part of his
                    knowledge in mythological and classical matters, his fable, his history, and
                    even the seeming peculiarities of his language, to which,” says Mr Capell, “we
                    have given for title, The School of Shakspeare.” Nothing surely could be more
                    properly conceived than such designs; nor have we ever met with any thing better
                    grounded on the subject of “the learning of Shakspeare,” than what may be found
                    in the long note to this part of Mr Capelľs Introduction. It is more solid than
                    even the popular “Essay” on this topic. Certain quaintnesses of style, and
                    peculiarities of printing and punctuation, attended the whole of this
                    publication. The outline, however, was correct; and the critic, with unremitting
                    toil, succeeded in his undertaking. But while he was diving into the classics of
                    Caxton, and working his way under ground, like the river Mole, in order to
                    emerge in all his glory,—while he was looking forward to his triumphs, —certain
                    other active spirits went to work upon his plan, and, digging out the promised
                    treasures, laid them prematurely before the public, defeating the effect of our
                    critic’s discoveries by anticipation. Steevens, Malone, Farmer, Percy, Reed, and
                    a whole host of literary ferrets, burrowed into every hole and corner of the
                    warren of modern antiquity, and overran all the country, whose map had been
                    delineated by Edward Capell. Such a contingency nearly staggered the steady and
                    unshaken perseverance of our critic on the very eve of the completion of his
                    labours; and, as his editor informs us—for, unhappily, at the end of near forty
                    years the publication was posthumous, and the critic himself no more—he was
                    almost determined to lay the work wholly aside. By the encouragement of some
                    noble and worthy persons, however, he persevered; and to such their
                    encouragement, and his perseverance, the public was, in 1783, indebted for three
                    large volumes in 4to, under the title of “Notes and various readings of
                    Shakspeare; together with the School of Shakspeare, or Extracts from divers
                    English Books that were in print in the Author’s time; evidently showing from
                    whence his several Fables were taken, and some parcel of his Dialogue. Also
                    farther extracts, which contribute to a due understanding of his Writings, or
                    give a light to the History of his Life, or to the Dramatic History of his Time.
                    By Edward Capell.” Besides the works already mentioned, Mr Capell was the editor
                    of a volume of ancient poems called “Prolusions and the alteration of “Anthony
                    and Cleopatra,” as acted at Drury Lane in 1758. He died on the 24th January
                    1781.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
