<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0706-6116-0701-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CIRCARS, Northern (7th edition, volume 6, page
                    701)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94c35">Extents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4736m682">Lakes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qn5zh77">Mahommedanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ww77817">Telingas</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h708258">Surveying</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:990901">Lakes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1748515">Exceptionalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193356116?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CIRCARS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Northern</hi></label>, an
                    extensive province of Hindustan, lying on the western side of the Bay of Bengal.
                    It is a narrow slip of territory, extending from 15° 2' to the 20th degree of
                    north lat., but is little more than one degree in breadth. The sea bounds it on
                    the east along a coast 470 miles in length, from the port of Mootapilly to the
                    town of Maloud in Orissa, on the borders of the Chilca Lake. From about fifty to
                    seventy miles inland it is divided from the province of Hyderabad by a range of
                    small detached hills, extending to the banks of the Godavery; and it is
                    separated from Gundwana to the north of that river by a great ridge of
                    mountains, impassable, where they have hitherto been explored, for horse or
                    wheel-carriage, and which are continued to the northern, extremity of the
                    Circars at Goomsur. From this last place the same unbroken chain curves to the
                    eastward, and, together with the Chilca Lake, forms an almost impenetrable
                    barrier, fifty miles in extent, to the north on the side of Cuttack, with the
                    exception of a tongue of land between Lake Chilca and the sea. Towards the south
                    the small river Gonde-zama<pb break="no" facs="nls:193356129?mode=fullsize"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0706-6129-0702"/>, which empties itself at Mootapilly, separates
                    this territory from the districts of Ongole, and forms the most definite modern
                    frontier of the Carnatic below the Ghauts.</p>
                <p>The area of the Circars is 17,000 square miles, of which it is estimated that
                    only one fifth is in cultivation or fallow, twice that portion in pasture, and
                    the remainder is occupied by woods, water, towns, barren hills, or a sandy waste
                    three miles in breadth, which borders the whole extent of the coast. The country
                    for about thirty-five miles inland is a level plain, with only two remarkable
                    interruptions in its greatest length along the shore. Beyond this about fifteen
                    miles farther inland, and parallel to it, the country is much more elevated,
                    being agreeably variegated with hills easy of access, and remarkably fertile.
                    Beyond these tracts of plain and hilly ground, to the north of the Godavery, a
                    still higher region extends close to the great ridge of mountains which stretch
                    far inland. This region is poor, unhealthy, and thinly inhabited.</p>
                <p>The grand divisions of this province are properly five; being so many portions of
                    its length, principally marked by rivers running across from the hills on the
                    west to the sea. Of these divisions the first is Guntoor or Mortizabad, the most
                    southerly province, bounded on the north by the river Kistnah, which, after
                    running a curve of 600 miles from the Balaghaut Hills, near the coast of
                    Malabar, separates this province on the north from the second division, namely,
                    Condapilly or Mustaphabad. Ellore is the third division; and these two divisions
                    are adjacent to each other, as well as to the Guntoor Circar, and occupy the
                    whole space lying between the Kistnah and Godavery. The fourth division, namely,
                    Rajcmundry, towards the south is separated from Ellore in its greatest breadth
                    by the Godavcry. The fifth division is Cicacole, the most northerly of the
                    whole.</p>
                <p>The climate of the Northern Circars, though it has a general resemblance to that
                    of Hindustan north of the Kistnah, is still distinguished by local peculiarities
                    arising from its maritime situation, and the extent and position of the inland
                    hills. The periodical rain usually sets in about the middle of June with a
                    westerly wind, and continues in moderate showers until the latter end of August,
                    which is the period of the small grain harvest. The rain continues in greater
                    abundance from this period until the beginning of November, when it generally
                    ceases, and is succeeded by a strong north-easterly wind, tempered by the mild
                    influence of the sea over which it blows. The harvest for rice and bajarry,
                    which .are the great productions of the country north of the Godavery, finishes
                    about the middle of this latter season, early in January; and in like manner the
                    vernal equinox terminates the harvest south of that river for the different
                    species of maize, as well as of other grains, and peas. Then commences the hot
                    season, which is always moderate towards the northern extremity of the Circars,
                    near Ganjam, owing to the constant breezes from the sea. On the south the hot
                    season is moderated for two months by sea-breezes from the south blowing along
                    the shore; but afterwards, until the period of the rains, the wind blowing over
                    a parched loose soil of great extent, and especially over the almost dry and
                    sandy bed of the Kistnah, becomes so heated that it raises the thermometer for
                    an entire week to 105, and frequently to 110 degrees. In the hilly regions the
                    air is in a remarkably noxious state; and throughout the different seasons of
                    the year the hill fever, which is prevalent, is frequently fatal to strangers.
                    It is generally ascribed to the state of the atmosphere, contaminated with the
                    exhalations of a fertile soil, pent up in valleys, or impeded in its circulation
                    by the luxuriant growth of plants, or by the trees with which the villages are
                    surrounded. All these provinces along the coast have a sandy soil, which
                    improves gradually towards the hills; and it seldom produces more than oen croþ
                    annually, which, as there is an abundant supply of water, is extremely rich. The
                    country is well watered by running streams, many of which are divided
                    artificially into canals, and being conducted into tanks and reservoirs, are
                    thus rendered subservient to cultivation. The province accordingly abounds in
                    all the different sorts of grain which have been already mentioned; it is
                    properly the granary of the Carnatic during the north-east monsoon. Fruits,
                    roots, and greens are scarce, or reared with difficulty, to the south of the
                    Godavery; nor towards the north are they so excellent as in some other
                    provinces. Sugar and cotton are also scantily produced in Rajemundry and
                    Jehapoor. Tobacco and bay salt, of superior quality, have lately been produced
                    in such abundance as greatly to exceed the home demand. The forests of
                    Rajemundry, from the commencement of the hills along the banks of the Godavery,
                    yield an inexhaustible supply of the best and largest teak timbers; and if
                    proper use were made of this advantage, an article would be procured of great
                    advantage to commerce. The cocoa and the palmyra, or, in the more northerly
                    provinces, the tree which produces thegum-arabic, are the materials from which
                    are constructed about 500 of those unwieldy vessels with two masts, called
                    doo-nies, from 60 to 300 tons each. The domestic animals found in this province
                    are chiefly sheep and the larger species of horned cattle. The neighbouring sea
                    and its numerous inlets abound with almost every species of Indian fish,
                    together with some that are common to Europe, such as mullet, sole, and
                    pomphlet, a small fish resembling a turbot.</p>
                <p>Cotton is the staple produce, from which are fabricated cloths of different
                    degrees of fineness. Plain cloth, which is valuable in foreign markets, is
                    chiefly wrought in the island of Nagar and its vicinity; it forms the groundwork
                    of the best printed calicoes in Europe, and of those beautifully painted ones
                    called palampores in the districts of Masulipatam. The coarser plain cloths,
                    which are made to the north and south of the Godavery, or coloured with chay
                    root, which is the madder of the East, and which grows in most perfection in the
                    pure sands annually overflowed by the Krishna, are in great demand, both abroad
                    and at home. Muslins are, besides, manufactured at Cicacole, beautiful woollen
                    carpets at Ellore, and silks at Burrampore. But these are rather objects of
                    curiosity than of any great general advantage; as is also the art of painting,
                    or inlaying ivory and black wood in the cabinet work at Vizagapatam.
                    Ship-building is carried on extensively in the ports of Coringa and Narsapore,
                    the two principal mouths of the Godavery. Here ships of 500 tons are built, and
                    about 50,000 tons of small craft are employed in the coasting trade.</p>
                <p>This province trades with Europe, with the neighbouring Indian ports, and with
                    the inland provinces of the Deccan. The European nations who have establishments
                    on the coast export the fine cotton manufactures, which are also purchased by
                    foreign adventurers. In return for these manufactures, and for salt, which they
                    export, treasure is frequently brought from Madras, the principal part of the
                    Madras investment of piece-goods being provided in the Northern Circars. The
                    coasting trade consists chiefly in the exportation of various sorts of grain to
                    Madras, in return for which are received the coarser sorts of cloths; European
                    and China goods for the use of officers and others employed in that quarter,
                    namely, wines of various sorts, ale, brandy, glass-ware, stationery, tea,
                    copper, steel, hardware, &amp;c.; also various goods received from the East,
                    such as betel-nut to a great amount, alum, cloves, benjamin, pepper, tin,
                    dammer, borax, and a quantity of arrack. The articles carried to the interior bv
                    the <pb break="no" facs="nls:193356142?mode=fullsize"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0706-6142-0703"/> native traders are salt, piece-goods of native
                    manufacture, copper, and raw silk, the latter chiefly from Bengal, in return for
                    which are received cotton and wheat.</p>
                <p>The native inhabitants of the Northern Circars, with the exception of some
                    thousand Mahommedans dispersed throughout the principal towns, and in the army,
                    are wholly Hindus, and may, on a moderate computation, be estimated at two and a
                    half millions. They are composed of the two nations of Telinga, and Oria, Woria,
                    or Orissa, formerly divided from each other by the Godavery, but, since their
                    union under the same government, a good deal mixed among themselves, as well as
                    with some of the neighbouring tribes. They have each their peculiar dialect,
                    apparently of the Sanscrit language, as well as their peculiar rites, customs,
                    and national traits. The four great castes or divisions of the people are common
                    in both countries, but with less deviations from original institutions in Oria,
                    where Brahminical abstinence from animal food is very general among all the
                    higher tribes. The Brahmins continue to enjoy their pre-eminence and
                    consideration among the other classes. The Rachewars, Rowars, and Velmas, of
                    which denominations the principal Zemindars are composed, affect the warlike
                    character and manners of Rajpoots. The Ráchewars are of the ancient race of the
                    Orissa sovereigns, who were forced to fly before the conquering arms of the
                    Mahommedans from the plains to the highland woods. The Rowars, or Worians, being
                    petty chieftains of the military tribe, were enabled, after the Mahommedan
                    conquest, to acquire an independent jurisdiction in the mountainous tract to the
                    west of Cicacole. The Velmas are of Telinga origin; and being driven from the
                    Carnatic in the year 1662 by the Mahommedans, established themselves on the
                    borders of the Krishna. The remainder are husbandmen, cow-herds, weavers,
                    artificers, all of the Sudra or last great caste. The retail dealers form a
                    third class.</p>
                <p>It was not till the year 1471 that the Mahommedans extended their arms to the
                    Northern Circars. In 1541 they conquered Condapilly; and nine years afterwards
                    they extended their conquests over all Guntoor, and the districts of
                    Masulipatam. But the conquerors appear to have acquired but a very imperfect
                    possession of the country, as it was again conquered from the Hindu princes of
                    Orissa about the year 1571, during the reign of Ibrahim Kootub Shah of Hyderabad
                    or Golcondah. In 1687 these provinces, with the empire of Hyderabad, were added
                    to the extensive empire of Aurungzebe. But this monarch was too busily employed
                    in conquering the larger provinces of the Deccan, and curbing the Mahratta
                    power, to regulate his conquest with due care. In 1724 the issue of a great
                    battle transferred in fact, though not in form, these provinces from the house
                    of Timour to that of Nizam ul Moolk, who reformed the administration of the
                    revenues and the civil and military establishment. He was succeeded by his third
                    son Salabut Jung, who being indebted for his elevation to the French East’India
                    Company, in return for their services granted them the district of Condavir or
                    Guntoor, and soon afterwards the other Circars. In 1759, by the conquest of the
                    fortress of Masulipatam, that great commanding bulwark, the dominion of the
                    maritime provinces on either side, from the river Gondegama to the Chilca Lake,
                    was necessarily transferred from the French to the British. But they left them
                    under the administration of the Nizam, with the exception of the town and
                    fortress of Masulipatam, which were retained by the English East India Company.
                    In 1765 Lord Clive obtained from the Mogul a grant of four of the Circars,
                    namely, the Cicacole, Rajamundry, Ellore, and Condapilly, which in the following
                    year was confirmed by a treaty entered into with the Nizam, who had by this time
                    superseded Salabut Jung in ,his authority. The remaining Circar of Guntoor
                    devolved to the East India Company in 1788.</p>
                <p>The local government of the Northern Circars, which was continued under the
                    management of the natives, was superseded in 1769 by the appointment of chiefs
                    and councils; and this mode of government continued until 1794. At the same time
                    the power of the Zemindars was broken, and a more efficient mode of collecting
                    the revenue has since been adopted. In 1802 and 1804 a permanent settlement of
                    the territorial revenue was introduced, when the province was divided into five
                    collectorships or districts, namely, Ganjam, Vizagapatam, Rajamundry,
                    Masulipatam, and Guntoor. (See Appendix to the <hi rend="italic">Fifth Report of
                    the Select Committee on the Affairs of the East India Company</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> J. Grant’s <hi rend="italic">Political Survey of the
                    Northern Circars</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> C. N. White’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Minute</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> Rennelľs <hi rend="italic">Memoir of a Map
                    of Hindustan</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi><hi rend="italic">Letter of Sir Thomas
                    Munro, Bart.</hi> &amp;c.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
