<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0706-5193-0630-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CHRISTINA (7th edition, volume 6, page 630)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xw47w7c">Bavarians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s11w">Woman</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qn6g">Crowns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p843w5c">Hand</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204537">Sweden</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204558">Denmark</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206891">Poland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:828986">Bavarians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881894">Cousins</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1739388">Womanism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1895887">Womanizers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:884318">Crowns</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950823">Hand</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1095688">Respect</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193355193?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CHRISTINA</label>, a daughter of Gustavus Adolphus, king of
                    Sweden, was born in 1626, and succeeded to the crown in 1633, when only seven
                    years of age. This princess discovered, even in her infancy, what she afterwards
                    expressed in her memoirs, namely, an invincible antipathy for the employments
                    and conversation of women; and she had the natural awkwardness of a man with
                    respect to all the little works which generally fall to their share. On the
                    contrary, she was fond of violent exercises, and such amusements as consist in
                    feats of strength and activity. She had also both ability and taste for abstract
                    speculations; and amused herself with languages and the sciences, particularly
                    that of legislation and government. She derived her knowledge of ancient history
                    from its best sources: Polybius and Thucydides were her favourite authors. As
                    she was the sovereign of a powerful kingdom, it is not strange that almost all
                    the princes in Europe aspired to her hand. Amongst these were the prince of
                    Denmark, the elector Palatine, the elector of Brandenburg, the king of Spain,
                    the king of the Romans, Don John of Austria, Stanislaus king of Poland, John
                    Cassimir his brother, and Charles Gustavus duke of Deux Ponts, of the Bavarian
                    Palatinate family, son of the great Gustavus’s sister, and consequently her
                    first cousin. To this nobleman, as well as to all his competitors, she
                    constantly refused her hand; but she caused him to be appointed her successor by
                    the states. Political interests, differences of religion, and contrariety of
                    manners, furnished Christina with pretences for <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193355206?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0706-5206-0631"/> rejecting all
                    her suitors; but hcr real motives were the love of independence, and a strong
                    aversion she had conceived, even in her infancy, to the marriage yoke. “Do not
                    force me to marry,” said she to the states; “for if I should have a son, it is
                    not more probable that he should be an Augustus than a Nero.”</p>
                <p>One of the great affairs that employed Christina while she occupied the throne,
                    was the peace of Westphalia, in which many conflicting interests were to be
                    reconciled, and many claims to be ascertained. It was concluded .in the month of
                    October 1648. The success of the Swedish arms rendered Christina the arbitress
                    of this treaty, at least in regard to the affairs of Sweden, to which the peace
                    confirmed the possession of many important countries. No public event of
                    importance took place during the rest of Christina’s reign; for there were
                    neither wars abroad, nor troubles at home. Her reign was distinguished by an
                    active patronage of learning and genius. She drew about hcr, wherever she was,
                    all the distinguished characters of her time; Grotius, Pascal, Bochart,
                    Descartes, Gassendi, Saumaise, Naude, Vossius, Heinsius, Meibom, Scudery,
                    Menage, Lucas, Holstcntius, Lambecius, Bayle, Madame Dacier, Filicaja, and many
                    others. The arts never fail to immortalize the prince who protects them; and
                    almost all these illustrious persons have celebrated Christina, either in poems,
                    letters, or literary productions of some other kind, the greater part of which
                    are now forgotten, though the general celebrity they conferred in a great
                    measure remains.</p>
                <p>Though Christina at first was fond of the power and splendour of royalty, yet she
                    began at length to feel that it embarrassed hcr; and the same love of
                    independence and liberty which had determined her against marriage at last made
                    her weary of the crown. Accordingly, as it grew more and more irksome to her,
                    she resolved to abdicate; and, in 1652, she communicated <hi rend="superscript">
                    1</hi> her resolution to the senate. The senate zealously remonstrated against
                    it, and was joined by the people, nay even by Charles Gustavus himself, who was
                    to succeed her. She yielded to their importunities, and continued to sacrifice
                    hcr own pleasure to the will of the public till the year 1654, when she carried
                    hcr design into execution. Christina, besides abdicating her crown, abjured her
                    religion; an act which was universally approved by one party and censured by
                    another; for whilst the Catholics triumphed, the Protestants were offended. No
                    prince, after a long imprisonment, ever showed so much joy upon being restored
                    to his kingdom, as Christina did in quitting hers. When she came to a little
                    brook, which separates Sweden from Denmark, she got out of her carriage, and,
                    leaping on the other side, cried out in a transport of joy, “At last I am free,
                    and out of Sweden, whither, I hope, I shall never return.” She dismissed her
                    women, and laying aside the habit of lier sex, <hi rend="superscript"> ,ζ</hi> I
                    would become a man,” said she; “yet I do not love men because they are mcn, but
                    because they are not women.” She made her abjuration at Brussels, where she saw
                    the great Condé, who, after his defection, made that city his asylum. “Cousin,”
                    said she, “who would have thought, ten years ago, that we should have met at
                    this distance from our respective countries?” During her residence in France she
                    excited universal disgust, not only by violating all the customs of the country,
                    but by observing others directly opposed to them. She treated the ladies of the
                    court with the greatest rudeness and contempt; and when they came to embrace
                    her, she being in male attire, cried out, “W <hi rend="superscript"> τ</hi> hat
                    a strange eagerness these women have to kiss me! Is it because I look like a man
                    ?”</p>
                <p>The murder of Monaldechi is to this hour an inscrutable mystery. It is, however,
                    of a piece with the expressions constantly used by Christina in her letters,
                    with respect to those with whom she was offended; for she scarcely ever
                    signified her displeasure without threatening the life of the offender. “If you
                    fail in your duty,” said she to her secretary, whom she sent to Stockholm after
                    her abdication, “not all the power of the King of Sweden shall save your life,
                    though you should take shelter in his arms.” A musician having quitted her
                    service for that of the Duke of Savoy, she was so transported with rage as to
                    disgrace herself by these words, in a letter written with her own hand: “He
                    lives only for me; and if he does not sing for me, lie shall not sing long for
                    any body else.”</p>
                <p>Upon the whole, she appears to have been a strange compound of faults and
                    foibles, pushed to the most extravagant excess. She says of herself, “that she
                    was mistrustful, ambitious, passionate, haughty, impatient, contemptuous,
                    satirical, incredulous, undevout, of an ardent and violent temper, and extremely
                    amorous ;” a disposition, however, to which, if she may be believed, her pride
                    and her virtue were always superior.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
