<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0706-4101-0546-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CHIMNEY (7th edition, volume 6, page 546)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m32nc36">Fires</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40k26c70">Fire</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sn0143x">Chimneys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b56d58r">Floors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fr9h">Smoking</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qb9vd72">Scythians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:925697">Fires</term>
                    <term ref="fast:925173">Fire</term>
                    <term ref="fast:857077">Chimneys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:927635">Floors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:927616">Flooring</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1109953">Scythians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205534">Libya</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193354101?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CHIMNEY</label>, in <hi rend="italic">Architecture, a</hi>
                    particular part of <hi rend="italic">a</hi> house where the fire is made, having
                    a tube or funnel to carry off the smoke. The word <hi rend="italic">chimney</hi>
                    comes from the French <hi rend="italic">cheminée,</hi> and that from the Latin
                    <hi rend="italic">caminata,</hi> a chamber in which is a chimney; while <hi
                    rend="italic">caminata,</hi> again, is derived from <hi rend="italic"
                    >caminus,</hi> and that from the Greek <hi rend="italic">κάμινος,</hi> chimney,
                    from κα∕ω, <hi rend="italic">uro,</hi> I burn.</p>
                <p>It is usually supposed that chimneys are of modern invention, and that the
                    ancients made use only of stoves; but Octavio Ferrari endeavours to prove that
                    chimneys were in use among the ancients. To this end he cites the authority of
                    Virgil,</p>
                <p>Et jam summa procul villarum culmina fumant, and that of Appian, who says, that
                    of those persons proscribed by the triumvirate, some hid themselves in wells and
                    common sewers, and some on the tops of houses and in chimneys (xαwα⅛j <hi
                    rend="italic">wrωξο(f&gt;ια</hi><hi rend="italic">∣</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >,</hi><hi rend="italic">fumaria</hi><hi rend="italic">sub</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >tecto posita)</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> while Aristophanes, in one of his
                    comedies, introduces his old man, Polycleon, shut up in a chamber, whence he
                    endeavours to make his escape by the <hi rend="italic">chimney.</hi></p>
                <p>Chimneys, however, are, in Professor Beckmann’s opinion, of comparatively modern
                    origin; and in order to show the ground upon which he comes to this conclusion,
                    we shall lay before our readers some observations from his elaborate
                    dissertation on this subject.</p>
                <p>When the triumviri, says Appian, caused those who had been proscribed by them to
                    be sought for by the military, some of them, in order to avoid the bloody hands
                    <hi rend="italic">of</hi> their persecutors, hid themselves in wells, and
                    others, as Ferrarius translates the words, <hi rend="italic">in</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">fumaria</hi><hi rend="italic">sub</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >tecto,</hi><hi rend="italic">qua scilicet</hi><hi rend="italic">fumus e tecto
                    evolvitur.</hi> The true translation, however, in Beckmann's opinion, is <hi
                    rend="italic">fumosa</hi><hi rend="italic">coenacula.</hi> The principal persons
                    of Rome endeavoured to conceal themselves in the smoky apartments of the upper
                    story under the roof, which, in general, were inhabited only by poor people; and
                    this seems to be confirmed by what Juvenal expressly says, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Parus venit</hi><hi rend="italic">in ccenacula miles.</hi></p>
                <p>Those passages of the ancients which speak of smoke rising up from houses, have
                    with equal impropriety been supposed to allude to chimneys, as if the smoke
                    eould not make its way through doors and windows. Seneea says, “Last evening I
                    had some friends with me, and on that account a stronger smoke was raised; not
                    such a smoke, however, as bursts forth from the kitehens of the great, and which
                    alarms the watchmen, but sueh an one as signifies that guests have arrived.”
                    Those whose judgments are not already warped by prejudice, will undoubtedly find
                    the true sense of these words to be, that the smoke forced its way through the
                    kitchen windows. Had the houses been built with chimney funnels, one cannot
                    conceive why the watchmen should have been alarmed when they observed a stronger
                    smoke than usual arising from them; but as the kitchens had no convenience of
                    that nature, an apprehension of fire, when extraordinary entertainments were to
                    be provided in the houses of the rich for large companies, seems to have been
                    well founded; and on such occasions people appointed for that purpose were
                    stationed in the neighbourhood, to be constantly on the watch, and to be ready
                    to extinguish the flames in case a fire should happen. There are to be found in
                    Roman authors many other passages of a similar kind, which it is hardly
                    necessary to mention, such as that of Virgil,</p>
                <p>Et jam summa procul villarum culmina fumant; and the following words of Plautus,
                    descriptive of a miser:</p>
                <p>Quin divûm atque hominum clamat continuo fidem,</p>
                <p>Suam rem periisse, seque eradicarier, De suo tigillo fumus si qua exit foras.</p>
                <p>The passage of Aristophanes above alluded to, however, and which, according to
                    the usual translation, seems to refer to a common chimney, may, especially when
                    we consider the illustration of the scholiasts, be explained by a simple hole in
                    the roof, as Reiske has supposed; and indeed<pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193354114?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0706-4114-0547"/> this appears
                    to be the more probable, as we find mention made of a top or covering (τjjλ∕α)
                    with which the hole was closed.</p>
                <p>It has been said that the instances of chimneys remaining among the ruins of
                    ancient buildings are fcw, and that the rules given by Vitruvius for building
                    them are obscure; but it appears that there exists no remains oí ancient
                    chimneys, and that Vitruvius gives no rules, either obscure or perspicuous, for
                    building what, in the modern acceptation of the word, deserves the name of a
                    chimney The ancient mason-work still to be found in Italy does not determine the
                    question. Of the walls of towns, temples, amphithcatres, baths, aqueducts, and
                    bridges, there are some, though very imperfect remains, in which chimneys cannot
                    be expected; but of common dwellinghouses none are to be seen, except at
                    Herculaneum, and there no traces of chimneys have yet been discovered The
                    paintings and pieces of sculpture which are preserver; afford as little
                    information, for nothing can be perceived ir them which bears the smallest
                    resemblance to a modern chimney.</p>
                <p>If there were no funnels in the houses of the ancients to carry off the smoke,
                    the directions given by Columella, to make kitchens so high that the roof should
                    not catch fire, were of the utmost importance. An accident of the kind, which
                    the author seems to have apprehended, had almost happened at Beneventum, when
                    the landlord whc entertained Maecenas and his company was making a strong fire
                    in order to get some birds the sooner roasted.</p>
                <p>Ubi sedulus hospes</p>
                <p>Paene arsit, macros dum turdos versat in igne; Nam vaga per veterem dilapso
                    flamma culinam Vulcano summum properabat, lambere tectam.</p>
                <p>Had there been chimneys in the Roman houses, Vitruvius certainly would not have
                    failed to describe their construction, which is sometimes attended with
                    considerable difficulties, and which is intimately connected with the regulation
                    of the plan of the whole edifice. He does not, however, say a word on the
                    subject; neither does Julius Pollux, who has collected with great care the Greek
                    names of every part of a dwelling-house; and Grapaldus, who in later times made
                    a collection of the Latin terms, has not given a Latin word expressive of a
                    modern chimney.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Caminus,</hi> as far as we have been able to lcarn, signified
                    first a chemical or metallurgic furnace, in which a crucible was placed for
                    melting and refining metals; secondly, a smith’s forge; and, thirdly, a hearth
                    on which portable Stoves or fire-pans were placed for warming the apartment. In
                    all these, however, there appears no trace of a chimney. Herodotus relates, that
                    a king of Libya, when one of his servants asked for his wages, offered him in
                    jest the sun, which at that time shone into the house through an opening in the
                    roof, under which the fire was perhaps made in the middle of the edifice. If
                    such a hole must be called a chimney, our author admits that chimneys were in
                    use among the ancients, especially in their kitchens; but it is obvious that
                    such chimneys bore no rcscmblance to ours, through which the sun could not dart
                    his rays upon the floor of any apartment.</p>
                <p>However imperfect may be the information which can be collected from the Greek
                    and Roman authors respecting the manner in which the ancients warmed their
                    apartments, it nevertheless shows that they commonly used for that purpose a
                    large fire-pan or portable stove, in which they kindled wood, and, when the wood
                    was well lighted, carried it into the room, or perhaps they filled it with
                    burning coals. When Alexander the Great was entertained by a friend in winter,
                    as the weather was cold and raw, a small fire basin was brought into the
                    apartment to warm it. The prince, observing the size of the vessel, and that it
                    contained only a few coals, desired his host, in a jeering manner, to bring more
                    wood or to fetch frankincense; giving him thus to understand that the fire was
                    fitter for burning perfumes than to produce heat. Anacharsis, the Scythian
                    philosopher, though displeased with many of the Grecian customs, praised the
                    Greeks, because they shut out the smoke, and brought only fire into their
                    houses.</p>
                <p> We are informed by Lampridius, that the extravagant Heliogabalus caused to be
                    burned in such stoves, Indian</p>
                <p>, spices, and costly perfumes, instead of wood. It is also worthy of notice, that
                    coals were found in some of the <hi rend="subscript"> l</hi> apartments of
                    Herculaneum, but neither stoves nor chim- , neys.</p>
                <p>It is well known to every scholar, that the useful arts of life were invented in
                    the East; and that the customs, ' manners, and furniture of eastern nations,
                    have remain- . ed from time immemorial almost unchanged. In Persia, I which Sir
                    William Jones seems to have considered as ι the original country of mankind, the
                    methods employed ι by the inhabitants for warming themselves have a great
                    resemblance to those employed by the ancient Greeks and &gt; Romans for the same
                    purpose. According to De la Ville, <hi rend="subscript"> l</hi> the Persians
                    make fires in their apartments, not in chim-I neys as we do, but in stoves in
                    the earth, which they call <hi rend="italic">;</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >tennor.</hi> These stoves consist of a square or round hole, I two spans or a
                    little more in depth, and in shape not un-</p>
                <p>• like an Italian cask. That this hole may throw out heat sooner, and with more
                    strength, there is placed in it an iron vessel of the same size, which is either
                    filled with burning coals, or a fire of wood and other inflammable substances is
                    made in it. When this is done, they place over the hole or stove a wooden top,
                    like a small low table, and spread above it a large coverlet quilted with
                    cotton, which hangs down on all sides to the floor. This covering condenses the
                    heat, and causes it to warm the whole apartment. The people who eat or converse
                    there, and some who sleep in it, lie down on the floor upon the carpet, and lean
                    with their shoulders against the wall, on square cushions, upon which they
                    sometimes also sit; for the <hi rend="italic">ien-</hi><hi rend="italic">*
                    nor</hi> is constructed in a place equally distant from the walls on both sides.
                    Those who are not very cold put their feet only under the table or covering; but
                    those who require more heat may put their hands under it, or creep under it
                    altogether. By these means the stove diffuses over the whole body, without
                    causing uneasiness to the head, so penetrating and agreeable a warmth, that I
                    never experienced any thing more pleasant. Those, however, who require less heat
                    let the coverlet hang down on their side to the floor, and enjoy without any
                    inconvenience from the stove the moderately-heated air of the apartment. They
                    have a method also’of stirring up or blowing the fire when necessary, by means
                    of a small pipe united with the tennor or stove under the earth, and made to
                    project above the floor as high as is judged necessary; so that, when a person
                    blows into it, the wind, having no other vent, acts immediately upon the fire
                    like a pair of bellows. When there is no longer occasion to use this stove, both
                    holes, that is to say, the mouth of the stove and that of the pipe which conveys
                    the air to it, are closed up by a flat stone made for that purpose. Scarcely any
                    appearance of them is then to be perceived, nor do they occasion inconvenience,
                    especially in a country where it is always customary to cover the floor with a
                    carpet, and where the walls are plastered. In many parts these ovens are used to
                    cook victuals, by kettles placed over them. They are employed also to bake
                    bread; and for this purpose they are covered with a large broad metal plate, on
                    which the cake is laid; but if the bread is thick and requires more heat, it is
                    put into the stove itself. (See <hi rend="italic">History of Invent.</hi> ii.
                    88.) <pb break="no" facs="nls:193354127?mode=fullsize"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0706-4127-0548"/> Beckmann further observes, that the oldest
                    account of chimneys is to be found in an inscription at Venice, which relates,
                    that, in the year 1347, a great many chimneys were thrown down by an earthquake.
                    It would appear, however, that in some places they had been in use for a
                    considerable time before that period; and De Gataris, in his history of Padua,
                    relates, that Franeesco de Carraro, lord of Padua, came to Rome in 1368, and
                    finding no chimneys in the inn where he lodged, because at that time fire was
                    kindled in a hall in the middle of the floor, he caused two chimneys like those
                    which had <hi rend="italic">long</hi> been used at Padua to be constructed by
                    masons and carpenters, whom he had brought along with him. Over these chimneys,
                    the first whieh had ever been seen at Rome, he affixed his arms, and these still
                    remained in the time of De Gataris, who died of the plague in 1405.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
