<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0827-0778-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ZENO of Elea (9th edition, volume 24, page 778)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:978609">Ionians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:886086">Cynicism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1027064">Motion</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1052850">Paradoxes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1052841">Paradox</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1158235">Truth</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4js9hb31">Motion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49k45t2j">Truth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bn9x62g">Rest</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46t0gw81">Belief</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n827/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ZENO <hi rend="smallcaps">of Elea</hi></label>, son of
                    Teleutagoras, is supposed to have been born towards the beginning of the 5th
                    century B.c. The pupil and the friend of Parmenides, he sought to recommend his
                    master’s doctrine of the existence of the One by controverting the popular
                    belief in the existence of the Many. In virtue of this method of indirect
                    argumentation he is regarded as the inventor of “dialectic,” that is to say,
                    disputation having for its end not victory but the discovery or the transmission
                    of truth. He is said to have been concerned in a plot against a tyrant, and on
                    its detection to have borne with exemplary constancy the tortures to which he
                    was subjected; but authorities differ both as to the name and the residence of
                    the tyrant and as to the circumstances and the issue of the enterprise.</p>
                <p>In Plato’s <hi rend="italic">Parmenides,</hi> Socrates, “then very young,” meets
                    Parmenides, “an old man some sixty-five years of age,” and Zeno, “a man of about
                    forty, tall and personable,” and engages them in philosophical discussion. But
                    it may be doubted whether such a meeting was chronologically possible. Plato’s
                    account of Zeno’s teaching (<hi rend="italic">Parmenides,</hi> 128 <hi
                    rend="italic">sq.)</hi> is, however, presumably as accurate as it is precise. In
                    reply to those who thought that Parmenides’s theory of the existence of the One
                    involved inconsistencies and absurdities, Zeno tried to show that the assumption
                    of the existence of the Many carried with it inconsistencies and absurdities
                    grosser and more numerous. In early youth he collected his arguments in a book,
                    which, according to Plato, was put into circulation without his knowledge.</p>
                <p>Of the paradoxes used by Zeno to discredit the belief in plurality and motion,
                    eight survive in the writings of Aristotle and Simplicius. They are commonly
                    stated as follows.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See
                    Zeller, <hi rend="italic">Die Philosophie d. Griechen,</hi> I. 540 <hi
                    rend="italic">sq.; Grundriss,</hi> 54.</p></note> (1) If the Existent is Many,
                    it must be at once infinitely small and infinitely great,— infinitely small,
                    because the parts of which it consists must be indivisible and therefore without
                    magnitude; infinitely great, because, that any part having magnitude may be
                    separate from any other part, the intervention of a third part having magnitude
                    is necessary, and that this third part may be separate from the other two the
                    intervention of other parts having magnitude is necessary, and so on <hi
                    rend="italic">αd infinitum.</hi> (2) In like manner the Many must be numerically
                    both finite and infinite,—numerically finite, because there are as many things
                    as there are, neither more nor less; numerically infinite, because, that any two
                    things may be separate, the intervention of a third thing is necessary, and so
                    on <hi rend="italic">ad infinitum.</hi> (3) If all that is is in space, space
                    itself must be in space, and so on <hi rend="italic">ad infinitum.</hi> (4) If a
                    bushel of com turned out upon the floor makes a noise, each grain and each part
                    of each grain must make a noise likewise; but, in fact, it is not so. (5) Before
                    a body in motion can reach a given point, it must first traverse the half of the
                    distance; before it can traverse the half of the distance, it must first
                    traverse the quarter; and so on <hi rend="italic">ad infinitum.</hi> Hence, that
                    a body may pass from one point to another, it must traverse an infinite number
                    of divisions. But an infinite distance (which Zeno fails to distinguish from a
                    finite distance infinitely divided) cannot be traversed in a finite time.
                    Consequently, the goal can never be reached. (6) If the tortoise has the start
                    of Achilles, Achilles can never come up with the tortoise; for, while Achilles
                    traverses the distance from his starting-point to the starting-point of the
                    tortoise, the tortoise advances a certain distance, and while Achilles traverses
                    this distance the tortoise makes a further advance, and so on <hi rend="italic"
                    >ad infinitum.</hi> Consequently, Achilles may run <hi rend="italic">ad
                    infinitum</hi> without overtaking the tortoise. [This paradox is virtually
                    identical with (5), the only difference being that, whereas in (5) there is one
                    body, in (6) there are two bodies, moving towards a limit. The “infinity” of the
                    premise is an infinity of subdivisions of a distance which is finite; the
                    “infinity” of the conclusion is an infinity of distance. Thus Zeno again
                    confounds a finite distance infinitely divided with an infinite distance. If the
                    tortoise has a start of 1000 feet, Achilles, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n828/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0828-0779"/> on the supposition that his speed is ten times
                    that of the tortoise, must traverse an infinite number of spaces,—1000 feet, 100
                    feet, 10 feet, &amp;c.,—and the tortoise must traverse an infinite number of
                    spaces,—100 feet, 10 feet, 1 foot, &amp;c.,—before they reach the point, distant
                    from their starting-points 1111 <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 9</hi> feet and 111 <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 9</hi> feet respectively, at which the tortoise is overtaken.
                    In a word, 1000, 100, 10, &amp;c., in (6) and ½, ¼, ⅛, &amp;c., in (5) are
                    convergent series, and 1111 <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 9</hi> and 1 are the limits to which they respectively
                    approximate.] (7) So long as anything is in one and the same space, it is at
                    rest. Hence an arrow is at rest during every moment of its flight, and therefore
                    also during the whole of its flight. (8) Two bodies moving with equal speed
                    traverse equal spaces in equal times. But, when two bodies move with equal speed
                    in opposite directions, the one passes the other in half the time in which it
                    passes it when at rest. These propositions appeared to Zeno to be
                    irreconcilable.</p>
                <p>In short, the ordinary belief in plurality and motion seemed to him to involve
                    fatal inconsistencies, whence he inferred that Parmenides was justified in
                    distinguishing the mutable movable Many from the immutable immovable One, which
                    alone is really existent. In other words, Zeno re-affirmed the dogma, “The Ent
                    is, the Nonent is not.” It may seem strange that a reasoner so acute should
                    confound that which is infinitely divisible with that which is infinitely great,
                    as in (1), (2), (5), and (6); that he should identify space and magnitude, as in
                    (3); that he should neglect the imperfection of the organs of sense, as in (4);
                    that he should resolve motion into a senes of states of rest, and on the
                    strength of this analysis deny the reality of motion, as in (7); and that he
                    should ignore the relativity of speed, as in (8). But Zeno’s perplexity was
                    genuine, and his end was positive. He was neither an eristic seeking an
                    argumentative victory, nor a sceptic despairing of truth, but an honest thinker,
                    breaking ground in a new field with indifferent success.</p>
                <p>Great as was the importance of these paradoxes of plurality and motion in
                    stimulating speculation about space and time, their direct influence upon Greek
                    thought was less considerable than that of another paradox,— strangely neglected
                    by historians of philosophy,—the paradox of predication. We learn from Plato <hi
                    rend="italic">(Parmenides,</hi> 127 D) that “the first hypothesis of the first
                    argument” of Zeno’s book above mentioned ran as follows: “If existences are
                    many, they must be both like and unlike [unlike, inasmuch as they are not one
                    and the same, and like, inasmuch as they agree in not being one and the same,
                    Proclus, <hi rend="italic">On the Parmenides,</hi> ii. 143]. But this is
                    impossible; for unlike things cannot be like, nor like things unlike. Therefore
                    existences are not many.” That is to say, not perceiving that the same thing may
                    be at once like and unlike in different relations, Zeno regarded the attribution
                    to the same thing of likeness and unlikeness as a violation of what was
                    afterwards known as the principle of contradiction; and, finding that plurality
                    entailed these attributions, he inferred its unreality. Now, when without
                    qualification he affirmed that the unlike thing cannot be like, nor the like
                    thing unlike, he was on the high road to the doctrine maintained three-quarters
                    of a century later by the Cynics, that no predication which is not identical is
                    legitimate. He was not indeed aware how deeply he had committed himself;
                    otherwise he would have observed that his argument, if valid against the Many of
                    the vulgar, was valid also against the One of Parmenides, with its plurality of
                    attributes, as well as that, in the absence of a theory of predication, it was
                    useless to speculate about knowledge and being. But others were not slow to draw
                    the obvious conclusions; and it may be conjectured that Gorgias’s sceptical
                    development of the Zenonian logic contributed, not less than Protagoras’s
                    sceptical development of the Ionian physics, to the diversion of the
                    intellectual energies of Greece from the pursuit of truth to the pursuit of
                    culture.</p>
                <p>For three-quarters of a century, then, philosophy was at a standstill; and, when
                    in the second decade of the 4th century the pursuit of truth was resumed, it was
                    plain that the difficulty raised by Zeno must be met before the problems which
                    had occupied the earlier thinkers—the problem of knowledge and the problem of
                    being—could be so much as attempted. Accordingly, in the seventh book of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Republic,</hi> where Plato propounds his scheme of Academic
                    education, he directs the attention of studious youth primarily, if not
                    exclusively, to the concurrence of inconsistent attributes; and in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Phaedo,</hi> 102B-103A, taking as an instance the tallness and the
                    shortness simultaneously discoverable in Simmias, he offers his own theory of
                    the immanent idea as the solution of the paradox. Simmias, he says, has in him
                    the ideas of tall and short. Again, when it presently appeared that the theory
                    of the immanent idea was inconsistent with itself, and moreover inapplicable to
                    explain predication except where the subject was a sensible thing, so that
                    reconstruction became necessary, the Zenonian difficulty continued to demand and
                    to receive Plato’s best attention. Thus, in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Parmenides,</hi> with the paradox of likeness and unlikeness for his text, he
                    inquires how far the current theories of being (his own included) are capable of
                    providing, not only for knowledge, but also for predication, and in the
                    concluding sentence he suggests that, as likeness and unlikeness, greatness and
                    smallness, &amp;c., are relations, the initial paradox is no longer paradoxical;
                    while in the <hi rend="italic">Sophist,</hi> Zeno’s doctrine having been shown
                    to be fatal to reason, thought, speech, and utterance, the principle which in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Parmenides</hi> is applied to αύτά <hi rend="italic">καθ'
                    α</hi> ύ <hi rend="italic">τά εΐδη</hi> and to sensible particulars is extended
                    to include the case of <hi rend="italic">εΐδη</hi> which are not αύτά <hi
                    rend="italic">καθ' α</hi> ύ <hi rend="italic">τά.</hi> It would seem then that,
                    not to Antisthenes only, but to Plato also, Zeno’s paradox of predication was a
                    substantial difficulty; and we shall be disposed to give Zeno credit accordingly
                    for his perception of its importance.</p>
                <p>In all probability Zeno did not observe that in his controversial defence of
                    Eleaticism he was interpreting Parmenides’s teaching anew. But so it was. For,
                    while Parmenides had recognized, together with the One, which is, and is the
                    object of knowledge, a Many, which is not, and therefore is not known, but
                    nevertheless becomes, and is the object of opinion, Zeno plainly affirmed that
                    plurality, becoming, and opinion are one and all inconceivable. In a word, the
                    fundamental dogma, “The Ent is, the Nonent is not,” which with Parmenides had
                    been an assertion of the necessity of distinguishing between the Ent, which is,
                    and the Non-ent, which is not, but becomes, was with Zeno a declaration of the
                    Non-ent’s absolute nullity. Thus, just as Empedocles developed Parmenides’s
                    theory of the Many to the neglect of his theory of the One, so Zeno developed
                    the theory of the One to the neglect of the theory of the Many. With the
                    severance of its two members Eleaticism proper, the Eleaticism of Parmenides,
                    ceased to exist.</p>
                <p>The first effect of Zeno’s teaching was to complete the discomfiture of
                    philosophy. For the parodox of predication, which he had used to disprove the
                    existence of plurality, was virtually a denial of all speech and all thought,
                    and thus led to a more comprehensive scepticism than that which sprang from the
                    contemporary theories of sensation. Nevertheless, he left an enduring mark upon
                    Greek speculation, inasmuch as he not only recognized the need of a logic, and
                    grappled, however unsuccessfully, with one of the most obvious of logical
                    problems, but also by the invention of dialectic provided a new and powerful
                    instrument against the time when the One and the Many should be reunited in the
                    philosophy of Plato.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Bibliography.—</hi> F. W. A. Mullach, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Fragmenta Philosophorum Graecorum,</hi> Paris, 1860, i. 266 <hi rend="italic"
                    >sq.</hi>; Zeller, <hi rend="italic">Die Philosophie d. Griechen,</hi> Leipsic,
                    1876, i. 534-552; P. Tannery, <hi rend="italic">Pour l'Histoire de la Science
                    Hellène,</hi> Paris, 1887, pp. 247-261. Ignoring the philosophical aspect of
                    Zeno’s teaching, Tannery supposes him to have maintained in opposition to the
                    Pythagoreans that body is not a sum of points, time not a sum of moments, and
                    motion not a sum of passages from point to point. For histories of philosophy
                    and other works upon Eleaticism, see <hi rend="smallcaps">Parmenides.</hi> (H.
                    JA.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
