<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0874-0825-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ZUCCARO, or Zucchero (9th edition, volume 24, page
                    825)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1109125">Scots</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1050530">Painters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:852215">Chapels</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1137041">Success</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94k2c">Painters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z892g7x">Chapels</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9785q">Success</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46d5pd61">Dog</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n874/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ZUCCARO, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Zucchero</hi></label>,<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>So spelt by
                    Vasari.</p></note> the name of two Italian painters.</p>
                <p>I. <hi rend="smallcaps">Taddeo Zuccaro</hi> (1529-1566), one of the most popular
                    painters of the so-called Roman mannerist school, was the son of an almost
                    unknown painter at St Angelo in Vado, called Ottaviano Zuccaro, where he was
                    born in 1529. While yet a boy Taddeo found his way to Rome; and, though
                    suffering great hardships from poverty and want of friends, he succeeded at an
                    early age in gaining a knowledge of painting and in finding patrons to employ
                    him. His first start in life, while only seventeen years old, was due to a pupil
                    of Correggio, named Daniele da Parma, who engaged him to assist in painting a
                    series of frescos in a chapel at Vitto near Sora, on the borders of the Abruzzi.
                    After that Taddeo returned to Rome in 1548, and began his career as a fresco
                    painter, by execut ing a series of scenes in monochrome from the life of Furius
                    Camillus on the front of the palace of a wealthy Roman named Jacopo Mattei. From
                    that time his success was assured, and for the rest of his short life he was
                    largely employed by the popes Julius III. and Paul IV., by Della Rovere, duke of
                    Urbino, and by other rich patrons of art in Rome and elsewhere. His best frescos
                    were an historical series painted on the walls of a new palace at Caprarola,
                    built for Cardinal Alessandro Farnese, for which Taddeo also designed a great
                    quantity of rich decorations in stucco relief after the style of Giulio Romano
                    and other pupils of Raphael. Nearly all his paintings were in fresco, very large
                    in scale, and often in <hi rend="italic">chiaroscuro</hi> or monochrome; they
                    were more remarkable for rapidity of execution and a certain boldness of style
                    than for any higher qualities. The very great estimation in which Taddeo’s
                    frescos were held is a striking proof of the very rapid degradation of taste
                    which took place during the second half of the 16th century. His work is
                    mannered in style, artificial and pompous in conception, and lacks any close or
                    accurate knowledge of the human form and its movements. The long chapter which
                    Vasari devotes to this painter and his brother Federigo is only one of many
                    examples of the writer’s habit of giving undue prominence to the artists of his
                    own time and school. Taddeo Zuccaro died in Rome in 1566; he is buried in the
                    Pantheon, not far from Raphael.</p>
                <p>Taddeo’s easel pictures are less common than his decorative frescos. A small
                    painting on copper of the Adoration of the Shepherds, formerly in the collection
                    of James II., is now at Hampton Court; it is a work of very small merit. The
                    Caprarola frescos were engraved and published by Prenner, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Illustri Fatti Farηesiaηi Coloriti nel Real Palazzo di Caprarola,</hi> Rome,
                    1748-50.</p>
                <p>II. <hi rend="smallcaps">Federigo Zuccaro</hi> (1543-1609), the younger brother
                    and pupil of Taddeo, was born in 1543. In 1550 he was placed under his brother’s
                    charge in Rome, and during his lifetime worked as his assistant; he completed
                    the Caprarola frescos, which were unfinished when Taddeo died in 1566. In a
                    short time Federigo attained to an eminence far beyond his very limited merits
                    as a painter, and was perhaps the most popular artist of his generation.
                    Probably no other painter has ever produced so many enormous frescos crowded
                    with figures on the most colossal scale, all executed under the unfortunate
                    delusion, common in his time, that grandeur of effect could be attained merely
                    by great size combined with extravagance of attitude and exaggeration of every
                    kind. Federigo’s first work of this sort was the completion of the painting of
                    the dome of the cathedral at Florence, under the patronage of the grand-duke
                    Francesco I.; the work had been begun by the art-historian Vasari, who wrote in
                    the most generous language about his more successful rival. The inner surface of
                    this beautiful cupola was disfigured by Federigo in the most tasteless way.
                    Regardless of the injury to the apparent scale of the interior of the church, he
                    painted about 300 figures, each nearly 50 feet high, sprawling with violent
                    contortions all over the surface. Happily age has so dimmed these pictures that
                    their presence is now almost harmless.</p>
                <p>After this achievement Federigo was recalled to Rome by Gregory XIII. to continue
                    in the Pauline chapel of the Vatican the scheme of decoration which had been
                    begun by Michelangelo during his failing years. A quarrel which arose between
                    the painter and some members of the papal court led to his departure from Italy.
                    He first visited Brussels, and there made a series of cartoons for the
                    tapestry-weavers. Thence, in 1574, Federigo passed over to England, where his
                    fame was already known, so that he at once received a large number of
                    commissions to paint the portraits of various distinguished persons, among them
                    Queen Elizabeth, Mary Queen of Scots,<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Engraved by Vertue.</p></note> Sir Nicholas <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n875/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0875-0826"/> Bacon, Sir Francis Walsingham, Lord High Admiral
                    Howard, and others. A curious full-length portrait of Elizabeth in fancy dress,
                    now at Hampton Court, is attributed to this painter, though very doubtfully.
                    Another picture in the same collection appears to be a <hi rend="italic"
                    >replica</hi> of his painting of the Allegory of Calumny, as suggested by
                    Lucian’s description of a celebrated work by Apelles; it was the satire in this
                    directed against some of his courtier enemies which was the immediate cause of
                    the pope’s displeasure and Federigo’s temporary exile from Rome. His success as
                    a painter of portraits and other works in oil was more reasonable than the
                    admiration expressed for his colossal frescos. A portrait of a Man with Two Dogs
                    in the Pitti Palace at Florence is a work of some real merit, as is also the
                    Dead Christ and Angels in the Borghese Gallery in Rome. After a short exile
                    Federigo was pardoned by the pope and recalled to Rome to finish his work on the
                    vault of the Pauline chapel. In 1585 he was invited by Philip II. of Spain to
                    decorate the new Escorial at a yearly salary of 2000 crowns. He accepted this
                    offer, and worked at the Escorial from January 1586 to the end of 1588, when he
                    returned to Rome. He there founded in 1595, under a charter confirmed by Sixtus
                    V., the Academy of St Luke, of which he was the first president. This is still
                    the chief academy of painters in Italy, and its organization suggested to Sir
                    Joshua Reynolds his scheme for founding the English Royal Academy.</p>
                <p>Federigo, like his contemporary Giorgio Vasari, aimed at being an art critic and
                    historian as well as a practical artist, but with very different success. His
                    chief book, <hi rend="italic">L'Idea de' Pittori, Scultori, ed Architetti</hi>
                    (Turin, 1607), is a senseless mass of the most turgid bombast. Little can be
                    said in praise of his smaller works, consisting of two volumes printed at
                    Bologna in 1608, describing his visit to Parma and a journey through central
                    Italy.</p>
                <p>Federigo was raised to the rank of a <hi rend="italic">Cavaliere</hi> not long
                    before his death, which took place at Ancona in 1609.</p>
                <p>For both Taddeo and Federigo Zuccaro, see Vasari, pt. iii., and Lanzi, <hi
                    rend="italic">Storia Pittorica,</hi> Roman School, epoch iii. (J. H. Μ. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
