<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0821-0772-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ZEBRA (9th edition, volume 24, page 772)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:799938">Africans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:799932">Africanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1084886">Quagga</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1184160">Zebras</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1135518">Stripes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1142046">Tail</term>
                    <term ref="fast:900541">Ear</term>
                    <term ref="fast:900686">Earrings</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4794135j">Tail</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43x83w2q">Zebras</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94f4j">Ear</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g08p">Groups</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4930p034">Hoof</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n821/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ZEBRA</label>. In the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Horse</hi>
                    (vol. xii. p. 175) the general zoological and anatomical characters of the genus
                    <hi rend="italic">Equus,</hi> and its relationship to other animals, were fully
                    described. Among the existing species mention was made of certain forms
                    distinguished from the rest by the peculiar coloration, being marked by
                    conspicuous dark stripes on a lighter ground, and by their exclusively African
                    habitat. These are the <hi rend="smallcaps">Quagga</hi> (see vol. xx. p. 146)
                    and two, if not three, distinct species to which the name zebra is commonly
                    applied. The animal of this group which was first known to Europeans, and was
                    formerly considered the most common, is the True Zebra <hi rend="italic">(Equus
                    zebra,</hi> Linn.), sometimes called the Mountain Zebra. It inhabits the
                    mountainous regions of the Cape Colony; but now, owing to the advances of
                    civilized man into its somewhat restricted range, it has become very scarce, and
                    is even, like its ally the quagga, threatened with extermination at no distant
                    date. The second species, Burchell’s Zebra <hi rend="italic">(Equus
                    burch-elli,</hi> Gray), still roams in large herds over the plains to the north
                    of the Orange river, but in yearly diminishing numbers. Both species are subject
                    to considerable individual variations in marking, but the following are the
                    principal characters by which they can be distinguished.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Equus zebra</hi> is the smaller of the two (about 4 feet high
                    at the shoulders), and has longer ears, a tail more scantily clothed with hair,
                    and a shorter mane. The general ground colour is white, and the stripes are
                    black; the lower part of the face is bright brown. With the exception of the
                    abdomen and the inside of the thighs, the whole of the surface is covered with
                    stripes, the legs having narrow transverse bars reaching quite to the hoofs, and
                    the base of the tail being also barred. The outsides of the ears have a white
                    tip and a broad black mark occupying the greater part of the surface, but are
                    white at the base. Perhaps the most constant and obvious distinction between
                    this species and the next is the arrangement of the stripes on the hinder part
                    of the back, where there are a number of short transverse bands reaching to the
                    median longitudinal dorsal stripe, and unconnected with tho uppermost of the
                    broad stripes which pass obliquely across the haunch from the flanks towards the
                    root of the tail. There is often a median longitudinal stripe under the
                    chest.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Equus burchelli</hi> is a rather larger and more robust animal,
                    with smaller ears, a longer mane, and fuller tail. The general ground colour of
                    the body is pale yellowish brown, the limbs nearly white, the stripes dark brown
                    or black. In the typical form they do not extend on to the limbs or the tail;
                    but there is a great variation in this respect, even in animals of the same
                    herd, some being striped quite down to the hoofs (this form has been named <hi
                    rend="italic">E. chapmanni).</hi></p>
                <p>There is a strongly marked median longitudinal ventral black stripe, to which the
                    lower ends of the transverse side stripes are usually united, but the dorsal
                    stripe (also strongly marked) is completely isolated in its posterior half, and
                    the uppermost of the broad haunch stripes runs nearly parallel to it. A much
                    larger proportion of the ears is white than in the other species. In the middle
                    of the wide intervals between the broad black stripes of the flanks and haunches
                    fainter stripes are generally seen.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">E. grevyi.—</hi> Under this name a zebra has lately been
                    described which was sent in 1882 to Paris from the Galla country, lying to the
                    south of Abyssinia, the most northern locality in which zebras have hitherto
                    been met with. In most of its characters it resembles <hi rend="italic">E.
                    zebra,</hi> but the stripes are finer and more numerous than in the typical
                    examples of that species, and it has a strong, black, and isolated dorsal
                    stripe. Considering the great variations that are met with in the markings of
                    animals of this group, it is doubtful whether the aberrant characters of this
                    individual are sufficient to separate it specifically from the true zebra of
                    South Africa. The question will be cleared up when any complete scientific
                    examination has been made of other specimens, and also of the zebras which are
                    known to exist in the neighbourhood of Lake Nyanza, and which are apparently of
                    the same form. It is curious that the most northern and the most southern of the
                    districts inhabited by zebras both contain identical or closely allied species,
                    while the intermediate territory is occupied by a totally different form, <hi
                    rend="italic">E. burchelli.</hi> It should be mentioned that the last-named
                    animal is generally spoken of as the “quagga” by colonists and hunters. Its
                    flesh is relished by the natives as food, and its hide is very valuable for
                    leather. Although the many attempts that have been made to break in and train
                    zebras for riding or driving have sometimes been rewarded with partial success,
                    the animal has never been domesticated in the true sense of the word. (W. H.
                    F.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
