<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0719-0670-0616-10" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SALAMANCA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:804171">Albas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:987598">Kindness</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1155984">Trees</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1065075">Plains</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1124682">Soils</term>
                    <term ref="fast:878993">Corn</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x63b58d">Kindness</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17ss11">Trees</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mc8rm1n">Plains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pc5x">Soils</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48w3845p">Corn</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.28490931&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=670" org="uniform" part="N"
                sample="complete" type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">SALAMANCA</label>, one of the departments into which
                    the kingdom or province of Leon, in Spain, is divided. It is situated between
                    lat. 40° and 41° 38' north. The river Duero forms its limit to the north and
                    north-west, except where it comes in contact with Portugal. Estremadura is on
                    its southern side, and the province of Segovia to the eastward. It extends over
                    471 square leagues, and its population amounts to 272,982 souls. It generally
                    consists of an open country with extensive plains, and for the most part
                    destitute of trees. The soil is more fruitful than its appearance would suggest.
                    It yields excellent corn, and in moist summers the harvests are abundant; but it
                    is subject to that want which the greater part of Spain feels from the scarcity
                    of water; for although there are several rivers in the department, the influence
                    of their moisture extends but a small distance from their banks. The principal
                    of these rivers is the Duero, into which the Alba, the Tormes, and the Agueda
                    run, whilst the Alagon, taking a southern course, runs into the Tagus. From the
                    nature of the soil through which these rivers pass, they have worn very deep
                    channels, and therefore cannot be used for the purposes of irrigation, without a
                    portion of labour and expenditure which the inhabitants are neither willing nor
                    able to bestow upon them. Though generally the department is destitute of wood,
                    yet in some parts there are extensive forests of evergreen oak trees, without
                    any brushwood under them; and the oaks themselves are without those spreading
                    branches and lofty tops with which our forests exhibit these trees. They are,
                    however, of considerable benefit to the inhabitants by their copious produce of
                    acorns, on which large droves of pigs are fed. The peasants who attend to these
                    animals precede the drove, and proceeding from tree to tree, beat them with a
                    kind of flail, causing the acorns to fall, which the swine most greedily devour.
                    They thus proceed daily from tree to tree till the food they supply is
                    exhausted. The hams of the pigs fattened in this way are most highly esteemed.
                    In this department large flocks of the merino kind of sheep are fed; and many of
                    the stationary kind are bred here, whose wool is of a very inferior degree of
                    fineness. In the early part of the late war the plains of Salamanca were very
                    favourable to the operations of the French armies, who being superior in
                    cavalry, could act on them with the most powerful effect. The cattle of this
                    province are reckoned to be 9363 horses, 6163 mules, 22,002 asses, 107,800 oxen,
                    103,401 goats, and 107,200 pigs. Of fruits it yields 9500 fanegas of chestnuts,
                    502,000 of nuts, and 12,000 of raisins.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Salamanca,</hi> a city of Spain, head of the
                    department of the same name, in the province or kingdom of Leon. It is situated
                    on the river Tormes, over which there is a bridge standing, the piers of which
                    were built by the Romans, and there remain twelve of the arches constructed by
                    them, and thirteen of more recent date, probably erected since the expulsion of
                    the Moors. At a short distance Salamanca has a most imposing effect. Its lofty
                    towers and cupolas, the magnificent Gothic cathcdral, the numerous convents and
                    colleges, and the lengthened bridge which leads to them, present a landscape of
                    the first order.</p>
                <p part="N">The immediate vicinity of the city is fruitful, being on a plain
                    surrounded by mountains of no great elevation, though the Sierra de Guadarrama
                    is visible in the distance, towering above them. It is well supplied from its
                    fields with wine, corn, fruits, and edible vegetables. It grows some flax and
                    oil, but procures a part of the latter from Estremadura and Andalusia.</p>
                <p part="N">The principal fame of Salamanca has arisen from its university, which is
                    one of the largest establishments for education in Spain, if not in Europe. The
                    professors are not generally distinguished for their learning or activity, and
                    principally exercise their faculties in keeping the minds of the pupils down to
                    that level of inquiry and pursuit which is best calculated to secure their
                    attachment to the existing civil and religious institutions of their country.
                    Every inquiry which may have a tendency to lead them from this beaten track is
                    most carefully checked; and even books of science, if composed by foreigners,
                    are viewed with a suspicion that there may be in them some latent heretical
                    tenets. Under such restraints, it is not wonderful that the orthodoxy of the
                    university of Salamanca is unimpeached. The spirit of loyalty was, in fact, so
                    great, that at the com-<pb break="no"
                        facs="ht:chi.28490931&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=671" xml:id="kp-eb0719-0671-0617"
                    /> mencement of the invasion a regiment was formed from the students, which was
                    soon disciplined and effective, but the whole of which was almost destroyed at
                    the fatal battle of Medellin.</p>
                <p part="N">No establishment of the kind in Spain enjoys revenues equal to this
                    university, and none under proper regulations could be more beneficial to this
                    or any country; but science and knowledge are so checked by the tendency towards
                    the preservation of the religion of the state, and the apprehension that
                    knowledge may give a bias contrary to the interests of the church, that a vast
                    deal of time, which might be usefully employed, is devoted, both by pupils and
                    tutors, to a course of studies which, to say the least, neither tends to enlarge
                    the boundaries of knowledge nor to strengthen the minds of the students. Besides
                    the candidates for holy orders, great numbers of the sons of good families from
                    all parts of Spain are sent to this seminary to pass a few years; and hence the
                    number of the members of the university has at some periods amounted to more
                    than four thousand. The regular inhabitants of the city, exclusive of the
                    university, amount to 13,500 persons.</p>
                <p part="N">The cathedral is a fine object of the Gothic kind, though of no earlier
                    erection than the reign of Charles I. of Spain, in the beginning of the
                    sixteenth century; and as at that period Gothic architecture was on the decline
                    in Spain, it will not bear very rigid criticism. It is, however, a magnificent
                    mass of building, and is adorned with paintings from the pencil of Titian,
                    Spagnoletti, and some other great masters. The college formerly belonging to the
                    order of Jesuits is a very large pile of building, now occupied by regular
                    canons. The church, dedicated to St Mark, within it, has some of the best
                    productions of the Spanish painter Mengs, but being a representation of the
                    various parts of the life of Loyola, the founder of the order of Jesuits,
                    whatever merit they may have as paintings, they have now none as historical
                    pieces.</p>
                <p part="N">The principal square of Salamanca, in the centre of the city, is a fine
                    object. The buildings that surround it are handsome and lofty, and supported by
                    piazzas, under which is the principal public walk for the inhabitants. It is
                    situated in latitude 4L 21. N.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
