<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0719-0695-0641-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SANHEDRIM, or Sanhedrin</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1033099">Nasi</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198506">Mark</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1033832">Nationalism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45q4rn8c">Mark</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204236">Israel</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.28490931&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=695" org="uniform" part="N"
                sample="complete" type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">SANHEDRIM, or <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Sanhedrin</hi></label>, from the Greek word Σ <hi rend="italic"
                        >υvεδϑιov</hi>, which signifies a council or assembly of persons sitting
                    together, was the name by which the Jews called the great council of the nation,
                    assembled in an apartment of the temple of Jerusalem to determine the most
                    important affairs of their church and state. This council consisted of seventy
                    senators. The room they met in was a rotunda, half of which was built without
                    the temple, and half within; that is, one semicircle was within the compass of
                    the temple, the other semicircle was built without, for the senators to sit in,
                    it being unlawful for any one to sit down in the temple. The Nasi, or prince of
                    the sanhedrim, sat upon a throne at the end of the hall, having his deputy at
                    his right hand, and his sub-deputy at his left. The other senators were ranged
                    in order on each sidc.</p>
                <p part="N">The rabbin pretend, that the sanhedrim has always subsisted in their
                    nation from the time of Moses down to the destruction of the temple by the
                    Romans. They date the establishment of it from what happened in the wilderness,
                    some time after the people departed from Sinai, in the year of the world 2514.
                    Moses, being discouraged by the continual murmurings of the Israelites,
                    addressed himself to God, and desired to be relieved at least from some part of
                    the burden of the government. ' Then the Lord said to him,</p>
                <p part="N">“Gather unto me seventy men of the elders of Israel, whom thou knowest
                    to be the elders of the people, and officers over them; and bring them unto the
                    tabernacle of the congregation, that they may stand there with thee: And I will
                    come down and talk with thee there; and I w ill take of the spirit which is upon
                    thee, and will put it upon them; and they shall bear the burden of the people
                    with thee, that thou bear it not thyself alone.” The Lord, therefore, poured out
                    his spirit upon these men, who began at that time to prophesy, and have not
                    ceased ever since. The sanhedrim was composed of seventy counsellors, or rather
                    seventy-two, being six out of each tribe; and Moses, as president, made up the
                    number to seventy-three. To prove the uninterrupted succession of the judges of
                    the sanhedrim, there is nothing unattempted by the partisans of this opinion.
                    They find a proof where others cannot so much as perceive any appearance or
                    shadow of it. Grotius may be consulted in many places of his commentaries, and
                    in his first book <hi rend="italic">De jure belli et pacis</hi> (c. iii. art.
                    20), and Selden <hi rend="italic">De Synedriis veterum Hebrttorum;</hi> also
                    Calmet’s Dissertation concern ing the Polity of the ancient Hebrews, printed
                    before his Commentary upon the Book of Numbers.</p>
                <p part="N">As to the personal qualifications of the judges of this bench, their
                    birth was to be untainted. They were often taken from the race of the priests or
                    Levites, or out of the number of the inferior judges, or from the lesser
                    sanhedrim, which consisted only of twenty-three judges. They were to be skilful
                    in the law, as well traditional as written. They were obliged to study magic,
                    divination, fortune-telling, physic, astrology, arithmetic, and languages. The
                    Jews say they were to know to the number of seventy tongues; that is, they were
                    to know all the tongues, for the Hebrews acknowledged but seventy in all, and
                    perhaps this is too great a number. Eunuchs were excluded from the sanhedrim
                    because of their cruelty, usurers, decrepid persons, players at games of chance,
                    such as had any bodily deformities, those that had brought up pigeons to decoy
                    others to their pigeon-houses, and those that made a gain of their fruits in the
                    sabbatical year. Some also exclude the high priest and the king, because of
                    their power; but others will have it that the kings always presided in the
                    sanhedrim whilst there were any kings in Israel. Lastly, it was required that
                    the members of the sanhedrim should be of a mature age, of a handsome person,
                    and of considerable fortune. We speak now according to the notions of the
                    rabbin, without pretending to warrant their opinions.</p>
                <p part="N">The authority of the great sanhedrim was very extensive. This council
                    decidcd such causes as were brought before it by way of appeal from the inferior
                    courts. The king, the high priest, and the prophets, were under its
                    jurisdiction. If the king offended against the law, for example, if he married
                    above eighteen wives, if he kept too many horses, if he hoarded up too much gold
                    and silver, the sanhedrim had him stripped and whipped in their presence. But
                    whipping, they say, among the Hebrews was not at all ignominious; and the king
                    bore this correction by way of penance, and himself made choice of the person
                    that was to exercise this discipline over him. The general affairs of the nation
                    were also brought before the sanhedrim. The right of judging in capital cases
                    belonged to this court, and the sentence could not be pronounced in any other
                    place, but in the hall called <hi rend="italic">Lasehat-haggazith,</hi> or the
                        <hi rend="italic">hall paved with stones,</hi> supposed by some to be the
                        <hi rend="italic">Λι0oστϑωτoς,</hi> or pavement, mentioned in John xix. 13.
                    Hence it came to pass, that the Jews were forced to quit this hall when the
                    power of life and death was taken out of their hands, forty years before the
                    destruction of their temple, and three years before the death of Jesus Christ.
                    In the time of Moses this council was held at the door of the tabernacle of the
                    testimony. As soon as the people were in possession of the land of promise, the
                    sandhedrim followed the tabernacle. It was kept successively at Gilgal, at
                    Shiloh, at Kirjath-jearim, at Nob, at Gibeon in the house of Obed-edom; and,
                    lastly, it was settled at Jerusalem until the Babylonish captivity. During the
                    captivity it was kept up at Babylon. After the return from Babylon, it continued
                    at Jerusalem until the time of the Sicarii or Assassins. Then finding that these
                    profligate wretches, whose number increased every day, sometimes escaped
                    punishmcnt by favour of the president or judges, it was removed to Hanoth, which
                    were certain abodes situated, as the rabbin tell us, upon the mountain of the
                    temple. From thence they came down into the city of Jerusalem, withdrawing
                    themselves by degrees from the temple. Afterwards they removed to Jamia, thence
                    to Jericho, to Uz-zah, to Sepharvaim, to Bethsanim, to Sephoris, last of all to
                    Tiberias, where they continued till the time of their utter extinction. And this
                    is the account the Jews themselves give us of the sanhedrim.</p>
                <p part="N">But the learned do not agree with them in all this. Father Petau fixes
                    the beginning of the sanhedrim not till Gabinius was governor of Judaea, who,
                    according to Josephus, erect<pb break="no"
                        facs="ht:chi.28490931&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=696" xml:id="kp-eb0719-0696-0642"
                    />ed tribunals in the five principal cities of Judaea; at Jerusalem, at Gadara,
                    at Amathus, at Jericho, and at Sephora or Sephoris, a city of Galilee. Grotius
                    places the origin of , the sanhedrim under Moses, as the rabbin do; but he makes
                    it terminate at the beginning of Herod’s reign. Mr Basnage at first thought that
                    the sanhedrim began under Gabinius; but afterwards he places it under Judas
                    Maccabaeus, or under his brother Jonathan. We see, indeed, under Jonathan
                    Maccabaeus, in the year 3860, that the senate along with the high priest sent an
                    embassy to the Romans. The rabbin say, that Alexander Jannaeus, king of the
                    Jews, of the race of the Asmonaeans, appeared before the sanhedrim, and claimed
                    a right of sitting there, whether the senators would or not. Josephus informs
                    us, that when Herod was but yet governor of Galilee, he was summoned before the
                    senate, where he appeared. It must be therefore acknowledged that the sanhedrim
                    was in being before the reign of Herod. It was in being afterwards, as we find
                    from the Gospel and from the Acts. Jesus Christ in St Matthew (v. 22)
                    distinguishes two tribunals. “Whosoever is angry with his brother without a
                    cause shall be in danger of the judgment this, they say, is the tribunal of the
                    twenty-three judges. “And whosoever shall say to his brother Raca, shall be in
                    danger of the council ;” that is, of the great sanhedrim, which had the right of
                    life and death, at least generally, and before this right was taken away by the
                    Romans. Some think that the jurisdiction of the council of twenty-three extended
                    to life and death also; but it is certain that the sanhedrim was superior to
                    this council.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p part="N"
                            >See also Mark, xiii. 9, xiv. 55, xv. 1; Luke, xxii. 52, 66; John, xi.
                            47; Acts, iv. 15, v. 21; where mention is made of the synedrion or
                            sanhedrim.</p></note></p>
                <p part="N">From all this it may be concluded, that the origin of the sanhedrim is
                    involved in uncertainty; for the council of the seventy elders established by
                    Moses was not what the Hebrews understand by the name of sanhedrim. Besides, we
                    cannot perceive that this establishment subsisted either under Joshua, the
                    judges, or the kings. We find nothing of it after the captivity till the time of
                    Jonathan Maccabaeus. The tribunals erected by Gabinius were very different from
                    the sanhedrim, which was the supreme court of judicature, and fixed at
                    Jerusalem, whereas Gabinins established five at five different cities. Lastly,
                    it is certain that this senate was in being in the time of Jesus Christ; but the
                    Jews themselves inform us that they had then no longer the power of life and
                    death (John, xviii. 31).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
