<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0719-0718-0662-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SAW</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r47q">Cuttings</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mg7fz12">Cutting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93d6n">Bar</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44t6f430">Timber</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1179191">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="fast:885683">Cutting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150988">Timber</term>
                    <term ref="fast:979089">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1174522">Wheels</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1057765">Perdix</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:817721">Arts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204556">Norway</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204537">Sweden</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208963">Turkey</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.28490931&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=718" org="uniform" part="N"
                sample="complete" type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">SAW</label>, an instrument which serves to cut into
                    pieces several solid matters, as wood, stone, ivory, and the like.</p>
                <p part="N">The best saws are of tempered steel ground bright and smooth; those of
                    iron are only hammer-hardened. Hence the first, besides their being stiffer, are
                    likewise found smoother than the last. They are known to be well hammered by the
                    stiff bending of the blade; and to be well and evenly ground, by their bending
                    equally in a bow.</p>
                <p part="N">The lapidaries, too, have their saw, as well as the workmen in mosaic;
                    but of all mechanics, none have so many saws as the joiners, the chief of which
                    are the following. The pit-saw, which is a large two-handed saw, employed for
                    sawing timber in pits, and chiefly used by the sawers. The whip-saw, which has
                    likewise two handles, used in sawing such large pieces as the hand-saw will not
                    easily reach. The hand-saw is made to be used by an individual, of which there
                    are different kinds, as the frame-saw, which is furnished with cheeks. By the
                    twisted cords which pass from the upper parts of these cheeks, and the tongue in
                    the middle of them, the upper ends are drawn close together, and the lower set
                    farther asunder. The tenon-saw, which being very thin, has a back to keep it
                    from bending. The compass-saw, which is very small, and its teeth usually not
                    set. Its use is to cut a round, or any other compass-kerf, on which account the
                    edge is made broad, and the back thin, that it may have a compass to turn
                    in.</p>
                <p part="N">At an early period, the trunks of trees were split with wedges into as
                    many and as thin pieces as possible; and if it were necessary to have them still
                    thinner, they were hewn on both sides to the proper size. This simple and
                    wasteful manner of making boards has been still continued in some places to the
                    present day. Peter the Great of Russia endeavoured to put a stop to it, by
                    forbidding hewn dales to be transported on the river Neva. The saw, however,
                    though so convenient and beneficial, has not been able to banish entirely the
                    practice of splitting timber used in building, or in making furniture and
                    utensils; and indeed it must be allowed that this method is attended with
                    peculiar advantages which that of sawing can never possess. The wood-splitters
                    perform their work more expeditiously than sawers, and split timber is much
                    stronger than that which has been sawn: for the fissure follows the grain of the
                    wood, and leaves it whole; whereas the saw, which proceeds in the line chalked
                    out for it, divides the fibres, and by these means lessens its cohesion and
                    solidity. Split timber, indeed, turns out often crooked and warped; but for many
                    purposes to which it is applied this is not injurious, and these faults may
                    sometimes be amended. As the fibres, however, retain their natural length and
                    direction, thin<pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.28490931&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=719"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0719-0719-0663"/> boards particularly can be bent much better.
                    This is a great advantage in making pipe-staves, or sieve-frames, which require
                    still more art, and in forming various implements of a similar kind.</p>
                <p part="N">Our common saw, which requires only to be guided by the hand, however
                    simple it may be, was not known to the inhabitants of America when they were
                    subdued by the Europeans. The inventor of this instrument has been inserted in
                    their mythology by the Greeks, with a place, in which, amongst their gods, they
                    honoured the greatest benefactors of the earliest ages. By some he is called
                    Talus, and by others Perdix. None except Pliny make Daedalus the inventor; but
                    Hardouin, in the passage where this occurs, reads Talus for Daedalus. Talus is
                    the name of the inventor according to Diodorus Siculus, Apollodorus, and others.
                    He was the son of Daedalus’s sister, and was by his mother placed under the
                    tuition of her brother, to be instructed in his art. Having found the jaw-bone
                    of a snake, he employed it to cut through a small piece of wood, and by these
                    means was induced to fabricate a similar instrument of iron, that is, to make a
                    saw. This invention, by which labour is greatly facilitated, excited the envy of
                    his master, and prompted him to put Talus privately to death. Being asked, when
                    burying the body, what he was depositing in the earth, he replied, a serpent.
                    This ambiguous answer discovered the murder; and thus a snake was the cause of
                    the invention, of the murder, and of its being brought to light. By others the
                    inventor is called Perdix, who is supposed to have been the son of a sister of
                    Daedalus. Perdix did not employ the jaw-bone of a snake for a saw', but the
                    back-bone of a fish, as is mentioned by Ovid.</p>
                <p part="N">The saws of the Grecian carpenters had the same form, and wore made with
                    equal ingenuity as the same instruments at present. This appears from a painting
                    preserved among the antiquities of Herculanum. Two genii are represented at the
                    end of a bench consisting of a long table resting on two four-footed stools, and
                    the piece of wood to be sawn through is secured by cramps. The saw with which
                    the genii arc at work bears a striking resemblance to our frame-saw'. It
                    consists of a square frame, having a blade in the middle, the teeth of which are
                    perpendicular to the plane of the frame. The piece of wood to be sawn extends
                    beyond the end of the bench, and one of the workmen appears standing, and the
                    other sitting on the ground. The arms in which the blade is fastened have the
                    same form as that which is given to them at present. In the bench are seen
                    holes, in which the cramps holding the timber are stuck. They are shaped like
                    the figure 7; and the ends of them reach below the boards which form the top of
                    it.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Saw</hi><hi rend="italic">-Mills.</hi> The
                    most beneficial improvement of the operation of sawing was the invention of
                    saw-mills, which are driven either by water or by wind. Mills of the first kind
                    were erected in Germany, on the small river Ruer, as early as the fourth
                    century. The art of cutting marble with a saw is very ancient. According to
                    Pliny, it was invented in Caria. Stones of the soap-rock kind, which are softer
                    than marble, were sawn at that period; but it appears that the harder kinds of
                    stone were also then sawn; for we are informed of the discovery of a building
                    which was encrusted with cut agate, carnelian, lapis lazuli, and amethysts.
                    There is, however, no account in any of the Greek or Roman writers of a mill for
                    sawing wood; and as modern authors speak of saw-mills as new and uncommon, it
                    appears that the oldest construction of them has been forgotten, or that some
                    interesting improvement has made them appear entirely new.</p>
                <p part="N">Becher says that saw-mills were invented in the seventeenth century,
                    which is a mistake; for when the Infant Henry sent people to settle in the
                    island of Madeira, discovered in 1420, he gave orders for saw-mills to be
                    erected, for the purpose of sawing into deals the various species of excellent
                    timber with which the island abounded, and which were afterwards exported to
                    Portugal. There was a sawmill in the city of Breslau about the year 1427,
                    producing a yearly rent of three merks; and in 1490, the magistrates of Erfurt
                    purchased a forest, in which they erected a sawmill, besides renting another in
                    the neighbourhood. The first saw-mill in Norway was erected about the year 1530.
                    In the year 1552 there was a saw-mill erected at Joachimethal, the property of a
                    mathematician called Jacob Geusen. In 1555, the Bishop of Ely, ambassador from
                    Queen Mary of England to the court of Rome, having seen a saw-mill in the
                    vicinity of Lyons, the writer of his travels gave a particular description of
                    it. The first saw-mill was erecte&lt;l in Holland at Saardam in 1596, the
                    invention of which is ascribed to Cornelius Cornelissen. The first mill of this
                    kind in Sweden was erected in the year 1653.</p>
                <p part="N">In England, saw-mills had at first a similar effect with printing in
                    Turkey, the ribbon-loom in the dominions of the church, and the crane at
                    Strasburg. When attempts were made to introduce them, they were violently
                    opposed, because it was apprehendcd that the sawers would thus be deprived of
                    the means of procuring subsistence. An opulent merchant in 1767 or 1768, by
                    desire of the Society of Arts, caused a saw-mill to be erected at Limehouse,
                    driven by wind; but it was demolished by the mob, and the damage was sustained
                    by the nation, while some of the rioters were punished. This, however, was not
                    the only mill of the kind then in Great Britain; for at Leith there was one
                    driven by wind some years before. Saw-mills are very common in America, where
                    the moving power is generally water. Some have been constructed on a very
                    extensive plan.</p>
                <p part="N">The mechanism of a sawing-mill may be reduced to three principal things.
                    The first is, that the saw is drawn up and down as long as is necessary, by a
                    motion communicated to the wheel by water. The second is, that the piece of
                    timber to be cut into boards is advanced by an uniform motion to receive the
                    strokes of the saw; for here the wood is to meet the saw, and not the saw to
                    follow the wood, therefore the motion of the wood and that of the saw ought
                    immediately to depend the one on the other. The third is, that where the saw has
                    cut through the whole length of the piece, the whole machine stops of itself,
                    and remains immoveable; lest having no obstacle to surmount, the moving power
                    should turn the wheel with too great velocity, and break some part of the
                    machine.</p>
                <p part="N">When a completely cylindrical pillar is to be cut out of one block of
                    stone, the first thing will be to ascertain in the block the position of the
                    axis of the cylinder, then lay the block so that such axis shall be parallel to
                    the horizon, and let a cylindrical hole of from one to two inches diameter be
                    bored entirely through it. Let an iron bar, whose diameter is rather less than
                    that of this tube, be put through it, having just room to slide freely to and
                    fro as occasion may require. Each end of this bar should terminate in a screw,
                    on which a nut and frame may be fastened. The nut-frame should carry three flat
                    pieces of wood or iron, each having a slit running along its middle from nearly
                    one end to the other, and a screw and handle must be adapted to each slit. By
                    these means the frame-work at each end of the bar may readily be so adjusted as
                    to form equal isosceles or equilateral triangles; the iron-bar will connect two
                    corresponding angles of these triangles, the saw to be used two other
                    corresponding angles, and another bar of iron or of wood the two remaining
                    angles, to give sufficient strength to the whole frame. By this construction the
                    workmen are enabled to place the saw at any proposed distance from the hole
                    drilled through the middle of the block; and then, by giving the alternating
                    motion to the saw-frame, the cylinder may at length be cut from the block, as
                    required.</p>
                <p part="N">If it were proposed to saw a conic frustum from such a block, then let
                    two frames of wood or iron be fixed to those parallel ends of the block which
                    are intended to coincide<pb break="no"
                        facs="ht:chi.28490931&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=720" xml:id="kp-eb0719-0720-0664"
                    /> with the bases of the frustum, circular grooves being previously cut in these
                    frames to correspond with the circumferences of the two ends of the proposed
                    frustum; the saw being worked in these grooves will manifestly cut the conic
                    surface from the block. This, we believe, is the contrivance of Sir George
                    Wright.</p>
                <p part="N">The best method of drilling the hole through the middle of the proposed
                    cylinder seems to be this. On a carriage running upon four low wheels let two
                    vertical pieces, each having a hole just large enough to admit the borer to play
                    freely, be fixed two or three feet asunder, and so contrived that the pieces and
                    holes to receive the borer may, by screws, be raised or lowered at pleasure,
                    while the borer is prevented from sliding to and fro by shoulders upon its bar,
                    which are larger than the holes in the vertical pieces, and which, as the borer
                    revolves, press against those pieces; let a part of the boring bar between the
                    two vertical pieces be square, and a grooved wheel with a square hole of a
                    suitable size be placed upon this part of the bar; then the rotatory motion may
                    be given to the bar by an endless band which shall pass over this grooved wheel
                    and a wheel of a much larger diameter in the same plane, the latter wheel being
                    turned by a winch-handle in the usual way.</p>
                <p part="N">Circular saws, acting by a rotatory motion, have been long known in
                    Holland, where they are used for cutting wood used in veneering. They were
                    introduced into this country, we believe, by General Bentham, and are now used
                    in the dock-yard at Portsmouth, and in a few other places; but they are not as
                    yet so generally adopted as might be wished, considering how well they are
                    calculated to abridge labour, and to accomplish with expedition and accuracy
                    what is very tedious and irksome to perform in the usual way. Circular saws may
                    be made to turn either in horizontal, vertical, or inclined planes, and the
                    timber to be cut may be laid upon a plane inclined in any direction; so that it
                    may be sawn by lines making any angle whatever, or at any proposed distance from
                    each other. When the saw is fixed at a certain angle, and at a certain distance
                    from the edge of the frame, all the pieces will be cut of∙the same size, without
                    marking upon them by a chalked line, merely by causing them to be moved along,
                    and keeping one side in contact with the side of the frame; for then, as they
                    are brought one by one to touch the saw revolving on its axle, and are pressed
                    upon it, they are soon cut through.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
