<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0719-0681-0627-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SALVADOR, St, or Βahia</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206830">Brazil</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s756m31">Saints</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86q1x">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zn7v">Sugar</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43x83n13">Sugars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q52fm3g">Ports</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:838162">Brazilians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:829042">Bays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1103658">Saints</term>
                    <term ref="fast:880858">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1137272">Sugar</term>
                    <term ref="fast:868919">Comarcas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:827746">Barrels</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.28490931&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=681" org="uniform" part="N"
                sample="complete" type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">SALVADOR, <hi rend="smallcaps">St</hi>, or <hi
                            rend="smallcaps">Βahia</hi></label>, a large and important province of
                    Brazil, extending from the Belmonte, in latitude 15° 25' south, to the Rio Real,
                    which divides it from Seregipe d’el Rey, in latitude 11° 38' south. The river St
                    Francisco separates it from Pernambuco on the west and north-west, while on the
                    south-west it touches on Minas Geraes. It is divided into three comarcas, Bahia,
                    Ilheos, and Jacobina; the former two comprising the coast, and the latter the
                    western part of the province. The eastern is divided from the western portion by
                    a chain of mountains of considcrable elevation, from the eastern side of which
                    proceed the numerous streams flowing into the prolific district of Reconcave, or
                    forming the rivers of Ilheos. A considerable portion of Jacobina is occupied
                    with cattle-plains, which are not susceptible of cultivation. It was formerly
                    rich in gold, and, according to Cazal, it still produces that metal, and also
                    silver, copper, iron, saltpetre, and crystals. This comarca comprehends the
                    country on which the Rio St Francisco enters when it leaves the province in
                    which it originates. The inhabitants are scattered everywhere over its surface,
                    and occupy themselves chiefly in breeding cattle. “The regular winter or wet
                    season,” says Southey, “extends only some thirty leagues from the coast; and
                    what rain falls in the interior comes only in thunder-showers, which are of
                    course irregular, in no part frequent, and occur seldomer in the northern part
                    of the province than in the south. After rain, the ground is presently covered
                    with rich verdure, and the cattle fatten; but when drought succeeds to this
                    season of abundance, they are reduced to browse upon such shrubs as resist the
                    burning sun. The streams fail, and if the tanks which the thunder-showers had
                    filled are also dried, a dreadful mortality ensues. Because of the frequency of
                    this evil, the province cannot depend upon its own pastures, but looks to Goyaz
                    and Piauhy for a regular supply.” Jacobina, the capital of the comarca, is still
                    a town of some<pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.28490931&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=682"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0719-0682-0628"/> importance, although the mines have ceased to
                    be productive, and its smelting-house is broken up. It is situated near the left
                    bank of the southern branch of the Ilapicuru, three miles below a lake which
                    communicates with the river. Its inhabitants cultivate wheat, which is not found
                    farther north, and the fruits as well as the pulse and grain of Portugal
                    flourish in this elevated district. They export in particular large quantities
                    of quince marmalade. There are some other towns in the comarca, but few of any
                    material importance. Rio de Contas, a town situated about a hundred and thirty
                    miles south of Jacobina, lies on the high road from Bahia to Goyaz. It owed its
                    origin to its gold mines, which were discovered in 1718. But these have failed,
                    and the inhabitants have betaken themselves to the more advantageous occupation
                    of agriculture. Fifty miles west-south-west of Contas is Villa Nova do Principe,
                    formerly called Caytete, the inhabitants of which are employed in raising cotton
                    and breeding cattle.</p>
                <p part="N">The comarca of the Ilheos begins at Belmonte, and extends northward to
                    the river Jiquirica. The Rio Pardo, which, according to Prince Maximilian, is
                    the limit between the province of Porto Seguro and this comarca, rises in Serro
                    Frio, and falls into the sea by three branches.</p>
                <p part="N">The Bay of Bahia, or All-Saints, has been pronounced one of the finest
                    harbours in the world. The entrance, which is nearly three leagues wide, is from
                    the south, having the continent on the right hand, and the long island of
                    Itaparica on the left. According to Mr Henderson, this island forms two
                    entrances, the eastern or proper entrance being eight miles in width, and the
                    western or false bar being less than two miles across. The bay is twelve leagues
                    in diameter, and thirty-six leagues in circumference, without including the
                    islands or remote parts. The anchorage is secure. Vessels are here sheltered
                    from every wind, and there is accommodation for the united navies of the world.
                    This little Mediterranean is spotted with above a hundred islands, many of which
                    are cultivated and inhabited. The city of St Salvador, better known by the name
                    of Bahia, is, with the exception of Rio, the largest and most flourishing city
                    in Brazil. In ecclesiastical dignity it claims the precedency, being an
                    archiepiscopal see. It has also a higher antiquity, and was long the capital of
                    the empire. Notwithstanding the removal of the seat of government to Rio, the
                    natural advantages of Bahia will enable it, under all changes, to preserve its
                    rank as the second city in Brazil. It is situated on the right side of the bay,
                    where the land, at a small distance from the shore, rises steeply to a high
                    ridgy hill, on the summit of which the city is chiefly erected. From the
                    inequality of the ground, and the plantations interspersed, it occupies a
                    considerable space, its length from north to south being four miles. The
                    buildings are chiefly of the seventeenth century, the churches being of course
                    the most conspicuous edifices. The town has a magnificent appearance from the
                    water, but when entered, its interior is found not to correspond with its
                    imposing aspect at a distance. In the lower town, where the port is situated,
                    the houses are high, and the streets confined and narrow, wretchedly paved, and
                    kept in a very filthy state. The upper town, from its height, and from the slope
                    of the streets, is much cleaner than the port, and although far from being well
                    built, has a number of handsome private houses and public buildings. Here are
                    the cathedral, the archiepiscopal palace, the governor’s palace, the ex-Jesuits’
                    church (built entirely of marble brought from Europe, but now degraded into
                    barracks for soldiers), the misericordia with its hospital, and various other
                    edifices. The cathedral, and several other churches, are handsome, and richly
                    ornamented. The city is protected by a number of forts and batteries, some of
                    which are garrisoned. Society is not considered so polished here as at Rio.
                    Gaming, the resource of vacant minds, is eagerly followed by both sexes.</p>
                <p part="N">Intellectual pursuits seem to be little cultivated; and a large library,
                    containing some valuable manuscripts respecting the interior of America, is
                    allowed to remain in a neglected state. Bahia contains thirty-six churches, a
                    number of monasteries, has a university, a number of schools of instruction, a
                    foundling hospital, the library already mentioned, a few printing-presses, and
                    is the centre of a very considerable trade. There are about a hundred and twenty
                    wholesale merchants, and amongst other manufactures carried on are those of
                    cotton, glass, rum, and sugar. There are companies engaged in the whale-fishery,
                    and in ship-building.</p>
                <p part="N">The best idea of the great importance of the trade of Bahia will be
                    formed from the following statements of the exports and imports. A statement of
                    the quantities of Brazilian produce exported from the port of Salvador or Bahia
                    in the year ending the 1st of October 1835: Sugar, 47,428 cases of thirteen
                    hundredweights, 474 half cases, and 3071 barrels; cotton, 40,320 bags of about
                    160 pounds; 148,752 hides; coffee, 12,601 sacks and 131 barrels; tobacco, 54,419
                    bales, 172 sacks, and 5739 barrels; rum, 6129 pipes; molasses, 315 pipes;
                    besides many other smaller articles. The number of vessels which cleared from
                    the port was 244.</p>
                <p part="N">A statement of the value of merchandise imported into the port of Bahia
                    or Salvador in the year ending the 1st of July 1835: Cotton manufactures to the
                    value of L.664,104, of which Great Britain furnished L.573,097; woollen goods to
                    the value of L.67,517, of which Great Britain supplied L.64,740 worth; linen
                    manufactures to the value of L.77,863, Great Britain supplying L.57,497 worth;
                    silk L.42,086, of which Great Britain supplied L.5657 worth, and France
                    L.25,053; and numerous other articles, of which a large proportion is furnished
                    by Great Britain; the total value of the imports being L.1,412,521.</p>
                <p part="N">The population of this city is estimated at 150,000. The environs of
                    Bahia arc very beautiful; and being constantly refreshed by land and sea
                    breezes, the climate is deemed very healthy. The Reconcave, as the country which
                    extends round the whole sweep of this beautiful bay is denominated, is one of
                    the richest and most populous parts of Brazil. It varies in breadth from twelve
                    to forty miles. Upon the rivers which intersect it, and fall into the bay, are
                    situated many flourishing towns, which carry on a considerable trade with the
                    capital. One of the largest is Cachoeira, situated on the river Paraguassu,
                    which divides it into two parts. Near this town was found a mass of native
                    copper, weighing a ton and a half. Fifteen miles below Cachoeira, on the same
                    river, is Maragogype, also a considerable town. The other chief towns are St
                    Amaro, on the right bank of the Serigy or Serzipe, twelve miles from its mouth,
                    and forty north-west of Bahia; and Jaguaripe, on the right bank of the river of
                    the same name, seven miles from its mouth, the inhabitants of which are chiefly
                    manufacturers of earthenware. On the island of Itaparica, which is twenty-three
                    miles in length from north to south, and ten in breadth, is a considerable town,
                    with 16,000 inhabitants, who engage in the whale-fishery. The population of the
                    whole province of St Salvador is estimated at 600,000. <hi rend="smallcaps">( r.
                        r. r.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
