<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> <?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0637-0599-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86q1x">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93f63">Chains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1202705">Gambia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="fast:880858">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="fast:851789">Chains</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028427">Mouth</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=637" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VERD, CAPE</label>, a promontory on the west coast of Africa,
                    forty miles north-west of the mouth of the river Gambia, in 14° 45' north lat,
                    and 14° 40' west long. The Cape Verd islands are situate about 400 miles west of
                    the Cape; they consist of ten islands beside islets and rocks, and belong to
                    Portugal. The principal is San Jago, the barren and melancholy appearance of
                    which is in unison with the wretchedness of the inhabitants. The island of Mayo
                    produces cattle and cotton; the island of Fuego (or Fire), so called from its
                    active volcano, is abundant in fruits. Brava, or St. John’s, produces excellent
                    wine and saltpetre. These four islands form a chain, running from east to west.
                    The island Boa-Vista, which is fertile in cotton and indigo, forms, with the
                    island Sel, or Do Sal, a line north and south. The four remaining islands form
                    part of a chain in the direction of south-east to north-west, and succeed each
                    other in the following order: St. Nicholas, one of the largest and best governed
                    of the archipelago; Santa Lucia, high and wooded, with only brackish water; San
                    Vincente, wooded and abounding in tortoises; and San Antonia, the mountains of
                    which are said to equal the peak of Teneriffe in height. All these islands are
                    subject to destructive droughts; but their natural produce might render them of
                    considerable value under an intelligent government. Their population is reckoned
                    at about 42,000.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
