<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> <?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0700-0660-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43j3985w">Danes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zn7v">Sugar</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43x83n13">Sugars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g68c">Virginal</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1137272">Sugar</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1137549">Sugars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1747280">Virgins</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1167649">Virginity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:887617">Danes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204558">Denmark</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=700" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VIRGIN ISLANDS</label>, situate between 17° 40', and 80° 40'
                    N. lat., and between 64° 30' W. long. Sir Francis Drake is said to have called
                    them the Virgin islands in honour of Queen Elizabeth; but this is a mistake, for
                    they were called Las Virgines by Columbus, in honour of the eleven thousand
                    virgins in the Romish ritual. The principal of these is Santa Cruz, a Danish
                    possession about twenty-one miles long, and about five broad, which has an area
                    of more than 100 square miles. It is one of the best cultivated islands in the
                    West Indies. Sugar is its staple commodity. The population of the island is
                    reckoned at 32,000. St Thomas, another Danish island, about twelve miles long,
                    with an area of about fifty square miles, possesses a safe and capacious
                    harbour, and carries on a considerable trade. The population amounts to about
                    8000. St John’s is the only other possession of Denmark in this group of any
                    importance. Its population is about 2500.</p>
                <p>The principal British islands are Tortola, Virgingorda, and Anegada. The
                    exportable products chiefly consist of sugar and molasses. Tortola is about
                    twelve miles long and four broad. Anegada and Virgingorda are each about tcn
                    miles long. Besides a number of very small islands, Culebra or Passage island,
                    and Vieque or Crab island, belong to Britain. The latter is sixteen miles long
                    and four broad, but is uninhabited. The British, Danes, and Spaniards have the
                    right of cutting wood in it, and fishing on its coasts. The climate is more
                    healthy than in the average of the West India islands. Excepting Tortola, the
                    other islands contain a very small number of inhabitants.</p>
                <p>The population of these three islands in 1835, consisted of</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell> Free persons, white and coloured Apprentices, </cell>
                        <cell> Males. </cell>
                        <cell> Females. </cell>
                        <cell> Total. </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell> 1678 </cell>
                        <cell> 1902 </cell>
                        <cell> 3580 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell> 1944 </cell>
                        <cell> 2207 </cell>
                        <cell> 4151 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell> 3622 </cell>
                        <cell> 4109 </cell>
                        <cell> 7731 </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
