<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> <?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0701-0661-08" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1057512">Peppers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1174325">Wheat</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1175881">Wine</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k64b101">Pepper</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=701" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VIZAGAPATAM</label>, a considerable town and district of
                    Hindustan, in the province of the Northern Circars. The district, principally
                    situated between the 17th and 19th degrees of north latitude, is mountainous,
                    and many of the hills are wild and destitute of vegetation. The principal
                    trading towns of the district are, Vizagapatam and Bimlipatam. A considerable
                    trade is carried on with Calcutta, Ceylon, the Maldavie islands, &amp;c., from
                    which are imported pepper, wheat, wine, cocoa nuts, coir, and cowries. The
                    exports consist of wax, salt, rice, and indigo. A considerable quantity of cloth
                    is manufactured in the adjacent country. Vizagapatam is the capital of the
                    district. A river from the north, and turning short eastward to the sea, forms
                    an <pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=702"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0721-0702-0662"/>arm of land one mile and a half in length, and
                    600 yards in breadth, nearly in the middle of which the town and fort are
                    situated. The town is inconsiderable, the Europeans generally residing in
                    Watloor, a village to the south of the harbour. At Semachellum, near to this
                    village, is a Hindu temple of great sanctity. It was here that the British had a
                    factory in 1689, when during a rupture with Auren-zebe, our countrymen and all
                    their warehouses were seized, and all the residents put to death. In 1757 it was
                    taken by Μ. Bussy. It was acquired by the British in 1765, with all the rest of
                    the province, under the administration of Lord Clive; and it now forms one of
                    the five districts into which the Northern Circars were divided in 1803, when
                    the Bengal residence and judicial system were introduced. Travelling distance
                    from Madras 483 miles; from Nagpoor 394; from Hydrabad 355, and from Calcutta
                    557 miles. Long. 83. 28. E. Lat. 17. 42. N.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
