<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> <?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0642-0604-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1007944">Mansions</term>
                    <term ref="fast:880260">Corrections</term>
                    <term ref="fast:937895">Gardens</term>
                    <term ref="fast:937852">Gardening</term>
                    <term ref="fast:937845">Gardeners</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bh84">Gardens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xs5jg6k">Gardening</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=642" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VERSAILLES</label>, a city of France, the capital of an
                    arrondissement of the same name, in the department of the Seine and Oise, which
                    extends over 331 square miles, is divided into eight cantons, and those into 114
                    communes, containing, in 1836, 133,551 inhabitants. This city is extensive, is
                    divided into the new and the old town, is splendidly built, and, by the
                    magnificence of its appearance, must have been very appropriate for the
                    circumstances of France, when its state of society was different from what now
                    exists; when there were nobles to occupy the splendid mansions, and more than
                    80,000 inhabitants of all classes. The palace was built by Louis XIV, between
                    the years 1673 and 1680. It is a most magnificent and extensive pile of
                    building, decorated with the remains of that correct and chaste style of
                    architecture which was the prevailing taste of the time in which it was erected.
                    It is however in a dilapidated condition, and its noble apartments destitute of
                    furniture, and almost of occupants. The gardens are in tolerable<pb break="no"
                        facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=643" xml:id="kp-eb0721-0643-0605"
                    /> preservation, and especially the water-works, the exhibition of which on
                    Sundays and holidays, still draws to Versailles a large proportion of the more
                    vulgar of the Parisians. In 1836, the inhabitants of Versailles amounted to
                    29,209, among whom are many English and other foreign families, drawn to it by
                    the cheapness with which the ornamental parts of education can be obtained. Some
                    manufactures have been introduced, especially for fire-arms of the most
                    luxurious kind; besides which many watches are made, some cotton goods, and many
                    smaller articles. It is the place where, in 1783, was signed the peace with
                    England, by which the independence of America was established. Lat. 48. 48. 21.
                    Long. 2. 1. 17. E.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
