<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> <?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0703-0663-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028427">Mouth</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198506">Mark</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f39x">Mouth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45q4rn8c">Mark</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=703" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VOLGA</label>, the largest river in Europe, derives its
                    origin from two small lakes in the forest of Volkonski about 80 miles from Tver,
                    a town in Russia. It is navigable a few miles above that town. This noble river
                    waters some of the finest provinces in the Russian empire, and at last falls
                    into the Caspian sea, by several mouths, below Astracan. The Volga is subject to
                    annual inundations. In the year 1774, the inundations exceeded the lowest water
                    mark by nearly 40 feet, since which period they have been rather on the decline;
                    for in 1775, they rose only to 39 feet 2 inches above that mark; in 1782, they
                    rose to 26 feet; in 1785, to 25 feet 2 inches; and in the year 1791, their
                    r&gt;eight was the same. Pallas is of opinion that this phenomenon may have
                    originated from the diminished quantity of snow and rain which had fallen in the
                    higher countries; from the greater evaporation of the Caspian sea, and the
                    gradual extension of the different mouths of the river, or perhaps from the
                    joint operation of all these causes.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
