<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0025-0016-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">USHER, James (9th edition, volume 24, page 16)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1163204">Ushers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888134">Daughters</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g8x">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bn4t">Religions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4610vs0f">Archbishops</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n25/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">USHER, <hi rend="smallcaps">James</hi></label> (1580-1656),
                    prelate and scholar, was born in the parish of St Nicholas, Dublin, on 4th
                    January 1580. He was the eldest son of Arnold Usher, one of the six clerks in
                    Chancery, and descended from the house of Nevill, one of whose scions,
                    accompanying John Plantagenet to Ireland in the capacity of usher in 1185,
                    adopted his official title as a surname. James Usher was sent to a school in
                    Dublin opened by two political agents of James VI. of Scotland, who adopted this
                    manner of averting the suspicions of Elizabeth’s Government from their real
                    object, which was to secure a party for James in Ireland in the event of the
                    queen’s death. In 1593 Usher matriculated as one of the first students at the
                    newly-founded university of Dublin, whose charter had been obtained in 1592 by
                    his uncle Henry Usher, archbishop of Armagh. He proved a diligent student,
                    devoting much attention to controversial theology, graduated as M.A. in 1600,
                    and became a fellow of Trinity College. On the death of his father in 1598 he
                    resigned the family estate to his younger brother, reserving only a small
                    rent-charge upon it for his own maintenance, and prepared to enter into holy
                    orders. When he was but nineteen he accepted a challenge put forth by Henry
                    Fitzsimons, a learned Jesuit, then a prisoner in Dublin, inviting discussion of
                    Bellarmine’s arguments in defence of Roman Catholicism, and acquitted himself
                    with much distinction. In 1600 he was appointed proctor of his college and
                    catechetical lecturer in the university, though still a layman, and was ordained
                    deacon and priest on the same day, in 1601, while still under the canonical age,
                    by his uncle the primate. In 1606 he became regius professor of divinity and
                    also chancellor of St Patrick’s cathedral, Dublin. He was a frequent visiter to
                    England to purchase books for his college library, and upon similar errands,
                    making on these occasions the acquaintance of the most eminent scholars in
                    London, Oxford, and Cambridge, such as Camden, Selden, Sir Thomas Bodley, and
                    Sir Robert Cotton. He took his degree of D.D. in 1612, and in the following year
                    published his first printed work, though not his first literary composition,—
                    <hi rend="italic">Gravissimae Quaestionis de Christianarum Ecclesiarum, in
                    Occidentis praesertim partibus, ab Apostolicis temporibus ad nostram usque
                    aetatem, continua 'successione et statu, Historica Explicatio,</hi> wherein he
                    took up the history of the Western Church from the point where Jewel had left
                    off in his <hi rend="italic">Apology for the Church of England,</hi> and carried
                    it on from the 6th till past the middle of the 13th century, but never completed
                    it. In this same year he married Phoebe, daughter of Dr Luke Chaloner, a wealthy
                    heiress. In 1615 he took part in an attempt of the Irish clergy to impose a
                    Calvinistic confession, embodying the Lambeth Articles of 1595, upon the Irish
                    Church, and was delated to King James in consequence. But on his next visit to
                    England in 1619 he brought with him an attestation to his orthodoxy and high
                    professional standing, signed by the lord deputy and the members of the privy
                    council, which, together with his own demeanour in a private conference with the
                    king, so influenced the latter that he nominated Usher to the vacant see of
                    Meath, of which he was consecrated bishop in 1620. In 1622 he published a
                    controversial <hi rend="italic">Discourse of the Religion anciently Professed by
                    the Irish and British,</hi> designed to show that they were in agreement with
                    the Church of England and opposed to the Church of Rome on the points in debate
                    between those churches. In 1623 he was made a privy <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n26/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0026-0017"/> councillor for Ireland, and in the same year was
                    summoned to England by the king that he might more readily carry on a work he
                    had already begun upon the antiquity of the British churches. While he was
                    detained on this business the archbishop of Armagh died in January 1624, and the
                    king at once nominated Usher to the vacant primacy; but severe illness and other
                    causes impeded his return to Ireland until August 1626.</p>
                <p>For many years Archbishop Usher was actively employed both in the government of
                    his diocese and in the publication of several learned works, amongst which may
                    be specified <hi rend="italic">Emmanuel</hi> (a treatise upon the Incarnation),
                    published in 1638, and <hi rend="italic">Britannicarum Ecclesiarum
                    Antiquitates,</hi> in 1639. In 1634 he took part in the convocation which
                    drafted the code of canons that formed the basis of Irish ecclesiastical law
                    till the disestablishment of the Irish Church in 1869, and defeated the attempt
                    of Bramhall, then bishop of Derry and later his own successor in Armagh, to
                    conform the Irish Church exactly to the doctrinal standards of the English. He
                    put the matter on the ground of preserving the independence of the Irish Church,
                    but the real motive at work was to maintain the Calvinistic element introduced
                    in 1615. In 1640 he paid another visit to England on one of his usual scholarly
                    errands, meaning to return when it was accomplished. But the rebellion of 1641
                    broke out while he was still at Oxford, and he never saw his native country
                    again. He published a collection of tracts at Oxford in that year, inclusive of
                    a defence of Episcopacy and of the doctrine of non-resistance. One blot on his
                    memory is that, being one of the five prelates whom Charles I. consulted whether
                    he could conscientiously assent to the Act of attainder against the earl of
                    Strafford after having pledged his word to him for his safety, Usher joined in
                    the casuistical advice given by all except Juxon, who alone told the king that
                    his pledged word could not be lawfully broken. All Usher’s property in Ireland
                    was lost to him through the rebellion, except his books and some plate and
                    furniture, but he was assigned the temporalities of the vacant see of Carlisle
                    for his support. In 1643 he was offered a seat in the Assembly of Divines at
                    Westminster, but declined it publicly in terms which drew upon him the anger of
                    the House of Commons, and an order for the confiscation of his library was
                    averted only by the interposition of Selden. He quitted Oxford in 1645 and went
                    into Wales, where he remained till 1646, when he returned to London, and was in
                    1647 elected preacher to the Society of Lincoln’s Inn, an office he continued to
                    hold till a little before his death. During his residence in Wales a
                    hyper-Calvinistic work entitled <hi rend="italic">A Body of Divinity; or the Sum
                    and Substance of the Christian Religion,</hi> was published under his name by
                    Downham; and, though he repudiated the authorship in a letter to the editor,
                    stating that the manuscript from which it was printed was merely a
                    commonplace-book into which he had transcribed the opinions of Cartwright and
                    other English divines, often disapproving of them and finding them dissonant
                    from his own judgment, yet it has been persistently cited ever since as Usher’s
                    genuine work, and as lending his authority to positions which he had long
                    abandoned, if he ever maintained them. In 1648 he had a conference with Charles
                    I. in the Isle of Wight, assisting him in the abortive negotiations with
                    Parliament on the question of Episcopacy. In 1650-54 he published the work which
                    at the time and for more than a century afterwards was accounted his most
                    important production, the <hi rend="italic">Annales Veteris et Novi
                    Testamenti,</hi> in which he propounded a scheme of Biblical chronology which
                    held its ground until disproved by very recent advances in scholarship, and
                    whose dates were inserted by some unknown authority in the margin of reference
                    editions of the authorized version. He was to some extent favoured by Cromwell
                    after he became lord protector, who seems to have promised Usher a pension and a
                    grant for twenty-one years of the lands belonging to the see of Armagh; but
                    there is no proof that either was actually carried out. In 1655 Usher published
                    his last work, <hi rend="italic">De Graeca LXX. Interpretum Versions
                    Syntagma.</hi> He died on 20th March 1656, in Lady Peterborough’s house at
                    Reigate in Surrey. His body was buried in Westminster abbey, in the chapel of St
                    Erasmus. To one daughter who survived him he left his library, and she sold it
                    to the officers and soldiers of Cromwell’s army in Ireland, who deposited it in
                    Dublin castle, whence it was removed at the Restoration and given, according to
                    Usher’s original purpose, by direction of Charles II. to the library of Trinity
                    College, of which it still forms a part.</p>
                <p>Usher’s works are very numerous, and were first collected by Ellington and Todd,
                    Dublin, 1847, in 17 vols. (R. F. L.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
