<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0903-0490-0475-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BEAVER (9th edition, volume 3, page 475)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx06c7f">Welsh</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kj6q">Canadians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47941107">Rodentia</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p88c">Beaver</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j09wd22">Teething</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hh6c56c">Teeth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:829421">Beavers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1145710">Teeth</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198486">Dams</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1242804">Scandinavia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206891">Poland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n490/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BEAVER</label>, the English name of a genus of Mammals
                    belonging to the order <hi rend="italic">Rodentia,</hi> the two known species of
                    which are among the largest members of that group. Both beavers, European and
                    American, measure about 2 feet in length, exclusive of the tail, which is about
                    10 inches long, and are covered with the fur to which they owe their chief
                    commercial value. This consists of two kinds of hair,— the one close-set, silky,
                    and of a greyish colour; the other much coarser and longer, and of a reddish
                    brown. Beavers are essentially aquatic in their habits, never travelling by land
                    unless driven to it by necessity. Their hind feet are webbed to the nails, and
                    in swimming those only are used, the front legs remaining motionless by the
                    side. They differ from all other rodents in possessing a broad horizontally
                    flattened tail, somewhat oval in form and covered with scales, which they use as
                    an aid to their progress through the water, and not as a trowel for plastering
                    their mud houses as was formerly supposed. The front incisor teeth in each jaw
                    have a sharp chisel-like edge, and are so formed as to preserve this through
                    life. They consist of an outer layer of orange-coloured enamel, and a broad
                    inner layer of a softer substance. As the creature gnaws, the softer material is
                    worn away more rapidly than the enamel, which thus protrudes in a sharp ridge.
                    There is a continuous growth at the roots of those teeth to repair the constant
                    waste that goes on at the cutting edge, so that should one of the incisors be
                    destroyed, the opposite tooth, meeting with no check to its enlargement, will
                    grow to an enormous length; and beavers have been found in which this abnormal
                    growth had proved fatal by preventing the other teeth from coming together. The
                    enamel is exceedingly hard; and, until superseded by English files, those teeth,
                    fixed in wooden handles, were used by the North American Indians in carving
                    their weapons of bone. The question whether the American and European beavers
                    are the same or different species, has given rise to some controversy; but it is
                    now generally conceded, chiefly on anatomical grounds, that they are distinct,
                    although in outward appearance they are almost identical.</p>
                <p>The European Beaver <hi rend="italic">{Castor fiber)</hi> was at one time an
                    inhabitant of the British Isles, having been found, according to Pennant, in
                    certain Welsh rivers as late as the 12th century, while fossil remains of it
                    occur in various parts of the country. In Scandinavia beavers are now
                    extinct,—the last known specimen having been killed in 1844. Isolated pairs are
                    still occasionally met with on the banks of the Rhone, the Weser, and the Elbe;
                    and a considerable number are to be found in one of the parks belonging to the
                    emperor of Austria, on the banks of the Danube, where they are strictly
                    preserved. They also occur, though sparingly, in Russia and Poland, in the
                    streams of the Ural Mountains, and in those which flow into the Caspian Sea.
                    They are said to live in burrows on the banks of rivers, like the common water
                    rat, and to show little of the architectural instinct so conspicuous in the
                    American species; this, however, is probably more owing to unfavourable external
                    conditions than to want of the faculty, for there is at least one
                    well-authenticated instance of a colony of beavers, on a small stream near
                    Magdeburg, whose habitations and dam were exactly similar to those found in
                    America.</p>
                <p>The American Beaver <hi rend="italic">{Castor canadensis)</hi> extends over that
                    part of the American continent included between the Arctic circle and the tropic
                    of Cancer; owing, however, to the gradual spread of population over part of this
                    area, and still more to the enormous quantity of skins that, towards the end of
                    last century and the beginning øf the present, were exported to Europe,
                    numbering about 200,000 annually, this species was in imminent danger of
                    extirpation. More recently the employment of silk and of the fur of the South
                    American Coypu in the manufacture of hats, so lessened the demand for beaver
                    skins that the trapping of these animals became unprofitable; and being thus
                    little sought after for many years, they have again become abundant in such of
                    their old haunts as have not yet been occupied by man, so that the trade in
                    beaver <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n491/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0903-0491-0476"/> skins has now nearly attained its former
                    proportions. Solitary beavers, always males, and known as “old bachelors,” or
                    idlers, are found inhabiting burrows similar to those seen in Europe. These are
                    generally found in the neighbourhood of new townships, and are supposed to be
                    individuals that have remained after the colony had broken up, or that from some
                    cause or another have been expelled from the society of their fellows. The
                    American Beaver, however, is essentially social, inhabiting lakes, ponds, and
                    rivers, as well as those narrow creeks which connect the lakes together. They
                    generally, however, prefer flowing waters, probably on account of the advantages
                    afforded by the current for transporting the materials of their dwellings. They
                    also prefer deepish water, no doubt because it yields a better protection from
                    the frost. When they build in small creeks or rivers, the waters of which are
                    liable to dry or to be drained off, instinct leads them to the formation of
                    dams. These differ in shape according to the nature of particular localities.
                    Where the water has little motion the dam is almost straight; where the current
                    is considerable it is curved, with its convexity towards the stream. The
                    materials made use of are drift wood, green willows, birch, and poplars; also
                    mud and stones intermixed in such a manner as must evidently contribute to the
                    strength of the dam; but there is no particular method observed, except that the
                    work is carried on with a regular sweep, and that all the parts are made of
                    equal strength. “In places,” says Hearne, “which have been long frequented by
                    beavers undisturbed, their dams, by frequent repairing, become a solid bank,
                    capable of resisting a great force both of ice and water; and as the willow,
                    poplar, and birch generally take root and shoot up, they by degrees form a kind
                    of regular planted hedge, which I have seen in some places so tall that birds
                    have built their nests among the branches.” Their houses are formed of the same
                    materials as the dams, with little order or regularity of structure, and seldom
                    contain more than four old, and six or eight young beavers. It not unfrequently
                    happens that some of the larger houses have one or more partitions, but these
                    are only posts of the main building left by the sagacity of the builders to
                    support the roof, for the apartments, as some call them, have usually no
                    communication with each other except by water. The beavers carry the mud and
                    stones with their fore-paws, and the timber between their teeth. They always
                    work in the night, and with great expedition. They cover their houses late every
                    autumn with fresh mud, which freezing when the frost sets in, becomes almost as
                    hard as stone, and thus neither wolves nor wolverines can disturb their
                    well-earned repose.</p>
                <p>The favourite food of the American Beaver is the plant called √V^ <hi
                        rend="italic">uphar</hi><hi rend="italic">luteum,</hi> which bears a
                    resemblance to a cabbage stalk, and grows at the bottom of lakes and rivers.
                    They also gnaw the bark of birch, poplar, and willow trees. But during the
                    bright summer days which clothe even the far northern regions with a luxuriant
                    vegetation, a more varied herbage, with the addition of berries, is consumed.
                    When the ice breaks up in spring they always leave their embankments, and rove
                    about until a little before the fall of the leaf, when they return again to
                    their old habitations, and lay in their winter stock of wood. They seldom begin
                    to repair the houses till the frost sets in, and never finish the outer coating
                    till the cold becomes pretty severe. When they erect a new habitation they fell
                    the wood early in summer, but seldom begin building till towards the end of
                    August.</p>
                <p>The flesh of the American Beaver is usually eaten by the Indians and the Canadian
                    voyageurs; and when roasted in the skin it is esteemed a delicacy. It is said to
                    taste like pork. The <hi rend="italic">castoreum,</hi> of the beaver is a
                    substance contained in two pyriform sacs, situated near the organs of
                    reproduction, of a bitter taste, and slightly foetid odour, at one time largely
                    employed as a medicine for derangement of the nervous system, as hysteria,
                    &amp;c., but now little used. Fossil remains of both beavers are found in the
                    Tertiary beds of the continents still inhabited by them, accompanied in each
                    case by remains of an extinct species. The latter appear from their remains to
                    have been much larger than those now existing.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
