<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0572-0557-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BENEDICT, St</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 3, page 557</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4dv1cp19">Food</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v97zt6b">Poisoners</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b48w3821v">Poisons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b46q1sn03">Rope</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xs5jm0g">Evil</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b47p8tc5z">Abbeys</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48911q68">Baptists</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="16" ref="fasttopic:830322">Benedictionals</term>
                    <term n="16" ref="fasttopic:830317">Benediction</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:930458">Food</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n572/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BENEDICT, <hi rend="smallcaps">St</hi></label>, the founder
                    of the celebrated Benedictine order, is the most illustrious name in the early
                    history of Western monasticism. To him more than to any other the monastic
                    system, which was destined to exercise such an influence for centuries, owes its
                    extension and organization. Benedict was born at Nursia in Umbria about the year
                    480. He belonged to an old Italian family, and was early sent to Rome to be
                    educated. But the disorder and vices of the capital drove him into solitude
                    while still a youth. It was a time of public peril and social ruin. The Roman
                    empire was crumbling to pieces, shaken by the successive inroads of barbarians,
                    and a prey to every species of violence and corruption. Young Benedict fled from
                    the wickedness around him. He gave up his literary studies and preferred to be
                    wisely ignorant <hi rend="italic">(scienter</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >nesciens).</hi> This is the statement of his biographer Gregory the Great, from
                    whom come all the details that we know of Benedict’s life. It is needless to say
                    that many of these details are of such a character that it is impossible for
                    modern historical criticism to accept them in their literal meaning. It is of no
                    use, however, trying to disentangle the truth from the falsehood. The reader can
                    easily make allowance for the imaginative exaggerations of the story.</p>
                <p>When Benedict fled from Rome he took refuge in a solitary gorge formed by the
                    Anio, in its picturesque course, about 40 miles from the city. There, in a dark
                    inaccessible grotto near Subiaco, he found seclusion and shelter. A neighbouring
                    monk supplied him with food let down by a rope, with a small bell attached,
                    which gave notice of the approach of the food. Once the devil broke the rope,
                    but his malice was foiled by the pious ingenuity of the monk. Other and graver
                    dangers assailed him. The Evil One took the shape of a beautiful woman, with
                    whose image the youthful recluse had been familiar in Rome, and so worked upon
                    his senses that he was on the point of abandoning his solitude in search of the
                    beauty which haunted him. But summoning all his fortitude he stripped himself of
                    the vestment of skins which was his only covering, rushed naked amongst the
                    thorns and briars which grew around his retreat, and rolled himself amongst them
                    till he had extinguished the impure flame which devoured him. No impulses of
                    sensual passion ever revisited him. But trials of a different kind assailed him.
                    After spending about three years in retirement a neighbouring convent of monks
                    insisted upon choosing him as their head. He warned them of the severity of the
                    rule he would be bound to exercise, but they would not be dissuaded from their
                    purpose. He had hardly commenced his office, however, when they broke out into
                    fierce resentment against him, and attempted to poison him. The cup containing
                    the poison was no sooner taken into the hands of Benedict than it burst asunder;
                    and, calmly reproving them for their ingratitude, he left them and withdrew once
                    more into his solitude.</p>
                <p>By this time, however, the fame of Benedict had spread, and it was impossible for
                    him to remain inactive. Multitudes gathered around him, and no fewer than twelve
                    select cloisters were planted in the lonely valley of the Anio and on the
                    adjacent heights. Young patricians from Rome and elsewhere were attracted to
                    these fraternities; and amongst them one of the name of Maurus (St Maur), who
                    began to share in popular esteem something of the sanctity and miraculous
                    endowments of Benedict, and who was destined to be his successor. But with
                    increasing fame came also jealousy of his position and duties. A renewed attempt
                    was made by an envious priest to administer poison to the saint; and, miraculous
                    interpositions having again come to his rescue, the same priest, by name
                    Florentius, had recourse to the diabolical device of sending seven lewd girls
                    within the precincts of the monastery, to seduce the monks by their gestures and
                    sports. Benedict determined to depart from a neighbourhood so full of danger,
                    notwithstanding the long period of thirty years during which he had laboured to
                    consecrate it and spread abroad the blessings of an ascetic Christianity. He
                    journeyed southwards, and at length settled at Monte Cassino, an isolated and
                    picturesque hill near the source of the Liris. There at this time an ancient
                    temple of Apollo still stood, to which the ignorant peasants brought their
                    offerings. Benedict, in his holy enthusiasm, proceeded <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n573/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0573-0558"/> to demolish the temple and to erect in its place
                    two oratories, one to St John the Baptist and the other to St Martin, whose
                    ascetic fame had travelled to Italy from the south of Gaul. Around these sacred
                    spots gradually rose the famous monastery which was destined to carry the name
                    of its founder through the Christian world, and to give its laws, as Milman
                    says, “to almost the whole of Western monasticism.”</p>
                <p>Benedict survived fourteen years after he had began this great work. His sanctity
                    and influence grew with his years, in illustration of which it is told how the
                    barbarian king Totila, who made himself master of Rome and Italy, sought his
                    presence, and, prostrating himself at his feet, accepted a rebuke for his
                    cruelties, and departed a humbler and better man. His last days were associated
                    with the love and devotion of his sister Scolastica, who too had forsaken the
                    world and given herself to a religious life with an enthusiasm and genius for
                    government hardly less than his own. She had established a nunnery near Monte
                    Cassino; but the rules of the order permitted the brother and sister to meet
                    only once a year. He had come to pay his accustomed visit. They had spent the
                    day in devout converse, and, in the fulness of her affection, Scolastica
                    entreated him to remain, and “speak of the joys of heaven till the morning.”
                    Benedict was not to be prevailed upon, 7hen his sister burst into a flood of
                    tears, and bowed her ead in prayer. Immediately the heavens became overcast;
                    thunder was heard, and the rain fell in torrents, so that it was impossible for
                    Benedict to depart for the night, which was spent in spiritual exercises. Three
                    days later Benedict saw in vision the soul of his sister entering heaven, and in
                    a few days afterwards his own summons came. He died standing, after partaking of
                    the holy communion, and was buried by the side of his sister.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">Benedictines,</hi> or followers of St Benedict, were
                    those who submitted to the monastic rule which he instituted. This rule will be
                    generally described in the article on <hi rend="smallcaps">Monasticism.</hi> It
                    is sufficient to say here that its two main principles were labour and
                    obedience. It was the distinction of Benedict that he not merely organized the
                    monks into communities, but based their community-life, in a great degree, on
                    manual labour, in contrast to the merely meditative seclusion which had hitherto
                    been in vogue both in the East and the West. Probably, not even the founder
                    himself foresaw all the prospective advantages of his law, which was destined
                    not merely to make many a wilderness and solitary place to rejoice with
                    fertility, but to expand, moreover, into a noble intellectual fruitfulness,
                    which has been the glory of the Benedictine order. The law of obedience was
                    absolute, but was tempered by the necessity on the part of the superior of
                    consulting all the monks assembled in a council or chapter upon all important
                    business. The abbot or superior was also elected by all the monks, whose liberty
                    of choice was unrestricted. No right of endowment properly subsisted within the
                    monastery; and the vow of <hi rend="italic">stability</hi> once undertaken after
                    the expiry of the year of novitiate could never be recalled. Food and clothing
                    were of the simplest kind, and all duly regulated; and the intervals of labour
                    were relieved by a continually recurring round of religious service from prime
                    to evensong. The Benedictine rule spread almost universally in the West,—not in
                    rivalry of any other rule, but as the more full and complete development of the
                    monastic system. In France and England especially it took rapid root; and “in
                    every rich valley, by the side of every clear and deep stream, arose a
                    Benedictine ’abbey ”—a centre of local good and Christian civilization. See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Abbey. (j. t.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
