<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0903-0291-0276-04" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BALEARIC ISLANDS (9th edition, volume 3, page
                    276)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:848634">Catalans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:994553">Lead</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1174325">Wheat</term>
                    <term ref="fast:927119">Flax</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205459">Algeria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ww7759r">Moors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ft8dp2t">Sand</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v00z">Travelers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g08p">Groups</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4639kb2c">Lead</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n29p91c">Wheat</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n291/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BALEARIC ISLANDS</label>, a remarkable group in the western
                    part of the Mediterranean Sea, lying to the S. and E. of Spain, between 38° 40
                        <hi rend="superscript"> z</hi> and 40° 5' N. lat., and between l <hi
                        rend="superscript"> o</hi> and 5° E. long. The name, as now employed,
                    includes not only the ancient <hi rend="italic">Insuloe</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Baleares</hi><hi rend="italic">(Major</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Minor),</hi> but also the <hi rend="italic">Pityusoe</hi> or Pine Islands,
                    as the two more western were called. The origin of the name Baleares is a mere
                    matter of conjecture, and the reader may choose any of the derivations usually
                    offered with about an equal chance of not being right. On the other hand, it is
                    obvious that the modern Majorca (or, in Spanish, Mallorca) and Minorca <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n292/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0903-0292-0277"/> (in Spanish, Menorca) are obtained from the
                    Latin <hi rend="italic">Major</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Minor,</hi> through the
                    Byzantine forms Mαιopικα and Mιvopικa; while Iviza is plainly the older Ebusus,
                    a name of, probably, Carthaginian origin. The <hi rend="italic">Ophiusa</hi> of
                    the Greeks <hi rend="italic">(Colubraria</hi> of the Romans) is now known as
                    Formentera.</p>
                <p>Majorca is the largest island of the group, having an area of 1430 square miles.
                    Its shape is that of a trapezoid, with the angles directed to the cardinal
                    points; and its diagonal, from Cape Grozer in the W. to Cape Pera in the E., is
                    about sixty miles. On the N.W. the coast is highly precipitous, but on the other
                    sides it is low and sloping. On the N.E. there are several considerable bays, of
                    which the chief are those of Alcudia and Pollenza; while on the S.W. is the
                    Stillmore important bay of Palma. No fewer than twelve ports or harbours are
                    enumerated round the island, of which may be mentioned Andraix, Soller, and
                    Porto Colom. In the N.W. Majorca is traversed by a chain of mountains running
                    parallel with the coast, and attaining its highest elevation in Silla de
                    Torillas, 4600 feet above the sea. Towards the south and east the surface is
                    comparatively level, though broken by isolated peaks of considerable height. The
                    northern mountains afford great protection to the rest of the island from the
                    violent gales to which it is exposed, and render the climate remarkably mild and
                    pleasant, while the heats of summer are tempered by the sea-breezes. The scenery
                    of Majorca is varied and beautiful, with all the picturesqueness of outline that
                    usually belongs to a limestone formation. Some of the valleys, such as those of
                    Valdemoza and Soller, with their luxuriant vegetation, are delightful resorts.
                    There are quarries of marble, of various grains and colours—those of Santagny,
                    in the partido of Manacor, being especially celebrated; while lead, iron, and
                    cinnabar have also been obtained. Coal of a jet-like character is found at
                    Benisalem, where works were commenced in 1836, at Selva, where it has been mined
                    since 1851, near Santa Maria, and elsewhere. It is used in the industrial
                    establishments of Palma, and in the manufacture of lime, plaster, and bricks, in
                    the neighbourhood of the mines,—a considerable quantity being also exported to
                    Barcelona. The inhabitants are principally devoted to agriculture, and most of
                    the arable land of the islands is under cultivation. The mountains are terraced;
                    and the old pine woods have in many places given place to the olive, the vine,
                    and the almond tree, to fields of wheat and flax, or to orchards of figs and
                    oranges. For the last-mentioned fruits the valley of Soller is one of the most
                    important districts, the produce being largely transmitted to France, and
                    realising about £25,000 per annum. The oil harvest is very considerable, and
                    Inca is the centre of the oil district. The wines are light but excellent,
                    especially the Muscadel and Montona. The agricultural methods of the islands are
                    still somewhat primitive, but the introduction of machinery indicates
                    improvement, as well as the drainage, by an English company, of a marsh and
                    lake, 8000 acres in extent, near the town of Alcudia. During the summer there is
                    often great scarcity of water; but, according to a system handed down by the
                    Moors, the rains of autumn and winter are collected in enormous reservoirs,
                    which contain sufficient water to last through the dry season; and on the
                    payment of a certain rate, each landholder in turn has his fields flooded at
                    certain intervals. Mules are used in the agriculture and traffic of the island.
                    The cattle are small, but the sheep are large and well fleeced. Pigs are largely
                    reared, and exported to Barcelona. There is abundance of poultry and of small
                    game. A good deal of brandy is made and exported. Excellent woollen and linen
                    cloths are woven. The silkworm is reared, and its produce manufactured; and
                    canvas, rope, and cord are largely made, from both native and foreign materials.
                    The average value of the imports of the island is £550,000, and the exports
                    amount to rather more. The roads are excellent, the four principal being those
                    from Alcudia, Manacor, Soller, and Andraix to the capital. A railway is in
                    course of construction from Palma by Inca to Alcudia, and the stock is all held
                    by Mallorquins. A telegraphic line passes from Palma to Valcenia, and there is
                    regular steam communication with Barcelona and Alicante. A Majorcan bank has
                    been established, and a credit association for the development of the resources
                    of <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n293/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0903-0293-0278"/> the island. The people are industrious and
                    hospitable, and pique themselves on their loyalty and orthodoxy. They are often
                    but poorly educated, and their superstition is great; crime, however, is rare.
                    Vaccination is common throughout the island, except in the cities,—the women
                    often performing the operation themselves when medical assistance cannot be got.
                    Castilian is spoken by the upper and commercial classes; the lower and
                    agricultural employ a dialect resembling that of the Catalans, with whom, also,
                    their general appearance and manners connect them. Besides the towns already
                    mentioned, Lluchmayor and Campos are places of considerable size; and the castle
                    of Belbez near Palma, which was the former residence of the kings, is worthy of
                    notice. Population of the island, 204,000.</p>
                <p>Minorca, the second of the group in size, is situated 27 miles E.N.E. of Majorca.
                    It has an area of 260 square miles, and extends about 35 miles in length. The
                    coast is deeply indented, especially on the north, with numerous creeks and
                    bays,—that of Port Mahon being one of the finest in the Mediterranean, if not
                    the best of them all, as the couplet of Andrea Doria quaintly puts it—</p>
                <lg>
                    <l> “Junio, Julio, Agosto, y puerto Mahon </l>
                    <l> Los mejores puertos del Mediterraneo son ”— </l>
                </lg>
                <p>“June, July, August, and Port Mahon are the best harbours of the Mediterranean.”
                    The ports Addaya, Fornelle, Ciudadela, and Nitja may also be mentioned. The
                    surface of the island is uneven, flat in the south and rising irregularly
                    towards the centre, where the mountain El Toro—probably so called from the
                    Arabic Tor, a height, though the natives have a legend of a <hi rend="italic"
                        >toro</hi> or bull—has an altitude of 5250 feet. Owing to want of shelter
                    from mountains, the climate is not so equable as that of Majorca, and the island
                    is exposed in autumn and winter to the violence of the north winds. The soil of
                    the island is of very unequal quality; that of the higher districts being light,
                    fine, and fertile, and producing regular harvests without much labour or
                    cultivation, while that of the plains is chalky, scanty, and alike unfit for
                    pasture and the plough. Some of the valleys have a good alluvial soil; and where
                    the hills have been terraced, they are cultivated to the summit. The wheat and
                    barley raised in the island are sometimes sufficient for home consumption; there
                    is rarely a surplus. The <hi rend="italic">Hedysarum</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >coronarium,</hi> or zulla, as it is called by the Spaniards, is largely
                    cultivated for fodder. Wine, oil, potatoes, legumes, hemp, and flax are produced
                    in moderate quantities; fruit of all kinds, including melons, pomegranates,
                    figs, and almonds, is abundant. The moniato, or sweet potato, is grown and
                    exported to Algeria. The caper plant is common throughout the island, growing on
                    ruined walls. Horned cattle, sheep, goats, &lt;fcc,, are reared, and the island
                    abounds with small game. Stone of various kinds is plentiful; a soft stone,
                    easily quarried, and acquiring hardness by exposure, is used for building. In
                    the district of Mercadal and in Mount Santa Agueda are found marbles and
                    porphyries superior to those of Italy, and lime and slate are also abundant.
                    Lead, copper, and iron might be worked were it not for the scarcity of fuel.
                    There are manufactures of the wool, hemp, and flax of the island; and formerly
                    there was a good deal of boat-building; but, with the exception of agriculture,
                    all branches of industry are comparatively neglected. The principal exports are
                    wheat, cattle, cotton-stuffs, and shoes. A n excellent road, constructed in
                    1713-15 by Brigadier Kane, to whose memory a monument was erected at the first
                    milestone, runs through the island from S.E. to N.W., and connects Port Mahon
                    with Ciudadela, passing by Alayor, Mercadal, and Ferrerias. Ciudadela, which was
                    the capital of the island till Mahon was raised to that position by the English
                    during their occupancy of the island, still possesses considerable remains of
                    its former importance. Population of the island, 39,000.</p>
                <p>Iviça, Iviza, or, in Spanish, Ibiza, the <hi rend="italic">Ebusus</hi> of the
                    ancients, lies 50 miles S.W. of Majorca, and about 60 from Cape San Martin on
                    the coast of Spain, between 38° 50' and 39° 8' N. lat., and between l <hi
                        rend="superscript"> o</hi> 14' and l <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> 38' E.
                    long. Its greatest length from N.E. to S.W. is about 25 miles, and its greatest
                    breadth about 13. The coast is indented by numerous small bays, the principal of
                    which are those of San Antonio on the N.W., and of Iviza on the S.E. coast. Of
                    all the Balearic group, Iviza is the most varied in its scenery and the most
                    fruitful. The hilly parts are richly wooded. It was on one of the summits called
                    Campsey that one of the stations in the celebrated measurement of an arc of the
                    meridian was placed. The climate is for the most part mild and agreeable, though
                    the hot winds from the African coast are sometimes troublesome. Oil, corn, and
                    fruits (of which the most important are the common fig, the prickly pear, the
                    almond, and the carob-bean) are the principal productions of the island; but the
                    inhabitants are rather indolent, and their modes of culture are very primitive.
                    Hemp and flax are also grown. There are numerous salt-pans along the coast,
                    which were formerly worked by the Spanish Government, but are now in the hands
                    of a joint-stock company. Carob-beans, almonds, charcoal, and lead are the other
                    articles of export, to which may be added stockings of native manufacture The
                    imports are rice, flour, and sugar, woollen goods, and cotton. The capital of
                    the island, and, indeed, the only town of much importance,—for the population is
                    remarkably scattered,— is Iviza or La Ciudad, a fortified town on the S.E.
                    coast, consisting of a lower and upper portion, and possessing a good harbour.
                    The population of the island is about 21,000, ci whom·5500 are resident in the
                    capital.</p>
                <p>South of Iviza lies the smaller and more irregular island of Formentera, which is
                    said to derive its name from the production of wheat. It is situated between l
                        <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> 22' and l <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> 37'
                    E. long. With Iviza it agrees both in general appearance and in the character of
                    its productions, but it is altogether destitute of streams. Goatsand sheep are
                    found in the mountains, and the coasts are greatly frequented by flamingoes. The
                    last station in the measurement of the arc of the meridian was in this
                    island.</p>
                <p>There are several smaller islands in the Balearic group, such as Cabrera, or Goat
                    Island, and Conejera, or Babbit Island, south of Majorca, but none of them are
                    of any size or importance except Cabrera, which is full of caverns, and is used
                    as a place of banishment. In 1808 it was the scene of a deed of gross
                    barbarity—a large number of Frenchmen being landed on the island, and almost
                    allowed to perish for want of food.</p>
                <p>Of the origin of the early inhabitants of the Balearic Islands nothing is
                    certainly known, though Greek and Roman writers refer to Boeotian and Rhodian
                    settlements. According to general tradition the natives, from whatever quarter
                    derived, were a strange and savage people till they received some tincture of
                    civilisation from the Carthaginians, who early took possession of the islands,
                    and built themselves cities on their coasts. Of these cities, Mahon, the most
                    important, still retains the name which ft derived from the family of Mago.
                    About twenty-three years after the destruction of Carthage the Romans accused
                    the people of the islands of piracy, and sent against them Q. Caecilius
                    Metellus, who soon reduced them to obedience, settled amongst them 3000 Roman
                    and Spanish colonists, founded the cities of Palma and Pollentia, and introduced
                    the cultivation of the olive. Besides valuable contingents of the celebrated
                    Balearic slingers the Romans derived from their new conquest mules (from
                    Minorca), edible snails, <hi rend="italic">sinopc,</hi> and pitch. Of their
                    occupation numerous traces still exist,—the most remarkable being the aqueduct
                    at Pollentia.</p>
                <p>In 423 A.D. the islands were taken possession of by the Vandals, and in 798 by
                    the Moors. They became a separate Moorish kingdom in 1009, which, becoming
                    extremely obnoxious for piracy, was the object of a crusade directed against it
                    by Pope Pascal IL, in <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n294/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0903-0294-0279"/> which the Catalans took the lead. This
                    expedition was frustrated at the time, but was resumed by Don Jaime, king of
                    Aragon, and the Moors expelled in 1232. During their occupation the island was
                    populous and productive, and an active commerce was carried on with Spain and
                    Africa. Don Jaime conferred the sovereignty of the isles on his third son, under
                    whom and his successors they formed an independent kingdom up to 1349, from
                    which time their history merges in that of Spain. In 1521 an insurrection of the
                    peasantry against the nobility, whom they massacred, took place in Majorca, and
                    was not suppressed without much bloodshed. In the war of the Spanish Succession
                    all the islands declared for Charles; the duke of Anjou had no footing anywhere
                    save in the citadel of Mahon. Minorca was reduced by Count Villars in 1707; but
                    it was not till June 1715 that Majorca was subjugated, and meanwhile Port Mahon
                    was captured by the English under General Stanhope in 1708. In 1713 theisland
                    was securedtothembythe peace of Utrecht; but in 1756 it was invaded by a force
                    of 12,000 French, who, after defeating the unfortunate Admiral Byng, captured’
                    Port Mahon. Restored to England in 1769 by the peace of Versailles the island
                    remained in our possession till 1782, when it was retaken by the Spaniards.
                    Again seized by the English in 1798, it was finally cided to Spain by the peace
                    of Amiens in 1803. When the French invaded Spain in 1808, the Mallorquins did
                    not remain indifferent; the governor, D. Juan Miguel de Vives, announced, amid
                    universal acclamation, his resolution to adhere to Ferdinand VII. At first the
                    Junta would take no active part in the war, retaining the corps of volunteers
                    that were formed for the defence of the island; but finding it quite secure,
                    they transferred a succession of them to the Peninsula to reinforce the allies.
                    Such was the animosity excited against the French when their excesses were known
                    to the Mallorquins, that some of the French prisoners, conducted thither in
                    1810, had to be transferred with all speed to the island of Cabrera, a
                    transference which was not effected before some of them had been killed.</p>
                <p>Armstrong’s <hi rend="italic">Hist, of Minorca,</hi> 1756; Dameto’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Hist, del reyno</hi><hi rend="italic">Balearico</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">o de Mallorca; Hist, of Balearic Islands,</hi> London, 1716;
                    Vincente Mut’s <hi rend="italic">Historia</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi>
                    Cleghorn’s <hi rend="italic">Diseases of Minorca,</hi> 1751; Wernsdorf, <hi
                        rend="italic">Antiquitates Balearicae;</hi> Clayton’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Sunny South,</hi> 1869; George Sand, in <hi rend="italic">Revue des Deux
                        Mondes,</hi> 1841; DΗermilly, <hi rend="italic">Hist, du</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Royaume</hi><hi rend="italic">de Minorque,</hi> Maestricht,
                    1777; “Balearic Islands,” in Bates’s <hi rend="italic">Illustrated Travels,</hi>
                    vol. i.; <hi rend="italic">Die</hi><hi rend="italic">Balearen</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">in</hi><hi rend="italic">Wort und</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Bild</hi><hi rend="italic">geschildert,</hi> Leipsic, 1871; “Klima der
                    Balearen” in the <hi rend="italic">Zeit, der</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Oesterr.</hi><hi rend="italic">Gesell, für Meteorologie,</hi> 1874; Juan
                    Ramis, <hi rend="italic">Antiguedadcs</hi><hi rend="italic">Celticas</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">de la Isla de Menorca,</hi> Mahon, 1818; Pauli, “Ein Monat auf
                    den Balearen” in <hi rend="italic">Das Ausland,</hi> 1873; Arago, <hi
                        rend="italic">De ma jeunesse, Oeuvres,</hi> vol. i.; Biot, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Recueil</hi><hi rend="italic">d'Observations</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >géodésiques,</hi> Ac., 1821.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
