<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0473-0458-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BAYLE, Pierre</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 3, page 458</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z139">Chairs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4x63b58d">Kindness</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1025853">Months</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:851811">Chairs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:987598">Kindness</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1150276">Thoughtfulness</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:844604">Calvinists</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n473/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BAYLE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Pierre</hi></label>, author of
                    the famous <hi rend="italic">Historical and Critical Dictionary,</hi> was born
                    on the 18th November 1647, at Carlat-lc-Comte, near Foix, in the south of
                    France. He was educated at first by his father, a Calvinist minister, and was
                    afterwards sent to an academy at Puy-Laurens, where he studied with such
                    assiduity as seriously to injure his health. After a short residence at home he
                    entered a Jesuit college at Toulouse. While there he devoted much of his time to
                    controversial works on theology, and ended by abjuring Calvinism and embracing
                    the Roman Catholic faith. In this, however, he continued only seventeen months,
                    abruptly resuming his former religion. To avoid the punishment inflicted on such
                    as relapsed from the Catholic Church, he withdrew to Geneva, where he resumed
                    his studies, and for the first time became acquainted with the philosophical
                    writings of Descartes. For some years he acted as tutor in various families; but
                    in 1675, when a vacancy occurred in the chair of philosophy at the Protestant
                    university of Sedan, he was prevailed upon to compete for the post, and was
                    successful. In 1681 the university at Sedan was suppressed, but almost
                    immediately afterwards Bayle was appointed professor of philosophy and history
                    at Rotterdam. Here in 1682 he published his famous letter on comets, and his
                    critique of Maimbourg ’ s work on the history of Calvinism. The great reputation
                    achieved by this critique stirred up the envy of Bayle’s colleague, Jurieu, who
                    had written a book on the same subject, and who afterwards did all in his power
                    to injure his former friend. In 1684 Bayle began the publication of his <hi
                    rend="italic">Nouvelles de la République des Lettres,</hi> a kind of journal of
                    literary criticism, which was continued with great success for several years. In
                    1690 appeared a work entitled <hi rend="italic">Avis aux Réfugiés,</hi> which
                    Jurieu attributed to Bayle, whom he attacked with the bitterest animosity. After
                    a long quarrel Bayle was deprived of his chair in 1693. He was not much
                    depressed by this misfortune, being at the time closely engaged in the
                    preparation of his great Dictionary, which appeared in 1697. A second edition
                    was called for in 1702. The few remaining years of Bayle’s life were devoted to
                    miscellaneous writings, arising in many instances out of criticisms made upon
                    his Dictionary. He died on the 28th December 1706, after some months’ suffering
                    from chest disease, which he would not permit to interfere with his literary
                    labours. Bayle’s erudition, despite the low estimate placed upon it by Leclerc,
                    seems to have been very considerable. He was an ardent student, and his reading
                    was varied and extensive. As a critic he was second to none in his own time, and
                    even yet one can admire the lightness and delicacy of his touch, and the skill
                    with which he handles his subject. The <hi rend="italic">Nouvelle-de</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">la République des Lettres</hi> was the first thorough-going
                    attempt to popularize literature, and it was eminently successful. The
                    Dictionary, however, is Bayle’s masterpiece, and in it appear to perfection his
                    various qualities, —extensive and curious information, fluency of style, and
                    that light sceptical spirit which has became closely associated with his name.
                    Bayle’s scepticism is of a peculiar kind. It is not a distrust of the power of
                    human knowledge grounded on a scientific investigation of the nature of thought
                    in itself. It is rather the scepticism of the literary man of the world, who in
                    his reading has encountered so many opposing and well-supported arguments on all
                    subjects, that he feels inclined to hold that no certainty can ever be attained.
                    On this account, perhaps, his sceptical criticism, though it did much to
                    liberate thought from the bonds of authority, has had little influence on pure
                    philosophy. Examples of Bayle’s critical mode of investigation may be seen in
                    his articles on the Greek sceptical philosophers, particularly those on
                    Pyrrhonism, Zeno, Carneades, and Chrysippus.</p>
                <p>See Dea Maizeaux, <hi rend="italic">Vie</hi><hi rend="italic">de Bayle;</hi>
                    Feuerbach, <hi rend="italic">Pierre</hi><hi rend="italic">Bayle,</hi> 1838;
                    Daιniron, <hi rend="italic">Philosophie en</hi><hi rend="italic">France</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">au</hi> xvii <hi rend="superscript"> mβ</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Siècle.</hi></p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n474/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0474-0459"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
