<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0903-0414-0399-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BARRY, James (9th edition, volume 3, page 399)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:815177">Art</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100369">Rooms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:817559">Artists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4154dp40">Artists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vp7r">Home</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6j808">Gaming</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n414/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BARRY, <hi rend="smallcaps">James</hi></label>, an eminent
                    painter, was born at Cork on the lltlι October 1741. His father had been a
                    builder, and, at one time of his life, a coasting trader between the two
                    countries of England and Ireland. To this business of trader James was destined,
                    and he actually made, when a boy, several voyages’; but these being forced upon
                    him, he on one occasion ran away from the ship, and on all others manifested
                    such an aversion to the life and habits of a sailor, as to induce his father to
                    relinquish all hopes of him in this line, and to suffer him to pursue his
                    inclinations, which led strongly towards drawing and study. At the schools in
                    Cork to which he was sent, he was distinguished above his school-fellows by his
                    talents and industry; his habits differed from those of ordinary boys; he seldom
                    mixed in their games or amusements, but during play-hours stole off to his own
                    room, where he worked at his pencil, or studied some book that he had borrowed
                    or bought. As his industry was excessive, his advances in the acquisition of
                    knowledge were rapid, and he was regarded as a prodigy by his school-fellows.
                    About the age of seventeen he first attempted oil painting, and between that and
                    the age of twenty-two, when he first went to Dublin, he produced several large
                    pictures, which decorated his father’s house, <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n415/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0903-0415-0400"/> and represented subjects net often chosen by
                    young artists, such as Aeneas escaping with his family from the flames of Troy,
                    Susanna and the elders, Daniel in the lions’ den, &lt;fcc. At this period he
                    also produced the painting which first brought him into public notice, and
                    gained him the acquaintance and patronage of Edmund Burke. The picture was
                    founded on an old tradition of the landing of St Patrick on the sea-coast of
                    Cashel, and of the conversion and baptism of the king of that district by the
                    patron saint of Ireland. Barry’s manner of treating it was such as to gain for
                    him the applause and admiration of the connoisseurs of London, where it was
                    exhibited in 1762 or 1763.</p>
                <p>By the liberality of Burke and his other friends, Barry, in the latter part of
                    1765, was enabled to proceed to the Continent, where he remained till the
                    beginning of 1771, studying his art with an enthusiasm which seemed to augur the
                    highest success, and making observations on the different <hi rend="italic"
                        >chefs</hi><hi rend="italic">d'oeuvre</hi> of Italy with equal independence
                    of judgment and nicety of discrimination. He proceeded first to Paris, then to
                    Rome, where he remained upwards of three years, from Rome to Florence and
                    Bologna, and thence home through Venice. His letters to the Burkes, giving an
                    account of Michel Angelo, Raffaelle, Titian, and Leonardo dα Vinci, show a
                    complete insight into the characteristic merits of their works, and would make
                    us wonder (if the case were at all singular) how he could enter with such force,
                    delicacy, and feeling, into excellences of which he transplanted nothing into
                    his own works.</p>
                <p>Even in copying from the antique he manifested the same aversion to labour, or to
                    that kind of labour which, by showing us our defects, compels us to make
                    exertions to remedy them. He made all his drawings from the antique by means of
                    a <hi rend="italic">delineator,</hi> that is, a mechanical instrument, to save
                    the trouble of acquiring a knowledge both of form and proportion. Barry painted
                    two pictures while abroad, his Adam and Eve, and his Philoctetes. The first of
                    these he sent home as a specimen of his progress in the art. It does not appear
                    to have given much satisfaction. His Philoctetes he brought home with him. It is
                    a coarse, unclassical performance,—the direct opposite, indeed, of all that he
                    thought it to be. Soon after his return to England he produced his picture of
                    Venus, which has been compared, though with little justice, to the Galatea of
                    Raffaelle, the Venus of Titian, and the Venus de Medici. In 1773 he exhibited
                    his Jupiter and Juno on Mount Ida, which was much praised by some critics of
                    that day. His Death of General Wolfe, in which the British and French soldiers
                    are represented in very primitive costumes, was considered as a falling off from
                    his great style of art, the painting of Greek subjects, and, accordingly, it is
                    said to “have obtained no praise.” His fondness for Greek costume was assigned
                    by his admirers as the cause of his reluctance to paint portraits,—as if the
                    coat were of more importance than the face. His fastidiousness in this respect,
                    and his frequent excuses or blunt refusals to go on with a portrait of Burke
                    which he had begun, caused a misunderstanding with his early patron, which does
                    not appear to have been ever entirely made up. The difference between them is
                    said to have been widened by Burke’s growing intimacy with Sir Joshua Reynolds,
                    and by Barry’s feeling some little jealousy of the fame and fortune of his rival
                    “in a humbler walk of the art.” About the same time he painted a pair of
                    classical subjects, Mercury inventing the lyre, and Narcissus looking at himself
                    in the water, the last suggested to him by Burke. He also painted an historical
                    picture of Chiron and Achilles, and another of the story of Stratonice, for
                    which last the duke of Richmond gave him a hundred guineas. In 1773 it was
                    proposed to decorate the interior of St Paul’s with historical and sacred
                    subjects; but the plan fell to the ground, from not meeting with the concurrence
                    of the bishop of London and the archbishop of Canterbury. Barry was much
                    mortified at the failure, for he had in anticipation fixed upon the subject he
                    intended to paint,— the rejection of Christ by the Jews when Pilate proposes his
                    release. In 1773 he published <hi rend="italic">An Inquiry into the real and
                        imaginary Obstructions to the Acquisition of the Arts in England,</hi>
                    vindicating the capacity of the English for the fine arts, and tracing their
                    slow progress hitherto to the Reformation, to political and civil dissensions,
                    and, lastly, to the general direction of the public mind to mechanics,
                    manufactures, and commerce. In the year 1774 a proposal was made, through Mr
                    Valentine Green, to Reynolds, West, Cipriani, Barry, and other artists, to
                    ornament the great room of the Society for the Encouragement of Arts,
                    Manufacturers, and Commerce, in the Adelphi, with historical and allegorical
                    paintings. This proposal was at the time rejected by the artists themselves;
                    but, in 1777, Barry made an offer to paint the whole on condition of being
                    allowed the choice of his subjects, and being paid by the society the expenses
                    of canvas, paints, and models. His offer was accepted, and he finished the
                    series of pictures at the end of seven years, instead of two, as he had proposed
                    to himself, accomplishing his task to the entire satisfaction of the members of
                    the society, who granted him two exhibitions, and at different periods voted him
                    50 guineas, their gold medal, and 200 guineas. Of the six paintings making up
                    the series, only one, that of the Olympic Games, shows any artistic power.</p>
                <p>Soon after his return from the Continent Barry had been chosen a member of the
                    Royal Academy; and in 1782 he was appointed professor of painting, in the room
                    of Mr Penny, with a salary of .£30 a year. The lectures which he delivered from
                    the chair were full of strong sense and wholesome advice, both to the students
                    and academicians. Among other things, he insisted much on the necessity of
                    purchasing a collection of pictures by the best masters as models for the
                    students, and proposed several of those in the Orleans collection. This
                    recommendation was not relished by the academicians, and quarrels arose, which
                    reached such a height, that, in 1799, Barry was expelled from the academy, soon
                    after the appearance of his <hi rend="italic">Letter to the Dilettanti
                        Society,</hi> a very amusing but eccentric publication, full of enthusiasm
                    for his art and at the same time of contempt for the living professors of it.
                    After the loss of his salary, a subscription was set on foot by the earl of
                    Buchan to relieve him from his difficulties, and to settle him in a larger house
                    to finish bis picture of Pandora. The subscription amounted to £1000, with which
                    an annuity was bought, but of this he was prevented from enjoying the benefit,
                    for, on the 6th of February 1806, he was seized with a pleuritic fever, and died
                    on the 22d of the same month. On the 14th of March his remains were interred in
                    the cathedral of St Paul’s.</p>
                <p>As an artist Barry is more distinguished for the strength of his conceptions, and
                    for his resolute and persistent determination to apply himself only to great
                    subjects, than for his skill in designing or for beauty in his colouring. His
                    ideas were generally fine, but the realization of them was almost without
                    exception unsuccessful. His drawing is rarely good, his colouring frequently
                    wretched. This curious contradiction in his artistic powers λvas in complete
                    harmony with his general character. He was extremely impulsive and unequal;
                    sometimes morose, sometimes sociable and urbane; jealous of his contemporaries,
                    and yet capable of pronouncing a splendid eulogy on Reynolds.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
