<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0871-0854-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BOERHAAVE, Hermann</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 3, page 854</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1103279">Sacrum</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1043068">Occasionalism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1062841">Physicians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:851811">Chairs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f41h">Physicians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z139">Chairs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n871/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BOERHAAVE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Hermann</hi></label>, one of
                    the most celebrated physicians of modern times, was born at Voorhout near
                    Leyden, December 31, 1668. Destined for the clerical profession, to which his
                    father belonged, he received a liberal education, and early displayed unusual
                    abilities. At the age of sixteen he entered the University of Leyden, where he
                    studied under Gronovius, Ryckius, Trigland, and other distinguished men, and
                    obtained the highest academical honours. In 1690 he took his degree in
                    philosophy; on which occasion he delivered an inaugural dissertation <hi
                    rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">distinctione</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >mentis</hi><hi rend="italic">a corpore,</hi> wherein he attacked the doctrines
                    of Epicurus, Hobbes, and Spinoza. Being left, on the death of his father,
                    without any provision, he was compelled to support himself by teaching
                    mathematics. By the advice of Vandenberg, the burgomaster of Leyden, Boerhaave
                    now applied himself with ardour to the study of medicine, to which indeed he had
                    early manifested a decided inclination. The works of Hippocrates among the
                    ancients, and those of Sydenham among the moderns, were the especial objects of
                    his study; but his reading was by no means confined to these authors. In 1693 he
                    took his degree of M.D. at Harderwyck in Guelderland, and immediately entered on
                    the studies of his profession. His merits were soon recognized, and in 1701 he
                    was appointed by the University of Leyden to supply the place of Drelincourt as
                    lecturer on the institutes of medicine. His inaugural discourse on this occasion
                    was entitled <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">commendando
                    Hippocratis</hi><hi rend="italic">studio,</hi> in which he recommended to his
                    pupils that great physician as their model. In 1709, the university appointed
                    him successor to Hotton in the chair of botany and medicine, in which capacity
                    he did good service, not only to his own university, but also <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi> to botanical science, by his improvements and
                    additions to the botanic garden of Leyden, and by the publication of numerous
                    works descriptive of new species of plants. He was appointed in 1714 rector of
                    the university. In the same year he succeeded Bidloo in the chair of practical
                    medicine, and in this capacity he had the merit of introducing into modern
                    practice the system of clinical instruction. Four years later he was appointed
                    to the <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n872/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0872-0855"/> chair of chemistry, and delivered an inaugural
                    discourse, which contains the germs of his celebrated <hi rend="italic">Elements
                    of Chemistry.</hi> In 1728 he was elected into the Royal Academy of Sciences of
                    Paris, and two years later into the Royal Society of London; to both of which he
                    communicated his chemical researches In 1729 declining health obliged him to
                    resign the chairs of chemistry and botany; and in 1731 he resigned the
                    rectorship of the university, to which office he had been re-elected On this
                    occasion he delivered a discourse <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Honore</hi><hi rend="italic">Medici</hi><hi rend="italic">Servitute.</hi> This
                    great and good man died, after a lingering and painful illness, on the merning
                    of the 23d September 1738.</p>
                <p>From the time of Hippocrates, no physician had more justly merited thç esteem of
                    his contemporaries and the admiration of posterity than Boerhaave. To uncommon
                    intellectual abilities he united those amiable qualities of the heart which give
                    them so great a value to society. His personal appearance was simple and
                    venerable. He taught very methodically, and with great precision; his style was
                    eloquent, and his delivery dignified and graceful. He sometimes also gave his
                    lectures a lively turn; but his raillery was never coarse or satirical. He
                    possessed remarkable powers of memory, and was an accomplished linguist A
                    declared foe to all excess, he considered decent mirth as the salt of life. He
                    was fond of music, with which he had a scientific acquaintance; and during
                    winter he had a weekly concert in his house. It was his daily practice
                    throughout life, as soon as he rose in the morning, which was generally very
                    early, to retire for an hour to private prayer and meditation on some part of
                    the Scriptures. He often told his friends, when they asked him how it was
                    possible for him to go through so much fatigue, that it was this practice which
                    gave him spirit and vigour in the business of the day.</p>
                <p>Of his sagacity, and the wonderful penetration with which he often discovered and
                    described, at first sight, such distempers as betray themselves by no symptoms
                    to common eyes, very surprising accounts have been transmitted to us. Yet so far
                    was he from having presumptuous confidence in his own abilities, or from being
                    puffed up by prosperity, that he was condescending to all, and remarkably
                    diligent in his profession. His great skill and celebrity as a physician brought
                    him a large fortune. He left his only surviving daughter two millions of
                    florins.</p>
                <p>The genius of Boerhaave raised the fame of the University of Leydeα, especially
                    as a school of medicine, so as to make it a resort of strangers from every part
                    of Europe. All the princes of Europe sent him disciples, who found in this
                    skilful professor not only an indefatigable teacher, but an affectionate
                    guardian. When Peter the Great went to Holland in 1715, to instruct himself in
                    maritime affairs, he also took lessons from Boerhaave. The reputation of this
                    eminent man was not confined to Europe; a Chinese mandarin wrote him a letter
                    directed “To the illustrious Boerhaave, physician in Europe,” and it reached him
                    in due course. The city of Leyden raised a splendid monument to his memory in
                    the church of St Peter, inscribed “To the health-giving genius of Boerhaave,”
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Salutifero</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Boerhaavπ</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">genio</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Sacrum.</hi></p>
                <p>The principal works of Boerhaave are—(1.) <hi rend="italic">Institutiones</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Medoeoe,</hi> Leyden, 1708; (2.) <hi rend="italic">Aphorismi
                    de</hi><hi rend="italic">cognoscendis</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">curandis Morbis,</hi> Leyden, 1709,—on this work, which was the
                    text-book of Boerhaave’s lectures, Van Swieten published a commentary in 5 vols.
                    4to; (3.) <hi rend="italic">Libellus</hi><hi rend="italic">de Materia</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Medica et Remediorum Formulis,</hi> Leyden, 1719; (4.) <hi
                    rend="italic">Institutiones et Experimenta</hi><hi rend="italic">Chemioe,</hi>
                    Paris, 1724.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
