<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0598-0581-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BÉRANGER, Pierre Jean de</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 3, page 581</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795c7h">Republicanism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cm4s">Gueux</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4k35mg3z">Socialism</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68967">Songs</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4p843w5c">Hand</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1095066">Republicanism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:991032">Lambs</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1126120">Songs</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n598/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BÉRANGER, <hi rend="smallcaps">Pierre Jean de</hi></label>,
                    the national song-writer of France, was born at Paris on the 19th August 1780.
                    The aristocratic particle before the name was a piece of groundless vanity on
                    the part of his father, which the poet found useful as a distinction. He was
                    descended, in truth, from a country innkeeper on the one side, and, on the
                    other, from a tailor in the Rue Montorgueil. Of education, in the narrower
                    sense, he had but little. From the τoof of his first school he beheld the
                    capture of the Bastille, and this stirring memory was all that he acquired.
                    Later on he passed some time in a school at Péronne, founded by one Bellenglise
                    on the principles of Rousseau, where the boys were formed into clubs and
                    regiments, and taught to play solemnly at politics and war. Béranger was
                    president of the club, made speeches before such members of Convention as passed
                    through Péronne, and drew up addresses to Tallien or Robespierre at Paris. In
                    the meanwhile he learned neither Greek nor Latin—not even French, it would
                    appear; for it was after he left school, from the printer Laisney, that he
                    acquired the elements of grammar. His true education was of another sort. In his
                    childhood, shy, sickly, and skilful with his hands, as he sat at home alone to
                    carve cherry stones, he was already forming for himself those habits of
                    retirement and patient elaboration which influenced the whole tenor of his life
                    and the character of all that he wrote. At Péronne he learned of his good aunt
                    to be a stout republican; and from the doorstep of her inn, on quiet evenings,
                    he would listen to the thunder of the guns before Valenciennes, and fortify
                    himself in his passionate love of France and distaste for all things foreign.
                    Although he could never read Horace save in a translation, he had been educated
                    on <hi rend="italic">Telemaque,</hi> Racine, and the dramas of Voltaire, and
                    taught, from a child, in the tradition of all that is highest and most correct
                    in French.</p>
                <p>After serving his aunt for some time in the capacity of waiter, and passing some
                    time also in the printing office of one Laisney, he was taken to Paris by his
                    father. Here he saw much low speculation and many low royalist intrigues. In
                    1802, in consequence of a distressing quarrel, he left his father and began life
                    for himself in the garret of his ever memorable song. For two years he did
                    literaιy hackwork, when he could get it, and wrote pastorals, epics, and all
                    manner of ambitious failures. At the end of that period (1804) he wrote to
                    Lucien Bonaparte, enclosing some of these attempts. He was then in bad health,
                    and in the last stage of misery. His watch was pledged. His wardrobe consisted
                    of one pair of boots, one greatcoat, one pair of trousers with a hole in the
                    knee, and “three bad shirt3 which a friendly hand wearied itself in endeavouring
                    to mend.” The friendly hand was that of Judith Frère, with whom he had been
                    already more or less acquainted since 1796, and who continued to be his faithful
                    companion until her death, three months before his own, in 1857. She must not be
                    confounded with the Lisette of the songs; the pieces addressed to her (Zα <hi
                    rend="italic">Bσnne</hi><hi rend="italic">Vieille, Maudit Printemps,</hi>
                    &amp;c.) are in a very different vein. Lucien Bonaparte interested himself in
                    the young poet, transferred to him his own pension of 1000 francs from the
                    Institute, and set him to work on a <hi rend="italic">Death of Nero.</hi> Five
                    years later, through the same patronage, although indirectly, Béranger became a
                    clerk in the university at a salary of another thousand.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile he had written many songs for convivial occasions, and “to console
                    himself under all misfortunes some, according to Μ. Boiteau, had been already
                    published by his father; but he set no great store on them himself; and it was
                    only in 1812, while watching by the sick-bed of a friend, that it occurred to
                    him to write down the best he could remember. Next year he was elected to the
                    <hi rend="italic">Caveau Moderne,</hi> and his reputation as a song-writer began
                    to spread. Manuscript copies of <hi rend="italic">Les Gueux, Le Sénateur,</hi>
                    above all of <hi rend="italic">Le Roi</hi><hi rend="italic">d</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> ,</hi><hi rend="italic">Yvetot,</hi> a satire against
                    Napoleon, whom he was to magnify so much in the sequel, passed from hand to hand
                    with acclamation. It was thus that all his best works went abroad; one man sang
                    them to another over all the land of France. He was the only poet of modern
                    times who could altogether have dispensed with printing.</p>
                <p>His first collection escaped censure. “We must pardon <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n599/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0599-0582"/> many things to the author of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Hoi d’Yvetot”</hi> said Louis XVIII. The second (1821) was more
                    daring. The apathy of the Liberal camp, he says, had convinced him of the need
                    for some bugle call of awakening. This publication lost him his situation in the
                    university, and subjected him to a trial, a fine of 500 francs, and an
                    imprisonment of three months Imprisonment was a small affair for Béranger. At
                    Sainte Pélagie he occupied a room (it had just been quitted by Paul Louis
                    Courier), warm, well-furnished, and preferable in every way to his own poor
                    lodging, where the water froze on winter nights. He adds, on the occasion of his
                    second imprisonment, that he found a certain charm in this quiet, claustral
                    existence, with its regular hours and long evenings alone over the fire. This
                    second imprisonment of nine months, together with a fine and expenses amounting
                    to 1100 francs, followed on the appearance of his fourth collection. The
                    Government proposed through Laffitte that, if he would submit to judgment
                    without appearing or making defences, he should only be condemned in the
                    smallest penalty. But his public spirit made him refuse the proposal; and he
                    would not even ask permission to pass his term of imprisonment in a <hi
                    rend="italic">Maison</hi><hi rend="italic">de Santé,</hi> although his health
                    was more than •usually feeble at the time. “When you have taken your stand in a
                    contest with Government, it seems to me,” he wrote, “ridiculous to complain of
                    the blows it inflicts on you, and impolitic to furnish it with any occasion of
                    generosity.” His first thought in La Force was to alleviate the condition of the
                    other prisoners.</p>
                <p>In the revolution of July he took no inconsiderable part. Copies of his song, <hi
                    rend="italic">Le</hi><hi rend="italic">Vieux Drapeau,</hi> were served out to
                    the insurgent crowd. He had been for long the intimate friend and adviser of the
                    leading men; and during the decisive week his counsels went a good way towards
                    shaping the ultimate result. “As for the republic, that dream of my whole life,”
                    he wrote in 1831, “I did not wish it should be given to us a second time
                    unripe.” Louis Philippe, hearing how much the songwriter had done towards his
                    elevation, expressed a wish to see and speak with him; but Béranger refused to
                    present himself at court, and used his favour only to ask a place for a friend,
                    and a pension for Rouget de l’Isle, author of the famous <hi rend="italic"
                    >Marseillaise,</hi> who was now old and poor, and whom he had been already
                    succouring for five years.</p>
                <p>In 1848, in spite of every possible expression of his reluctance, he was elected
                    to the assembly, and that by so large a number of votes (4471) that he felt
                    himself obliged to accept the office. Not long afterwards, and with great
                    difficulty, he obtained leave to resign. This was the last public event of
                    Béranger’s life. He continued to polish his songs in retirement, visited by
                    nearly all the famous men of France. He numbered among his friends
                    Chateaubriand, Thiers, Laffitte, Michelet, Lamennais, Mignet. Nothing could
                    exceed the amiability of his private character; so poor a man has rarely been so
                    rich in good actions; he was always ready to receive help from his friends when
                    he was in need, and always forward to help others. His correspondence is full of
                    wisdom and kindness, with a smack of Montaigne, and now and then a vein of
                    pleasantry that will remind the English reader of Charles Lamb. He occupied some
                    of his leisure in preparing his own memoirs, and a certain treatise on <hi
                    rend="italic">Social and Political Morality,</hi> intended for the people, a
                    work he had much at heart’ but judged at last to be beyond his strength. He died
                    on the 16th July 1857. It was feared that his funeral would be the signal for
                    some political disturbance; but the Government took immediate measures, and all
                    went quietly. The streets of Paris were lined with soldiers and full of
                    townsfolk, silent and uncovered. From time to time cries arose :—“<hi
                    rend="italic">Honneur, Honneur à Béranger !”</hi></p>
                <p>The songs of Béranger would scarcely be called songs in England. They are
                    elaborate, written in a clear and sparkling style, full of wit and incision. It
                    is not so much for any lyrical flow as for the happy turn of the phrase that
                    they claim superiority. Whether the subject be gay or serious, light or
                    passionate, the medium remains untroubled. The special merits of the songs are
                    merits to be looked for rather in English prose than in English verse. He worked
                    deliberately, never wrote more than fifteen songs a year and often less, and was
                    so fastidious that he has not preserved a quarter of what he finished. “I am a
                    good little bit of a poet,” he says himself, “clever in the craft, ana a
                    conscientious worker, to whom old airs and a modest choice of subjects <hi
                    rend="italic">(le</hi><hi rend="italic">coin</hi><hi rend="italic">ou je</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">me stιis</hi><hi rend="italic">confiné),</hi> have brought some
                    success.” Nevertheless, he makes a figure of importance in literary history.
                    When he first began to cultivate the <hi rend="italic">chanson,</hi> this minor
                    form lay under some contempt, and was restricted to slight subjects and a
                    humorous guise of treatment. Gradually he filled these little chiseled toys of
                    verbal perfection with ever more and more of sentiment. From a date
                    comparatively early he had determined to sing for the people. It was for this
                    reason that he fled, as far as possible, the houses of his influential friends,
                    and came back gladly to the garret and the street comer. Thus it was, also, that
                    he came to acknowledge obligations to nmile Debraux, who had often stood between
                    him ana the masses as interpreter, and given him the key-note of the popular
                    humour. Now, he had observed in the songs of sailors, and all who labour, a
                    prevailing tone of sadness; and so, as he grew more masterful in this sort of
                    expression, he sought more and more after what is deep, serious, and constant in
                    the thoughts of common men. The evolution was slow; and we can see in his own
                    works examples of every stage, from that of witty indifference in fifty pieces
                    of the first collection, to that of grave and even tragic feeling in <hi
                    rend="italic">Les Souvenirs</hi><hi rend="italic">du Peuple</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">Le</hi><hi rend="italic">Vieux Vagabond.</hi> And this innovation
                    involved another, which was as a sort of prelude to the great romantic movement.
                    For the <hi rend="italic">chanson,</hi> as he says himself, opened up to him a
                    path in which his genius could develop itself at ease; he escaped, by this
                    literary postern, from strict academical requirements, and had at his disposal
                    the whole dictionary, four-fifths of which, according to La Harpe, were
                    forbidden to the use of more regular and pretentious poetry. If he still kept
                    some of the old vocabulary, some of the old imagery, he was yet accustoming
                    people to hear moving subjects treated in a manner more free and simple than
                    heretofore; so that his was a sort of conservative reform, preceding the violent
                    revolution of Victor Hugo and his army of uncompromising romantics. He seems
                    himself to have had glimmerings of some such idea; but he withheld his full
                    approval from the new movement on two grounds :—first, because the romantic
                    school misused somewhat brutally the delicate organism of the French language;
                    and second, as he wrote to Sainte-Beuve in 1832, because they adopted the motto
                    of “Art for art,” and set no object of public usefulness before them as they
                    wrote. For himself (and this is the third point of importance) he had a strong
                    sense of political responsibility. Public interest took a far higher place in
                    his estimation than any private passion or favour. He had little toleration for
                    those erotic poets who sing their own loves and not the common sorrows of
                    mankind, “who forget,” to quote his own words, “forget beside their mistress
                    those who labour before the Lord.” Hence it is that so many of his pieces are
                    political, and so many, in the later times at least, inspired with a socialistic
                    spirit of indignation and revolt. It is by this socialism that he becomes truly
                    modern, and touches hands with Burns.</p>
                <p>The following books may be consulted :— <hi rend="italic">Ma Biographie</hi> (his
                    own memoirs); <hi rend="italic">Vie</hi><hi rend="italic">de Béranger,</hi> by
                    Paul Boiteaπ, 1861; <hi rend="italic">Correspondance de Béranger,</hi> edited by
                    Paul Boiteau, 4 vols. 1860; <hi rend="italic">Béranger et Lamennais</hi> (by
                    Napoléon Peyrat), 1857; <hi rend="italic">Quarante-Cinq lettres de Béranger
                    publiées par Madame Louise</hi><hi rend="italic">Colet.</hi> (almost worthless),
                    1857; <hi rend="italic">Béranger, ses amis, ses ennemis, et scs critiques,</hi>
                    by A. Arnould, 2 vols., 1864; J. Janin, <hi rend="italic">Béranger et son
                    Temps,</hi><hi rend="italic">2</hi> vols., 1866; also Sainte-Beuve’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Portraits Contemporains,</hi> vol. i. (R. L. S.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
