<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0233-0218-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BACON, Roger</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 3, page 218</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b49882p6v">Methodism</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62f7n">Reading</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4zs2kn9v">Tracts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2tc9j">Franciscans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4125q963">Dominicans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="36" ref="fasttopic:825145">Bacon</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:838515">Brewers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1030128">Museums</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1018631">Methodism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n233/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BACON, <hi rend="smallcaps">Roger</hi></label>. The 13th
                    century, an age peculiarly rich in great men, produced few, if any, who can take
                    higher rank than Roger Bacon. He is in every way worthy to be placed beside such
                    thinkers as Albertus Magnus, Bonaventura, and Thomas Aquinas. These had an
                    infinitely wider renown in their day, while he was ignored by his contemporaries
                    and neglected by his successors; but modern criticism has restored the balance
                    in his favour, and is even in danger of going equally far in the opposite
                    direction. Bacon, it is now said, was not appreciated by his age because he was
                    so completely in advance of it; he is a 16th or 17th century philosopher, whose
                    lot has been by some accident cast in the 13th century; he <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n234/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0234-0219"/> is no schoolman, but a modern thinker, whose
                    conceptions of science are more just and clear than are even those of his more
                    celebrated namesake.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See
                    Dühring, <hi rend="italic">Kritische</hi><hi rend="italic">Ges. d. Phil.,</hi>
                    192, 249-51.</p></note> In this view there is certainly a considerable share of
                    truth, but it is much exaggerated. As a general rule, no man can be completely
                    dissevered from his national antecedents and surroundings, and Bacon is not an
                    exception. Those who take up such an extreme position regarding his merits have
                    known too little of the state of contemporary science, and have limited their
                    comparison to the works of the scholastic theologians. We never find in Bacon
                    himself any consciousness of originality; he has no fresh creative thought or
                    method to introduce whereby the face of science may be changed; he is rather a
                    keen and systematic thinker, who is working in a well-beaten track, from which
                    his contemporaries were being drawn by the superior attractions of theology and
                    metaphysics.</p>
                <p>Roger Bacon was born in 1214, near Ilchester, in Somersetshire. His family
                    appears to have been in good circumstances, for he speaks of his brother as
                    wealthy, and he himself expended considerable sums on books and instruments; but
                    in the stormy reign of Henry III. they suffered severely, their property was
                    despoiled, and several members of the family were driven into exile. Roger
                    completed his studies at Oxford, though not, as current traditions assert, at
                    Merton or at Brazenose, neither of those colleges having then been founded. His
                    great abilities were speedily recognised by his contemporaries, and he came to
                    be on terms of close intimacy with some of the most independent thinkers of the
                    time. Of these the most prominent were Adam de Marisco and Robert Grosseteste
                    <hi rend="italic">(Capitd),</hi> afterwards bishop of Lincoln, a man of liberal
                    mind and wide attainments, who had especially devoted himself to mathematics and
                    experimental science.</p>
                <p>Very little is known of Bacon’s life at Oxford; it is said he took orders in
                    1233, and this is not improbable. In the following year, or perhaps later, he
                    crossed over to France, and studied for a considerable length of time at the
                    university of Paris, then the centre of intellectual life in Europe. The years
                    Bacon spent there were unusually stirring. The two great orders, the Franciscans
                    and Dominicans, were in the vigour of youth, and had already begun to take the
                    lead in theological discussion. Alexander of Hales, the author of the great <hi
                    rend="italic">Summa,</hi> was the oracle of the Franciscans, while the rival
                    order rejoiced in Albertus Magnus, and in the rising genius of the angelic
                    doctor, Thomas Aquinas.</p>
                <p>The scientific training which Bacon had received, partly by instruction, but more
                    from the study of the Arab writers, made patent to his eyes the manifold defects
                    in the imposing systems reared by these doctors. It disgusted him to hear from
                    all around him that philosophy was now at length complete, that it had been
                    reduced into compact order, and was being set forth by a certain professor at
                    Paris. Even the great authority on which they reposed, Aristotle, was known but
                    in part, and that part was rendered well-nigh unintelligible through the
                    vileness of the translations; yet not one of those professors would learn Greek
                    so that they might arrive at a real knowledge of their philosopher. The
                    Scriptures, if read at all in the schools, were read in the erroneous versions;
                    but even these were being deserted for theÄwtfence« of Peter Lombard. Physical
                    science, if there was anything deserving that name, was cultivated, not by
                    experiment in the true Aristotelian way, but by discussion and by arguments
                    deduced from premises resting on authority or custom. Everywhere there was a
                    show of knowledge covering and con cealing fundamental ignorance. Bacon,
                    accordingly, who knew what true science was, and who had glimpses of a
                    scientific <hi rend="italic">orqanon</hi> or method, withdrew from the usual
                    scholastic routine, and devoted himself to languages and experimental
                    researches. Among all the instructors with whom he came in contact in Paris,
                    only one gained his esteem and respect; this was an unknown individual, Petrus
                    de Maharncuria Picardus, or of Picardy, probably identical with a certain
                    mathematician, Petrus Peregrinus of Picardy, who is perhaps the author of a MS.
                    treatise, <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Magnete,</hi> contained in
                    the Bibliothèque Impériale at Paris. The contrast between the obscurity of such
                    a man and the fame enjoyed by the fluent young doctors of the schools seems to
                    have roused Bacon’s indignation. In the <hi rend="italic">Opus Minus</hi> and
                    <hi rend="italic">Opus Tertium</hi> he pours forth a violent tirade against
                    Alexander of Hales, and against another professor, not mentioned by name, but
                    spoken of as alive, and blamed even more severely than Alexander. This anonymous
                    writer, he says, who entered the order when young <hi rend="italic"
                    >(puerulιιs),</hi> who had received no proper or systematic instruction in
                    science or philosophy, for he was the first in his order to teach such subjects,
                    acquired his learning by teaching others, and adopted a dogmatic tone, which has
                    caused him to be received at Paris with applause as the equal of Aristotle,
                    Avicenna, or Averroes. He has corrupted philosophy more than any other; he knows
                    nothing of optics or perspective, and yet has presumed to write <hi
                    rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic">naturalibus;</hi> he is ignorant of
                    speculative alchemy, which treats of the origin and generation of things; he,
                    indeed, is a man of infinite industry, who has read and observed much, but all
                    his study is wasted because he is ignorant of the time foundation and method of
                    science.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>It is difficult
                    to identify this unknown professor. Brewer thinks the reference is to Richard of
                    Cornwall; but the little we know of Richard is not in harmony with what is said
                    here, nor with the terms in which he is elsewhere spoken of by Bacon. Erdmann
                    conjectures Thomas Aquinas, which is extremely improbable, as Thomas was
                    unquestionably not the first of his order to study philosophy. Cousin and
                    Charles think that Albertus Magnus is aimed at, and certainly much of what is
                    said applies with peculiar force to him. But some things do not at all cohere
                    with what is otherwise known of Albert. The unknown is said to have received no
                    regular philosophic training; we know that Albert did. The unknown entered the
                    order when very young; unless the received date of Albert’s birth be false, he
                    did not enter till nearly twenty-eight years of age. Albert, too, could not be
                    said with justice to be utterly ignorant of alchemy, and his mechanical
                    inventions are well known. It is worth pointing out that Brewer, in transcribing
                    the passage bearing on this <hi rend="italic">(Op. Ined.</hi> p. 327), has the
                    words <hi rend="italic">Fratrum puerulus,</hi> which in his marginal note he
                    interprets as applying to the Franciscan order. In this case, of course, Albert
                    could not be the person referred to, as he was a Dominican. But Charles, in his
                    transcription, entirely omits the important word <hi rend="italic">Fratrum.</hi>
                    There are other instances in which Brewer and Charles do not agree, <hi
                    rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> according to Brewer, Bacon speaks of Thomas and Albert
                    as <hi rend="italic">puen</hi><hi rend="italic">duorum ordinum</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> according to Charles, he says, <hi rend="italic"
                    >primi</hi><hi rend="italic">duorum</hi><hi rend="italic">ordinum</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> a discrepancy not unimportant.</p></note></p>
                <p>It is probable that Bacon, during his stay in Paris, acquired considerable
                    renown. He took the degree of doctor of theology, and seems to have received
                    from his contemporaries the complimentary title of <hi rend="italic"
                    >doctor</hi><hi rend="italic">mirabilis.</hi> In 1250 he was again at Oxford,
                    and probably about this time, though the exact date cannot be fixed, he entered
                    the Franciscan order. His fame spread very rapidly at Oxford, though it was
                    mingled with suspicions of his dealings in magic and the black arts, and with
                    some doubts of his orthodoxy. About 1257, Bonaventura, general of the order,
                    interdicted his lectures at Oxford, and commanded him to leave that town and
                    place himself under the superintendence of the body at Paris. Here for ten years
                    he remained under constant supervision, suffering great privations, and strictly
                    prohibited from writing anything which might be published. But during the time
                    he had been at Oxford his fame had reached the ears of the Papal legate in
                    England, Guy de Foulques, a man of culture and scientific tastes, who in 1265
                    was raised to the papal chair as Clement IV. In the following year he wrote to
                    Bacon, who had been already in communication with him, ordering him,
                    notwithstanding <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n235/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0235-0220"/> any injunctions from his superiors, to write out
                    and send to him a treatise on the sciences which he had already asked of him
                    when papal legate. Bacon, who in despair of being ever able to communicate his
                    results to the world, had neglected to compose anything, and whose previous
                    writings had been mostly scattered tracts, <hi rend="italic">capitula</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">quadam,</hi> took fresh courage from this command of the Pope.
                    Relying on his powerful protection, he set at naught the many obstacles thrown
                    in his way by the jealousy of his superiors and brother friars, and despite the
                    want of funds, instruments, materials for copying, and skilled copyists,
                    completed in about eighteen months three large treatises, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Opus</hi><hi rend="italic">Majus,</hi><hi rend="italic">Opus Minus,</hi> and
                    <hi rend="italic">Opus Tertium,</hi> which, with some other tracts, waere
                    despatched to the Pope by the hands of one Joannes, a young man trained and
                    educated with great care by Bacon himself.</p>
                <p>The composition of such extensive works in so short a time is a marvellous feat.
                    We do not know what opinion Clement formed of them, but before his death he
                    seems to have bestirred himself on Bacon’s behalf, for in 1268 the latter was
                    released and permitted to return to Oxford. Here he continued his labours in
                    experimental science, and also in the composition of complete treatises. The
                    works sent to Clement he regarded as mere preliminaries, laying down principles
                    which were afterwards to be applied to the several sciences. The first part of
                    an encyclopaedic work probably remains to us in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Compendium</hi><hi rend="italic">Studii Philosophice,</hi> belonging to the
                    year 1271. In this work Bacon makes a vehement attack upon the ignorance and
                    vices of the clergy and monks, and generally upon the insufficiency of the
                    existing studies. In 1278 he underwent the punishment which seems to have then
                    been the natural consequence of outspoken opinions. His books were condemned by
                    Jerome de Ascoli, general of the Franciscans, a gloomy bigot, who afterwards
                    became Pope, and the unfortunate philosopher was thrown into prison, where he
                    remained for fourteen years. During this time, it is said, he wrote the small
                    tract <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Retardandis Senectutis
                    Accidentibus,</hi> but this is merely a tradition. In 1292, as appears from what
                    is probably his latest composition, the <hi rend="italic">Compendium</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Studii Theologice,</hi> he was again at liberty. The exact time of
                    his death cannot be determined; 1294 is probably as accurate a date as can be
                    fixed upon.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Bacon's Works.—</hi> Leland has said that it is easier to
                    collect the leavee of the Sibyl than the titles of the works written by Roger
                    Bacon; and though the labour has been somewhat lightened by the publications of
                    Brewer and Charles, referred to below, it is no easy matter even now to form an
                    accurate idea of his actual productions. His writings, so far as known to us,
                    may be divided into two classes, those yet in manuscript and those printed. An
                    enormous number of MSS. are known to exist in British and French libraries, and
                    probably all have not yet been discovered. Many are transcripts of works or
                    portions of works already published, and therefore require no notice. Of the
                    others, several are of first-rate value for the comprehension of Bacon’s
                    philosophy, and, though extracts from them have been given by Charles, it is
                    clear that till they have found an editor, no representation of his philosophy
                    can be complete.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The
                    more important MSS. are :—(1.; The extensive work on the fundamental notions of
                    physics, called <hi rend="italic">Communia Naturalium,</hi> which is found in
                    the Mazarin Library at Paris, in the British Museum, and in the Bodleian and
                    University College Libraries at Oxford; (2.) On the fundamental notions of
                    mathematics, <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Communibus</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Mathematical,</hi> part of which is in the Sloane collection, part
                    in the Bodleian; (3.) <hi rend="italic">Baconis</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Physica,</hi> contained among the additional MSS. in the British Museum; (4.)
                    The fragment called <hi rend="italic">Quinta Pars</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Compendii Theologice,</hi> in the Brit. Mus.; (5.) the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Metaphysica,</hi> in the Biblioth. Impér. at Paris; (6.) The <hi rend="italic"
                    >Compendium</hi><hi rend="italic">Studii Theologice,</hi> in the Brit. Mus.;
                    (7.) The logical fragments, such as the <hi rend="italic">Summa
                    Dialectices,</hi> in the Bodleian, and the glosses upon Aristotle’s physics and
                    metaphysics in the library at Amiens.</p></note></p>
                <p>The works hitherto printed (neglecting reprints) are the following :—(1.) <hi
                    rend="italic">Speculum</hi><hi rend="italic">Alchimioe,</hi> 1541—translated
                    into English, 1597; (2.) <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Mirabili</hi><hi rend="italic">Potestate Artis</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">N^aturce,</hi> 1542—English translation, 1659; (3.) <hi
                    rend="italic">Libellus</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Retardandis Senectutis Accidentibus,</hi> 1590—translated as the “Cure of Old
                    Age,” 1683; (4.) <hi rend="italic">Sanioris</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Medicines</hi><hi rend="italic">Magistri</hi><hi rend="italic">D. Rogeri
                    Baconis Anglici de Arte Chymice</hi><hi rend="italic">Scripta,</hi> 1603—a
                    collection of small tracts containing <hi rend="italic">Excerpta</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic">Libro</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Avicennoe</hi><hi rend="italic">de Anima, Breve</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Breviarium, Verbum</hi><hi rend="italic">Abbreviatum,<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>At the close of the <hi rend="italic">Verb.
                    Abbreυ.</hi> is a curious note, concluding with the words, “<hi rend="italic"
                    >ipse Bogerus</hi><hi rend="italic">fuit discipulus fratris</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Alberti 1"</hi></p></note></hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    2</hi><hi rend="italic">Secretum Secretorum, Tractatus Trium Verborum,</hi> and
                    <hi rend="italic">Speculum Secretorum;</hi> (5.) <hi rend="italic"
                    >Perspectiva,</hi> 1614, which is the fifth part of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Opus</hi><hi rend="italic">Majus</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> (6.) <hi
                    rend="italic">Specula</hi><hi rend="italic">Mathematica,</hi> which is the
                    fourth part of the same; (7.) <hi rend="italic">Opus</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Majus</hi><hi rend="italic">ad</hi><hi rend="italic">Clementem</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">IV.,</hi> edited by Jebb, 1733; (8.) <hi rend="italic"
                    >Opera</hi><hi rend="italic">hactenus Inedita,</hi> by J. S. Brewer, 1859,
                    containing the <hi rend="italic">Opus Tertium, Opus Minus, Compendium</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Studii Philosophice,</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Secretis Operibus</hi><hi rend="italic">Naturae.</hi></p>
                <p>How these works stand related to one another can only be determined by internal
                    evidence, and this is a somewhat hazardous method. The smaller -works, which are
                    chiefly on alchemy, are unimportant, and the dates of their composition cannot
                    be ascertained. It is known that before the <hi rend="italic">Opus</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Majus</hi> Bacon had already written some tracts, among which an
                    unpublished work, <hi rend="italic">Computus</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Naturalium,</hi> on chronology, belongs probably to the year 1263; while, if
                    the dedication of the <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Secretis
                    Operibus</hi> be authentic, that short treatise must have been composed before
                    1249.</p>
                <p>It is, however, with the <hi rend="italic">Opus</hi><hi rend="italic">Majus</hi>
                    that Bacon’s real activity begins. That great work, which has been called by
                    WheweU at once the Encyclopaedia and the Organum of the 13th century, requires a
                    much fuller notice than can here be given. As published by Jebb it consists of
                    six parts; there should, however, be a seventh, <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Morali Philosophia,</hi> frequently referred to in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Opus Tertium.</hi> Part I. (pp. 1-22), which is sometimes
                    designated <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Utilitate
                    Scientiarum,</hi> treats of the four <hi rend="italic">offendicula,</hi> or
                    causes of error. These are, authority, custom, the opinion of the unskilled
                    many, and the concealment of real ignorance with show or pretence of knowledge.
                    The last error is the most dangerous, and is, in a sense, the cause of all the
                    others. The <hi rend="italic">offendicula</hi> have sometimes been looked upon
                    as an anticipation of the more celebrated doctrine of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Idola</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> the two classifications, however, have
                    little in common. In the summary of this part, contained in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Opus Tertium,</hi> Bacon shows very clearly his perception of the
                    unity of science, and the necessity of an encyclopaedical treatment. “Nam omnes
                    scientiae sunt annexae, et mutuis se fovent auxiliis, sicut partes ejusdem
                    totius, quarum quaelibet opus suum peragit, non solum propter se, sed pro
                    aliis.”— <hi rend="italic">(Op.</hi><hi rend="italic">Ined.,</hi> p. 18.)</p>
                <p>Part II. (pp. 23-43) treats of the relation between philosophy and theology. All
                    true wisdom is contained in the Scriptures, at least implicitly; and the true
                    end of philosophy is to rise from the imperfect knowledge of created things to a
                    knowledge of the Creator. Ancient philosophers, who had not the Scriptures,
                    received direct illumination from God, and only thus can the brilliant results
                    attained by them be accounted for.</p>
                <p>Part III. (pp. 44-57) treats of the utility of grammar, and the necessity of a
                    true linguistic science for the adequate comprehension either of the Scriptures
                    or of books on philosophy. The necessity of accurate acquaintance with any
                    foreign language, and of obtaining good texts, is a subject Bacon is never weary
                    of descanting upon. He lays down very clearly the requisites of a good
                    translator; he should know thoroughly the language he is translating <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n236/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0236-0221"/> from, the language into which he is translating,
                    and the subject of which the book treats.</p>
                <p>Part IV. (57-255) contains an elaborate treatise on mathematics, “the alphabet of
                    philosophy,” and on -its importance in science and theology. Bacon shows at
                    great length that all the sciences rest ultimately on mathematics, and progress
                    only when their facts can be subsumed under mathematical principles. This
                    singularly fruitful thought he exemplifies and illustrates by showing how
                    geometry is applied to the action of natural bodies, and demonstrating by
                    geometrical figures certain laws of physical forces. He also shows how his
                    method may be used to determine some curious and long-discussed problems, such
                    as the light of the stars, the ebb and flow of the tide, the motion of the
                    balance. He then proceeds to adduce elaborate and sometimes slightly grotesque
                    reasons tending to prove that mathematical knowledge is essential in theology,
                    and closes this section of his work with two comprehensive sketches of geography
                    and astronomy. That on geography is particularly good, and is interesting as
                    having been read by Columbus, who lighted on it in Petrus de Alliaco’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Imago Mundi,</hi> and was strongly influenced by its
                    reasoning.</p>
                <p>Part V. (pp. 256-357) treats of perspective. This was the part of his work on
                    which Bacon most prided himself, and in it, we may add, he seems to owe most to
                    the Arab writers Alkindi and Alhazen. The treatise opens with an able sketch of
                    psychology, founded upon, but in some important respects varying from,
                    Aristotle’s <hi rend="italic">De Anima.</hi> The anatomy of the eye is next
                    described; this is done well and evidently at first hand, though the functions
                    of the parts are not given with complete accuracy. Many other points of
                    physiological optics are touched on, in general erroneously. Bacon then
                    discusses very fully vision in a right line, the laws of reflection and
                    refraction, and the construction of mirrors and lenses. In this part of the
                    work, as in the preceding, his reasoning depends essentially upon his peculiar
                    view of natural agents and their activities. His fundamental physical maxims are
                    matter and force; the latter he calls <hi rend="italic">virtus,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">species, imago</hi><hi rend="italic">agentis,</hi> and by
                    numberless other names. Change, or any natural phenomenon, is produced by the
                    impression of a virtus or species on matter—the result being the thing known.
                    Physical action is, therefore, <hi rend="italic">impression,</hi> or
                    transmission of force in lines, and must accordingly be explained geometrically.
                    This view of nature Bacon considered fundamental, and it lies, indeed, at the
                    root of his whole philosophy. To the short notices of it given in the 4th and
                    5th parts of the <hi rend="italic">Opus</hi><hi rend="italic">Majus,</hi> he
                    subjoined two, or perhaps three, extended accounts of it. We possess at least
                    one of these in the tract <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Multiplicatione</hi><hi rend="italic">Specierum,</hi> printed as part of the
                    <hi rend="italic">Opus</hi><hi rend="italic">Majus</hi> by Jebb (pp. 358-444).
                    We cannot do more than refer to Charles for discussions as to how this theory of
                    nature is connected with the metaphysical problems of force and matter, with the
                    logical doctrine of universals, and in general with Bacon’s theory of
                    knowledge.</p>
                <p>Part VI. (pp. 445-477) treats of experimental science, <hi rend="italic"
                    >“</hi><hi rend="italic">domina</hi><hi rend="italic">omnium</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">scientiarum.”</hi> There are two methods of knowledge: the one by
                    argument, the other by experience. Mere argument is never sufficient; it may
                    decide a question, but gives no satisfaction or certainty to the mind, which can
                    only be convinced by immediate inspection or intuition. Now this is what
                    experience gives. But experience is of two sorts, external and internal; the
                    first is that usually called experiment, but it can give no complete knowledge
                    even of corporeal things, much less of spiritual. On the other hand, in inner
                    experience the mind is illuminated by the divine truth, and of this supernatural
                    enlightenment there are seven grades.</p>
                <p>• Experimental science, which in the <hi rend="italic">Opus Tertium</hi> (p. 46)
                    is distinguished from the speculative sciences and the operative arts in a way
                    that forcibly reminds us of Francis Bacon, is said to have three great <hi
                    rend="italic">prerogatives</hi> over all other sciences :—(1.) It verifies their
                    conclusions by direct experiment; (2.) It discovers truths which they could
                    never reach; (3.) It investigates the secrets of nature, and opens to us a
                    knowledge of past and future. As an instance of his method, Bacon gives an
                    investigation into the nature and cause of the rainbow, which is really a very
                    fine specimen of inductive research.</p>
                <p>The seventh part of the <hi rend="italic">Opus</hi><hi rend="italic">Majus,</hi>
                    not given in Jebb’s edition, is noticed at considerable length in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Opus</hi><hi rend="italic">Tertium</hi> (cap. xiv.) Extracts from
                    it are given by Charles, (pp. 339-348).</p>
                <p>As has been seen, Bacon had no sooner finished this elaborate work than he began
                    to prepare a summary to be sent along with it. Of this summary, or <hi
                    rend="italic">Opus Minus,</hi> part has come down and is published in Brewer’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Op. Ined.</hi> (313-389), from what appears to be the only MS.
                    The work was intended to contain an abstract of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Opus</hi><hi rend="italic">Majus,</hi> an account of the principal vices of
                    theology, and treatises on speculative and practical alchemy. At the same time,
                    or immediately after, Bacon began a third work as a preamble to the other two,
                    giving their general scope and aim, but supplementing them in many points. The
                    part of this work, generally called <hi rend="italic">Opus Tertium,</hi> is
                    printed by Brewer (pp. 1-310), who considers it to be a complete treatise.
                    Charles, however, has given good grounds for supposing that it is merely a
                    preface, and that the work went on to discuss grammar, logic (which Bacon
                    thought of little service, as reasoning was innate), mathematics, general
                    physics, metaphysics, and moral philosophy. He founds his argument mainly on
                    passages in the <hi rend="italic">Communia</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Naturalium,</hi> which indeed prove distinctly that it was sent to Clement, and
                    cannot, therefore, form part of the <hi rend="italic">Compendium,</hi> as Brewer
                    seems to think. It must be confessed, however, that nothing can well be more
                    confusing than the references in Bacon’s works, and it seems well-nigh hopeless
                    to attempt a complete arrangement of them until the texts have been collated and
                    carefully printed.</p>
                <p>All these large works Bacon appears to have looked on as preliminaries,
                    introductions, leading to a great work which should embrace the principles of
                    all the sciences. This great work, which is perhaps the frequently referred to
                    <hi rend="italic">Liber Sex</hi><hi rend="italic">Scientiarum,</hi> he began,
                    and a few fragments still indicate its outline. First appears to have come the
                    treatise now called <hi rend="italic">Compendium</hi><hi rend="italic">Studii
                    Philosophice</hi> (Brewer, pp. 393-519), containing an account of the causes of
                    error, and then entering at length upon grammar. After that, apparently, logic
                    was to be treated; then, possibly, mathematics and physics; then speculative
                    alchemy and experimental science. It is, however, very difficult, in the present
                    state of our knowledge of the MSS., to hazard even conjectures as to the
                    contents and nature of this last and most comprehensive work.</p>
                <p>Bacon’s fame in popular estimation has always rested on his mechanical
                    discoveries. Careful research has shown that very little in this department can
                    with accuracy be ascribed to him. He certainly describes a method of
                    constructing a telescope, but not so as to lead one to conclude that he was in
                    possession of that instrument. Gunpowder, the invention of which has been
                    claimed for him on the ground of a passage in his works, which fairly
                    interpreted at once disposes of any such claim, was already known to the Arabs.
                    Burning-glasses were in common use, and spectacles it does not appear he made,
                    although he was probably acquainted with the principle of their construction.
                    His wonderful predictions (in the <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Secretis')</hi> must be taken <hi rend="italic">cum</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >grano</hi><hi rend="italic">salis</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and it is not to
                    be forgotten that he believed in astrology, in the doctrine of signatures, and
                    in the philosopher’s stone, and <hi rend="italic">knew</hi> that the circle had
                    been squared.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n237/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0237-0222"/>
                <p>The best work on Koger Bacon is undoubtedly that of E. Charles, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Roger Bacon,</hi><hi rend="italic">sa</hi><hi rend="italic">Vie,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">scs Ouvrages, ses</hi><hi rend="italic">Doctrines cC</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">après des textes inédits,</hi> 1861. Against the somewhat
                    enthusiastic estimate and modern interpretation given in this work, Schneider in
                    his <hi rend="italic">Roger Bacon,</hi><hi rend="italic">Eine Monographie,</hi>
                    Augsburg, 1873, has reclaimed. He points out very clearly certain aspects in
                    which Bacon appears as a mere scholastic. The new matter contained in the
                    publications of Charles and Brewer was summarised by H. Siebert, <hi
                    rend="italic">Roger Bacon: Inaugural Dissertation,</hi> Harburg, 1861. <hi
                    rend="italic">Of.</hi> also, J. K. Ingram, <hi rend="italic">On the Opus</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Majus</hi><hi rend="italic">of Bacon,</hi> Dublin, 1858; Cousin,
                    <hi rend="italic">Fragments, Phil,</hi><hi rend="italic">du Moyen</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Age</hi> (reprinted from <hi rend="italic">Journal des
                    Savans,</hi> 1848); Saisset, <hi rend="italic">Précurseurs et</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Disciples de Descartes,</hi> pp. 1-58 (reprinted from <hi
                    rend="italic">Revue de Deux Mondes,</hi> 1861); Prantl, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Gesell. der Logik,</hi> iii. 120-129 (a severe criticism of Bacon’s logical
                    doctrines). (R. AD.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
