<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0409-0394-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BARRISTERS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 3, page 394</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4sj19s90">Students</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz36">Inns</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:881212">Counseling</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1085637">Queens</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1136041">Students</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:796146">Acting</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n409/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BARRISTERS</label>, in England, are the highest class of
                    lawyers who have exclusive audience in all the superior courts. Every barrister
                    must be a member of one of the four ancient societies called Inns of Court,
                    viz., Lincoln’s Inn, the Inner and Middle Temples, and Gray’s Inn. The existence
                    of these societies as schools can be traced back to the 13th century, and their
                    rise is attributed to the clause in Magna Charta, by which the Common Pleas were
                    fixed at Westminster instead of following the king’s court, and the professors
                    of law were consequently brought together in London. Associations of lawyers
                    acquired houses of their own in which students were educated in the common law,
                    and the degrees of barrister (corresponding to apprentice or bachelor) and
                    sergeant (corresponding to doctor) were conferred. These schools of law are now
                    represented by the Inns of Court, which still enjoy the exclusive privilege of
                    calling to the bar, and through their superior order of <hi rend="italic"
                    >benchers</hi> control the discipline of the profession.</p>
                <p>Every person not otherwise disqualified may be admitted as a student of law by
                    passing a general examination in London, or on producing evidence of his having
                    passed a public examination at a university. The year is divided into four
                    terms, and every student must keep twelve terms before he can be called to the
                    bar. A term is kept by the student’s dining six (if a university man, three)
                    times in the hall of his society. Until quite recently the Inns of Court
                    exercised little or no supervision over the legal education of their students.
                    Any student who had duly kept his terms might be admitted to the bar on
                    producing either a certificate of having passed the general examination of the
                    Council of Legal Education, or a certificate of attendance at certain public
                    lectures, or of having read in the chambers of a barrister or special pleader
                    for at least twelve months. The examination not being compulsory, was only used
                    as a qualification for call by a minority of students, and neither of the other
                    tests afforded any security as to the applicant’s fitness for admission. The
                    regulations both as to legal education and examinations have been very greatly
                    altered. A complete staff of public lecturers and tutors has been established,
                    and every student must pass an examination in jurisprudence, civil and
                    international law, and English law, before being admitted to his call. Persons
                    connected with the law in any inferior capacity (such as that of solicitor and
                    solicitor’s clerk), or with trade, will not be admitted as students; and the
                    benchers, besides, have the right of rejecting any applicant with or without
                    cause assigned. For sufficient reasons, and subject to an appeal to the Common
                    Law judges as visitors, they may reject the petition of a student to be called
                    to the bar, or expel from their society and from the profession any barrister or
                    bencher of the inn. This power has been exercised in several cases within recent
                    years, and the bencher3 appear to take cognizance of any kind of misconduct,
                    whether professional or not, which they may deem unworthy of the rank of
                    barrister. The age at which a student may be called to the bar is twenty-one
                    years.</p>
                <p>The peculiar business of barristers is the advocacy of causes in open court, but
                    in England a great deal of other business falls into their hands. They are the
                    chief conveyancers, and the <hi rend="italic">pleadings (i.e.,</hi> the counter
                    statements of parties previous to joining issue) are in all but the simplest
                    cases drafted <hi rend="subscript"> ι</hi> by them. There is, indeed, a separate
                    class of <hi rend="italic">conveyancers</hi> and <hi rend="italic">special
                    pleaders,</hi> being persons who have kept the necessary number of terms
                    qualifying for a call, but who, instead of being called, take out licences to
                    practise <hi rend="italic">under the bar.</hi> There are still a few persons who
                    act under such special licences, but in general conveyancing and special
                    pleading form part of the ordinary work of a junior barrister. The highest rank
                    among barristers is that of king’s or queen’s counsel. They lead the case in
                    court, and give opinions on cases submitted to them, but they do not accept
                    conveyancing or pleading, nor do they admit pupils to their chambers. Precedence
                    among queen’s counsel, as well as among outer barristers, is determined by
                    seniority. The order of sergeants at law still exists, but no new appointments
                    have recently been made, and it will probably be allowed to become extinct, the
                    title of queen’s counsel being generally preferred. Sergeants rank after queen’s
                    counsel. Although every barrister has a right to practise in any court in
                    England, it will be found, in fact, that each special class of business has its
                    own practitioners, so much so indeed, that the bar may almost be said to be
                    divided into several professions. The most marked distinction is that between
                    barristers practising in Chancery and barristers practising in the courts of
                    Common Law. The fusion of Law 'and Equity contemplated by the Judicature Act,
                    1873, may be expected in course of time to break down this distinction; but for
                    many years there has been a complete separation between these two great branches
                    of the profession. There are also subordinate distinctions in each branch.
                    Counsel at Common Law attach themselves to one or other of the circuits into
                    which England is divided, and may not practise elsewhere unless under special
                    conditions. In Chancery the queen’s counsel for the most part restrict
                    themselves to one or other of the courts of first instance (those of the
                    Vice-Chancellors or Master of the Rolls). Business before the court of
                    Admiralty, the court of Probate and Divorce, the Privy Council, and
                    parliamentary committees, exhibits, though in a less degree, the same tendency
                    to specialization. In some of the larger provincial towns there are now local
                    bars of considerable strength. In Manchester and Liverpool alone there are
                    believed to be between seventy and eighty practising barristers; and the
                    probable extension of this system cannot fail to have a most important influence
                    on the future character of the profession. The bar of Ireland exhibits in its
                    general arrangements the same features as the bar of England. Every Irish
                    barrister must have kept at least six terms in one of the English Inns of Court.
                    There is no connection whatever between the Scotch and English bars.</p>
                <p>Counsel is not answerable for anything spoken by him relative to the cause in
                    hand and suggested in the client’s instructions, even though it should reflect
                    on the character of another and prove absolutely groundless, but if he mention
                    an untruth of his own invention, or even upon instructions if it be impertinent
                    to the matter in hand, he is then liable to an action from the party injured.
                    Counsel may also be punished by the summary power of the court or judge as for a
                    contempt, and by the benchers of the inn to which he may belong on cause
                    shown.</p>
                <p>The rank of barrister is a necessary qualification for nearly all offices of a
                    judicial character, and a very usual <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n410/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0410-0395"/> qualification for other important appointments.
                    Not only the judgeships in the Superior Courts of Law and Equity at home and in
                    the colonies, but nearly all the magistracies of minor rank—recorderships,
                    county court judgeships, &lt;fcc., —are restricted to the bar. The result is a
                    unique feature in the English system of justice, viz., the perfect harmony of
                    opinion and interest between the bar as a profession and all degrees of the
                    judicial bench.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Revising Barristers</hi> are counsel of not less than seven
                    years’ standing appointed to revise the lists of parliamentary voters.</p>
                <p>Barristers cannot maintain an action for their fees, which are regarded as
                    gratuities, nor can they, by the usage of the profession, undertake a case
                    without the intervention of an attorney.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
