<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0477-0462-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BEARD</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 3, page 462</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:829278">Beards</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:921600">Fashion</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:950823">Hand</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="26" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vm0g">Beard</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b41834b98">Wards</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b40000538">Islam</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4g44hs7q">Fashion</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4p843w5c">Hand</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4t14tq07">Hair</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204236">Israel</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n477/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BEARD</label>. The tradition that Adam was created with a
                    beard (which may be described as bushy rather than flowing), is recorded on
                    ancient monuments, and especially on an antique sarcophagus, which is one of the
                    ornaments of the Vatican. The Jews, with the Orientals generally, seem to have
                    accepted the tradition for a law. The beard was a cherished and a sacred thing.
                    Israel brought it safe out of the bondage of universally shaven Egypt, and the
                    beard was the outward and visible sign of a true man. To rudely touch his beard
                    was to cruelly assail his dignity. Children and other kinsfolk might gently
                    touch it as a sign of love; a fugitive might reverentially raise his hand to it
                    when praying for succour; and he who put his hand on his own beard and swore by
                    it bound himself by the most solemn of oaths, to violate which would render him
                    infamous among his fellow-men. To touch the beard in the allegiance of love
                    established peace and trustfulness between the two parties. When Joab went in to
                    Amasa he took the beard of the latter to kiss him, saying the while, “Art thou
                    in health, my brother <hi rend="italic">1”</hi> Therefore it was that Amasa took
                    no heed of the sword in Joab’s hand, which Joab at once thrust beneath the
                    other’s fifth rib. The Scriptures abound with examples of how the beard and its
                    treatment interpreted the feelings, the joy, the sorrow, the pride, or the
                    despondency of the wearer.</p>
                <p>Although the Jews carried their beards with them from their bondage in Egypt, the
                    Egyptians were not at all insensible of the significance of that appendage. They
                    did not despise the type of manhood. Accordingly, on days of high festival they
                    wore false beards, as assertions of their dignity in the scheme of creation, and
                    they represented their male deities with beards “tip-tilted” at the ends. The
                    general reader having laudable curiosity on this matter may be safely referred
                    to the pages of Herodotus,—a writer who has much to say pertinently to the
                    subject, and who, after being maligned as the second father of lies, is now
                    praised for his modesty, and relied on for his trustworthiness.</p>
                <p>The modern Mahometans, especially those who have most come in contact with
                    Europeans, have a good deal fallen away from old conservative ideas respecting
                    the beard. Once, this glorious excrescence, as it was held to be, was made, by
                    the followers of Islam, a help to salvation. The hairs which came from it in
                    combing were preserved, broken in two, and then buried. The breaking was a sort
                    of stipulation with some angel who was supposed to be on the watch, and who
                    would look to the safe passage of the consigners of the treasure into the
                    paradise of never-failing sherbet and ever-blooming houris. The first sultan who
                    broke through the orthodox oppression of beardedness was Selim I. (1512-20).
                    This act was a violent shock to the whole body of the faithful, and especially
                    of the Mufti. The very highest priest alone could dare to remonstrate with so
                    absolute a monarch. Selim put aside the remonstrance with a joke, <hi
                    rend="italic">“I</hi> have cut off my beard,” he said, “in order that my vizier
                    may have nothing to lead me by!” But a crafty minister can find on the face of
                    the most beardless and cruel of despots wherewithal to lead him in the way the
                    minister would have him go. Still, the fact that the Prophet never let razor
                    reap a harvest on his chin, for possession of the hairy produce of which all
                    Islam would have fought with affectionate fury, long made, and still makes, the
                    beard a part of religion. The sultan and the shah, chiefs of the two parties in
                    their church, have pretty fair apologies for beards; but this is far below the
                    bearded glories of the days before the Prophet, when the kings of Persia tied up
                    their bearded plaits with gold thread, and the princes of Nineveh went abroad
                    with beards curled and oiled, like the Assyrian bulls themselves. It has been
                    said that in Asia wars have been proclaimed on alleged grievances connected with
                    sharing. Tartars and Persians, and Chinese and Tartars, are reported to have
                    resorted to sanguinary arbitration on the question of clipping or shaving.
                    Probably they who declared the war were as clever in finding a pretext as the
                    more civilized aggressors of much later days.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n478/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0478-0463"/>
                <p>It we turn to Europe and begin with classical times, having—</p>
                <p>the wealth of Ormus and of Ind,</p>
                <p>Or where the gorgeous East, with richest hand, Showers on her kings barbaric
                    pearl and gold,—</p>
                <p>we may remember that the Greeks and Romans once styled as barbarians, or bearded,
                    unshaven savages, all nations who were out of the pale of their own customs and
                    religion. Nevertheless, the young Roman, anxious for beard and moustache, used
                    to apply the household oil to his chin and cheeks, in order to bring thereon
                    that incipient fringe which would entitle him to be called “.barbatulus.” The
                    full-furnished man was “barbatus.” It was not till the beard ceased to be
                    universally worn, and Sicilian barbers set up in Rome (about 300 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi>), that the Romans began to apply the word, translated
                    “barbarous,” to the rude men and manners of the early ages, and of the beard
                    universal. But, after all, we may still see, in old counterfeit presentments,
                    that the fashionable, clipped beard of young Roman “swells” in the last days of
                    the Republic, and of some of the emperors from the .time of Hadrian, is not
                    nearly so majestic as the flowing hair depending from the chin of Numa
                    Pompilius. Nero offered some of the hair of his beard to Jupiter Capitolinus,
                    who could have furnished a dozen emperors from his own. Homer, Virgil, Pliny,
                    Plutarch, Strabo, Diodorus, Juvenal, Persius, are among the writers who furnish
                    material for a volume on beards. One Roman emperor, Julian, wrote a work on the
                    subject, which is commonly supposed to be as fierce a denunciation against
                    beards, as King James’s <hi rend="italic">Blast</hi> was against tobacco; but
                    Julian in his <hi rend="italic">Misopogon,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Enemy of
                    the Beard,</hi> descants satirically “with pleasure and even with pride,” says
                    Gibbon, “on the length of his nails and the inky blackness of his hands,
                    protests that although the greatest part of his body was covered with hair, the
                    use of the razor was confined to his head alone, and celebrated with visible
                    complacency the shaggy and <hi rend="italic">populous</hi> beard which he fondly
                    cherished, after the example of the philosophers of Greece.” Persius undoubtedly
                    associated wisdom with the beard. He exhausted the whole vocabulary of praise
                    when he designated Socrates by the term <hi rend="italic">Magister</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Barbatus.</hi> In this, however, there is less wit than in the
                    rejoinder of the young ambassador to a king, who had expressed his wrath at
                    having a beardless youth sent to him as an envoy. “If,” said the latter, “my
                    master had thought you would have laid so much account on a beard, he would have
                    sent you a goat.”</p>
                <p>The most notable circumstance in the history of the beard among the Greeks is
                    that of its abolition,—in the Macedonian army, at least, for strategic reasons.
                    Alexander the Great abolished the beards of his soldiers, for the sufficient
                    reason that they gave handles to their enemies whereby to lay hold of them. The
                    Macedonian warriors probably obeyed with reluctance; but obedience was as much a
                    matter of course as it was with the Ephori who, by Lacedaemonian law, had to
                    undergo what seemed the ridiculous ceremony of being shaved, merely to show
                    their ready obedience to legal enactment. As they were mortal men, it may be
                    supposed that acquisition of office was happy compensation for the loss of a
                    beard.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Goth</hi> is equivalent for the older term of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Barbarian.</hi> One is about as unjust in its application as the other. Gothic
                    rudeness is often illustrated by the case of the “ugly rush” made by the
                    northern warriors into the Capitol, where the conscript fathers sat in silence
                    and fearlessness, waiting events. One of these unlettered soldiers lifted his
                    hand to the beard of an old legislator, who, taking it for insult, smote the
                    Goth to the ground. Let us do the Goth the justice of believing that, awed by
                    the stern mute majesty of the senators, he raised his hand reverentially to the
                    beard. At all events, the taking it with such prompt and painful action was
                    dearly paid for in the swift retaliation which followed.</p>
                <p>If the phrase be not too light for use, we would say that as beards existed
                    before barbers, the Europeans, like all other people, were originally a bearded
                    people. The beard is perhaps more general now in Germany than elsewhere in
                    Europe; and Germany affords an example of the longest beard known, out of fairy
                    story, in the person of the painter Johan Mayo, whose beard was so long that
                    when he stood upright it still trailed on the ground; accordingly, he often
                    doubled it up in his girdle. Germany knows him as John the Bearded, just as it
                    does one of its emperors as Frederick Barbarossa; but many nations, ancient and
                    modern, can boast of men and monarchs who have been nicknamed from their
                    beards.</p>
                <p>When Peter the Great levied a tax on Russian beards, he was only following a
                    precedent which once existed in England. Noble chins were assessed at a rouble;
                    your commoner chin at a copec. It caused commotion, and there was much
                    compulsory shaving of those who did not pay. Beards are not now valued in
                    Russia. He who wears one seems to acknowledge that he has no very high place in
                    the social scale. On the other hand, beards were highly treasured in Spain till
                    the time of Philip V., who was unable to cultivate one. As was to be expected,
                    this infirmity set the fashion of affecting the infirmity; but beardless dons
                    were wont to exclaim with a sigh, “Since we have lost our beards, we have lost
                    our souls !” Thus, they unconsciously adopted something akin to the superstition
                    of the Roskolniki, a sect of schismatics who obstinately maintained that the
                    divine image resided in the beard. Portugal was not behind Spain in appreciating
                    the beard. When the Portuguese admiral, Juan de Castro, borrowed a thousand
                    pistoles from the city of Goa, he lent in pledge one of his whiskers, 'saying,
                    “All the gold in the world cannot equal this natural ornament of my valour.” In
                    these modern days one would not think much of the security of such a material
                    guarantee, nor of the modesty of the admiral who might have the face to offer
                    it.</p>
                <p>As Spaniards denuded their chins because their king could not grow a beard, so
                    the French grew beards, long after they had gone out of fashion, because their
                    king •found it necessary to do so. Francis the First, having wounded his chin,
                    concealed the ugly scar by covering it with a beard; and all loyal chins
                    forthwith affected to have scars to conceal. But when fashion and loyalty were
                    united the beard was carefully tended. It was not as in the time of the idle,
                    helpless, and long haired kings, who were less potential than their chief
                    officers, when the wild, dirty, and neglected beard was a type of that majesty,
                    made up of shreds and patches, which used to be paraded before the people on a
                    springless cart. Three hairs from a French king’s beard under the waxen seal
                    stamped on royal letter or charter, were supposed to add greater security for
                    the fulfilment of all promises made in the document itself. In course of time
                    fashion complimented majesty; a certain sort of moustache was called a “royale,”
                    and the little tuft beneath the lower lip was known by the term “imperiale.” As
                    a rule, the French chin assumed the appearance of that of the king for the time
                    being. The royal portrait reflects a general fashion from which only the
                    disloyal or the indifferent departed. On the subject of shaving, Talleyrand once
                    drew a fine distinction. Rogers asked him if Napoleon shaved himself. “Yes,”
                    replied the statesman; “one born to be a king has some one to shave him; but
                    they who acquire kingdoms shave themselves.” Tradition has exaggerated accounts
                    of bearded prisoners in the Bastille, but there was an official there whose duty
                    consisted in <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n479/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0479-0464"/> keeping the captive3 without beards. Some years
                    before the Revolution the celebrated lawyer and political writer Linguet was
                    incarcerated there. On the morning after his being locked up, an individual
                    entered his room who announced himself as the barber of the Bastille. “Very
                    well,” said the sharp-witted Linguet, “as you are the barber of the
                    Bastille—rasez-la.”</p>
                <p>Among the men of whom it was said of old that they would be known by their love
                    for one another, the beard ha≡ been a cause of much fierce uncharitableness. The
                    Greek Church, advocating the beard, and the Roman Church, denouncing it, were
                    not more forgetful of ever-blessed charity than the Belgian Reformers, the
                    close-shaven of whom wished the bearded members to be expelled as
                    non-Christians. The tradition concerning the Master whom both proposed to follow
                    was logically pleaded by the wearers of beards. As a general rule, in the
                    earlier time, the man who wore his hair short and his beard long, was accounted
                    as at least bearing the guise of respectability,— looking like a priestly
                    personage. There is a series of medals of the popes at Naples, from Clement VII.
                    (1523- 34) to Alexander VIII. (1689-91). All these are bearded. Clement’s beard
                    is long and dark; Alexander wears beard and moustaches. Perhaps Clement Giulio
                    de’ Medici set the fashion. Certain it is that a few years before, his kinsman,
                    Giovanni de’ Medici, Leo X. (1513-22), was always close-shaven, and beards were
                    not to be seen on the chin of Leo’s clerics and courtiers.</p>
                <p>In the 13th century beards are said to have first come into fashion in England.
                    If we may judge from the 15th century brasses in England, few men of distinction
                    enough to be so commemorated wore beards. Hotspur’s fop had his “chin new
                    reaped.” In the reign of Henry VIII. the fashion had so revived among lawyers
                    that the authorities of Lincoln’s Inn prohibited wearers of beards from sitting
                    at the great table, unless they paid double commons; but in all probability this
                    was before that sovereign ordered (1535) his courtiers to “poll their hair,” and
                    he let that crisp beard grow which is familiar to us all. Thence came a fiscal
                    arrangement; beards were taxed, and the levy was graduated according to the
                    condition of the wearer. In the Burghmote Book of Canterbury (quoted in <hi
                    rend="italic">Notes and Queries)</hi> there is the following entry :—“2nd Ed.
                    vi. The Sheriff of Canterbury and <hi rend="italic">another</hi> paid their dues
                    for wearing beards, 3s. 4d. and Is. 8d.” In the next reign, and in the year
                    1555, Queen Mary sent four agents to Moscow; all were bearded, but one of them,
                    a certain George Killingworth, was especially distinguished by a beard 5 feet 2
                    inches long, at sight of which a smile crossed the grim features of Ivan the
                    Terrible himself. George’s beard was thick, broad, and yellow; and, after
                    dinner, Ivan played with it, as with a favourite toy. Most of the Protestant
                    martyrs were burnt in their beards. Sir Thomas More, on the other hand, put his
                    out of the way, as he laid his head on the block, with the innocent joke so well
                    known. Elizabeth introduced a new impost with regard to beards. Every beard of
                    above a fortnight’s growth was subject to a yearly tax of 3s. 4d. The rate was
                    as heavy as the law authorizing it was absurd. It was made in the first year of
                    her reign, but it proved abortive. Fashion stamped it out, and men laughed in
                    their beards at the idea of paying for them. The law was not enforced, and the
                    Legislature left the heads of the people alone till much later times, when
                    necessity and the costs of war put that tax on hair-powder which even now
                    contributes a few thousands a year to the British Exchequer. The Vandyke beard,
                    pointed (as Charles the First and the illustrious artist, with most cavaliers,
                    wore it), was the most universally worn for a time. Beaumont and Fletcher, in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Queen of Corinth,</hi> make allusion, doubtless, to a
                    fashiou of wearing moustache and beard, common to the reign of the first James
                    as well as that of Charles.</p>
                <lg part="N">
                    <l part="F"> “His beard </l>
                    <l part="N"> Which now he puts i’ the posture of a T,— </l>
                    <l part="N"> The Roman T. Your T beard is the fashion, </l>
                    <l part="N"> And twofold doth express th’ enamoured courtier </l>
                    <l part="N"> As full as your fork-carving traveller.” </l>
                </lg>
                <p>John Taylor, the water-poet, notices the T beard, and mentions at least a score
                    of the various ways of wearing beards in his time, not forgetting the
                    contemporary proverb, “Beard natural, more hair than wit.” Hudibras, in text and
                    notes, affords numerous illustrations of this subject. The general idea that
                    beards did not come back with the monarchy does not seem to be correct, if the
                    old song (date 1660) is to be trusted—</p>
                <lg part="N">
                    <l part="N"> “Now of beards there be such a company, </l>
                    <l part="N" rend="indent1"> Of fashions such a throng, </l>
                    <l part="N"> That 'tis very hard to treat of the beard, </l>
                    <l part="N" rend="indent1"> Tho’ it be never so long.” </l>
                </lg>
                <p>Soon after this time, however, the beard in England was everywhere kept down by
                    the razor. At the close of last century the second Lord Rokeby (Mat. Robineau)
                    endeavoured to restore the fashion. “His beard,” says a contemporary, “forms one
                    of the most conspicuous traits of his person.” But too short a period had
                    elapsed since Lord George Gordon, the hero of “the Riots,” had turned Jew and
                    let his beard grow, to allow of any favour being awarded to an appendage which
                    seemed a type of infamy. To the literature of the beard a remarkable addition
                    was made in the present century by James Ward, R.A., the celebrated animal
                    painter. Mr Ward published a <hi rend="italic">Defence of the Beard,</hi> on
                    Scriptural grounds; he gave eighteen reasons why man was bound to grow a beard,
                    unless he was indifferent as to offending the Creator and good taste; for the
                    artist asserted himself as much as the religious zealot, and the writer asked,
                    “What would a Jupiter be without a beard? Who would countenance the idea of a
                    shaved Christ !” Mr Ward had what the French call “the courage of his opinions,”
                    and wore a beard of the most Jupiter-like majesty. Mr Muntz, M.P. for
                    Birmingham, followed the example, but it was not adopted by many others. A new
                    champion, however, appeared in 1860, but on peculiar ground. “Theologos”
                    expressed his views in the title-page of his work, namely,— <hi rend="italic"
                    >Shaving: a hr each of the Sabbath, and a hindrance to the spread of the
                    Gospel.</hi> A carrying out of the views of the writer would lead to the full
                    practice which prevailed among the Essenes, who never did on the Sabbath
                    anything whatever that they were in the regular habit of doing on other days.
                    “Theologos” points out that God gave the beard to man as a protection for his
                    throat and chest; and, he adds, with the most amusing simplicity, “Were the
                    beard in any other position its benefit and purpose might be doubted; but
                    situated where it is, no physiologist will dare to deny its intention.” Since
                    this naïve assertion was made, the beard, but not as a consequence, has grown
                    into favour; and though not universal, it is at least general, and a familiar
                    sight to us all.</p>
                <p>There is a disagreeable branch of the subject, demanding only a passing word,
                    namely, bearded women, hermaphroditic creatures, who have occasionally been
                    found in all conditions of life, from princesses in “marble halls” to objects
                    shown in exhibition-rooms or in vans at country fairs.</p>
                <l part="N"> —“You should be women,” </l>
                <p>says Macbeth,</p>
                <lg part="N">
                    <l part="N"> “And yet your beards forbid me to interpret </l>
                    <l part="N"> That you are so.” </l>
                </lg>
                <p>Sir Hugh Evans expressed the suspicion which attached to a bearded woman, when he
                    said of Falstaff, disguised as Mother Prat, “By yea and no, I think the 'oman is
                    a witch <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n480/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0480-0465"/> indeed; I like not when a ’ oman has a great
                    peard; I spy a great peard under her muffler.” The detestation with which a
                    bearded woman and a red-haired man were visited in France is almost savagely
                    illustrated in the following old lines :—</p>
                <lg part="N">
                    <l part="N"> “Homme roux et femme barbue, </l>
                    <l part="N"> De trente pas loin le salue, </l>
                    <l part="N"> Avecque trois pierres au poing, </l>
                    <l part="N"> Pour t’en aider à ton besoing.” </l>
                </lg>
                <p>(<hi rend="smallcaps">j. do.</hi>)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
