<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0209-0194-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BACH, Johann-Sebastian</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 3, page 194</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:1030269">Music</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:1030814">Musicals</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:815177">Art</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s24s">Mass</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4w08wh7j">Cantata</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2ch0v">Music</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs1k">Manners</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42r3nx59">Gifts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204901">Austria</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n209/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BACH, <hi rend="smallcaps">Johann-Sebastian</hi></label>, was
                    born at Eisenach in Thuringia, on March 21, 1685, the same year which gave birth
                    to his great contemporary Handel. His father held a musical appointment from the
                    town council, being himself descended from a musician. The family of the Bachs,
                    like those of some of the great Italian painters, may be cited as one of the
                    most striking instances of hereditary artistic genius. Through four consecutive
                    generations they followed the same calling, counting among their number no less
                    than fifty musicians of more or less remarkable gifts. Even of the first
                    ancestor of the family known to us, a miller and baker, who, owing to religious
                    persecutions, had to leave Pressburg in Austria for the Protestant north of
                    Germany, we are told that in his leisure hours he was fond of playing the lute,
                    the sounds of which, as the old family chronicle naively adds, must have mixed
                    sweetly with the clattering of the wheels of his mill. The accumulated artistic
                    gifts and traditions of his forefathers were at last brought to their highest
                    development by the genius of our master, who again transmitted them to his
                    numerous sons. Johann-Sebastian’s parents died before he had reached his tenth
                    year, and he was left to the care of his elder brother, an organist at Ohrdruf,
                    from whom he received his rudimentary musical education. According to a
                    tradition the elder Bach was by no means pleased with the rapid progress of his
                    more gifted brother, and even refused him access to the sources of knowledge
                    available at that primitive period; he was particularly anxious to withhold from
                    him a certain collection of compositions for the pianoforte, by contemporary
                    masters, which, however, the younger Bach contrived to obtain surreptitiously,
                    and which he copied at night in the course of six months. By practising the
                    music thus become his own on the pianoforte, he made himself master of the <hi
                    rend="italic">technique</hi> of an instrument, the capabilities of which he was
                    destined to enlarge and develop by the works of his own genius. In 1698 his
                    brother died, and Bach, at the age of fourteen, saw himself thrown on his own
                    resources for his further means of support. He went to Lüneburg, where his
                    beautiful soprano voice obtained him an appointment as chorister at the school
                    of St Michael. In this manner he became practically acquainted with the
                    principal works of vocal music, continuing at the same time his practice on the
                    organ and pianoforte. A special teacher of any of these instruments, or, indeed,
                    of the theory of music, Bach seems never to have had, at least <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n210/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0210-0195"/> not to our knowledge, and his style shows little
                    affinity to the modes of expression in use before him. In some measure, indeed,
                    it may be said that he new-created his own style, and, at the same time, that of
                    modem music in general, a proof both of the originality of his power and of the
                    autodidactic kind of his training. Nevertheless, Bach was anxious to profit by
                    the examples of contemporary masters of his art. We hear of frequent trips to
                    the neighbouring cities of Hamburg, Lübeck, and Celle, at that time important
                    centres of artistic life. In the first-mentioned city Keiser created sensation
                    by the unrivalled splendour of his operatic productions, while at Lübeck the
                    celebrated organist, Buxtehude, excited the enthusiastic admiration of the young
                    art-aspirant. In Celle, on the other hand, a celebrated band, composed chiefly
                    of French artists, offered an opportunity for the practical study of orchestral
                    music. Such were the elements of his self-education, to which must be added his
                    thorough knowledge of Palestrina and other masters of the grand old Italian
                    school, of most of whose works Bach possessed copies written with his own
                    hand.</p>
                <p>At the age of eighteen Bach returned to Thuringia, where his executive skill on
                    the organ and pianoforte attracted universal attention, and even obtained him
                    various musical appointments, of which we mention as the most important that of
                    court organist to the duke of Weimar. One, and not the least welcome, of his
                    official duties was the composition of sacred music. One of his most beautiful
                    sacred cantatas, <hi rend="italic">Ich hatte viel Belcümmerniss,</hi> was
                    composed during his stay at Weimar. An amusing incident of his otherwise quiet
                    and eventless career also belongs to this time. We are speaking of his musical
                    combat with the celebrated French organist, J. Louis Marchand, who had reached
                    Dresden on his travels, and lorded it over his artistic colleagues at the Saxon
                    court in the most sublime manner. The injured musicians, in their endeavours to
                    humble the pride of the Frenchman, at last hit upon the idea of proposing a
                    competition on the organ between him and Bach, whose fame at that time had begun
                    to spread far beyond his place of residence. He was summoned to Dresden, and the
                    day of the tournament fixed, at which the court and all the musical celebrities
                    of the town were to be present. At first Marchand treated his young and
                    comparatively unknown rival with scorn, but on hearing him perform at a
                    preparatory meeting, he was so struck with Bach’s power that he ignominiously
                    quitted the field, and vanished from Dresden before the day of the contest
                    arrived. This triumph led to Bach’s appointment as musical conductor <hi
                    rend="italic">(Kapellmeister)</hi> to the duke of Köthen, which he held from
                    1717-1723, after a previous stay at Weimar for nearly nine years. In 1723 he
                    removed to Leipsic, where the position of cantor at the celebrated
                    “Thomasschule,” combined with that of organist at the two principal churches of
                    Leipsic, was offered to him. It was here that the greater part of his works were
                    composed, mostly for the immediate requirements of the moment. Several of them
                    he engraved himself, with the assistance of his favourite son, Friedemann. The
                    further course of his life ran smoothly, only occasionally ruffled by his
                    altercations with his employers, the town-councillors of Leipsic, who, it is
                    said, were shocked by the “unclerical” style of Bach’s compositions, and by his
                    independent bearing generally. He was married twice, and had by his two wives a
                    family of eleven sons and nine daughters. In 1747 Bach made a journey to Potsdam
                    by the invitation of Frederick the Great, who, himself a musical amateur,
                    received the master with distinguished marks of regard. He had to play on the
                    numerous pianofortes of the king, and also to try the organs of the churches of
                    Potsdam. Two years after this event his sight began to fail, and before long he
                    became perfectly blind, a circumstance which again coincides with the fate of
                    his great contemporary, Handel. . Bach died of apoplexy on the 28th July 1750.
                    His loss was deplored as that of one of the greatest organists and pianoforte
                    players of his time. Particularly his powers of improvisation are described as
                    unrivalled by any of his contemporaries. Of his compositions comparatively
                    little was known. His MS. works were at his death divided amongst his sons, and
                    many of them have been lost in the course of time; only about one-half of his
                    greater works were recovered, when, after the lapse of nearly a century, the
                    verdict of his neglectful contemporaries was reversed by an admiring
                    posterity.</p>
                <p>The history of this Bach revival is closely connected with the name of
                    Mendelssohn, who was amongst the first to proclaim by word and deed the powers
                    of a genius almost too gigantic to be grasped by the receptivity of one
                    generation. By the enthusiastic endeavours of Mendelssohn, Schumann, and others,
                    the circle of Bach’s worshippers has increased rapidly. In 1850, a century after
                    his death, a society was started for the correct publication of all of Bach’s
                    remaining works, to which music owes the rescue from oblivion of some of its
                    sublimest emanations. Amongst those who have vastly contributed to establish the
                    <hi rend="italic">rapport</hi> between our master’s genius and modern lovers of
                    art, we also mention Dr Robert Franz, himself one of Germany’s greatest lyrical
                    composers, who has edited and adapted to the resources of the modern orchestra
                    several of Bach’s most beautiful works. Of these works, comprising almost all
                    the different forms of music, vocal and instrumental, barring the opera, we can
                    enumerate only the most important ones, referring the reader for further
                    information to the biographical and critical works by Bach’s son, Philipp
                    Emmanuel, by Forkel, and more recently by Bitter and Spitta. The last-mentioned
                    book has appeared quite lately, and exceeds its predecessors both by
                    comprehensiveness of research and critical appreciation. Of his numerous and
                    sacred oratorios, cantatas, and similar choral works, we name the so-called
                    Christmas oratorio (1734), the Passion music to the words of St John, and that
                    infinitely grander to the gospel of St Matthew (1734), also his Mass in B minor,
                    one of the greatest masterpieces of all times, and the Magnificat in D. Another
                    cantata is constructed on Luther’s grand chorale, <hi rend="italic">Ein'
                    feste</hi><hi rend="italic">Burg.</hi> The most celebrated amongst his
                    pianoforte compositions is the so-called <hi rend="italic">Woltemperirte
                    Clavier,</hi> a collection of preludes and fugues in the different keys of the
                    scale. For the orchestra we name the <hi rend="italic">Grande Suite in D,</hi>
                    and for his favourite instrument^ the organ, the so-called <hi rend="italic"
                    >Chromatic Fantasia.</hi> It remains to add a few words about Bach’s position in
                    the history of musical development. By Marx, a well-known critical writer, he
                    has been called the “Founder and Father of German Music;” and it cannot be
                    denied that no other German composer before him had attained a specifically
                    national type of musical utterance as distinguished from that of other nations.
                    This applies both to matter and manner. Bach has frequently founded his grandest
                    conceptions on the simplest tune of old chorales, that is, of purely popular
                    effusions of pious fervour, such as had survived in the living memory of the
                    nation from the time of Luther and his great revival of religious feeling.
                    Sometimes these tunes were adapted for religious purposes from still older songs
                    of a secular character, being thus thoroughly interwoven with the inmost feeling
                    of the German people. In raising these simple creations of popular growth to the
                    higher sphere of art, Bach has established his claim to the name of "the creator
                    of the <hi rend="italic">Germanic</hi> as opposed to the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Romance</hi> phase of musical art. This spirit of German, or to speak more <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n211/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0211-0196"/> accurately, North German nationality, thoughtful
                    yet waive, earnest yet tender, has also reacted on the form of Bach s creations.
                    Bach’s counterpoint, compared with the polyphonous splendour of Palestrina or
                    Orlando di Lasso, is, as it were, of a more intense, more immediately personal
                    kind. In his sacred cantatas, the alternate exclamations of the voices sometimes
                    rise to an almost passionate fervour of devotion, such as is known only to the
                    more individualised conception of human relations to the Deity peculiar to
                    Protestant worship,—applying that term in a purely emotional, that is, entirely
                    unsectarian sense. It is thus that Bach has vivified the rigid forms of the
                    fugue with the fire of individual passion. About the peculiarities of his style,
                    from a technical point of view, we can speak no further. How his style and his
                    genius, neglected by his contemporaries, and obscured by other masters, like
                    Haydn and Mozart, starting from a different basis and imbued with a different
                    spirit, have ultimately been destined to exercise a potent spell on modern art,
                    we have indicated already. <hi rend="smallcaps">(f. h.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
