<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0396-0381-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BAROMETER</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 3, page 381</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204556">Norway</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="48" ref="lcsh1910:b4jd4pp0f">Air</term>
                    <term n="22" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kh5s">Columns</term>
                    <term n="20" ref="lcsh1910:b48s4jt2v">Heights</term>
                    <term n="20" ref="lcsh1910:b4bz61762">Leveling</term>
                    <term n="14" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:939255">Gays</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1165420">Verniers</term>
                    <term n="48" ref="fasttopic:802066">Air</term>
                    <term n="33" ref="fasttopic:861723">Cisterns</term>
                    <term n="23" ref="fasttopic:1750261">Inch</term>
                    <term n="22" ref="fasttopic:868845">Columns</term>
                    <term n="20" ref="fasttopic:996970">Levellers</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n396/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BAROMETER</label>, the instrument by which the weight or
                    pressure of the atmosphere is estimated. The barometer was invented by
                    Torricelli, a pupil of Galileo, in 1643. It had shortly before been found, in
                    attempting to raise water from a very deep well near Florence, that, in spite of
                    all the pains taken in fitting the piston and valves, the water could by no
                    effort be made to rise higher in the pump than about 32 feet. This remarkable
                    phenomenon Torricelli accounted for by attributing pressure to the air. He
                    reasoned that water will rise in a vacuum only to a certain height, so that the
                    downward pressure or weight of the column of water will just balance the
                    pressure of the atmosphere; and he further argued that if a fluid heavier than
                    water be used it will not rise so high in the tube as the water. To prove this,
                    he selected a glass tube about a quarter of an inch in diameter and 4 feet long,
                    and hermetically sealed one of its ends; he then filled it with mercury and,
                    applying his finger to the open end, inverted it in a basin containing mercury.
                    The mercury instantly sank to nearly 30 inches above the surface of the mercury
                    in the basin, leaving in the top of the tube an apparent vacuum, which is,
                    indeed, one of the most perfect that can yet be produced, and is called after
                    this great experimenter, the <hi rend="italic">Torricellian vacuum.</hi> He next
                    converted the mercurial column into a form suited for observation by bending the
                    lower end of the tube, thus constructing what has since been called the siphon
                    barometer. The fundamental principle of the barometer cannot be better
                    illustrated than by his experiment (see fig. 2). In truth, a scale is all that
                    is required to render this simple apparatus a perfect barometer.</p>
                <p>The heights of the columns of two fluids in equilibrium are inversely as their
                    specific gravities; and as mercury is 10,784 times heavier than air, the height
                    of the atmosphere would be 10,784 times 30 inches, or nearly five miles, if it
                    were composed of layers equally dense throughout. But since air becomes less
                    dense as we ascend, owing to its great elasticity and the diminished pressure,
                    the real height of the atmosphere is very much greater. From observations of
                    luminous meteors, it has been inferred that the height is at least 120 miles,
                    and that, in an extremely attenuated form, it may even considerably exceed 200
                    miles.</p>
                <p>Various fluids might be used in constructing barometers. If water were used, the
                    barometric column would be about 35 feet long. The advantages, however, which
                    <hi rend="italic">water barometers</hi> might be supposed to possess in showing
                    changes of atmospheric pressure on a large scale, are more than counterbalanced
                    by a serious objection. The space in the tube above the column of water is far
                    from being a vacuum, being filled with aqueous vapour, which presses on the
                    column with a force varying with the temperature. At a temperature of 32° Fahr,
                    the column would be depressed half an inch, and at 75° a foot. Since in
                    mercurial barometers the space at the top of the column is one of the most
                    perfect vacuums that can be produced, the best fluid for the construction of
                    barometers is mercury. It is therefore the only fluid used where scientific
                    accuracy is aimed at. Pure mercury must be used in filling the tubes of
                    barometers; because if it be impure, the density will not be that of mercury,
                    and, consequently, the length of the columns will not be the same as that of a
                    column composed of pure mercury alone. Even should the density happen to be the
                    same as that of pure mercury the impurities would soon appear, impeding the
                    action of the fluid as it rises and falls, and thus rendering the instrument
                    unfit for accurate observation. In filling barometer tubes, air and moisture get
                    mixed with the mercury, and must be expelled by boiling the mercury in the tube.
                    It being essential that the mercury be quite freed from air and moisture, no
                    barometer should be used till it has been well ascertained that this has been
                    done. Some time after the instrument has been hung in an observing position, let
                    it be inclined gently and with care, so that the mercury may strike against the
                    top of the glass tube; if there is no air within, a sharp metallic click will be
                    heard, but if the sound is dull, the air and moisture have not been entirely
                    expelled. If the mercury should appear at any time to adhere somewhat to the
                    tube and the convex surface assume a more flattened form, it may be concluded
                    that air or moisture is present. If on examining the mercury with a lens minute
                    bubbles are visible, air is present. In all these cases the instrument must be
                    rectified.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n397/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0397-0382"/>
                <p>The best barometers are usually fitted with an <hi rend="italic">air-trap,</hi>
                    originally proposed by Gay-Lussac for the purpose of arresting the ascent to the
                    Torricellian vacuum of any air that may have found its way into the column by
                    the cistern. The air-trap is fitted into the tube somewhere between the scale
                    and the cistern. Barometers furnished with an air-trap can be conveyed from
                    place to place with more safety, and they remain longer in good working
                    order.</p>
                <p>There are two classes of barometers— <hi rend="italic">Siphon Barometers</hi> and
                    <hi rend="italic">Cistern Barometers.</hi> The <hi rend="italic">Siphon
                    Barometer</hi> (fig. 1) consists of a tube bent in the form of a siphon, and is
                    of the same diameter throughout. A graduated scale passes along the whole length
                    of the tube, and the height of the barometer is ascertained by taking the
                    difference of the readings of the upper and lower limbs respectively. This
                    instrument may also be read by bringing the zero-point of the graduated scale to
                    the level of the surface of the lower limb by means of a screw, and reading off
                    the height at once from the surface of the upper limb. This barometer requires
                    no correction for errors of capillarity or capacity. Since, however, impurities
                    are contracted by the mercury in the lower limb, which is usually in open
                    contact with the air, the satisfactory working of the instrument comes soon to
                    be seriously interfered with.</p>
                <p>Fig. 2. shows the <hi rend="italic">Cistern Barometer</hi> in its essential and
                    its simplest form. This barometer is subject to two kinds of error, the one
                    arising from capillarity, and the other from changes in the level of the surface
                    of the cistern as the mercury rises and falls in the tube, the latter being
                    technically called the <hi rend="italic">error of capacity.</hi> If a glass tube
                    of small bore be plunged into a vessel containing mercury, it will be observed
                    that the level of the mercury in the tube is not in the line of that of the
                    mercury in the vessel, but somewhat below it, and that the surface is convex.
                    The capillary depression is inversely proportional to the diameter of the tube.
                    If the diameter of the tube be 0T inch, the capillary depression of mercury in
                    boiled tubes, or <hi rend="italic">error of capillarity, is</hi> 0Ό70 inch; if
                    0'2 inch, the error is 0Ό29 inch; if 0 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 3 inch, it
                    is 0Ό14 inch; and if 0'5 inch, it is only 0Ό03 inch. Since capillarity depresses
                    the height of the column, cistern barometers require an addition to be made to
                    the observed height, in order to give the true pressure, the amount depending,
                    of course, on the diameter of the tube.</p>
                <p>The error of capacity arises in this way. The height of the barometer is the
                    perpendicular distance between the surface of the mercury in the cistern and the
                    upper surface of the mercurial column. Now, when the barometer falls from 30 to
                    29 inches, an inch of mercury must flow out of the tube and pass into the
                    cistern, thus raising the cistern level, and, on the other hand, when the
                    barometer rises, mercury must flow out of the cistern into the tube, thus
                    lowering the level of the mercury in the cistern. Since the scales of barometers
                    are usually engraved on their brass cases, which are fixed (and, consequently,
                    the zero-point from which the scale is graduated is also fixed), it follows
                    that, from the incessant changes in the level of the cistern, the readings would
                    be sometimes too high and sometimes too low, if no provision were made against
                    this source of error.</p>
                <p>A simple way of correcting the error of capacity is—· to ascertain (1) the
                    neutral point of the instrument, or that height at which the zero of the scale
                    is exactly at the height of the surface of the cistern, and (2) the rate ot
                    error as the barometer rises or falls above this point, and then apply a
                    correction proportional to this rate. In many of the barometers used on the
                    Continent the surface area of the cistern is 100 times greater than that of the
                    tube, in which case the error is small, and can, besides, be easily calculated.
                    This is a good barometer for ordinary observers, inasmuch as no error arises in
                    bringing the surface of the mercury of the cistern to the zero-point of the
                    scale, which one requires to have some skill as a manipulator and good light to
                    do correctly. Another way of getting rid of this error is effected by the <hi
                    rend="italic">Board of Trade Barometer,</hi> constructed originally by Adie of
                    London. In this barometer the error of capillarity is allowed for in fixing the
                    zeropoint of the scale, and the error of capacity is obviated by making the
                    scale-inches not true inches, but just so much less as exactly to counterbalance
                    the error of capacity.</p>
                <p>But the instrument in which the error of capacity is satisfactorily (indeed,
                    entirely) got rid of is <hi rend="italic">Fortiris Barometer.</hi> Fig. 3 shows
                    how this is effected. The cistern is formed of a glass cylinder, through which
                    the level of the mercury may be seen. The bottom is made like a bag, of flexible
                    leather, against which a screw works. At the top of the interior of the cistern
                    is a small piece of ivory, the point of which coincides with the zero of the
                    scale. By means of the screw, which acts on the flexible cistern bottom, the
                    level of the mercury can be raised or depressed so as to bring the ivory point
                    exactly to the surface of the mercury in the cistern. In some barometers the
                    cistern is fixed, and the ivory point is brought to the level of the mercury in
                    the cistern by raising or depressing the scale.</p>
                <p>What is called the <hi rend="italic">Fitzroy Barometer</hi> is only a modified
                    form of the siphon barometer, with the lower limb blown into a moderately-sized
                    bulb, resembling a cistern in some respects, and thus giving a larger range to
                    the readings of the upper limb. It is only suited for popular, not for
                    scientific purposes. The common <hi rend="italic">Wheel Barometer,</hi> the
                    popular form of the <hi rend="italic">weather glass,</hi> is also a modification
                    of the siphon barometer. A small weight, glass or iron, floats on the mercury in
                    the lower limb; to this weight a thread is attached, which is led round a
                    horizontal axis, a small weight being suspended at its free extremity to keep it
                    tight. The float rises and falls with the fluctuations of the barometer, and a
                    pointer fixed to a horizontal axis being turned by this means indicates the
                    height of the barometer by figures on a dial. Since the mercury only rises or
                    falls in the open end of the siphon to the extent of half the oscillation, a
                    cistern is added to the top of the upper limb to increase the amount of the
                    oscillation in the lower limb. This form of the barometer is only suited for
                    very rough purposes, since large and uncertain errors arise from the shortening
                    and lengthening of the thread with the varying dampness or dryness of the air,
                    and from the friction of the different parts of the mechanism of the
                    instrument.</p>
                <p>Since in working out the great atmospheric problem of the force of the wind in
                    its relation to the barometric gradient <hi rend="italic">(i.e.,</hi> the
                    differences of the pressures at different places, reduced to the same level)
                    readings from about the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n398/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0398-0383"/> hundredth of an inch (0Ό10), or even ιess,
                    require to be observed and stated with great accuracy, the extreme importance of
                    accurate sensitive barometers will be apparent,—instruments not only possessing’
                    a great range of scale, but a scale which will truly indicate the real
                    atmospheric pressure at all times. The two barometers which best satisfy this
                    requirement are <hi rend="italic">King’s Barometer,</hi> which has been in use
                    for many years at the Liverpool Observatory, and <hi rend="italic">IIowson</hi>
                    ’ <hi rend="italic">s Barometer.</hi> Fig. 4 shows the essential and peculiar
                    parts of Howson’s barometer. A is the barometer tube, which is of large
                    diameter, and longer than ordinary in order to admit of a greater length of
                    range. B is a movable cylindrical cistern, having attached to its bottom a long
                    hollow tube or stalk <hi rend="italic">c,</hi> hermetically sealed, springing to
                    a height of about 28 inches above the fixed level of the mercury in the cistern.
                    This stalk terminates a little below the upper level of the mercury, and its
                    upper end is thus exposed to no more downward pressure than that of the mercury
                    above it; consequently, there is an excess of upward pressure of the air which
                    tends to raise the cistern. When the excess of upward pressure is exactly
                    balanced by the weight of the cistern with its stalk and contained mercury up to
                    δ, an equilibrium will be established, which will keep the apparatus stationary
                    or hanging in suspension. If now the atmospheric pressure acting on the cistern
                    be increased, and if the thickness of the glass tube A be supposed to be
                    nothing, the cistern would continue to ascend to an indefinite extent, since
                    there is nothing to stop it. But as the glass is a substance of some thickness,
                    mercury is displaced by the glass as it is plunged further into the cistern; and
                    as it thus offers a resistance to the ascent of the cistern, the cistern will
                    come to rest when the quantity of mercury displaced is equivalent to the
                    increase of pressure. The extent of range which this barometer possesses over
                    the ordinary barometer is determined by the ratio of the internal area of the
                    tube A to that of the annulus of glass which bounds it,—the range increasing as
                    the internal area is increased, or as the thickness of the glass is
                    diminished.</p>
                <p>The liability of the barometer to be broken in carriage is great. This risk is
                    considerably lessened in the <hi rend="italic">Board of Trade Barometer,</hi>
                    which has the tube very much reduced in diameter for a part of its length,
                    breakage from “pumping” being so much lessened thereby that the instrument may
                    be sent as a parcel by rail, if only very ordinary care be taken in the
                    carriage. This is essentially the principle of the <hi rend="italic">Marine
                    Barometer,</hi> which, however, has the tube still more contracted. For rougher
                    modes of transit an ingeniously constructed iron barometer has been invented by
                    Mr T, Stevenson, C.E.</p>
                <p>The sympiezometer was invented by Adie of Edinburgh. It consists of a glass tube,
                    with a small chamber at the top and an open cistern below. The upper part of the
                    tube is filled with air, and the lower part and cistern with glycerine. When
                    atmospheric pressure is increased, the air is compressed by the rising of the
                    fluid; but when it is diminished the fluid falls, and the contained air expands.
                    To correct for the error arising from the increased pressure of the contained
                    air when its temperature varies, a thermometer and sliding-scale are added, so
                    that the instrument may be adjusted to the temperature at each observation. It
                    is a sensitive instrument, and well suited for rough purposes at sea and for
                    travelling, but not for exact observation. It has been for some time superseded
                    by the <hi rend="italic">Aneroid,</hi> which far exceeds it in handiness,
                    portability, and correctness. The <hi rend="italic">Aneroid Barometer</hi> was
                    invented by Vidi, and patented in England in 1844. Its action depends on the
                    effect produced by the pressure of the atmosphere on a circular metallic chamber
                    partially exhausted of air and hermetically sealed. Fig. 5 represents the
                    internal construction, as seen when the face is removed, but with the hand still
                    attached, <hi rend="italic">a</hi> is a flat circular metallic box, having its
                    upper and under surfaces corrugated in concentric circles. This box or chamber
                    being partially exhausted of air, through the short tube δ, which is
                    subsequently made air-tight by soldering, constitutes a spring, which is
                    affected by every variation of pressure in the external atmosphere, the
                    corrugations on it3 surface increasing its elasticity. At the centre of the
                    upper surface of the exhausted chamber there is a solid cylindrical projection
                    <hi rend="italic">X,</hi> to the top of which the principal lever <hi
                    rend="italic">cde</hi> is attached, as shown in the drawing. This lever rests
                    partly on a spiral spring at <hi rend="italic">cl;</hi> it is also supported by
                    two vertical pins, with perfect freedom of motion. The end <hi rend="italic"
                    >e</hi> of the lever is attached to a second or small lever <hi rend="italic"
                    >f,</hi> from which a chain <hi rend="italic">g</hi> extends to <hi
                    rend="italic">ħ,</hi> where it works on a drum attached to the axis of the hand,
                    connected with a hair spring at ∕q changing the motion from vertical to
                    horizontal, and regulating the hand, the attachments of which are made to the
                    metallic plate <hi rend="italic">i.</hi> The motion originates in the corrugated
                    elastic box <hi rend="italic">a,</hi> the surface of which is depressed or
                    elevated as the weight of the atmosphere is increased or diminished, and this
                    motion is communicated through the levers to the axis of the hand at <hi
                    rend="italic">h.</hi> The spiral spring on which the lever rests at <hi
                    rend="italic">d</hi> is intended to compensate for the effects of alterations of
                    temperature. The actual movement at the centre of the exhausted box, from whence
                    the indications emanate, is very slight, but by the action of the levers this is
                    multiplied 657 times at the point of the hand, so that a movement of the 22Oth
                    part of an inch in the box carries the point of the hand through three inches on
                    the dial. The effect of this combination is to multiply the smallest degrees of
                    atmospheric pressure, so as to render them sensible on the index.</p>
                <p>The instrument requires, however, to be repeatedly compared with a mercurial
                    barometer, being liable to changes from the elasticity of the brass chamber
                    changing, or from changes in the system of levers which work the pointer. Though
                    aneroids are constructed showing great accuracy in their indications, yet none
                    can lay any claim to the exactness of mercurial barometers. The mechanism is
                    liable to get fouled and otherwise go out of order, so that they may change
                    0’300 inch in a few weeks, or even indicate pressure so inaccurately and so
                    irregularly that no confidence can be placed in them for even a few days, if the
                    means of comparing them with a mercurial barometer be not at hand.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n399/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0399-0384"/>
                <p>Of the <hi rend="italic">self-registering barometers,</hi> the best are those
                    which accomplish this object by photography. This is done by concentrating the
                    rays of a gas flame by means of a lens, so that they strike the top of the
                    mercurial column. A sheet of prepared paper is attached to a frame placed behind
                    a screen, with a narrow vertical slit in the line of the rays. The mercury being
                    opaque throws a part of the paper in the shade, while above the mercury the rays
                    from the flame pass unobstructed to the paper. The paper being carried steadily
                    round on a drum at a given rate per hour, the height of the column of mercury is
                    photographed continuously on the paper. From the photograph the height of the
                    barometer at any instant may be taken. <hi rend="italic">King's, Hardfs,
                    Hough's, Hipps,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Thorell's self-registering
                    barometers</hi> may also be referred to as giving continuous records of the
                    pressure. In all continuously registering barometers, however, it is necessary,
                    as a check, to make eye-observations with a mercury standard barometer hanging
                    near the registering barometer from four to eight times daily.</p>
                <p>In constructing the best barometers three materials are employed, viz. :—(1)
                    brass, for the case, on which the scale is engraved; (2) glass, for the tube
                    containing the mercury; and (3) the mercury itself. Brass is the best material
                    for the case and scale, inasmuch as its co-efficient of expansion is well known,
                    and is practically the same though the alloy be not in all cases exactly alike.
                    It is evident that if the co-efficient of expansion of mercury and brass were
                    the same, the height of the mercury as indicated by the brass scale would be the
                    true height of the mercurial column. But this is not the case, the co-efficient
                    of expansion for mercury being considerably greater than that for brass. The
                    result is that if a barometer stand at 30 inches when the temperature of the
                    whole instrument, mercury and brass, is 32°, it will no longer stand at 30
                    inches if the temperature be raised to 69°; in fact, it will then stand at 30Ί
                    inches. This increase in the height of the column by the tenth of an inch is not
                    due to any increase of pressure, but altogether to the greater expansion of the
                    mercury at the higher temperature, as compared with the expansion of the brass
                    case with the engraved scale by which the height is measured. In order,
                    therefore, to compare with each other with exactness barometric observations
                    made at different temperatures, it is necessary to reduce them to the heights at
                    which they would stand at some uniform temperature. The temperature to which
                    such observations are now almost everywhere reduced is 32° Fahr.</p>
                <p>The following is Schumacher’s formula for computing the corrections for
                    barometers, whose heights are noted in English inches, for temperature <hi
                    rend="italic">t,</hi> according to Fahrenheit’s scale :—</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic">m(t-</hi> 32°) <hi
                    rend="italic">-s(</hi><hi rend="italic                     subscript"> t</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">t-</hi> 62°) <hi rend="superscript"> x</hi> ~ ~ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> A</hi> l + m(i-32°) ’</p>
                <p>where <hi rend="italic">h =</hi> height of barometer, <hi rend="italic">m</hi> =
                    expansion of mercury for l <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> Fahr. = 0'0001001, s =
                    expansion of brass for l <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> Fahr. = 0'00001041.</p>
                <p>The standard temperature of the English yard being 62° and not 32°, it will be
                    found in working out the corrections from the above formula that the temperature
                    of no correction is not 32° but 28° '5. If the scale be engraved on the glass
                    tube, or if the instrument be furnished with a glass scale or with a wooden
                    scale, different corrections are required These may be worked out from the above
                    formula by substituting for the co-efficient of the expansion of brass that of
                    glass which is assumed to be 0Ό0000498, or that of wood, which is assumed to be
                    0. Wood, however, should not be used, its expansion with temperature being
                    unsteady, as well as uncertain.</p>
                <p>If the brass scale be attached to a wooden frame and be free to move up and down
                    the frame, as is the case with many siphon barometers, the corrections for brass
                    scales are to be used, since the zero-point of the scale is brought to the level
                    of the lower limb; but if the brass scale be <hi rend="italic">fixed</hi> to a
                    wooden frame, the corrections for brass scales are only applicable provided the
                    zero of the scale be iixed at (or nearly at) the zero line of the column, and be
                    free to expand upwards. In siphon barometers, with which an observation is made
                    from two readings on the scale, the scale must be free to expand in one
                    direction. Again, if only the upper part of the scale, say from 27 to 31 inches,
                    be screwed to a wooden frame, it is evident that not the corrections for brass
                    scales, but those for wooden scales must be used. No account needs to be taken
                    of the expansion of the glass tube containing the mercury, it being evident that
                    no correction for this expansion is required in the case of any barometer the
                    height of which is measured from the surface of the mercury in the cistern.</p>
                <p>In fixing a barometer for observation, it is indispensable that it be hung in a
                    perpendicular position, seeing that it is the <hi rend="italic">perpendicular
                    distance</hi> of the surface of the mercury in the cistern and that of the top
                    of the column which is the true height of the barometer. Hence it is desirable
                    that the barometer swing in position; or if this be attended with risk or
                    inconvenience, it must be seen that it be clamped or permanently fixed in a
                    position exactly vertical. The surface of the mercurial column is convex, and in
                    noting the height of the barometer, it is not the chord of the curve,—an error
                    not unfrequently made,—but its tangent which is taken. This is done by setting
                    the straight lower edge of the vernier, an appendage with which the barometer is
                    furnished, as a tangent to the curve. The vernier is made to slide up and down
                    the scale, and by it the height of the barometer may be read true to 0Ό02 or
                    even to 0Ό01 inch. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Vernier.</hi></p>
                <p>In hanging a barometer the following points should be attended to :—(1), That it
                    be hung so that the mercurial column be quite perpendicular; (2), that the scale
                    be about 5 feet high, for facility of reading; (3), that the whole instrument,
                    particularly the scale and the cistern, be hung in a good light; and (4), that
                    it be hung in a position in which it will be exposed to as little fluctuation of
                    temperature as possible. A wall heated by a flue, and positions which expose the
                    instrument to the heat of the sun or to that of a fire, are very objectionable.
                    It is to be kept in mind that no barometric observation can be regarded as good
                    unless the <hi rend="italic">attached thermometer</hi> indicates a temperature
                    differing from that of the whole instrument not more than a degree. For every
                    degree of temperature the attached thermometer differs from the barometer, the
                    observation will be faulty to the extent of about 0'003 inch, which in
                    discussions of diurnal range, barometric gradients, lunar range, and many other
                    questions, is a serious amount.</p>
                <p>Before being used, barometers should be thoroughly examined as to the state of
                    the mercury, the size of cistern (so as to admit of low readings), and their
                    agreement with some known standard instrument at different points of the scale.
                    The pressure of the atmosphere is not expressed by the weight of the mercury
                    sustained in the tube by it, but by the perpendicular height of the column.
                    Thus, when the height of the column is 30 inches, it is not said that the
                    atmospheric pressure is 14'7 ft) on the square inch, or the weight of the
                    mercury filling a tube at that height whose transverse section equals a square
                    inch, but that it is 30 inches, meaning that the pressure will sustain a column
                    of mercury of that height.</p>
                <p>The height of the barometer is expressed in English inches in England and
                    America. In France and most European countries, the height is given in
                    millimètres,, a millimètre being the thousandth part of a mètre, which equals 39
                    <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 37O79 English inches. Up to 1869 the barometer
                    <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n400/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0400-0385"/> was given in half-lines in Russia, which,
                    equalling the twentieth of an English inch, were readily reduced to English
                    inches by dividing by 20. The metric barometric scale is now used in Russia. In
                    a few countries on the Continent the French or Paris line, equalling 0Ό88814
                    inch, still continues to be used. Probably millimètre and English inch scales
                    will soon be exclusively in use. The English measure of length being a standard
                    at 62° Fahr., the old French measure at 61° '2, and the metric scale at 32°, it
                    is necessary, before comparing observations made with the three barometers, to
                    reduce them to the same temperature, so as to neutralize the inequalities
                    arising from the expansion of the scales by heat.</p>
                <p>The barometer is a valuable instrument as an indicator of coming weather,
                    provided its readings be interpreted with intelligence. High pressures generally
                    attend fine weather, but they not unfrequently accompany wet stormy weather; on
                    the other hand, low pressures, which usually occur with wet and stormy weather,
                    not unfrequently accompany fine mild w eather, particularly in winter and in the
                    northern parts of Great Britain. The truth is, the barometer merely indicates
                    atmospheric pressure directly, whilst it indicates weather only inferentially.
                    The chief points to be attended to are its fluctuations taken in connection with
                    the wind and the state of the sky, but above all, the readings of the barometer
                    as compared with those at neighbouring places, since it is <hi rend="italic"
                    >difference</hi> of pressure, or the amount of the barometric gradient, which
                    determines the strength of the wind and the weather generally.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Barometrical Measurements of Heights.</hi></p>
                <p>The decisive experiment by which Pascal established the reality of atmospheric
                    pressure suggested to him the method of measuring heights by means of the
                    barometer. The first attempts to effect this were necessarily rude and
                    inaccurate, since they went on the assumption that the lower mass of air is of
                    uniform density. The discovery, however, of the actual relation subsisting
                    between the density of air and its elasticity by Boyle in England, and about the
                    same time by Mariotte in France, laid a sure foundation for this branch of
                    atmospheric physics —the relation being that, at the same temperature, the
                    pressure of a gas is exactly proportional to its density.</p>
                <p>The truth of this law may be shown by the following experiment. Take a glass
                    tube, of equal bore throughout, closed at one end, and bent in the form of a
                    siphon (fig. 1), and let us suppose that it contains in the closed limb a
                    portion of air AB, shut off from the atmosphere by mercury filling the lower
                    portion of the tube, and that the enclosed portion of air exists at the ordinary
                    pressure of the atmosphere or 30 inches. In this case the mercury in each limb,
                    being subject to the same pressure, will stand at the same level. If we now pour
                    mercury into the long limb (fig. 2) till the level in this limb stands 30 inches
                    above the level in the closed limb, the additional mercury will tend to compress
                    the air in A'B' with a pressure equal to that exerted by a column of 30 inches
                    of mercury. In the latter case, therefore, the air is subjected to a pressure of
                    two atmospheres, or GO inches, while in the former it was only subjected to a
                    pressure of one atmosphere or 30 inches. It will be found that the space A <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi> B' under the pressure of two atmospheres is only half
                    the space AB where the pressure is only one atmosphere. If mercury had been
                    filled in till the difference of level of the mercury in the two limbs was GO
                    inches, or a pressure of three atmospheres, the space occupied by the air in the
                    closed limb would have been only a third of the original space when the pressure
                    was only that of one atmosphere. Generally, Boyle’s law or Mariotte’s law is
                    this :—The volume of a gas varies inversely as the pressure. Since the same
                    quantity of air has been experimented with, it follows that the density is
                    doubled with a pressure of two atmospheres, and trebled with that of three, and
                    hence the pressure of a gas is proportional to its density.</p>
                <p>This law, however, only holds provided the temperature is the same. The familiar
                    illustration of a bladder, partially filled with air, expanding on being placed
                    near a fire, shows that if the pressure remains the same,—the pressure in this
                    case being that of the atmosphere,—the gas will occupy a larger space if its
                    temperature be raised. If the temperature be increased and the air be confined
                    so as to occupy the same space, the pressure will be increased.</p>
                <p>The relation between the temperature and pressure of gases was first discovered
                    by Gay-Lussac; and more recently our knowledge of this branch of the subject has
                    been greatly enlarged by the beautiful and accurate experiments of Régnault.
                    From those experiments it has been concluded that the co-efficient which denotes
                    increase of elasticity for l <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> Fahr, of air whose
                    volume is constant equals Ό02036; and that the co-efficient which denotes
                    increase of volume for l <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> Fahr, of air whose
                    elasticity is constant equals '002039. It may further be added that the
                    co-efficient of expansion for carbonic acid gas, hydrogen, and all other gasee,
                    is as nearly as possible the same.</p>
                <p>When a fluid is allowed to evaporate in the exhausted receiver of an air-pump,
                    vapour rises from it until its pressure reaches a certain point, after which all
                    further evaporation is arrested. This point depends on the nature of the fluid
                    itself and on the temperature, and it indicates the greatest vapour pressure
                    possible for the fluid at the particular temperature. Regnaυlt has shown the
                    amount of the vapour pressure of water at different temperatures, thus—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Temp.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Max. Pressure</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Temp.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Max. Pressure</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Fahr.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>of Vapour.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Fahr</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>of Vapour.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>inch.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>inch.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0Ό44</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>50</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0'361</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>10</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0Ό68</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>60</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0'518</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>20</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0Ί08</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>70</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0'733</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>30</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0165</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>80</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1Ό23</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>40</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>C'248</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>90</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1'410</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>If gases of different densities be put into the same vessel it is found that they
                    do not arrange themselves according to their densities, but are ultimately
                    diffused through each other in the most intimate manner. Each gas tends to
                    diffuse itself as in a vacuum, the effect of the presence of other gases being
                    merely to retard the process of their mutual diffusion. As regards the
                    atmosphere, evaporation goes on until the maximum vapour pressure for the
                    temperature has been attained, at which point the air is said to be saturated,
                    and whilst the temperature remains the same further evaporation is arrested.
                    Thus, at a temperature of 50° evaporation goes on until the vapour pressure
                    reaches 0'361 inch, but if the temperature were raised to G0° the process of
                    evaporation would be renewed, and go on till the vapour pressure rose to 0'518
                    inch. If at a vapour pressure of 0'518 inch the temperature were to fall from
                    60° to 50°, the air would no longer be capable of retaining the whole of the
                    aqueous vapour in suspension, but the surplus part would be condensed and fall
                    as rain. In tho change from the aeriform to the liquid state a quantity of
                    latent heat is given out. The yet uncertain effect of these changes,
                    particularly the change of form from the aeriform to the liquid state, on the
                    pressure, temperature, and movements of the air, renders it peculiarly desirable
                    that barometeric observations for the determination of <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n401/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0401-0386"/> heights should not he made when clouds are
                    forming or raiu is falling.</p>
                <p>Dalton has shown<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi
                    rend="italic">Meteorological Observations and Essays,</hi> 2d ed., p.
                    100.</p></note> that air charged with vapour is specifically lighter than when
                    it wants the vapour; in other words, the more vapour any given quantity of air
                    has in it the less is its specific gravity; and Sir William Thomson has
                    shown<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic"
                    >Mem, Lit. and Phil. Soc. Manchester,</hi> vol. ii. 3d series, j&gt;,
                    131.</p></note> that the condensation of vapour in ascending currents of air is
                    the chief cause of the cooling effect being so much less than that which would
                    be experienced by dry air. From these ascertained effects of aqueous vapour in
                    modifying the pressure and temperature of the atmosphere, the importance in the
                    barometric measurement of heights of full and accurate observations of the
                    hygrometry of the atmosphere and of the weather will be apparent.</p>
                <p>Since the equilibrium of the vapour atmosphere is being constantly disturbed by
                    every instance of condensation, by the ceaseless process of evaporation, and by
                    every change of-temperature, and since the presence of oxygen and nitrogen
                    greatly obstructs the free diffusion of the aqueous vapours, it follows that
                    Dalton’s law of the independent pressure of the vapour and the dry air does not
                    absolutely hold good. From the constant effort of the vapour to attain to a
                    state of equilibrium there is, however, a continual tendency to approach this
                    state. Since the equal diffusion of the dry air and the vapour is never reached,
                    observations can only indicate local humidity, and therefore as regards any
                    considerable stratum of air can only be regarded as approximate. Though
                    particular observations may often indicate a humidity wide of the mark, yet in
                    long averages a close approximation is reached, except in confined localities
                    which are exceptionally damp or dry. Hence in observations for the determination
                    of heights, the results of a long-continued series of observations should be
                    employed, and those hours should be chosen whose mean is near the daily
                    mean.</p>
                <p>The most recent results arrived at by Régnault are the best, but it is to be
                    regretted that the whole subject of the hygrometry, both as regards the methods
                    of observation and the methods of discussing the observations, is still in an
                    unsatisfactory state. This consideration, taken in connection with our defective
                    knowledge of the relation of aqueous vapour to radiant heat, of the mode of its
                    diffusion both vertically and horizontally, and of the influence exerted by its
                    condensation into cloud and rain, and with our ignorance of the merely
                    mechanical effects of ascending, descending, and horizontal currents of air in
                    increasing or diminishing barometric pressure, renders it evident that heights
                    deduced from barometric observations can only be regarded as approximate. It is
                    much to be desired, in stating results, that the limit of error were taken into
                    account, and the nearest round number in accordance therewith should alone be
                    given as the calculated result. Thus, it is a mistake to give as the height of a
                    place 1999 feet "when the calculation is based wholly on barometric
                    observations, and the limit of error amounts to 30 feet or more. The height 2000
                    should be given as the result.</p>
                <p>The correction for decrease of gravity at the higher station, as compared with
                    the force of gravity at the lower station or at;ea-level, must also be taken
                    into .account. Its amount is small, being, roughly speaking, only about 0Ό01
                    inch per 400 feet. Since⅛he force of gravity is diminished in proportion to the
                    square of the distance from the centre of gravity, the rate of its decrease with
                    the height varies in different latitudes. Places at the equator being farther
                    from the earth’s centre than places at the poles, it follows that the force of
                    gravity diminishes at a less rapid rate as we ascend at the equator than it does
                    at the poles. Now, since at the equator gravity diminishes less rapidly with the
                    height, the air at any given height will exert a higher pressure there than
                    anywhere else on the globe at the same height as compared with what it does at
                    the sea-level of the latitude. Hence a subtraction requires to be made at the
                    equator, and the amount to be subtracted diminishes as we proceed into higher
                    latitudes, till it falls to zero at latitude 45°, where the force of gravity is
                    assumed to be the mean. For higher latitudes an addition is required which
                    constantly increases till it reaches the maximum at the poles. This correction
                    is also small, being for 1000 feet less than 0Ό01 inch in Great Britain, and
                    less than 0Ό03 at the equator and the poles.</p>
                <p>Various formulae for the barometrical measurement of heights, based on these
                    principles, have been, given by Laplace and others, not a few of them being
                    unnecessarily refined and intricate when the real character of the data is taken
                    into consideration. The following formula by Rühlmann<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Lie</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Barometrischen Hühenmessungen und ihre Bedeutung für die Physik der
                    Atmosphäre,</hi> von Dr Richard Rühlmann, Leipsic, 1870.</p></note> is given as
                    the simplest and best, being based on the most recent results which have been
                    arrived at;— ⅛=18400∙2ζl∙00157 + 0∙003675-^-^ ∕ ^ + &lt;'∖</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">( V V'∖</hi></p>
                <p>∖ 1 + 0'378—x— ) (1 + 0Ό02623 cos. 2&lt;f&gt;)</p>
                <p>Λ <hi rend="superscript"> 2z + h</hi> λ <hi rend="italic superscript"> b</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">L</hi> ∏x in which <hi rend="italic">h</hi> is the difference in
                    mètres of level betw een thθ two stations <hi rend="italic">; t'</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">t"</hi> the temperature centigrade of the air at the two stations;
                    <hi rend="italic">b'</hi> and <hi rend="italic">b"</hi> the heights of the
                    barometer in millimètres, corrected for temperature and for all instrumental
                    errors; <hi rend="italic">σ</hi> and σ" the elastic force of vapour; &lt;5 the
                    mean of the latitudes of the two stations; and <hi rend="italic">z</hi> the
                    height of the lower station above the sea. Making—</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">( t</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">+t</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> ,,</hi><hi rend="italic">}</hi></p>
                <p>A = log. 18400,2(1 Ό0157 + 0 003675)—£— i, <hi rend="subscript"> rt</hi>, (
                    0'378∕&lt;√ <hi rend="italic">σ"X )</hi></p>
                <p>C—log. jl + <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> (<hi rend="subscript"> i</hi>
                    j∕+j∕∕Jp</p>
                <p>D = log. {l + 0 002623 cos. 2≠},</p>
                <p>„ , ( , 2z + Λ )</p>
                <p>E-log. j l + <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi> 37 <hi rend="subscript"> 8150</hi> ∫
                    ·</p>
                <p>Rühlmann has calculated the values A, C, D, and E for the different values of the
                    respective arguments, which are given in the tables appended to the -work.</p>
                <p>From formula (1) we obtain—</p>
                <p>log. ⅛=log. {log. <hi rend="italic">b</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">-</hi> log. δ"} +
                    (A + C + D + E) . . . (2).</p>
                <p>It is assumed that the whole stratum of air between the two heights is in a state
                    of rest, and that the means of the temperature and humidity observed at the two
                    stations are the means respectively of the stratum of air between them.</p>
                <p>If great accuracy is desired, both barometers. must be read from the zeros of
                    their scales, and the observations must be corrected for all merely instrumental
                    errors, and must be made strictly at the same time or times, seeing that a very
                    small error, arising either from imperfect observations, or from their not being
                    comparable, produces a comparatively large error in the calculated results.</p>
                <p>In deducing heights from <hi rend="italic">long-continued observations</hi> it
                    should be ascertained that the barometers and observations are good, and
                    observations should if possible be used which have been made at the same hours
                    of the day and during the same years. Observations at different hours of the day
                    are not comparable, since, owing to our imperfect knowledge of the differences
                    of daily barometric range, the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n402/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0402-0387"/> necessity for the application of any so-called
                    corrections for daily range must necessarily lead to error. The comparison
                    should also only be between observations made during the same years, since the
                    means of different years often differ widely from each other. Thus the
                    difference of height between two places at which barometrical observations were
                    made, from 1830 to 1859 and from 1850 to 1869 respectively, could be more
                    accurately ascertained from the ten years’ averages from 1850 to 1859 during
                    which observations were made at both places, than from the longer averages of
                    thirty and twenty years. Inattention to this point has often led to error,
                    especially in cases where at one of the places only a few years were available.
                    To secure greater accuracy, the calculations should be made on the mean for the
                    year, the two extreme months, January and July, and that month during which the
                    distribution of pressure is most uniform over the region where the places are
                    situated. Owing to the great differences in the distribution of atmospheric
                    pressure in different parts of the globe (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Atmosphere),</hi> comparison of the observations at the higher station with
                    those at more than one lower station is in some cases indispensable. Thus, if it
                    -were desired to compute the height of Dovre, in Norway, barometrically, it
                    should be compared both with Christiania and with Christiansund on the west
                    coast; for if compared with Christiania alone the calculated height would be too
                    high, and if with Christiansund too low, the reason being that the mean annual
                    pressure diminishes from Christiania to Christiansund. The same remark applies
                    to a large portion of Hindustan and to many other regions of the globe.</p>
                <p>The more special precautions to be taken in deducing heights from one or a few
                    observations, that is, from such data as travellers observe, are these :—that
                    the observations be made in as settled weather as possible, at those hours of
                    the day, at least, at which observations are made at the nearest meteorological
                    stations, and be repeated as long as possible from day to day; that the
                    barometer hang perpendicιdarly and in shade; and that the observations be not
                    made till the whole instrument has acquired the temperature of the surrounding
                    air. For, for every degree which the temperature indicated by the attached
                    thermometer differs from the temperature of the whole instrument, there is an
                    error of about 0Ό03 inch.</p>
                <p>From their portability and handiness the aneroid barometer, and the thermometer
                    for ascertaining the point at which water boils, are of great use in determining
                    heights,— the thermometer, if properly managed, being the more accurate of the
                    two. Since, owing to the sluggishness with which the aneroid often follows the
                    changes of pressure, especially low pressures, its readings should not be
                    recorded till it has hung for some hours at the place of observation, and if
                    this be not possible, the time w hich elapsed from arriving at the place and
                    making the observations should be stated. It may not be unnecessary to add that
                    every opportunity which presents itself should be taken of comparing it with a
                    standard mercurial barometer, owing to the variations, irregular or permanent,
                    to which aneroids are subject, and that the instrument should always be read in
                    one position, since the difference between the reading in a horizontal position
                    and the reading in a vertical position is often considerable.</p>
                <p>At a pressure of 29 ’ 905 inches distilled water boils at 212°. The temperature
                    of the boiling point varies with the nature of the vessel. Thus, if the interior
                    of the glass vessel be varnished with shell-lac, the temperature may rise to
                    221°; and if iron filings be dropped into the water, the temperature is lowered.
                    But in all these cases the temperature of the vapour arising from the water is
                    as nearly as possible the same. Hence in making observations with the
                    thermometer for hypsometrical purposes, the instrument is not plunged into the
                    water, but the whole instrument, bulb and stem, are by an apparatus used for the
                    purpose plunged into the vapour arising from the boiling water. The degrees on
                    the thermometer used aro greatly enlarged, thus admitting of a minute
                    subdivision of the scale and, consequently, of very precise readings. The
                    following are a few of the barometric heights corresponding to different
                    temperatures at which distilled water boils, taken from Regnault’s tables
                    revised by Moritz :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Boiling Point.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Barometer.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Boiling Point</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Barometer.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="subscript">
                            o</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>inches.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>,</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>inches.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>211</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>29'331</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>205</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>25-990</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>210</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>28'751</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>204</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>25'465</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>209</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>28∙180</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>203</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>24-949</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>208</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>27∙618</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>202</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>24'442</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>207</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>27-066</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>201</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>23'943</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>206</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>26-523 1</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>200</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>23-453</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The temperature of the vapour of the boiling water being observed, the pressure
                    is ascertained from the table, whence the height may be calculated, just as in
                    the case of pressures obtained by means of a mercurial barometer.</p>
                <p>The remark made by Sir John Leslie many years ago still holds good, that it is
                    preposterous, in the actual state of physical science, to effect any high
                    refinement in the formula for computing barometrical heights. What is required
                    on the part of the computer of heights from barometrical observations is
                    carefully to weigh the <hi rend="italic">limits of error</hi> due to the
                    instrument and methods of observations, to the hour of the day and the month of
                    the year (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Atmosphere,</hi> p. 28), and to the degree of
                    unsettledness of the weather at the time the observations were made, and to give
                    effect to these in the calculated results. From inattention to these simple
                    considerations a large proportion of important heights given in w orks of travel
                    and of physical geography are very erroneously stated, and consequently require
                    careful revision.</p>
                <p>For very rough approximations to the real height from observations of pressure
                    and temperature, Sir G. B. Airy has prepared a table showing the differences of
                    level corresponding to differences of pressure. It is from this table that the
                    heights corresponding to pressures engraved on many aneroids are usually taken.
                    The heights read off from the pressures should be corrected for observations of
                    temperature carefully taken at the upper and lower stations, the mean of these
                    two observations being assumed as the mean of the stratum of air occupying the
                    interval between the two heights. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a. b.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
