<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0519-0504-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BEETHOVEN, Ludwig van</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 3, page 504</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:815177">Art</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1030269">Music</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1030814">Musicals</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:821579">Austrians</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1135283">String</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1156809">Trios</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:873008">Concerto</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:873010">Concertos</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4599z39x">Concerto</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xn21">Sonata</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s24s">Mass</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mn33">Violin</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2ch0v">Music</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w744">Progress</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1210278">Belgium</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n519/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BEETHOVEN, <hi rend="smallcaps">Ludwig van</hi></label>, is
                    in music what Shakespeare is in poetry, a name before the greatness of which all
                    other names, however great, seem to dwindle. He stands at the end of an epoch in
                    musical history, marking its climax; but his works at the same time have ushered
                    in a new phase of progress, from which everything that is great in modern music
                    has taken its rise. This historic side of his genius will have to be further
                    dealt with when the progress of musical art is traced in its continuity. (See
                    article Music, historic section.) At present we have to consider Beethoven
                    chiefly as a man and an individual artist, showing at the same time the
                    reciprocal relations between his life and his work. For although the most ideal
                    artist in that most ideal of arts—music—he is always inspired by the deepest
                    sense of truth and reality. The grand note of sadness resounding in his
                    compositions is the reverberation of personal suffering. He was a great artist
                    only because he was a great man, and a sad man withal.</p>
                <p>The family of Beethoven is traceable to a village near Lowen in Belgium, in the
                    17th century. In 1G5O a member of this family, a lineal ancestor of our
                    composer, settled in Antwerp. Beethoven’s grandfather, Louis, owing to a quarrel
                    with his family, left Belgium for Germany, and came to Bonn in 1732, where his
                    musical talents and his beautiful voice did not long remain unnoticed. The
                    archbishop of Cologne, an art-loving prelate, received him amongst his
                    court-musicians; and the same position afterwards was held by Ludwig’s son,
                    Johann, our composer’s father. The latter was married to Maria Magdalena
                    Keverich, daughter of a cook, and widow of a <hi rend="italic"
                    >valet-de-chambre</hi> of the elector of Trêves. The day of our composer’s birth
                    is uncertain; he was baptised Dec. 17, 1770, and received <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n520/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0520-0505"/> the name of his paternal grandfather Louis, or,
                    in its Germanized form, Ludwig. Beethoven himself seems to have considered the
                    16th December of the said year his birthday, but documentary evidence is
                    wanting. At one period of his life he believed himself to have been born in
                    1772, being most likely deceived on the point by his father, who tried to endow
                    his son and pupil with the <hi rend="italic">prestige</hi> of miraculous
                    precocity. No less uncertain than the date is the exact place of the great
                    composer’s birth; two houses in Bonn claim the honour of having been the scene
                    of the important event. The youth of Beethoven was passed under by no means
                    happy circumstances. His father was of a rough and violent temper, not improved
                    by his passion for intoxicating drink, nor by the dire poverty under which the
                    family laboured. His chief desire was to reap the earliest possible advantage
                    from the musical abilities of his son, who, in consequence, had at the age of
                    five to submit to a severe training on the violin under the father’s
                    supervision. Little benefit was derived from this unsystematic mode of
                    instruction, which, fortunately, was soon abandoned for a more methodical course
                    of pianoforte lessons under a musician of the name of Pfeiffer. Under him and
                    two other masters, Van der Eden and Neefe, Beethoven made rapid progress as a
                    player of the organ and pianoforte; his proficiency in the theoretical knowledge
                    of his art the aspiring composer soon displayed in a set of Variations on a
                    March published in 1783, with the inscription on the title-page, <hi
                    rend="italic">“par</hi><hi rend="italic">un jeune</hi><hi rend="italic">amateur,
                    Louis van Beethoven,</hi><hi rend="italic">âgé dix ans,”</hi> a statement the
                    inaccuracy of which the reader will be able to trace to its proper source. In
                    1785 Beethoven was appointed assistant of the courtorganist Neefe; and in a <hi
                    rend="italic">catalogue</hi><hi rend="italic">raisonné</hi> of the musicians
                    attached to the court of the archbishop, he is described as “of good capacity,
                    young, of good, quiet behaviour, and poor.” The elector of Cologne at the time
                    was Max Franz, a brother of the Emperor Joseph, who seems to have recognized the
                    first sparks of genius in the quiet and little communicative youth. By him
                    Beethoven was, in 1787, sent for a short time to Vienna, to receive a few
                    lessons from Mozart, who is said to have predicted a great future for his
                    youthful pupil. Beethoven soon returned to Bonn, where he remained for the next
                    five years in the position already described. Little remains to be said of this
                    period of apprenticeship. Beethoven conscientiously studied his art, and
                    reluctantly saw himself compelled to alleviate the difficulties of his family by
                    giving lessons. This aversion to making his art useful to himself by imparting
                    it to others remained a characteristic feature of our master during all his
                    life. Of the compositions belonging to this time nothing now remains; and it
                    must be confessed that, compared with those of other masters, of Mozart or
                    Handel, for instance, Beethoven’s early years were little fertile with regard
                    either to the quantity or the quality of the works produced. Amongst the names
                    connected with his stay at Bonn we mention only that of his first friend, and
                    protector, Count Waldstein, to whom it is said Beethoven owed his appointment at
                    the electoral court, and his first journey to Vienna. To the latter city the
                    young musician repaired a second time in 1792, in order to complete his studies
                    under Haydn, the greatest master then living, who had become acquainted with
                    Beethoven’s talent as a pianist and composer on a previous occasion. The
                    relation of these two great men was not to be fruitful or pleasant to either of
                    them. The mild, easy-going nature of the senescent Viennese master was little
                    adapted to inspire with awe, or even with sympathy, the fiery Rhenish youth.
                    Beethoven in after life asserted that he had never learned anything from Haydn,
                    and seems even to have doubted the latter’s intention of teaching him in a
                    proper manner. He seems to have had more confidence in the instruction of
                    Albrechtsberger, a dry but thorough scholar. He, however, and all the other
                    masters of Beethoven agree in the statement, that being taught was not much to
                    the liking of their self-willed pupil. He preferred acquiring by his own
                    toilsome experience what it would have been easier to accept on the authority of
                    others. This autodidactic vein, inherent, it seems, in all artistic genius, was
                    of immense importance in the development of Beethoven’s ideas and mode of
                    expression.</p>
                <p>In the meantime his worldly prospects seemed to be of the brightest kind. The
                    introductions from the archbishop and Count Waldstein gave him admittance to the
                    drawingrooms of the Austrian aristocracy, an aristocracy unrivalled by that of
                    any other country in its appreciation of artistic and especially musical talent.
                    Vienna, moreover, had been recently the scene of Mozart’s truimphs; and that
                    prophet’s cloak now seemed to rest on the shoulders of the young Rhenish
                    musician. It was chiefly his original style as a pianist, combined with an
                    astonishing gift of improvisation, that at first impressed the amateurs of the
                    capital; and it seems, indeed, that even Haydn expected greater things from the
                    executive than from the creative talent of his pupil. It may be added here,
                    that, according to the unanimous verdict of competent witnesses, Beethoven’s
                    greatness as a pianoforte player consisted more in the bold, impulsive rendering
                    of his poetical intentions than in the absolute finish of his <hi rend="italic"
                    >technique,</hi> which, particularly in his later years, when his growing
                    deafness debarred him from self-criticism, was somewhat deficient.</p>
                <p>As a composer Beethoven appeared before the public of the Austrian capital in
                    1795. In that year his Three Trios for Pianoforte and Strings were published.
                    Beethoven called this work his <hi rend="italic">Opus</hi> 1, and thus seems to
                    disown his former compositions as juvenile attempts unworthy of remembrance. He
                    was at that time twenty-five, an age at which Mozart had reaped some of the
                    ripest fruits of his genius. But Beethoven’s works are not like those of the
                    earlier master, the result of juvenile and all but unconscious spontaneity; they
                    are the bitter fruits of thought and sorrow, the results of a passionate but
                    conscious strife for ideal aims. Before considering these works in their chief
                    features, we will add a few more remarks as to the life and character of their
                    author. The events of his outward career are so few and of so simple a kind that
                    a continuous narrative seems hardly required. The numerous admirers whom
                    Beethoven’s art had found amongst the highest circles of Vienna,—Archduke
                    Rudolf, his devoted pupil and friend, amongst the number,—determined him to take
                    up his permanent residence in that city, which henceforth he left only for
                    occasional excursions to Baden, Mödling, and other places in the beautiful
                    surroundings of the Austrian capital. It was here, in his lonely walks, that the
                    master received new impulse from his admiring intercourse with nature, and that
                    most of his grandest works were conceived and partly sketched. Except for a
                    single artistic tour to Northern Germany in 1796, Beethoven never left Vienna
                    for any length of time. A long-projected journey to England, in answer to an
                    invitation of the London Philharmonic Society, was ultimately made impossible by
                    ill-health. Beethoven’s reputation as a composer soon became established beyond
                    the limits of his own country, notwithstanding the charges of abstruseness,
                    unpopularity, and the like, which he, like most men of original power, had to
                    submit to from the obtuse arrogance of contemporary criticism. The summit of his
                    fame, so far as it manifested itself in personal honours conferred upon him, was
                    reached in 1815, when Beethoven celebrated by a Symphony the victories of the
                    Allies over the French oppressor, and was rewarded by the applause of the
                    sovereigns of Europe, assembled at the Congress of Vienna.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n521/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0521-0506"/>
                <p>In the same year lie received the freedom of that city, an honour much valued by
                    him. After that time his immediate popularity began to some extent to decline
                    before the ephemeral splendour of the composers of the day; and the great master
                    seemed henceforth to speak more to coming generations than to his ungrateful
                    contemporaries. When, however, on rare occasions he emerged from his solitude,
                    the old spell of his overpowering genius proved to be unbroken. In particular,
                    mention must be made of that memorable <hi rend="italic">Academie</hi> (concert)
                    in 1824, at which his 9th Symphony, and parts of the grand <hi rend="italic"
                    >Missa.</hi><hi rend="italic">Solemnis,</hi> were performed, producing a storm
                    of applause—inaudible, alas! to the composer, who had to be turned round by one
                    of the singers to realize, from the waving of hats and handkerchiefs, the effect
                    of his work on the excited multitude.</p>
                <p>The last-mentioned incident leads us to one of the most tragic features of
                    Beethoven’s life. By the bitter irony of fate, he who had given to thousands
                    enjoyment and elevation of the heart by the art of sound, was himself deprived
                    of the sense of hearing. The first traces of beginning deafness showed
                    themselves as early as 1797, and were perceived by the master with an anxiety
                    bordering on despair. Physicians and quacks were consulted with eagerness, but
                    all their efforts (partly impaired, it must be confessed, l»y the unruly
                    disposition of the patient) proved unable to stem the encroaching evil. The
                    Royal Library of Berlin possesses a melancholy collection of ear-trumpets and
                    similar instruments, partly made expressly for Beethoven to assist his weakened
                    sense, but all to no avail. In his latter years conversation with him could be
                    carried on by writing only, and of the charms of his own art he was wholly
                    deprived. But here, again, the victory of mind over matter,—of genius over
                    circumstance, — was evinced in the most triumphant manner. It has been asserted,
                    not without reason, that the euphonious beauty of some of Beethoven’s vocal
                    compositions has suffered through his inability to listen to them; but how grand
                    is, on the other hand, the spectacle of an artist deprived of all intercourse
                    with what to him in this world was dearest, and yet pouring forth the lonely
                    aspirations of his soul in works all the more sublime as we seem to hear in them
                    the voice of the innermost spirit of mankind, inaudible to the keen ears of
                    other mortals. If iu this manner the isolation of Beethoven further sublimated
                    his efforts as an artist, it, on the other hand, poignantly intensified his
                    sufferings as a man. His was a heart open to the impressions of friendship and
                    love, and, in spite of occasional roughness of utterance, yearning for the
                    responsive affection of his kind. It is deeply touching to read the following
                    words in the master’s last will, written during a severe illness in 1802 :—“Ye
                    men,” Beethoven writes, “who believe or say that I am inimical, rough, or
                    misanthropical, how unjust are you to me in your ignorance of the secret cause
                    of what appears to you in that light. . . , Born with a fiery, lively temper,
                    and susceptible to the enjoyment of society, I have been compelled early to
                    isolate myself and lead a lonely life; whenever I tried to overcome this
                    isolation, oh! how doubly bitter was then the sad experience of my bad hearing,
                    which repelled me again; and yet it was impossible for me to tell people, ‘
                    Speak louder, shout, for I am deaf.’”</p>
                <p>Domestic troubles and discomforts contributed in a minor degree to darken the
                    shadow cast over our master’s life by the misfortune just alluded to. Although
                    by no means insensible to female beauty, and indeed frequently enraptured in his
                    grand, chaste way, with the charms of some lady, Beethoven never married, and
                    was, in consequence, deprived of that feeling of home and comfort which only the
                    unceasing care of refined womanhood can bestow. His helplessness and ignorance
                    of worldly matters completely exposed him to the ill-treatment of servants,
                    frequently, perhaps, excited by his own morbid suspicions and complaints. On one
                    occasion the great master was discovered with his face bleeding from the
                    scratches inflicted by his own valet. It was from amidst such surroundings that
                    Beethoven ascended to the sublime elevation of such works as his <hi
                    rend="italic">Missa</hi><hi rend="italic">Solemnis</hi> or his 9th Symphony. But
                    his deepest wounds were to be inflicted by dearer and nearer hands than those of
                    brutal domestics. Beethoven had a nephew, rescued by him from vice and misery,
                    and loved with a more than father’s affection. His education the master watched
                    with unceasing care. For him he hoarded with anxious parsimony the scanty
                    earnings of his artistic labour. Unfortunately, the young man was unworthy of
                    such love, and at last disgraced his great name by an attempt at suicide, to the
                    deepest grief of his noble guardian and benefactor.</p>
                <p>Beethoven died on March 27, 1827, during a terrible thunderstorm. It ought to
                    fill every Englishman’s heart with pride that it was given to the London
                    Philharmonic Society to relieve the anxieties of Beethoven’s deathbed by a
                    liberal gift, and that almost the last utterances of the dying man were words of
                    thauks to his friends and admirers iu this country.</p>
                <p>Beethoven’s compositions, 138 in number, comprise all the forms of vocal and
                    instrumental music, from the sonata to the symphony,—from the simple song to the
                    opera and oratorio. In each of these forms he displayed the depth of his
                    feeling, the power of his genius; in some of them he reached a greatness never
                    approached by his predecessors or followers. His pianoforte sonatas have brought
                    the technical resources of that instrument to a perfection previously unknown,
                    but they at the same time embody an infinite variety and depth of emotion. His
                    nine symphonies show a continuous climax of development, ascending from the
                    simpler forms of Haydn and Mozart to the colossal dimensions of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Choral Symphony,</hi> which almost seems to surpass the
                    possibilities of artistic expansion, and the subject of which is humanity itself
                    with its sufferings and ideals. His dramatic works—the opera <hi rend="italic"
                    >Fidelio,</hi> and the overtures to <hi rend="italic">Egmont</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Coriolanus—</hi> display depth of pathos and force of dramatic
                    characterization. Even his smallest songs and pianoforte-pieces reflect a heart
                    full of love, and a mind bent on thoughts of eternal things.</p>
                <p>Beethoven’s career as a composer is generally divided into three periods of
                    gradual progress. We subjoin a list of his most important compositions, grouped
                    according to the principle indicated.</p>
                <p>The first period extends to the year 1800. At the beginning we see Beethoven
                    under the influence of his great predecessors, Haydn and Mozart, but progressing
                    in rapid strides towards independence of thought and artistic power. To this
                    time belong Three Trios for Pianoforte and Strings, <hi rend="italic">Op.</hi>
                    1; Sonata for Pianoforte in E flat, <hi rend="italic">Op.</hi> 7; Trio for
                    Pianoforte and Strings in B flat, <hi rend="italic">Op.</hi> 11; <hi
                    rend="italic">Sonate</hi><hi rend="italic">Pathétique</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >;</hi> First Concerto for Pianoforte and Orchestra in C, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Op.</hi> 15; <hi rend="italic">Adelaida</hi> (composed 1797); also the
                    celebrated Septuor, <hi rend="italic">Op.</hi> 20, and the First Symphony, <hi
                    rend="italic">Op.</hi> 21 (the last two works published in 1800).</p>
                <p>The second period, from 1800-1814, marks the climax of formal perfection. The
                    works of this time show the highest efforts of which music as an independent art
                    is capable. We mention the Mass in C, <hi rend="italic">Op.</hi> 86; our
                    master’s only opera, <hi rend="italic">Fidelio,</hi> and his overture and
                    incidental music to Goethe’s <hi rend="italic">Egmont;</hi> the Symphonies, Nos.
                    2-8, amongst which those called the <hi rend="italic">Pastoral,</hi> the <hi
                    rend="italic">Eroica,</hi><note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>This symphony was originally written in celebration of Napoleon, at that
                    time consul of the French Republic. When Beethoven heard of his assuming the
                    imperial title, he tore off the dedication and trampled it under
                    foot.</p></note> and those <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n522/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0522-0507"/> in C minor and A major deserve special mention;
                    Concerto for the Violin, <hi rend="italic">Op.</hi> 61; Concerti for the
                    Pianoforte, Nos. 3-5; Overtures to <hi rend="italic">Prometheus,
                    Coriolanus,</hi><hi rend="italic">Fidelio,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">King
                    Stephen;</hi> also numerous sonatas for the pianoforte, quartets, quintets, and
                    other pieces of chamber music.</p>
                <p>The third period may be described as that of <hi rend="italic">poetic</hi>
                    music,—a distinct poetic idea becoming the moving principle before which the
                    forms of absolute music have to yield. Beethoven has, by the works belonging to
                    this class, ushered in a new phase of music, as will be further shown in the
                    historical sketch of the art. We name that unequalled master-piece of symphonic
                    art, the Ninth or <hi rend="italic">Choral Symphony;</hi> the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Missa</hi><hi rend="italic">Solemnis;</hi> the Sonatas for Pianoforte, numbered
                    respectively <hi rend="italic">Op.</hi> 101, 102, 106, 109, 110, 111; the
                    marvellous Quartets for Strings, <hi rend="italic">Op.</hi> 127, 130, 132, 135;
                    also the 33 Variations on a Valse by Diabelli, <hi rend="italic">Op.</hi>
                    120.</p>
                <p>For fuller information on the great master’s life and works than our limited
                    space has permitted us to give, we refer the reader to the biographical and
                    critical works of Schindler, Thayer, Nohl, Marx, and Nottebohm, <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">(f. h.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
