<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0903-0850-0833-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BLOCK MACHINERY (9th edition, volume 3, page
                    833)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p843w5c">Hand</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r47q">Cuttings</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mg7fz12">Cutting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42b8vd88">Contractions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rb6w48j">Dockyards</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1750261">Inch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950823">Hand</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1179191">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1046386">Operationalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1115245">Shapes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1216469">Brunei</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n850/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BLOCK MACHINERY</label>. A block is a case with its contained
                    pulley or pulleys, by means of which weighty objects are hoisted or lowered with
                    facility. There is nothing in the appearance of a block which, to an unpractised
                    eye, would seem to require any stretch of mental ingenuity or of manual
                    dexterity to manufacture. It is a machine apparently so rude in its structure,
                    and so simple in its contrivance, that the name was probably given to it from
                    its general resemblance to a log ot wood, as is obviously the case with a
                    butcher’s block, a barber’s block, the block of the executioner, &amp;c. Of the
                    two constituent parts of a ship’s block, the external <hi rend="italic"
                        >shell</hi> and the internal <hi rend="italic">sheave,</hi> every carpenter
                    might make the one, and every turner the other; but still block-making is a
                    separate branch of trade, and it is necessary that it should be, for the whole
                    effici ency of the block depends upon the proper proportions being observed
                    between the various parts and the accuracy with which they are adjusted.</p>
                <p>Mr Walter Taylor of Southampton took out a patent in the year 1781, to secure the
                    benefit of some improvement he had made in the construction of the sheaves. He
                    also shaped the shells, cut the timber, &amp;c., by machinery driven by water,
                    and carried on so extensive a manufacture of blocks as to be able to contract
                    for nearly the whole supply of blocks and blockmakers’ wares required for the
                    use of the Royal Navy. Mr Dunsterville of Plymouth had a similar set of machines
                    wrought by horse-power. Both his blocks and Taylor’s were said to be superior to
                    those constructed by the hand, though still deficient in many respects.</p>
                <p>It would appear that it was the enormous quantity of blocks consumed in the
                    course of a long protracted war that first called the attention of the Admiralty
                    or Navy Board to the possibility of some reduction being made in the expense of
                    so important an article, and to the imprudence of depending entirely on a single
                    contractor. On these considerations, it seems to have been the intention of
                    Government to introduce, among other improvements in Portsmouth Dockyard about
                    1801, a set of machines for making blocks there. About this time, too, Mr Brunel
                    had completed a working model of certain machines for constructing, by an
                    improved method, the shells and sheaves of blocks. This model was submitted to
                    the inspection of the lords commissioners of the Admiralty, and it was decided
                    to adopt Mr Brunel’s more ingenious machinery.</p>
                <p>The advantages to be gained were those common to all cases in which machine work
                    supersedes hand labour, and consisted in the fact that, after the proper sizes
                    of each part had been determined by careful calculation and experience, the
                    machine could be made to observe these sizes with unerring accuracy, and so
                    avoid all variations due to the carelessness or ignorance of the workman; these
                    considerations are in blocks, perhaps more than in most things, of the utmost
                    importance. Another advantage was, that the blocks could be made by Brunei’s
                    machinery about 30 per cent, cheaper than hand-made blocks had been previously
                    obtained by contract, and the importance of this to the Admiralty in those days,
                    when all ships were so heavily rigged, having no steam to supplement their sail
                    power, will be sufficiently seen when it is stated that the remuneration which
                    Brunel was to receive for his invention was agreed to be the savings of one
                    year, and that these savings were estimated at £16,621; in addition to this he
                    received an allowance of a guinea a day for about six years while engaged on the
                    work, and was paid £1000 for his working model—the total amount paid to Brunel
                    for the invention amounting to about £20,000.</p>
                <p>The process may be described as follows :—Pieces of wood are cut roughly to the
                    size of the block, and the first operation is then performed by the <hi
                        rend="italic">boring-machine,</hi> which bores a hole for the pin, and one,
                    two, or three holes, as the case may be, for single, double, or treble blocks,
                    to receive the first stroke of the mortising chisel; the block is next taken to
                    the <hi rend="italic">mortising-machine,</hi> where the mortise or mortises for
                    the sheaves are cut; after this, to a <hi rend="italic">circular saw,</hi>
                    conveniently arranged for cutting off the corners and so preparing the block for
                    the <hi rend="italic">shaping-machine,</hi> which consists principally of two
                    equal and parallel circular wheels <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n851/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0903-0851-0834"/> moving on the same axis, to which one of them
                    is firmly fixed, but on which the other is made to slide; so that these two
                    wheels may be placed at any given distance from each other, and blocks of any
                    size admitted between their two rims or peripheries. For this purpose, both rims
                    are divided into ten equal parts, for the reception of ten blocks, which are
                    firmly fixed between the two wheels. When the double wheel with its ten attached
                    blocks is put in motion, the outer surface of the blocks, or those which are
                    farthest from the centre, strike against the edge of a chisel or gouge fixed in
                    a movable frame, which, being made to slide in a curved direction in the line of
                    the axis, cuts those outward faces of the blocks to their proper curvature. A
                    contrivance is attached to the cutting tool which allows of the curvature being
                    altered in any required way. One side being shaped, the ten blocks are then, by
                    a single operation, each turned one fourth part round, and another side is
                    exposed to the cutting instrument moving in the same direction as before. A
                    third side is then turned outwards, and after that the fourth side, when the
                    whole ten blocks are completely shaped.</p>
                <p>The velocity with which the wheels revolve, and the great weight with which their
                    peripheries are loaded, would make it dangerous to the workmen or bystanders,
                    if, by the violence of the centrifugal force, auy of the blocks should happen to
                    be thrown off from the rim of the wheels; to prevent the possibility of such an
                    accident, an iron cage or guard is placed between the workman and the
                    machine.</p>
                <p>The last operation is performed by the <hi rend="italic">scoring-machine,</hi>
                    which cuts a groove to receive the binding or strapping of the block. The
                    binding may be of iron or rope, and is very frequently of wire rope.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The Sheaves.—</hi> The machinery employed for making this part
                    of the block consists of a <hi rend="italic">circular saw,</hi> by which the log
                    is cut into plates of the thickness required for the sheaves, according to their
                    several diameters. These plates are next carried to a <hi rend="italic">crown
                        saw,</hi> which bores the central hole, and at the same time reduces them to
                    a perfect circle of the assigned diameter. The sheave, thus shaped, is next
                    brought to the <hi rend="italic">coahing-machine,</hi> a piece of mechanism not
                    inferior in ingenuity to the shaping machine for the shells. A small cutter, in
                    traversing round the central hole of the sheave, forms a groove for the
                    insertion of the <hi rend="italic">coak</hi> or <hi rend="italic">bush,</hi> the
                    shape of which is that of three semicircles, not concentric with each other, nor
                    with the sheave, but each having a centre equally distant from that of the
                    sheave. The manner in which the cutter traverses from the first to the second,
                    and from this to the third semicircle, after finishing each of them, is
                    exceedingly ingenious. So very exact and accurate is this groove cut for the
                    reception of the metal coak, and so uniform in their shape and size are the
                    latter cast, the casting being made not in sand but in iron moulds, that they
                    are invariably found to fit each other so nicely that the tap of a hammer is
                    sufficient to fix the coak in its place. The coaks are cast with small grooves
                    or channels in the inside of their tubes, which serve to retain the oil or
                    grease for the pins.</p>
                <p>The sheave, with its coak thus fitted in, is now taken to the <hi rend="italic"
                        >drilling-machine,</hi> which is kept in constant motion. In casting the
                    coaks a mark is left in the centre of each of the three semicircles. This mark
                    is applied by a boy to the point of the moving drill, which speedily goes
                    through the two coaks and the intermediate wood of the sheave. Rivets are put in
                    these holes and clenched by hand. The next operation is performed by the <hi
                        rend="italic">faxing-machine,</hi> which has two cutters, so arranged as to
                    finish the side and groove the edge simultaneously; then the hole for the pin is
                    enlarged to its exact size by the <hi rend="italic">broaching-machine.</hi> The
                    pins, which form a very important part of the block, are now made at Portsmouth,
                    not of <hi rend="italic">iron</hi> but of <hi rend="italic">steel,</hi>
                    carefully tempered by special appliances. They are turned by a <hi rend="italic"
                        >self-acting lathe,</hi> and are then reduced to the exact required
                    diameter, and polished in the <hi rend="italic">pin-polishing machine.</hi> They
                    are also, in this machine, subjected to a proof strain proportional to their
                    sectional area, and thus the strength of the pin is guaranteed.</p>
                <p>The blocks are invariably made of English elm, the grain of the wood running
                    lengthways of the block; but in Germany recently, blocks have been made with the
                    grain of the wood running across the block, the reason being that they are less
                    likely to be split by the pressure on the pin of the sheave. The sheaves are
                    made of lignum vitae.</p>
                <p>Three machines of each description for each operation, up to and including the
                    facing-machine, are required. The smallest sized machines will make blocks of
                    from 4 inches to 7 inches in length, the second size from 8 inches to 11 inches,
                    and the largest from 12 inches to 17 inches. Two sizes of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >broaching-machine,</hi> and one <hi rend="italic">pin-polishing
                        machine,</hi> are sufficient. Blocks larger than 17 inches are made by hand,
                    26 inches being the largest used in the Royal Navy.</p>
                <p>As will be seen from the foregoing account, all machine-made blocks are cut out
                    of a solid piece of wood; whereas hand-made blocks, larger than about 8 inches,
                    are usually made in pieces, filled in at the ends and riveted together. It is
                    questionable whether a block so made is not stronger than one cut out of the
                    solid, as in the latter case the short-grained wood at the ends of the mortises
                    is very liable to give way. In hand-made blocks the brass coak or tail of the
                    sheave is not made of the peculiar shape described for machine-made blocks, but
                    is usually of a circular shape.</p>
                <p>The machinery for Portsmouth Dockyard, on Brunel’s plans, was made by Maudslay,
                    whose firm—now the very eminent firm of Maudslay Sons and Field—has since
                    supplied block-making machinery to the Spanish, Turkish, and Russian
                    Governments, and also to Chatham Dockyard; the last mentioned, however, has
                    never been used, as the machinery at Portsmouth is capable of supplying all the
                    dockyards, the demand for blocks being much less for the steamships and
                    ironclads than it was formerly for the old sailing ships. The first cost of this
                    machinery is so great that no private firm has yet ventured to set it up, and
                    the whole of the blocks used in merchant ships are made by hand-labour, assisted
                    by a lathe and two or three other simple mechanical contrivances. (τ. <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">μ.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
