<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0609-0592-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BERKSHIRE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 3, page 592</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4x921m3r">Parks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zv9m">Streets</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43j3985w">Danes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49p2w64d">Barrows</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tv2w">Canals</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47p8th1t">Worth</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1174597">White</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1174816">Whites</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1053705">Parks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1134794">Streets</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:845230">Canals</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n609/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BERKSHIRE</label>, one of the south-eastern counties of
                    England, bounded on the N.E. by Buckinghamshire, from which it is separated by
                    the Thames; N. by Oxfordshire and a small portion of Gloucester; W. by Wilts <hi
                    rend="italic">; S.</hi> by Hants; and S.E. by Surrey. It is of a very irregular
                    figure, extending from east to west fully 60 miles; while from north to south,
                    in its widest part, it is about 35 miles, and in its narrowest part, at Reading,
                    not more than 7. Area, 450,132 acres.</p>
                <p>In respect to the character of its surface and soil, the county may be
                    conveniently regarded as consisting of two divisions—the eastern, containing the
                    six districts east and inclusive of Bradfield, and the western, embracing the
                    remaining six districts. The surface of the eastern division is partly level and
                    partly undulating, and in many places, as at Windsor, it is beautifully wooded.
                    The highest ground is at Bagshot Heath, a sandy plateau 460 feet high, at the
                    south-east comer of the county. The character of the soil in the eastern
                    division is considered poorer than in the west, and consists mostly of blue clay
                    and gravel, resting on a chalk formation. In this division, tillage, dairy
                    farming, and manufacturing are more extensively pursued than in the other, and
                    it is consequently more thickly populated. The western or upland division
                    contains a large proportion of elevated ground, and its soil is a reddish
                    gravelly loam. Here a line of chalk hills, reaching from Aid worth to Ashbury
                    (which includes the ∏sley Downs), runs east and west, separating the two fertile
                    valleys of the Kennet and the Thames. Another range of chalk downs, known as the
                    Cuckamsley Hills, extends from the neighbourhood of Wantage to the border of
                    Wiltshire, the highest point being White-Horse Hill, 893 feet high. In this part
                    of the county the rearing of sheep is largely carried on, while in the district
                    of Hungerford, which is situated in the basin of the Kennet, the soil allows a
                    large breadth of tillage, and a greater number of persons are engaged in
                    agricultural pursuits there than any other district in the county.</p>
                <p>Wheat and beans are extensively cultivated; and a species of peat found on the
                    banks of the Kennet yields ashes that are of great value to the soils near that
                    river. In the vales of Kennet and White-Horse dairy farming predominates. Near
                    Faringdon pigs are extensively reared, and the breed is celebrated. The estate
                    of Pusey, in the district of Faringdon, presents one of the best examples of
                    high class farming, while in the eastern division the model farms in the
                    district of Wokingham, the property of John Walter, Esq., M.P. for the county,
                    may be referred to as the best specimens of the recent improvements in
                    agriculture. Mr Walter’s mansion at Bearwood, too, is an instance of a baronial
                    residence seldom equalled in extent and admirable disposition.</p>
                <p>Few parts of England are better supplied with the facilities of water
                    communication than the county of Berks. It is connected by means of the Thames
                    with London on the one hand, and on the other with the Severn at two separate
                    points on that river;—one through the Thames and Severn canal, some miles below
                    Gloucester, the other through the River Kennet and the Kennet and Avon canal by
                    Bath and Bristol. Besides the navigable rivers, it enjoys the benefit of the
                    Wilts and Berks canal, which connects the Thames at Abingdon with the Avon at
                    Trowbridge in Wiltshire, and communicates with the Kennet and Avon canal. The
                    other rivers, which all finally fall into the Thames, are the Ock, the Loddon,
                    the Enborne, and the Lamboum.</p>
                <p>The turnpike roads are generally good. The principal of these are the roads from
                    London to Bath and Oxford, both of which enter the county at Maidenhead, and
                    soon afterwards separate, the former running S.W. to Reading, the latter nearly
                    N.W. to Henley. Eight branches of railway intersect the county, viz., the Great
                    Western, from Maidenhead to Reading, and from Reading to Shriven ham; the branch
                    from Didcot to Hincksey and Oxford; the Berks and Hants railway branches from
                    Reading to Mortimer and Basingstoke, and from Reading to Newbury and Hungerford;
                    the Reading, Guildford, and Reigate line; and the Reading, Wokingham, and
                    Staines branch of the South-Western Railway.</p>
                <p>Berkshire is not a manufacturing county, although the woollen manufacture was
                    introduced here as long ago as the time of the Tudors. There are some
                    paper-mills, particularly in the neighbourhood of Newbury, and an extensive
                    biscuit manufactory at Reading. The chief trade consists in agricultural
                    produce.</p>
                <p>From its vicinity to the metropolis, the salubrity of the climate, and the
                    general beauty of the country, few counties have more numerous seats of the
                    nobility and gentry than are to be found in Berkshire. Among these stands
                    preeminent the royal castle of Windsor, the favourite residence of our monarchs
                    during many centuries. There may also be mentioned Wytham Abbey (earl of
                    Abingdon); Ashdown Park and Hamstead Marshall (earl of Craven); Coleshill (earl
                    of Radnor); Shrivenham House (Viscount Barrington); Easthampstead Park (marquis
                    of Downshire); Englefield House (R. Benyon, Esq., M.P.); Aldermaston House
                    (Higford Burr, Esq.); South Hill Park (Rt. Hon. Sir W. G. Hayter, Bart.); Pusey
                    House (Sydney Bouverie Pusey, Esq.); Bearwood (John Walter, Esq., M.P.); and
                    Lockinge House (Col. Loyd Lindsay, V.C., M.P.)</p>
                <p>The county comprises 20 hundreds, 6 municipal boroughs, and 142 parishes, besides
                    14 others chiefly or partially included in Berks. The county is in the diocese
                    of Oxford and the ecclesiastical province of Canterbury. It forms an
                    archdeaconry by itself, and is divided into the four rural deaneries of
                    Abingdon, Newbury, Reading, and Wallingford. It is in the Oxford circuit, and
                    the assizes are held at Reading. County courts are held at Abingdon, Faringdon,
                    Hungerford, Maidenhead, Newbury, Reading, Wallingford, Wantage, Windsor, and
                    Wokingham.</p>
                <p>Berkshire returns 3 members to parliament for the county, 2 for the borough of
                    Reading, and 1 for each of the boroughs of Abingdon, Wallingford, and
                    Windsor.</p>
                <p>At the three decennial enumerations the population of the county was as follows
                    :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Houses.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Population.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Increase per cent.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1851</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>35,075</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>170,065</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1861</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>37,324</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>176,256</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1871</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>41,821</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>196,475</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>10</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The chief increase has taken place in the eastern division of the county, where
                    the density of the population amounted in 1871 to about 1 person to 1 <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi> 5 acre; while in the western it was 1 person to 3 <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi> 5 acres. The principal towns in the county are
                    Reading (pop. 32,324), Windsor (11,769), Newbury (6602), Maidenhead (6173),
                    Abingdon (5799), Wantage (3295), and Wallingford (2972). The population of the
                    parliamentary districts differs from the above, as these districts include
                    persons located beyond the boundaries of the boroughs.</p>
                <p>Antiquities, both Roman and Saxon, are numerous in various parts of this county.
                    Watling Street enters Berkshire from Bedfordshire at the village of Streatley,
                    and leaves it at Newbury. Another Roman road passes from Reading to Newbury,
                    where it divides into two branches, one passing to Marlborough in Wiltshire, and
                    the other to Cirencester in Gloucestershire. A branch of Icknield Street passes
                    from Walling!ord to Wantage. Near Wantage<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n610/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0610-0593"/> Ï3 a Roman camp, of a quadrangular form; and
                    there are other remains of encampments at East Hampstead near Wokingham, at
                    Pusey, on White-Horse Hill, and at Sino-dun Hill, near Wallingford. At Lawrence
                    Waltham there is a Roman fort, and near Dench worth a fortress said to have been
                    built by Canute the Dane, called Cherbury Castle. Barrows are very numerous in
                    the downs in the N.W. of the county, particularly between Lambourn and Wantage.
                    Dragon Hill is supposed to have been the burying-place of a British prince
                    called Uther Pendragon, and near to it is Uffington Castle, supposed to be of
                    Danish construction. On White-Horse Hill, in the same vicinity, is the rude
                    figure of what is called a horse, although it bears a greater resemblance to a
                    greyhound. It has been formed by cutting away the turf and leaving the chalk
                    bare. It occupies nearly an acre of land, and is said to have been executed by
                    Alfred to celebrate a victory over the Danes in the reign of his brother
                    Ethelred, in the year 872. This memorial, not having been “scoured” for many
                    years, is nearly obliterated by the growth of the turf over the chalk. It is
                    part of the property of the earl of Craven.</p>
                <p>Berkshire comprehended the principality inhabited by the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Atrebates,</hi> a tribe of people who originally migrated from Gaul. Under the
                    Romans it formed part of <hi rend="italic">Britannia</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Prima,</hi> and during the Saxon heptarchy was included in the kingdom of the
                    West Saxons. When Alfred divided the country into shires, hundreds, and
                    parishes, it obtained the name of <hi rend="italic">Berocscire,</hi> which was
                    subsequently changed to that which it now bears. It was frequently the scene of
                    military operations from the time of Offa down to the troubles in the reign of
                    Charles I. During the civil war two battles were fought at Newbury. In 1643,
                    after a siege, Reading was taken by the Parliamentary forces, and the Royalist
                    party were expelled from the whole of the county except Wallingford.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
