<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0685-0668-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BIGAMY</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 3, page 668</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:964412">Husbands</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:950030">Habit</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1058777">Personals</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:978902">Irish</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cn85">Habit</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sx86">Personality</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9q84g">Widows</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n685/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BIGAMY</label>, according to the statute now in force (24 and
                    25 Vict. c. 100, § 57), is the offence committed by a person who “being married
                    shall marry any other person during the life of the former husband or wife.” In
                    the canon law the word had a rather wider meaning, and the marriage of a widow
                    came within its scope. At the Council of Lyons (1274 A.D.) bigamists were
                    stripped of their privilege of clergy. This canon was adopted and explained by
                    the English statute 4 Edward I. st. 3, c. 5; and bigamy, therefore, became a
                    usual counterplea to the claim of <hi rend="italic">benefit of clergy.</hi>
                    However, by 1 Edward VI. c. 12, § 16, every person entitled to the benefit of
                    clergy is to be allowed the same, “although he hath been divers times married to
                    any single woman or single women, or to any widow or widows, or to two wives or
                    more.” A bigamous marriage, by the ecclesiastical law of England, is simply
                    void. By the statute 1 James I. c. 11, confirmed by later statutes, the offence
                    was made a felony. It is immaterial whether the second marriage has taken place
                    within England and Ireland or elsewhere, and the offence may be dealt with in
                    any county or place where the defendant shall be apprehended or be in custody.
                    The following clause embodies the necessary exceptions to the very general
                    language used in the definition of the offence :—“Provided that nothing in this
                    section contained shall extend to any second marriage contracted elsewhere than
                    in England and Ireland by any other than a subject of Her Majesty, or to any
                    person marrying a second time whose husband or wife shall have been continuously
                    absent from such person for the space of seven years then last past,*and shall
                    not have been known by such person to be living within that time, or shall
                    extend to any person who at the time of such second marriage shall have been
                    divorced from the bond of the first marriage, or to any person whose former
                    marriage shall have been declared void by any court of competent jurisdiction.”
                    The punishment is penal servitude for not more than seven nor less than five
                    years, or imprisonment with or without hard labour, not exceeding two years. A
                    valid marriage must be proved in the first instance in order to support a charge
                    of bigamy. A <hi rend="italic">voidable</hi> marriage, such as were marriages
                    between persons within the prohibited degrees before 5 and 6 Will. IV. c. 54,
                    will be sufficient, but a marriage which is absolutely voïcZ, as all such
                    marriages now are, will not. For example, if a woman marry B during the lifetime
                    of her husband A, and after A ’ s death marry C during the lifetime of B, her
                    marriage with C is not bigamous, because her marriage with B was a nullity. In
                    regard to the second marriage (which constitutes the offence) the English courts
                    have held that it is immaterial whether, but for the bigamy, it would have been
                    a valid marriage or not. An uncle, for example, cannot marry his niece; but if
                    being already married he goes through the ceremony of marriage with her he is
                    guilty of bigamy. In an Irish case, however, it has been held that to constitute
                    the offence the second marriage must be one w hich, but for the existence of the
                    former marriage, would have been valid. With reference to the case in which the
                    parties to the first marriage have been divorced, it may be observed that no
                    sentence or act of any foreign country can dissolve an English marriage <hi
                    rend="italic">a vinculo</hi> for grounds on which it is not liable to be
                    dissolved <hi rend="italic">a vinculo</hi> in England (R. <hi rend="italic"
                    >v.</hi> Lolley, in Russell and Ryan’s <hi rend="italic">Criminal Cases,</hi>
                    237). Hence, a divorce <hi rend="italic">a vinculo</hi> for adultery, in a
                    Scotch court, of persons married in England is not within the statute.</p>
                <p>In Scotland, at the date of the only statute respecting bigamy, that of 1551,
                    cap. 19, the offence seems to have been chiefly considered in a religious point
                    of view, as a sort of perjury, or violation of the solemn vow or oath which was
                    then used in contracting marriage; and, accordingly, it was ordained to be
                    punished with the proper pains of perjury. But this injunction has not in every
                    instance been complied with; and, from considerations of policy or expediency,
                    the court has long been in the habit of inflicting an arbitrary punishment,
                    suited, as nearly as may be, to the degree of guilt brought home to the
                    prisoner. Neither marriage need be regular, but it is not yet settled whether a
                    marriage constituted by habit and repute, or by promise <hi rend="italic"
                    >subséquente</hi><hi rend="italic">copula,</hi> can be relevantly libelled in a
                    <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n686/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0686-0669"/> charge of bigamy. The parties to the first
                    marriage must, of course, have been lawfully entitled to marry. It is a good
                    defence that the accused λvas divorced from his first wife before contracting
                    the second marriage, even though the decree should afterwards have been set
                    aside, unless it has been obtained βorruptly and set aside for that reason. It
                    is also a good defence that, at the time of contracting the second marriage, the
                    accused had reasonable grounds for believing the other spouse to be dead. To
                    constitute the crime of bigamy, it is not necessary that the second marriage
                    should be such that, but for the first marriage, it would have been legal. The
                    punishment is imprisonment, and occasionally penal servitude.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
