<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0903-0547-0532-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BELIEF (9th edition, volume 3, page 532)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g8x">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bn4t">Religions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1ms2d">Reviews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b56d92n">Intuitionalism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46t0gw81">Belief</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z892f8z">Faith</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zg6gc5h">Reason</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46688j6x">Reasoning</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49k45t2j">Truth</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1198492">Faith</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1042815">Objectivity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150276">Thoughtfulness</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1091272">Reason</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1091282">Reasoning</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:840025">Buddhas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:895791">Division</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n547/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BELIEF</label> (τrtστιs, <hi rend="italic">Fides,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Foi,</hi><hi rend="italic">Glaube),</hi> with its synonyms
                    Assurance, Confidence, Conviction, Credence, Trust, Persuasion, Faith, is in
                    popular language taken to mean the acceptation of something as true which is not
                    known to be true, the mental attitude being a conviction that is not so strong
                    as certainty, but is stronger than mere opinion. For the grounds of such
                    conviction, ordinary language refers at once to probable as opposed to intuitive
                    or demonstrative evidence. Such popular phrases do not, of course, amount to a
                    definition of belief; but this is not to be expected from them, especially if,
                    as may be laid down with some confidence, no logical definition of the process
                    be possible. It may be described and marked off from similar or contrasted
                    states, but a rigidly scientific definition of what appears to be a simple,
                    ultimate fact is not attainable. The general explanation, however, is so far
                    unsatisfactory in that it throws no light upon the most interesting question
                    with regard to belief, its province, and does not tell us what are the objects
                    of belief as opposed to those of knowledge. To answer this it is necessary to
                    describe somewhat more minutely the mental process under examination.</p>
                <p>1. Unfortunately for purposes of analysis, the word belief is used in a variety
                    of relations which seem at first sight to have but little in common. We are said
                    to believe in what lies beyond the limits of our temporal experience, in the
                    supersensible, in God and a future life. Again, we are said to believe in the
                    first principles or ultimate verities from which all trains of demonstration
                    must start; as conditions of demonstration, these are themselves indemonstrable,
                    and are therefore objects of belief.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p>This has been pointed out by a long line of thinkers,
                            from Aristotle to Jacobi and Hamilton.</p></note> We receive by belief
                    perceptions of single matters of fact, which from their very nature cannot be
                        demonstrated.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>So
                            knowledge through the senses is called <hi rend="italic"
                                >Offenbarung</hi> by Jacobi and Lotze <hi rend="italic"
                                >(Mikrokosmus,</hi> iii. 548).</p></note> We believe from memory the
                    facts of past experience; we have expectation or belief in future events. We
                    accept truths on the evidence of testimony; and finally, we believe that our
                    actual consciousness of things is in harmony with reality. From this
                    unsystematic arrangement of objects of belief it will be possible to eliminate
                    certain classée by noting in the first instance what we are not said to believe,
                    but to know. By knowledge may be understood generally the conviction of truth
                    which rests on grounds valid for all intelligence, and which is expressed in
                    propositions necessary both for our thinking and for reality. At the same time
                    we are commonly and correctly said to know states of consciousness when they are
                    immediately present, together with their differences, similarities, connections,
                    and relations to self. Whatever is necessarily connected with present
                    experience, and can be logically deduced from it, is also matter not of belief
                    but of knowledge. Again, we know all propositions of apodictic certainty, such
                    as those of mathematics and logic. Mathematical propositions carry us beyond
                    mere thinking; the laws which flow from the relations of space and time are not
                    only thought but known to be true of all objects of sensible experience, for no
                    objects whatsoever can form part of that experience save under these
                    quantitative conditions. It is therefore an error to say that we believe
                    abstract mathematical laws apply to objects; we know this with absolute
                    certainty. So also our cognizance of logical principles, such as the laws of
                    identity and contradiction, is matter of knowledge, of insight, not of belief.
                    It would appear, therefore, that knowledge extends to facts immediately present
                    in consciousness, and to certain relations true of all facts of sensible
                    experience; but in neither of these classes of cognition does there seem to be
                    given an absolute guarantee for the <hi rend="italic">existence</hi> of any fact
                    which is not immediately before us. That one object presented to us is known
                    seems to give no actual knowledge that another object ideally connected with it
                    has at the same time real being. Mathematical and logical laws are absolutely
                    true of all experience to which they apply, but this truth gives no certainty
                    that there will be experience. If there be objects of experience at all, they
                    must be subject to mathematical and logical law; but the question remains, is
                    there any ground, absolutely necessary and compelling assent, for holding that
                    there will be such experience.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Of.</hi> Lotze, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Mik.,</hi> iii. 547. “When one affirms that every object of thought
                            is identical with itself, that the same under the same conditions has
                            the same consequences, under different conditions different
                            consequences, that a cause precedes every effect,—all these are
                            universal truths, which tell us, indeed, what must be or take place if
                            tterε should <pb corresp="kp-eb0903-0548-0533" xml:id="pbn9533"/> be a
                            case of their application, but which tell us nothing of the real
                            existence of any case.”</p></note> This is an old matter of debate; it
                    lies at <pb corresp="pbn9533"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n548/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0903-0548-0533"/> the very root of the distinction between
                    knowledge and philosophical belief, and leads directly into the deepest problems
                    of metaphysical science, its solution depending upon the answer given to thie
                    doubt whether or not our thinking is merely formal, receiving materials and
                    working them up in forms which may have no correlates in reality. Hume, who in
                    this connection has given the impulse to all subsequent British thinking, laid
                    his finger with unerring precision on the crucial point, and deliberately
                    relegated all <hi rend="italic">matters of fact</hi> to the province of belief.
                    According to him, knowledge never passes beyond immediate intuition of ideas and
                    their relations. Whenever we touch upon real existence, past or future, belief,
                    not knowledge, is our instrument. An adequate discussion of the difficulty would
                    lead beyond the limits of the present inquiry; it may suffice to indicate
                    generally what can be said on one typical point of the debate. Is the
                    supposition of a causal connection among phenomena merely belief, or is it a
                    necessary condition of knowledge? If the latter, then our thinking carries us
                    with apodictic certainty beyond present experience of facts, for every causal
                    judgment is, <hi rend="italic">ipso facto,</hi> universal, and therefore extends
                    to all or any time. Now, no proof of the universality of law among phenomena can
                    ever be given from empirical grounds, for all such attempts virtually involve
                    the very principle in question. It is a necessary presupposition, without which
                    knowledge would be impossible. Its contrary is certainly not self-contradictory,
                    if by self-contradiction be meant impossibility of representation, for chaos can
                    be pictured; but the power of imagination is surely not the criterion of truth.
                    It is the power of knowing objects that is in question, and the non-existence of
                    the causal relation among phenomena would render actual experience impossible.
                    Objects cannot be known save under this supposition. A similar line of argument
                    directed towards others of the notions involved in what Kant has called
                    synthetical judgments <hi rend="italic">a priori,</hi> would show that such
                    notions are constitutive of our experience, that thought penetrates deeply into
                    phenomena, and that phenomenal relations are but types of the forms of real
                    cognition. It might, of course, still be maintained that all these synthetical
                    propositions are only formal,—are only true if experience be given,—and that a
                    wide field is still left for belief. Under certain conditions this may be
                    admitted. A doubt as to the very existence of experience is hardly a valid
                    argument, but that there should be specific connections of phenomena, permanent
                    and constant—that, for example, the same cause should continue to have the same
                    effects—may seem not quite a matter of knowledge. The real element of doubt in
                    such a case is not, however, whether the same cause under the same conditions
                    shall give the same effects, but whether in any definite instance we have
                    attained a thorough knowledge of the cause itself, and whether the conditions
                    will recur. The first of these doubts is overcome in the ordinary progress of
                    knowledge; the other concerns the empirical appearance of the effects, relates
                    therefore to what may be called the contingent, and forms the object of
                    belief.</p>
                <p>It follows from what has been said that we exclude from the province of belief
                    primitive truths and facts of immediate experience, with such phenomena, past or
                    future, aβ are connected causally or by rational links with facts immediately
                    known. There is still a wide field left for belief, (a.) In the stage of
                    knowledge which we call sensible cognition belief introduces itself <hi
                        rend="italic">; for</hi> consciousness, which unhesitatingly affirms the
                    correspondence of its content with reality, readily exhibits its falsity λvhen
                    submitted to analysis. The belief, though firm, is shown to be erroneous,—to be
                    merely the rapid summation of a number of signs, which themselves do not come
                    clearly before consciousness, and are therefore accepted without examination,
                    (δ.) In memory of our own past experience belief is involved. When I remember, I
                    have present to consciousness ideas which represent past reality. To have ideas
                    simply is to imagine; to have ideas which we are convinced represent past
                    experience is to have imagination <hi rend="italic">plus</hi> belief, <hi
                        rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> to remember. It should be observed that we are
                    frequently said to trust our memory, to believe that what we remember is true.
                    This phraseology is objectionable; we cannot properly be said to <hi
                        rend="italic">trust</hi> our memory, we simply use it. In the very fact of
                    remembering is involved the reference to past reality which is the essence of
                    belief, (c.) We believe testimony, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> we accept as
                    true facts not in our experience, and which possibly may never be. In this case
                    our belief is, that under certain conditions we should have the experience which
                    from the testimony we can picture to ourselves, (d.) Expectation, so far as
                    merely contingent elements are concerned, is a pure case of belief.</p>
                <p>2. So far as we have yet seen, all objects of belief have been or may be objects
                    of knowledge; and the most prominent distinction between the two is the presence
                    in the one of an actual intuition and its absence in the other. This
                    distinction, however, as we have pointed out,· is not absolute; all thinking of
                    reality is not belief. Belief is rather the thinking of reality which is
                    determined by grounds not necessarily valid for all intelligence, but
                    satisfactory for the individual thinker. The difference between imagination and
                    the thought of some reality does not seem capable of further analysis; it
                    expresses an ultimate fact. Attempts, however, have been made to work out a
                    psychology of belief, and to point out the characteristics differentiating ideas
                    believed in from mere pictures of the mind. These have been generally due to
                    British thinkers; and, since the time of Hume, the problem has become one of
                    considerable importance. Locke, who marked out very carefully the province of
                    belief and considered its grounds, made no attempt to analyse the state itself.
                        Hume,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>A theory
                            somewhat similar to that of Hume is worked out by Mr Bagehot, <hi
                                rend="italic">Contemporary Review,</hi> April 1871.</p></note>
                    however, puts the question clearly before himself and returns an unhesitating
                    answer. “As it is certain,” he says, “there is a great difference betwixt the
                    simple conception of the existence of an object and the belief of it, and as
                    this difference lies not in the parts or composition of the idea which we
                    conceive, it follows that it must be in the manner in which we conceive it. When
                    we are convinced of any matter of fact, we do nothing but conceive it along with
                    a certain feeling, different from what attends the reveries of imagination.”
                    “This feeling is nothing but a firmer conception or a faster hold that we take
                    of the object.” “This <hi rend="italic">manner</hi> of conception arises from a
                    customary conjunction of the object with something present to the memory or
                    senses.” From the last sentence to the elaborate theory of James Mill is but a
                    short step. According to Mill, belief is a case of constant association; an idea
                    is believed which is irresistibly called up in connection with present
                    experience. Thus in memory, the ideas of the past experience are irresistibly
                    associated with the idea of myself experiencing them, and this irresistibility
                    constitutes belief. Expectation, again, is the irresistible suggestion by
                    present experience of a consequent or train of consequents. And to memory and
                    expectation all ordinary cases of belief may be reduced.</p>
                <p>Both these theories are defective in the same point,—the analysis of what is
                    meant by object in general, and, consequently, of what is involved in thinking
                    of an object. Hume’s is open to the special objection that he makes the <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n549/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0903-0549-0534"/> difference between the believed and imagined
                    idea the same as that between impression and idea, which is an ultimate
                    distinction, and yet holds the difference to be merely one of degree. In Mill’s
                    account of memory it may be pointed out that the ideas of <hi rend="italic"
                        >past</hi> experience, and of myself as having had the experience, contain
                    in themselves the very element which is supposed to be got out of their
                    conjunction. With regard to expectation it is clear that ideas irresistibly
                    suggested by present experience are by no mean3 necessarily believed, and
                    further, that many of our beliefs do not arise from any such association. J. S.
                        Mill,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Notes to J.
                            Mill’s <hi rend="italic">Analysis,</hi> i. <hi rend="italic">Cf.
                                Dissertations,</hi> iii.</p></note> who subjects the association
                    theory of belief to a searching examination, comes to the conclusion that the
                    distinction between thinking of a reality and representing to ourselves an
                    imaginary picture is ultimate and primordial With his opinion later
                    investigators, as Mr Sully,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                                ><p><hi rend="italic">Sensation and Intuition.</hi> (On the
                            Development of Belief.)</p></note> concur.</p>
                <p>Professor Bain, in opposition to other psychologists, holds that belief is not so
                    much an intellectual state as a “phase of our active nature, otherwise called
                    the will.” “It is a growth or development of the will under the pursuit of
                    intermediate ends.” When, for instance, we perform certain acts as means towards
                    a desired end with as much vigour as if we were realizing the end itself, “we
                    are in a very peculiar situation, not implied in desire.” This situation is
                    belief, which is essentially <hi rend="superscript"> tt</hi> an anticipation of
                    the pleasure” of attaining the end. Belief being a form of activity, our
                    primitive state is one of complete confidence. The mind is filled with its
                    present experience, and confidently believes that the future will resemble it.
                    Ideas are so strongly taken up by the mind that they are accepted as real, and
                    influence the will. The various disappointments of this primitive confidence
                    give rise to definite avoidances of certain actions, and to pursuit of others,
                    in order to escape pain or gain pleasure. Action directed towards these
                    intermediate ends involves, or rather is, belief. This theory has to explain
                    expectation and memory. With regard to the first, “we make light of the
                    difference between the conceived future and the real present ;” or in other
                    words, “we are disposed to act in any direction where we have never been
                    checked.” Our primitive disposition to act is equivalent to full expectation. It
                    may be pointed out that this explanation throws no light on expectation of
                    events in which our activity could by no possibility be involved. But the theory
                    seems to break down entirely when applied to memory. There is first to be
                    explained the fact of memory, and then it has to be shown how reference to
                    activity is contained in it. “In surrendering our mind to the idea still
                    remaining, and so imparting a momentary quasi-reality, we have an experience
                    possessing the characteristic features of present reality.” ‘'We really make no
                    radical difference between a present and a proximate past.” This, in the first
                    place, would apply only to certain cases of memory. Secondly, imparting a
                    quasi-reality iβ not an explanation of the peculiar phenomenon of an idea
                    representing the past. It is an error, even on Professor Bain’s own principles
                    (see note to <hi rend="italic">Mill's Analysis,</hi> i. 342; <hi rend="italic"
                        >Emotions and Will,</hi> 2d ed. 525), to speak of <hi rend="italic"
                        >belief</hi> in a present reality, while here memory is explained as a
                    pseudo-realization of the ideas. Nor is he more successful in referring memory
                    to activity. To identify my remembrance of having run up against a wall to avoid
                    a carriage with the conviction that, should such a danger recur, I should again
                    run up against the wall (see <hi rend="italic">Emotions and Will,</hi> 2d. ed.,
                    554),is absurd. The whole theory seems but an instance of a not uncommon error
                    in psychology,—the confusion of the test or measure of a thing with the thing
                    itself. Belief is truly a motive to action,<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p>It is so defined by Bain <hi rend="italic"
                                >(Ment.</hi><hi rend="italic">and Moral Sc.,</hi> 372), who finds
                            great difficulty in reconciling his theory with ordinary phraseology.
                            Such an expression as the following has a curious ring :—“Belief is
                            identical with the activity or active disposition, at the moment, and
                            with reference to the thing <hi rend="italic">believed.”—</hi> (Note to
                                <hi rend="italic">Analysis,</hi> i. 395.)</p></note> and all that
                    has been said of it by Professor Bain would hold good of it in this relation; to
                    identify the two is to run together totally distinct processes.</p>
                <p>Modern German psychology has not approached the problem of belief from the same
                    side as the English. Beneke alone, by his analysis of <hi rend="italic"
                        >tact</hi> (see <hi rend="italic">Lehrbuch der</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Psych.,</hi> § 158, and <hi rend="italic">System</hi><hi rend="italic">der
                        Logik,</hi> i. 268, <hi rend="italic">seq.),</hi> has opened up a somewhat
                    fresh vein of thinking. His hints have been carried out by Germar <hi
                        rend="italic">(Die</hi><hi rend="italic">alte Streitfrage, Glauben oder
                        Wissen,</hi> 1856), who gives the following definition of belief: “If the
                    consciousness (of the truth of what we think) arises from <hi rend="italic"
                        >tact,</hi> and therefore without consciousness of the factors or grounds
                    through which it is produced, it is called belief; it is elevated to knowledge
                    when these factors are brought before consciousness” (p. 58).<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>With this view may be
                            compared much of what is said by J. IL Newman, <hi rend="italic">Grammar
                                of Assent;</hi> see specially 73, 2S1</p></note> In general the
                    example of Kant has been followed, who looked upon the question as belonging not
                    so much to psychology as to the theory of knowledge. His own discussion of the
                    subject and his distinction between <hi rend="italic">Meinen, Glauben,</hi> and
                        <hi rend="italic">Wissen</hi> have powerfully influenced later thought.
                    According to him, <hi rend="italic">Glaube</hi> (belief, in the sense of <hi
                        rend="italic">Fides</hi> as opposed to <hi rend="italic">Credulitas,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Foi</hi> as opposed to <hi rend="italic">Croyance)</hi> should
                    be confined to such propositions as rest on grounds subjectively not merely
                    sufficient but necessary; that is to say, the propositions believed in are
                    recognized as the demands of our moral or practical reason, and their truth can
                    never be disproved, for such disproof would be radically inconsistent with the
                    moral nature which we are conscious of possessing. Our confidence in their truth
                    is unwavering and practi cal, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> leading to action;
                    for without them we could not act in conformity with our moral nature.
                    Nevertheless, of the objects of such propositions we can never have scientific
                    knowledge.</p>
                <p>3. Kant’s distinction of <hi rend="italic">Meinung</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Glaube</hi> leads us directly to the one species of belief which has not
                    yet been considered. All objects of belief, so far as has yet appeared, might
                    come within our temporal experience; but we are said to believe in the
                    supersensible, which from its very definition seems to surpass experience and,
                    consequently, knowledge. To such belief the name <hi rend="italic">faith</hi> is
                    properly restricted, and in its nature it differs somewhat from the belief
                    hitherto discussed. There is not, of course, included in it the specifically
                    theological notion of faith as <hi rend="italic">Fiducia</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >(quoe est</hi><hi rend="italic">apprehensio meriti</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Θεανθρώπου</hi><hi rend="italic">appropriativa ad me et te in</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">individuo)</hi>; it corresponds rather to the <hi
                        rend="italic">Notitia</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Assensus,</hi> which are
                    also elements in theological faith, and may be defined as the subjective
                    expression of man’s relation to God. When understood in this sense, religious
                    belief is by no means a mere feeling, though it contains feeling as one of the
                    stages in its development, for mere feeling is in itself blind and valueless,
                    whereas faith is intelligent or rational. Nor is it a blank faith which would
                    have the same value whatever were the objects believed in, for religious belief
                    has a definite content; it is the acceptation of certain facts and truths and
                    the active realization of them. As its content is definite (for if it were not
                    so, the religions of Christ and of Mahomet, of Buddha and of Zoroaster, would
                    stand on the same level, all having subjective faith or conviction), belief of
                    necessity involves knowledge, rational construction of the facts believed. Faith
                    is but the lower stage of completed insight, and in its own development follows
                    the natural order of progress in knowledge, which begins with feeling and
                    intuition, rises through concrete representation into logical connection, <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n550/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0903-0550-0535"/> and finally culminates in rational cognition.
                    So religious Belief, which is primarily little more than a vague feeling of
                    something over and beyond the present state of existence, combined with the dim
                    sense of our own finite and dependent condition, gradually rises to a higher
                    stage, and in its efforts to attain some cognizance of the supersensible, begins
                    even to attach itself to natural objects. But as it can find in these no
                    satisfaction, it is compelled to construct some representations of the
                    supernatural which shall harmonize with our spiritual wants. In the formation of
                    these religious ideas we are not left without help, nor are they to be looked
                    upon as mere figments of the mind. The revelation which has been given in
                    nature, both physical and moral, and in the special experience to which the name
                    is more frequently applied, furnishes matter which is laid hold of aud pressed
                    into the service. Religious belief or faith always attaches itself to
                    representations, intuitions, or facts; it gives what Newman has called Real as
                    opposed to Notional Assent But it is not the less necessary that faith should be
                    raised to insight, and that we should construe in terms of thought what
                    religious experience brings before us as direct intuition. There must be
                    theology as well as religion. Nothing is believed which is not held to be so
                    connected with the rational nature of man as irretrievably to injure that nature
                    should its truth be overthrown. This is not to put knowledge in place of faith,
                    if knowledge be understood to apply only to the logically necessary; nor is it
                    to assert that what have been called truths of revelation could have been
                    discovered by natural reason. Knowledge, however, cannot be confined to the
                    abstract understanding; and nothing is more delusive than the total opposition
                    of revelation and reason. “What is there in the nature of things,” says
                    Augustine, “that God has done unreasonably Î” To affirm that reason does not of
                    itself discover the truths of revelation, is simply to bring against it the
                    reproach it may well bear, that it does not create experience. Reason has not to
                    make new facts, but to accept given experience, and evolve from it the pure
                    elements of thought which it contains, and in which its truth consists. Faith,
                    therefore, precedes knowledge, as Anselm used to say; but its priority is that
                    of time, not of authority.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                            ><p>See Scotus Erigena, <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic"
                                >Divis. Natur.,</hi> i. 69.</p></note></p>
                <p>4. There remains to be taken into account the interesting question of the grounds
                    and motives for belief. It is, of course, necessary to distinguish between these
                    two; the <hi rend="italic">cause</hi> of a belief may not be exactly a <hi
                        rend="italic">reason</hi> for it. Belief, though natural, is not always
                    rational, but frequently rests with happy unconsciousness on foundations utterly
                    inadequate to its support. But if we disregard this distinction and include both
                    causes and reasons under the title principles of belief, these may be divided
                    into three classes —(1), Testimony; (2), Feelings, Desires, or Wishes; (3),
                    Evidence of Reason. These are rarely dissevered in actual practice. Testimony,
                    to the reception of which the name belief is frequently restricted, is familiar
                    enough to require no extended notice. Our natural tendency is to accept all
                    testimony as true; it is experience alone that teaches caution. Where from the
                    nature of the case no such experience is to be had, credulity settles down into
                    firm and ineradicable conviction. The majority of men would be astonished to
                    find how much their belief depends upon the society into which they have been
                    born and in which they live. Dogmas at first forced upon a people gradually
                    become ingrained in the minds of those brought up in habitual contact with them.
                    There is hardly a limit to the possibility of instilling beliefs through
                    continued custom, and no resistance to analysis is so strong as that offered by
                    mere customary opinion, which has impercep tibly introduced itself into the very
                    life’s blood of those who share it.</p>
                <p>The feelings, though not so directly a source of convictions as testimony,
                    exercise an extensive and complex influence on belief. It has always been a
                    popular saying that a man believes what he wishes—that “the wish is father to
                    the thought;” and there can be no doubt that the superior force given to an idea
                    by the concentration on it of desire or affection, causes it to bulk so largely
                    in consciousness as to exclude the thought of its non-realization. The very idea
                    of a result opposed to what we earnestly desire is unpleasant enough to make us
                    resolutely shut it out of sight. This, however, is but a partial and limited
                    effect. We know very well that our belief is only occasionally swayed by our
                    wishes, and that necessity too often constrains us to believe what we willingly
                    would not. Our volition cannot directly compel belief. But the feelings play a
                    more important part; for it is by their means primarily that we stretch beyond
                    the field of direct knowledge and complete our limited experience with what we
                    feel to be necessary for the harmony of our moral and religious nature. We
                    believe that without which our nature would be dissatisfied, and this belief
                    takes its rise in the feelings,—the blind expressions of intellectual want,—
                    which form the first stage towards completed insight.</p>
                <p>It is hardly necessary to do more than refer to the rational grounds for belief.
                    Wherever our knowledge of any object or law is incomplete, belief is ready to
                    step in and fill up the gap by some hypothesis, which is in conformity with our
                    experience, is rationally connected with the facts to be explained, and is not
                    yet known to be true. Great portions of our so-called scientific knowledge are
                    nothing but rational belief,—hypotheses unverified, perhaps even
                    unverifiable,—and the settlement of the conditions or legitimacy of such
                    presumptions forms the principal part of inductive logic.</p>
                <p>Besides the works already referred to, the following treat of belief in general
                    :—Fechner, <hi rend="italic">Drei</hi><hi rend="italic">Motive</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">und Grunde des Glaubens,</hi> 1863; Ulrici, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Glauben und Wissen, Spekulation und</hi><hi rend="italic">exacte</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Wissenschaft,</hi> 1858; of religious belief in particular, in
                    addition to works on dogmatic theology or philosophy of religion:—Schwarz, <hi
                        rend="italic">Das Wesen der</hi><hi rend="italic">Religion,</hi> 1847;
                    Asher, <hi rend="italic">Der</hi><hi rend="italic">religiose</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Glaube,</hi> 1860; J. Köstlin, <hi rend="italic">Der
                        Glaube,</hi> 1860; Venn, <hi rend="italic">Hulsean Lectures for</hi> 1869.
                    (R. AD.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
