<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0851-0834-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BLOCKADE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 3, page 834</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4q52fm3g">Ports</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b43f4kn9d">Neutrality</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4610vv86">Enteritis</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1033832">Nationalism</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1036590">Neutrality</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1085685">Questioning</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1170328">War</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807488">Americans</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n851/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BLOCKADE</label>. It appears to have been the ancient
                    practice of belligerents at the outset of a war to forbid by proclamation all
                    trade on the part of neutrals with the enemy, and to treat as enemies all those
                    who contravened the proclamation; and neutrals acquiesced tacitly in this
                    practice until the commencement of the 17th century. In the course of that
                    century the ancient practice came into question, as imposing on the commerce of
                    fιeutrals an inconvenience not justified by any adequate necessity on the part
                    of belligerents, and it has since fallen into desuetude. Belligerents, however,
                    have still maintained, without any question on the part of neutrals, the
                    practice of intercepting supplies going over sea to an enemy under certain
                    conditions, namely, when a belligerent has invested an enemy’s port, with the
                    intention of reducing the enemy to surrender from the failure of supplies, and
                    for that object a stoppage of all supplies to such port has become a necessary
                    operation of the war. Any attempt, under such circumstances, on the part of a
                    neutral merchant to introduce supplies into the invested port is a direct
                    interference with the operations of the war, and is inconsistent with
                    neutrality, and it accordingly subjects the offending party to be treated <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n852/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0852-0835"/> as an enemy by the belligerent. The question,
                    What constitutes such a belligerent investment of an enemy’s port as to create
                    an obligation on the part of neutrals to abstain from attempting to enter it,
                    has been much controverted since the “armed neutrality” of 1780; but all
                    uncertainty as to the principle upon which the decision in each case must
                    proceed, has been put an end to by the declaration of the powers assembled in
                    congress at Paris in 1856, that “Blockades, in order to be binding, must be
                    effective, that is to say, must be maintained by a force sufficient really to
                    prevent access to the enemy’s coast.” The question of fact will still be a
                    subject for judicial inquiry in each case of capture, whether the conditions
                    under which a blockade has been maintained satisfy the above declaration. If an
                    asserted blockade is maintained in a manner which satisfies the above
                    declaration, there is no limit to the extent of an enemy’s coast which may be
                    placed under blockade. There is also a general consent amongst nations that a
                    neutral merchant must have knowledge of a blockade in order to be liable to be
                    treated as an enemy for attempting to break it; but there is not any uniform
                    practice amongst nations on this subject further than that when a blockade has
                    become notorious, the knowledge of it will be presumed against every neutral
                    vessel which attempts to enter the blockaded port. On the other hand, where a
                    blockade is not notorious, it is in accordance with the practice of nations to
                    give some notice of it to neutrals; and this notice may be communicated to them
                    either by actual warning given to each neutral vessel which seeks to cross the
                    line of blockade, or by a constructive warning to all neutrals resulting from an
                    official notification of the blockade on the part of the blockading power to all
                    powers in amity with it. It is a growing practice, if not altogether an
                    established practice, amongst nations which accredit to one another resident
                    envoys, for belligerents to notify diplomatically to the neutral powers the fact
                    that they have placed an enemy’s port under blockade; and it is the rule of the
                    prize courts of Great Britain and of the United States of America to hold that,
                    where such an official notification has been made, all the subjects of the
                    neutral powers may be presumed to have knowledge of the blockade. Other powers,
                    amongst which France may be mentioned, have been accustomed to direct their
                    blockading cruisers to give warning of the blockade to each vessel that attempts
                    to cross the line of blockade, and not to capture any vessel unless she attempts
                    to break the blockade after such warning; but the practice of France agrees with
                    the practice of other powers in hot giving such warning after a blockade has
                    become notorious. There is, further, a general practice amongst nations to treat
                    the act of sailing with an intention to enter a blockaded port as an unneutral
                    act, which will warrant the capture of a neutral merchant vessel by a
                    belligerent cruiser on any part of the high seas, unless clear evidence is
                    forthcoming from the captured vessel that the intention has been abandoned, or
                    that its execution was contingent on the blockade being raised. After a port has
                    been placed under blockade, egress is prohibited to all neutral vessels, except
                    to such as have entered the port before the blockade was established, if they
                    come out either in ballast or with cargoes taken on board before the
                    commencement of the blockade. No warning is required to affect such vessel with
                    a knowledge of the blockade, and if any such vessel should succeed in passing
                    through the blockading squadron it becomes liable to capture as good prize by a
                    belligerent cruiser on any part of the high seas, until it has reached its port
                    of destination, when the offence is considered to be purged. Under the ancient
                    practice both ship and cargo were confiscable for the breach of a blockade, and
                    even the captain and crew were liable to be treated as enemies. A milder
                    practice is now generally observed as regards the captain and crew, and a
                    certain equity is administered in the British and American prize courts towards
                    the owners of cargo, where the ship and the cargo do not belong to the same
                    parties, and the owners of the cargo have not any knowledge of the blockade, or
                    have been unabl⅛ to countermand the shipment of the cargo since the blockade has
                    become known to them. In such cases the cargo is released, although the ship may
                    be rightfully condemned to the captors. (τ. τ.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
