<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0324-0309-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BANDA ISLANDS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 3, page 309</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:813089">Archipelagoes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:999025">Lindens</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:851090">Ceramics</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980104">Islands</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zf6b">Malays</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4w08wh9h">Ceramics</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g08p">Groups</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n324/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BANDA ISLANDS</label>, a group in the East Indian
                    Archipelago, lying to the S. of Ceram, in lat. 4° 30' S. and long. 129° 50' E.
                    They are ten or twelve in number, and have an area of about 7150 square miles.
                    Their volcanic origin is distinctly marked. Banda Lantoir, which derives its
                    name from the <hi rend="italic">lontar</hi> or Palmyra palm, is the largest of
                    the group. From the sea this island appears lofty,— its sides being steep, and
                    crowned by a sort of table-land which extends nearly from one end to the other.
                    The whole is one continuous forest of nutmeg and <hi rend="italic">Canari</hi>
                    trees, the latter being planted to screen the former from the wind. The
                    unhealthiness of Lantoir has prevented it from becoming the seat of government,
                    for which in other respects it would naturally be chosen. The village of Selam
                    contains the ruins of the chief Portuguese settlement. A considerable <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n325/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0325-0310"/> fort, called Hollandia, commands the harbour.
                    Banda Neira lies S.∙ of Lantoir. It is the seat of the Dutch resident, whose
                    jurisdiction extends not only over the Banda Islands, but also over a part of
                    Ceram and several other small groups. Fort Nassau, which was built in 1609, is
                    the chief defence of the islands; and to the right and left of it extends the
                    village of Neira. Gunong Api is to the north of Neira, and derives its name—Fire
                    Mountain— from its large cone-shaped volcano, which rises 2320 feet above the
                    level of the sea, and is constantly emitting smoke. The peak was ascended by
                    Professor Rein ward t in 1821, by Μ. S. Müller in 1828, and in 1865 by Mr
                    Bickmore, who has given an interesting account of the adventure. Eruptions took
                    place in 1586, 1598, 1609, 1615, 1632, 1690, 1696, 1712, 1765, 1775, 1778, 1820,
                    1824; and earthquakes without eruptions occurred in 1629, 1683, 1710, 1767,
                    1816, and 1852. On the last occasion the sea swept up in an enormous wave over
                    Fort Nassau. Pulo Way—The Water Island—lies north of Neira. It is about 400 or
                    500 feet high, consists of coral rock, and is esteemed the healthiest of the
                    group. Pulo Rond or Roon—the Chamber Island—is about four miles further N., and
                    was at one time the seat of an English “factory.” Rosyngain, about seven miles
                    S.E. of Lantoir, is likely to become of some importance for its gold-mines. It
                    was formerly a convict station for Amboyna. Pulo Pisang—Banana Island—two miles
                    N.E. of Neira, produces fine fruits. The other islands Craka, Capella, Sonangy,
                    &amp;c., are uninhabited. In the space between Banda Lantoir and the islands of
                    Banda Neira and Gunong Api there is a very good harbour, formed with entrances
                    both from the E. and W., which enable vessels to enter it from either of the
                    monsoons. These channels are well defended with several batteries, particularly
                    the western one, which is very narrow. Between Gunong Api and Banda Neira there
                    is a third channel into this harbour from the N., but it is navigable for small
                    vessels only. The principal articles of commerce in the Banda group are nutmegs
                    and mace. The native population having been cleared off by the Dutch, the
                    plantations were worked by slaves and convicts till the emancipation of 1860.
                    The introduction of Malay and Chinese labourers has since taken place. The
                    plantations or <hi rend="italic">perken</hi> can neither be sold nor divided.
                    About 700,000 ft or upwards of nutmegs are obtained in a year, with a
                    proportionate quantity of mace. The imports are provisions, cloth, and iron-ware
                    from Batavia, and various native productions from the Aru Islands, Ceram,
                    &amp;c.</p>
                <p>The Banda Islands were discovered and annexed by the Portuguese Abreus about
                    1511; but in the beginning of the 17th century his countrymen were expelled by
                    the Dutch. In 1608 the English built a factory on Pulo Way, which was demolished
                    by the Dutch as soon as the English vessel left. Shortly after, however, Banda
                    Neira and Lantoir were resigned by the natives to the English, and in 1620 Pulo
                    Roon aud Pulo Way were added to their dominions; but, in spite of treaties into
                    which they had entered, the Dutch attacked and expelled their British rivals. In
                    1654 they were compelled by Cromwell to restore Pulo Roon, and to make
                    satisfaction for the massacre of Amboyna; but the English settlers not being
                    adequately supported from home, the island was retaken by the Dutch in 1664.
                    They retained undisturbed possession of their conquests in this quarter of the
                    globe until the year 1796, when the Banda Islands, along with all the other
                    Dutch colonies, were conquered by the British. They were restored by the treaty
                    of Amiens in the year 1800, again captured, and finally restored by the treaty
                    of Paris concluded in 1814. In the Presidency of Banda there are 111,194
                    inhabitants of whom 6000 belong to Neira.</p>
                <p>See Wallace's <hi rend="italic">Malay Archipelago;</hi> Bickmore’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Indian Archipelago;</hi> Linden’s <hi rend="italic">Banda</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">en</hi><hi rend="italic">Zijnc bcwoners,</hi> 1873; <hi
                    rend="italic">Trans, of Lueth Geog. Soc.,</hi> 1874.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
