<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0903-0262-0247-05" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BÂKARGANJ (9th edition, volume 3, page 247)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:840320">Buddhists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1097334">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="fast:880656">Cost</term>
                    <term ref="fast:829042">Bays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110447">Seasons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qb5b">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tw1v">Cost</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q67d">Costs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j96094w">Seasons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90242v">Puritans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48911q68">Baptists</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n262/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BÂKARGANJ</label>, a district of British India in the Dacca
                    division, under the Lieutenant-Governor of Bengal, situated between 23° 14' 27"
                    and 21° 48' N. lat., and 89° 55' 10" and 91° 4' 50" E. long. It is bounded on
                    the N. by the districts of Dacca and Faridpur, from which it is separated by the
                    Padmâ and Mainâkâtikhâl; on the E. by the Meghnâ and Shâhbâzpur rivers, and by
                    the Bay of Bengal, which separates it from Noâkhâlf and Tipperah; on the S. by
                    the Bay of Bengal; and on the W. by J esssr and Faridpur districts. Area, 4935
                    square miles; population, 2,377,433. The general aspect of the district is that
                    of a flat even country, dotted with clusters of bamboos and betel-nut trees, and
                    intersected by a perfect network of dark-coloured and sluggish streams. There is
                    not a hill or hillock in the whole district, but it derives a certain
                    picturesque beauty from its wide expanses of cultivation, and the greenness and
                    freshness of the vegetation. This is especially conspicuous in the rains, but at
                    no time of the year does the district present a dried or burnt-up appearance.
                    The villages, which are always walled round by groves of bamboos and betel-nut
                    palms, have often a very striking appearance; and Bâkarganj has many beauties of
                    detail which strike a traveller in passing through the country. The level of the
                    country is low, forming as it does a part of the great Gangetic delta; and the
                    rivers, streams, and water-courses are so numerous that it is very difficult to
                    travel except by boat at any season of the year. Every natural hollow is full of
                    water, around the margin of which long grasses, reeds, and other aquatic plants
                    grow in the greatest profusion, often making it difficult to say where the land
                    ends and where the water begins. Towards the north-west the country is very
                    marshy, and nothing is to be seen for miles but tracts of unreclaimed swamps and
                    rice lands, with a few huts scattered here and there, and raised on mounds of
                    earth. In the south of the district, along the sea face of the Bay of Bengal,
                    lie the forest tracts of the Sundarbans, the habitation of tigers, leopards, and
                    other wild beasts.</p>
                <p>The principal rivers of the district are the Meghnâ, the Arial Khan, and the
                    Haringhâtâ or Baleswar, with their numerous offshoots. The Meghna represents the
                    accumulated waters of the Brahmaputra and Ganges. It flows along the eastern
                    boundary of the district in a southerly direction for about 100 miles, till it
                    debouches into the Bay of Bengal. During the latter part of its course this
                    noble river expands into a large estuary containing many islands, the principal
                    of which is that of Dakshin Shâhbâzpur. The Arial Khan, a branch of the Ganges,
                    enters the district from the north, and flows generally in a south-easterly
                    direction till it falls into the estuary of the Meghnâ. The main channel of the
                    Arial Khan is about 1700 yards in width in the dry season, and from 2000 to 3000
                    yards in the rains. It receives a number of tributaries, sends off several
                    offshoots, and is navigable throughout the year by native cargo boats of the
                    largest size. The Haringhâtâ, Baleswar, Madhumati, and Garai, are various local
                    names for the same river in different parts of its course, and represent another
                    great offshoot of the Ganges. It enters Bâkarganj near the north-west corner of
                    the district, whence it forms its western boundary, and runs south, but with
                    great windings in its upper reaches, till it crosses the Sundarbans, and finally
                    falls into the Bay of Bengal by a large and deep estuary, capable of receiving
                    merchant ships of considerable burden. In the whole of its course through the
                    district the river is navigable by native boats of large tonnage, and by large
                    sea-going ships as high up as Morrellganj, in tbe neighbouring district of
                    Jessor. Among its many tributaries in Bâkarganj the most important is the Kacha,
                    itself a considerable stream and navigable by large boats all the year round,
                    which flows in a southerly direction for 20 miles, when it falls into the
                    Baleswar. Other rivers of minor importance are the Barisâl, Bishkhâli,
                    Nihâlganj, Khairâbâd, Ghâgar, Kumâr, &amp;c. * All the rivers in the district
                    are subject to tidal action from the Meghnâ on the north, and from the Bay of
                    Bengal on the south, and nearly all of them are navigable at high tide by
                    country boats of all sizes. The rise of the tide is very considerable in the
                    estuary of the Meghna, and many ofthe creeks and water-courses in the island of
                    Dakshin Shâhbâzpur, which are almost dry at ebb tide, contain 18 or 19 feet of
                    water at the flood. A very strong “bore” or tidal wave runs up the estuary of
                    the Meghnâ at spring tides, and a singular sound like thunder, known as the
                    “Barisal Guns,” is often heard far out at sea about the time it is coming in.
                    There are numerous marshes in the district, of great size and depth, and
                    abounding in fish. The following peculiarity of some of them is quoted from
                    Colonel GastrelΓs <hi rend="italic">Geographical and Statistical Report of the
                        District</hi> (1868):—“In some of the swamps, especially in those of
                    Bakarganj, the surface growth of aquatic plants, mixed with drift weeds, <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n263/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0903-0263-0248"/> grasses, and rice stalks, increases annually,
                    and in process of time a crust is formed capable of supporting human beings, and
                    on which rice is cultivated. Small floating patches are thus formed, and the
                    natives assert that in very strong blowing weather these are sometimes carried
                    from one side of the swamp to the other, and are a cause of great dispute. A
                    Government official, whose duties often took him to these swamps, mentioned that
                    the first time he found himself on ground of this kind, being totally unaware of
                    its nature, he was greatly alarmed at feeling, as he thought, the earth moving
                    beneath him; and still more astonished when, on seeking information from the
                    inhabitants, he was told ‘it was only the tide coming in.’ The owners of these
                    floating fields make holes through them, and catch the fish which are
                    immediately attracted by the light.”</p>
                <p>The census of 1872 disclosed a population of 2,377,433 souls in Bákarganj
                    district, spread over 4935 square miles, inhabiting 4269 villages and 321,657
                    houses; persons per square mile, 482; per village, 557; per house, 7 <hi
                        rend="superscript"> -</hi> 4. The Mahometans are the largest section of the
                    population, and number 1,540,965, or 64 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 8 per
                    cent, of the total inhabitants; Hindus, 827,393, or 34 ’ 8 per cent.; Buddhist,
                    4049, or ’ 2 per cent.; Christians, 4852, or '2 per cent.; and persons of
                    unspecified religion, 174 souls. The Musalmáns of Bákarganj are among the worst
                    of their creed, steeped in ignorance and prejudice, easily excited to violence
                    and murder, veιy litigious, and grossly immoral. The Faráizís or Puritan sect of
                    Mahometans are exceedingly numerous in the district. The Buddhist population
                    consists of Maghs or the people of Arákán, who first settled in Bákarganj about
                    seventy years ago, and have made themselves very useful in the clearing of the
                    Sundarbans. A gipsy-like tribe called the Bebájiás are rather numerous in this
                    district. They principally live in boats, travelling from place to place,
                    profess Muhammadanism, and gain their subsistence by wood-cutting in the
                    Sundarbans, fishing, iortune-telling, and trading in trinkets. The Christian
                    community of Bákarganj owes its origin to the Roman Catholic monastery at Bandel
                    near Calcutta, and to the Protestant (Baptist) missionaries at Serampur. The
                    principal native converts come from the Hindu low-caste Chandáls, &amp;c., who
                    subsist by cultivation.</p>
                <p>Barisál, the headquarters station, sitüated on the west bank of the Barisál
                    river, in 21° 41' 40'' N. lat., and 90° 24' 30" E. long., is the only town
                    containing upwards of 5000 inhabitants. In 1872 its population amounted to 7684
                    souls; municipal income, £1019, 18s.; municipal expenditure, £1006, 2s.;
                    incidence of taxation, 2s. 7|d. per head. There are also three other municipal
                    towns— (1.) Nalchití, a large trading village; principal exports, rice and
                    paddy; imports, salt, tobacco, oil, and sugar; (2.) Jhálakátí or Mahárájganj, a
                    large timber market, also trading in rice, paddy, and salt; (3.) Daulat Khán,
                    the principal village in the island of Dakshín, Sháhbázpur; exports, betel-nut.
                    A number of small trading villages exist throughout the district, and each
                    locality has its periodical fairs for purposes of traffic. The material
                    condition of the people is good. Every inhabitant is a small landholder, and
                    cultivates sufficient rice and other necessaries for the support of his family.
                    Owing to this reason, hired labour is very scarce, and during the harvest
                    season, when the few available labourers are sought for by the landholders, the
                    price of labour rises to Is. per diem. The average cost of living to a labouring
                    man is about 6s. per month. Except in the larger villages, the dwellings of the
                    people are very isolated. The inhabitants seldom congregate together into
                    hamlets, but each man builds his homestead on the highest spot on his own land
                    without any reference to his neighbours. Rice is the great crop of the district,
                    and three harvests are obtained annually—the <hi rend="italic">áman,</hi> or
                    winter rice; <hi rend="italic">áus,</hi> or autumn crop; and <hi rend="italic"
                        >boro,</hi> or spring rice. The former yields the finest grain, and is the
                    staple crop of the district. It is sown at the setting in of the rains in April
                    or May, transplanted from the beginning of June to the middle of August, and
                    reaped in November or December. About 100 varieties of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >áman</hi> rice are cultivated in the district. The <hi rend="italic"
                        >áus</hi> crop is sown in the early part of the hot weather, and reaped in
                    August. Upwards of 20 varieties of this rice are produced. The <hi rend="italic"
                        >boro</hi> or spring rice is of a coarse description, largely used by the
                    poorer classes, and is cultivated to a considerable extent in the alluvial river
                    accretions, and on other low-lying grounds. It is sown broadcast in December,
                    and reaped in April or May. Bákarganj exports its rice chiefly to Calcutta. The
                    average yield of rice land here is from 17½ to 22 cwt. per acre. Other crops—
                        <hi rend="italic">khesári (Lathyrus</hi><hi rend="italic">sativus),</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">rnusuri (fjicer lens), sarishd or</hi> mustard, rape-seed,
                    linseed, jute, sugar-cane, betel-nut, &lt;fcc. Manufactures—pottery, coarse
                    cloth, oil, fine mats, and molasses. The district has only five small roads, but
                    its rivers afford ample means of communication.</p>
                <p>Like all other districts of Bengal, Bákarganj has steadily increased in
                    prosperity since its administration passed into the hands of English officers,
                    and especially of late years, since the country has been directly under the
                    Crown. From the time of the acquisition of Bengal by the British in 1765 up the
                    end of 1817, Bákarganj formed a part of the Dacca district. It was then formed
                    into a separate collectorship, with the object of encouraging enterprising
                    persons to cultivate its immense tracts of waste lands. In 1818 the net revenue
                    of the district amounted to £96,438, and the net civil expenditure to £13,647.
                    Two years later (1820) the net district revenue had slightly decreased to
                    £95,709, while the net expenditure on civil administration had increased to
                    £16,659. During the next forty years both revenue and expenditure rapidly
                    increased, and in 1860-61 the net revenue of the district amounted to £150,305,
                    and the net civil expenditure to £32,584. In 1870-71 the total net revenue was
                    £203,445, and net civil expenditure, £44,902. The land revenue of Bákarganj is
                    settled in perpetuity with the <hi rend="italic">zαrnvηdars.</hi> In 1872 the
                    district contained 4729 estates, held by 5960 proprietors, who were assessed at
                    a total revenue of £143,156. In 1871 the machinery for protecting the district
                    consisted of 583 men of the regular police of all ranks, maintained at a total
                    cost of £11,186. Attached to the regular police is a river patrol consisting of
                    five boats, and manned by a crew of 35 men. The village watch or rural police
                    consisted in 1871 of 5135 men, maintained at a cost of £18,486, paid by the
                    landholders and villagers, each village watchman having besides a small plot of
                    ground rent free. A municipal police of 53 men was also maintained in the towns
                    and large villages, at a total cost of £403, 14s., defrayed out of municipal
                    receipts. Education is in a very backward state in Bákarganj, owing to the
                    inhabitants being almost wholly composed of petty husbandmen, the majority of
                    whom are Mahometans of the most bigoted tenets. In 1856-57 the district
                    contained 5 schools, attended by 482 pupils, and maintained at a total cost of
                    £595, 13s. In 1871-72 there were 78 Government and aided schools, attended by
                    3713 pupils, and maintained at a total cost of £3767, 12s., the total cost to
                    the state being £1232, 10s. This is exclusive of private schools uninspected by
                    the education department. The census report of 1872 returned the total number of
                    schools (Government and private) at 512, attended by a total of 7299 pupils.
                    Barisál town contains a Government school, which is the largest in Eastern
                    Bengal, and financially the most successful; the cost to Government for its 355
                    pupils in 1872 being only £31, 12s. Bákarganj district is divided into 5
                    magisterial sub-divisions, viz., Barisál, Dakshín Sháhbázpur, Mádá-rípur,
                    Pirozpur, ∙and Patuákhálí, comprising 18 police circles or <hi rend="italic"
                        >thdnás,</hi> and 54 fiscal divisions or <hi rend="italic">parganás.</hi>
                    The climate of Bákarganj is one of the healthiest in Eastern Bengal, owing to
                    the strong south-west monsoon, which comes up directly from the Bay of Bengal,
                    and keeps the atmosphere cool; but the heavy rain-fall and consequent humidity
                    of the atmosphere, combined with the use of bad water, are fruitful sources of
                    disease. The average annual temperature varies from 78° to 85°. The thermometer
                    ranges from 62° to 98°. The endemic diseases of Bákarganj<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n264/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0903-0264-0249"/> are fevers of the intermittent, remittent,
                    and continued types, attributable to the extreme dampness and malarious nature
                    of the district. Cholera is always present, the number of cases increasing in
                    the hot season and the beginning of the cold weather. Smallpox occasionally
                    makes its appearance in an epidemic form,—frequently caused by inoculation,
                    which is carried on to a great extent in Bâkarganj by the native medical
                    practitioners.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
