<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0903-0446-0431-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BATAVIA (9th edition, volume 3, page 431)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1116352">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1116439">Ships</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812571">Arabism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1243192">Borneo</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204543">Australia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4707wx1r">Ships</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zf6b">Malays</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ww7759r">Moors</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n446/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BATAVIA</label>, a large city and seaport on the north coast
                    of the island of Java, and the capital of all the Dutch settlements in the East.
                    It is situated on both sides of the river Jacatra or Tjiliwong, in a swampy
                    plain at the head of a capacious bay. The streets are for the most part straight
                    and regular, and many of them have a breadth of from 100 to 200 feet. In several
                    cases there is a canal in the centre lined with stone, and defended by low
                    parapets or banks, while almost every street and square is fringed with trees.
                    The old town has greatly changed from what it was in the 18th century. It was
                    then surrounded by strong fortifications, and contained a number of important
                    buildings, such as the town-house (built in 1652 and restored in 1706), the
                    exchange, the infirmary and orphan asylum, and the European churches. But the
                    ramparts were long ago demolished, and most of the public edifices have either
                    fallen into decay or been converted into magazines and warehouses. The great
                    church which was finished in 1760, at an expense of £80,000, had to be taken
                    down in consequence of its foundation having given way. Canals have been filled
                    up, streets have been altered, and the general character of the place
                    considerably modified. All the European inhabitants, except those immediately
                    connected with the shipping, have removed to the New Town, which has been
                    gradually formed by the integration of Weltevreden (<hi rend="italic"
                        >Well-content),</hi> Molenvliet <hi rend="italic">{Mill-stream),</hi>
                    Rijswijk <hi rend="italic">{Rice-town),</hi> Noordwijk <hi rend="italic"
                        >{North-town),</hi> Koningsplein <hi rend="italic">{King’s square),</hi> and
                    other suburban villages or stations. The situation of this modern part is higher
                    and healthier; and the grandeur and variety of its buildings far surpass
                    anything to be found in the older section of the city. The misplaced imitation
                    of Dutch arrangements has been happily avoided, and the natural advantages of
                    the situation and climate have been turned to account. The houses are frequently
                    separated from each other by rows of trees.</p>
                <p>As the chief city of the Dutch colonies in the East, Batavia contains numerous
                    buildings connected with the civil and military organization of the Government.
                    The chambers of the Council of the East Indies occupy a spacious edifice in
                    Rijswijk, and the governor-general’s hotel, or town-residence, is situated in
                    the same quarter. In the district of Weltevreden are the new palace, the
                    barracks, and the artillery school, as well as the military and civil hospital,
                    which can accommodate 600 patients, and not far off is the Frederik-Hendrik
                    citadel, which was built in 1837. Further inland, at Meester Cornelis (known for
                    its lake), Î3 a school for under-officers. The Koningsplein is a large open
                    square for military manoeuvres, about 390 feet long and 250 feet broad,
                    surrounded by mansions of the wealthier classes. Noordwijk is principally
                    inhabited by lesser merchants and subordinate officials. There is an
                    orphan-asylum in the district of Parapatta, and a poor-house <hi rend="italic"
                        >{Diaconie armenhaus)</hi> in Molenvliet. Besides those already mentioned,
                    Batavia has various educational and scientific institutions of note. In 1851 the
                    Government founded a medical school for <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n447/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0903-0447-0432"/> Javanese, and in 18G0 the “Gymnasium William
                    III.” in which a comprehensive education is bestowed. A society of arts and
                    sciences was established in 1778, a royal physical society in 1850, and a
                    society for the promotion of industry and agriculture in 1853. In addition to
                    the <hi rend="italic">Transactions</hi> of these societies—many of which contain
                    valuable contributions to their respective departments in their relation to the
                    East Indies—a considerable number of publications are issued in Batavia. Among
                    miscellaneous buildings of importance may be mentioned the public-hall known as
                    the <hi rend="italic">Harmonie,</hi> the freemasons’ lodge, the theatre, the
                    club-house, and several fine hotels.</p>
                <p>The population of Batavia is very varied,—the Dutch residents being a
                    comparatively small class, and greatly intermixed with Portuguese and Malays.
                    Here are found members of the different Indian nations, originally slaves; Moors
                    and Arabs, who are principally engaged in navigation, but also inhabit the Rua
                    Malacoa district, and trade in gold and precious stones; Javanese, who are
                    cultivators; and Malays, chiefly boatmen and sailors, and adherents of
                    Mahometanism. But, perhaps, the most important Asiatic element is the Chinese,
                    who are both numerous and industrious. They were long greatly oppressed by the
                    Dutch Government in various paltry ways, and in 1740 they were massacred to the
                    number of 12,000. But in spite of all this they have maintained their position,
                    and now enjoy a happier lot. In 1832 the population was found to consist of 2800
                    Europeans, 80,000 natives, 25,000 Chinese, 1000 Arabs, and 9500 slaves, a total
                    of 118,300 persons. The number of inhabitants is at present much less.</p>
                <p>Batavia is still a great commercial depot, though it has had to contend against
                    the rivalry of Singapore. The bay is rendered secure by a number of islands at
                    its mouth, and is capacious enough for a much larger trafiic than it has ever
                    seen; but it unfortunately grows very shallow towards the shore. Ships of 300 or
                    400 tons anchor about a mile and a half out; the river is navigable a couple of
                    miles inland for vessels of 30 or 40 tons, but the entrance is narrow, and
                    requires continual attention to keep it open.</p>
                <p>The exports from Batavia to the other islands of the archipelago, and to the
                    ports in the Malayan peninsula, are rice, sago, coffee, sugar, salt, oil,
                    tobacco, teak timber and planks, Java cloths, brass wares, &amp;c., and
                    European, Indian, and Chinese goods. The produce of the Eastern Islands is also
                    collected at its ports for re-exportation to India, China, and Europe,—namely,
                    gold-dust, diamonds, camphor, benzoin, and other drugs; edible bird-nests,
                    trepang, rattans, bees’ wax, tortoise-shell, and dyeing woods from Borneo and
                    Sumatra; tin from Banca; spices from the Moluccas; fine cloths from Celebes and
                    Bali; and pepper from Sumatra. From Bengal are imported opium, drugs, and
                    cloths; from China, teas, raw silk, silk piece-goods, varnished umbrellas,
                    coarse China wares, nankeen, paper, and innumerable smaller articles for the
                    Chinese settlers. British manufactures also are largely introduced. The number
                    of British ships that entered in 1870 was 103, with a tonnage of nearly 31,000
                    tons, the total number of vessels of all nationalities being 783, with a tonnage
                    of nearly 194,000.</p>
                <p>Almost the only manufactures of any importance are the distillation of arrack,
                    which is principally carried on by Chinese, the burning of lime and bricks, and
                    the baking of pottery; and even the brick-making is in a decaying condition. The
                    principal establishment for monetary transactions is the Java Bank, established
                    in 1828 with a capital of £500,000; but there are also agencies belonging to the
                    Bank of Rotterdam, and the Chartered Bank of India, Australia, aud China, as
                    well as a public savings bank.</p>
                <p>The Government has a naval establishment at the island of Onrust, about six miles
                    from the city; and among its other accommodations is a large iron floating dock
                    capable of holding vessels 400 feet long. Since 18G9, however, entrance has been
                    refused to merchant ships, which, consequently, feel the lack of proper docks in
                    the harbour. Proposals to build these and to extend the harbour, though
                    frequently under discussion, have had no result. Tramways were introduced into
                    the city in 1867, and are greatly patronized by the native population. A railway
                    to Buitenzorg, where the Government botanical gardens are situated, was opened
                    in 1871, the distance being about 40 miles inland.</p>
                <p>Batavia owes its origin to the Dutch general John Petersen Coen, who, in 1619,
                    took the town of Jacatra (which had been built on the ruins of the old Javanese
                    town of Sunda Calappa), destroyed it, and founded in its stead the present city,
                    which soon acquired a flourishing trade and increased in importance. The ruins
                    of Jacatra are to be found between Batavia and Anjol. In 1699 Batavia was
                    visited by a terrible earthquake, and the streams were choked by the mud from
                    the volcano of Gunong Salak (7244 feet high), by which the climate was so
                    affected that the city became notorious for its unhealthiness, and was in great
                    danger of being altogether abandoned. In the twenty-two years from 1730 to 1752,
                    1,100,000 deaths are said to have been recorded. General Daendals, who was
                    governor from 1808 to 1811, caused the ramparts of the town to be demolished,
                    and began to form the nucleus of a new city at Weltevreden. By 1816 nearly all
                    the Europeans had left the old town. In 1811 a British armament was sent against
                    the Dutch settlements in Java, which had been incorporated by France, and to
                    this force Batavia surrendered on the 8th of August. It was restored, however,
                    to the Dutch by the treaty of 1814.</p>
                <p>See Stavorinus, <hi rend="italic">Voyages to the East Indies;</hi> Barrow, <hi
                        rend="italic">Voyage to Cochin China;</hi> Sir George Staunton, <hi
                        rend="italic">Embassy to China;</hi> Daendel, <hi rend="italic">Staat
                        der</hi><hi rend="italic">Ncderl. O. Ind. Bezittungen;</hi> Junghuhn, <hi
                        rend="italic">Reisen der</hi><hi rend="italic">Java;</hi> Thorn, <hi
                        rend="italic">Mem. of the Conquest of Java;</hi> Sir S. Raffles, <hi
                        rend="italic">History of Java;</hi> Tèmininck, <hi rend="italic">L'Inde
                        Archip.;</hi> Veth, <hi rend="italic">Woordenboek v. Nederl. Ind.</hi></p>
                <p>B ATES, WILLIAM, D. D., an eminent Nonconformist divi ne, born in November 1625.
                    He was admitted to Emmanuel College, Cambridge, and removed thence to King’s
                    College in 1644. He was one of the commissioners at the conference in the Savoy,
                    for reviewing the public liturgy, and was concerned in drawing up the exceptions
                    to the Book of Common Prayer. Notwithstanding this he was appointed chaplain to
                    Charles II. soon after the Restoration, and became minister of St Dunstan’s in
                    the West; but he was afterwards deprived of his benefice for nonconformity.
                    Bates was of an amiable character, and enjoyed the friendship of the Lord-Keeper
                    Bridgeman, the Lord-Chancellor Finch, the earl of Nottingham, and Archbishop
                    Tillotson. He published <hi rend="italic">Select Lives of Illustrious ancl Pious
                        Persons,</hi> in Latin; and after his death all his works, except his <hi
                        rend="italic">Select Lives,</hi> were printed in one vol. fol.; again in
                    1723; and in 4 vols. 8vo, in 1815. He died in July 1699, in the 74th year of his
                    age.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
