<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0681-0664-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BICHAT, Marie-François-Xavier</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 3, page 664</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k877">Research</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4dv1cn3t">Functions</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4br8mh3x">Organ</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9q84g">Widows</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1095153">Research</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:936105">Functionals</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:936106">Functions</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1047771">Organisms</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1059227">Petitions</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n681/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BICHAT, <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Marie-François-Xavier</hi></label>, a celebrated French anatomist and
                    physiologist, was born at Thoirette in the department of Ain, in 1771. His
                    father, who was himself a physician, was his first instructor. He entered the
                    College of Nantua, and afterwards studied at Lyons. In mathematics and the
                    physical sciences he made rapid progress. Becoming passionately fond of natural
                    history he ultimately devoted himself to the study of anatomy and surgery, under
                    the guidance of Petit, chief surgeon to the -Hôtel Dieu at Lyons. He resumed for
                    a time his early Etudies, restricting himself, however, within such limits as
                    did not interfere with his medical pursuits. Petit soon discerned the superior
                    talents of his pupil, and, although the latter had scarcely attained the age of
                    twenty, employed him constantly as his assistant. The revolutionary disturbances
                    compelled Bichat to fly from Lyons and take refuge in Paris about the end of the
                    year 1793. He there became a pupil of the celebrated surgeon Desault. One day,
                    volunteering to supply the place of an absent pupil who was to have
                    recapitulated the lecture of the day before, he acquitted himself so admirably
                    that Desault was strongly impressed with his genius; and from that time Bichat
                    became an inmate in his house, and was treated as his adopted son. For two years
                    he actively participated in all the labours of Desault, prosecuting at the same
                    time his own researches in anatomy and physiology. The sudden death of Desault
                    in 1795 was a severe blow to Bichat. His first care was to acquit himself of the
                    obligations he owed his benefactor, by contributing to the support of his widow
                    and her son, and by conducting to a close the fourth volume of Desault’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Journal de</hi><hi rend="italic">Chirurgie,</hi> to which he added
                    a biographical memoir of its author. His next object was to reunite and digest
                    in one body the surgical doctrines which Desault had published in various
                    periodical works. Of these he composed, in 1797, the book entitled <hi
                    rend="italic">Oeuvres Chirurgicales</hi><hi rend="italic">de Desault,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">ou</hi><hi rend="italic">Tableau</hi><hi rend="italic">de sa
                    Doctrine, et de sa Pratique dans le Traitement des Maladies Externes,</hi> a
                    work in which, although he professes only to set forth the ideas of another, he
                    develops them with the clearness and copiousness of one who is a master of the
                    subject. He was now at liberty to pursue the full bent of his genius, and,
                    undisturbed by the storms which agitated the political world, he directed his
                    full attention to surgery, which it was then his design to practise. We meet
                    with many proofs of his industry at this period in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Recueil</hi><hi rend="italic">de la</hi><hi rend="italic">Société
                    Médicale</hi><hi rend="italic">d'Emulation,</hi> an association of which Bichat
                    was one of the most active members. In 1797 he began a course of anatomical
                    demonstrations, and his success encouraged him to extend the plan of his
                    lectures, and boldly to announce a course of operative surgery. Bichat’s
                    reputation was now fully established, and he was ever after the favourite
                    teacher with the Paris students. In the following year, 1798, he gave, in
                    addition to his course on anatomy and operative surgery, a separate course of
                    physiology. A dangerous attack of haemoptysis interrupted for a time these heavy
                    labours; but the danger was no sooner past than he plunged into new engagements
                    with the same ardour as before. He had now scope in his physiological lectures
                    for a fuller exposition of his original views on the animal economy, which
                    excited much attention in the medical schools at Paris. Sketches of these
                    doctrines were given by him in three papers contained in the Memoirs of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Société Médicale</hi><hi rend="italic">d'Emulation.</hi> The
                    doctrines were afterwards more fully developed in his <hi rend="italic">Traité
                    sur</hi><hi rend="italic">les Membranes,</hi> which appeared in 1800. In the
                    notes to a small work, in which he gave in a condensed form the lessons of
                    Desault on the diseases of the urinary passages, are found the germs of many of
                    Bichat’s peculiar views.</p>
                <p>His next publication was the <hi rend="italic">Récherches Physiologiques sur la
                    Vie et sur la Mort</hi> (1800), which consists of two dissertations. In the
                    first he explains his classification of functions, and traces the distinction
                    between the animal and organic functions in all its bearings. In the second he
                    investigates the connection between life and the actions of the three central
                    organs, the heart, lungs, and brain. But the work which contains the fruits of
                    his most profound and original researches is the <hi rend="italic">Anatomie
                    Générale,</hi> published in 4 vols. 8vo in 1801.</p>
                <p>Before Bichat had attained the age of eight-and-twenty he was appointed physician
                    to the Hôtel Dieu, a situation which opened an immense field to his ardent
                    spirit of inquiry. In the investigation of diseases he pursued the same method
                    of observation and experiment which had characterized his researches in
                    physiology. He learned their history by studying them at the bedside of his
                    patients, and by accurate dissection of their bodies after death. He engaged in
                    a series of examinations, with a view to ascertain the changes induced in the
                    various organs by disease, and in less than six months he had opened above six
                    hundred bodies. He was anxious also to determine, with more precision than had
                    been attempted before, the effects of remedial agents, and instituted with this
                    view a series of direct experiments on a very extensive scale. In this way he
                    procured a vast store of valuable materials for his course of lectures on the
                    Materia Medica, the completion of which was prevented by his death; but a great
                    part of the facts were embodied in the inaugural dissertations of his pupils.
                    Latterly, he also occupied himself with forming a new classification of
                    diseases.</p>
                <p>Bichat commenced a new work on anatomy, in which <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n682/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0682-0665"/> the organs were arranged according to his
                    peculiar classification of their functions, under the title of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Anatomie</hi><hi rend="italic">Descriptive,</hi> but he lived only to publish
                    the first two volumes. It was continued on the same plan, and completed in five
                    volumes by his assistants MM. Buisson and lloux. His death was occasioned by a
                    fall from a staircase at the Hôtel Dieu, which threw him into a fever. Exhausted
                    by excessive labour, and enfeebled by constantly breathing the tainted air of
                    the dissecting-room, he sank under the attack and died on the 22d July 1802,
                    attended to the last by the widow of his benefactor, from whom he had never been
                    separated. His funeral was attended by above six hundred of his pupils, and by a
                    large number of the physicians of Paris. His bust, together with that of
                    Desault, was placed in the Hôtel Dieu by order of Napoleon.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
