<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0903-0523-0508-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BEHAR (9th edition, volume 3, page 508)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1098511">Roads</term>
                    <term ref="fast:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:850620">Cent</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:970275">Indigo</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1093898">Religions</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g03">Cent</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k440">Indigo</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pp32">Roads</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g8x">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n523/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BEHAR</label>, a province of British India, under the
                    jurisdiction of the Lieutenant-Governor of Bengal, situated between 24° and 28°
                    N. lat., and 83° and 89° E. long. It comprises the districts of Champâran,
                    Tirhut, Shâhâbâd, Sârân, Patnâ, Purniah, Bhâgalpur, and the Santâl parganàs; and
                    is bounded on the N. by the independent kingdom of Nepâl; on the E. by the
                    Râjshâhi and Bardwân divisions of Bengal proper; on the S. by the Chhotâ Nâgpur
                    division; and on the W. by the North-Western Provinces. The general aspect of
                    the country is flat, except in the district of Monghir, where detached hills
                    occur, and in the south-east of the province, where the Râjmahal and Santâl
                    ranges abut upon the plains.</p>
                <p>Behar abounds in great rivers, such as the Ganges, with its tributaries, the
                    Ghagra, Gandak, Kusi, Mahananda, and Son. The Ganges enters the province near
                    the town of Baxar, flows eastward, and passing the towns of Dinâjpur, Patna,
                    Monghir, and Colgong, leaves the province at Râjmahal. It divides the province
                    into two almost equal portions; north of the river lie the districts of Sâran,
                    Champâran, Tirhut, Furniah, and part of Monghir and Bhâgalpur, and south of it
                    are Shâhâbâd, Patnâ, Gaya, the Santal parganàs, and the rest of Monghir and
                    Bhâgalpur. The Ganges and its northern tributaries are navigable by country
                    boats of large burden all the year round. The Son (the most important of the
                    southern tributaries) enters the province in the extreme south-west, and forming
                    for a short distance its boundary in that direction, flows north, past
                    Rhotâsgarh and Arah, separating the districts of Shâhâbâd from those of Gaya and
                    Patmi, and joins the Ganges opposite Châprâ. It has a very wide bed, and pours
                    down its waters with great velocity during the rains. The principal hills within
                    the province are the Moher hill in the district of Gaya, 1620 feet; Santal
                    pargami hills, 800 to 1600 feet; Rajmahal and Monghir hills, 1500 feet; and
                    Râjgarh hill in Patnâ, 1200 feet above sea-level.</p>
                <p>Behar Province contains eight districts, withan area of 42,417 square miles, and
                    a total population in 1872 of 19,736,101 souls, inhabiting 48,285 villages or
                    townships, and 3,252,036 houses; persons per square mile, 465; per village, 409.
                    The males numbered 9,797,649, or 49 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 6 per cent.,
                    and the females, 9,938,452, or 50 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 4 per cent., of
                    the total population. Of the provincial population, 16,526,850, or 83'7 per
                    cent., were Hindus; 2,636,053, or 13 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 4 per cent.,
                    Mahometans; 54 Buddhists; 8063 Christians; and 565,081, or 2’9 per cent., of
                    unspecified religion, mostly aborigines. Of the male adults, 3,613,231 are
                    returned as agriculturists, and 2,489,557 non-agriculturists. The aboriginal
                    tribes consist of the Bhars, Cherus, Dhângars, Kanjhârs, K liarwars, Kols, Mais,
                    Naiyâs, Nats, Pahariâs, Santals, and Tharus. The census of 1872 returned 49
                    towns as containing upwards of 5000 inhabitants, particulars of which will be
                    found in the accounts of the districts within which they are situated. Rice,
                    wheat, barley, pulses, maize, and various kinds of millets, form the principal
                    food-grains of the province. Rice is the main staple of food; but in elevated
                    and dry localities, wheat, maize, millet, and peas are substituted. Potatoes,
                    cabbages, &amp;c., were introduced by Europeans, and are now largely cultivated.
                    Many kinds of fruits and vegetables are also produced. The commercial staples
                    consist of oil-seeds, opium, indigo, sugar, cotton, and saltpetre. Upwards of
                    800,000 tons of oil-seeds were exported from Behar in 1872. The principal marts
                    for oil-seeds are Revelganj, in the Sâran district, and Roshrâ in Tirhut. The
                    cultivation of opium is a Government monopoly, and no person is allowed to grow
                    the poppy except on account of Government. The Behar Opium Agency has its
                    headquarters at the town of Patnâ. Annual engagements are entered into by the
                    cultivators, under a system of pecuniary advances, to sow a certain quantity of
                    land with P <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> PPy&gt; and the whole produce in the
                    form of opium is delivered to Government at a fixed rate. The area under poppy
                    cultivation in the Behar Agency in 1872 amounted to 330,925 acres. The Behar
                    indigo, generally called Tirhut indigo, yields about one-half of the total
                    produce of that dye which is annually exported from Calcutta. In the Bhâgalpur
                    division there are 44 factories, yielding on an average about 500 tons of indigo
                    a year. In the Patnâ division, indigo cultivation is almost entirely confined to
                    the north of the Ganges, in the districts of Tirhut, Sâran, and Champâran, which
                    in 1872 contained 104 factories, including outworks, and yielded 1958 tons of
                    the dye. The indigo industry is almost entirely conducted by Europeans, and the
                    total capital invested in the business in Behar is estimated at upwards of a
                    million sterling. Large quantities of sugar are exported, but the cotton grown
                    in the province is not sufficient for the requirements of the people, and has to
                    be supplemented by imports of raw cotton and English piece goods. Saltpetre is
                    largely refined in Tirhut, Sâran, and Champaran, and is exported both by rail
                    and river to Calcutta; the quantity exported by river in 1872 being 22,719 tons.
                    The manufactures of less importance are tasar-silk, paper, blankets, brass
                    utensils, fire-arms, carpets, coarse cutlery and hardware, leather, ornamenta of
                    gold and silver, Ac. Of minerals—lead, silver, and copper exist in the Bhâgalpur
                    division, but the mines are not worked. One coal-mine is worked in the Santal
                    parganàs. Before the construction of railways in India, the Ganges and the Grand
                    Trunk road afforded the sole means of communication from Calcutta to the
                    North-Western Provinces. But now the railroad is the great highway which
                    connects Upper India with Lower Bengal. The East Indian Railway runs throughout
                    the length of the province; total length of rail, upwards of 500 miles. Besides
                    the Grand Trunk road, the other important roads in the province are—(1), Road
                    from Synthia Railway Station to Bhâgalpur; (2), Darjiling road, from Kârâgolâto
                    Siliguri; (3), from Shahrghâti on the Grand Trunk road to Patnâ city, and thence
                    to Tirhut town. There are also many local roads under the management of the
                    district road committees. The gross revenue of the province in 1872 amounted to
                    £1,596,952, of which £1,184,906, or 74 per cent., was from land. In 1872 the 8
                    districts of the province were divided into 37 executive subdivisions, and
                    contained 52 civil judges and 80 magistrates. The total police force (regular,
                    municipal, and village) consists of 60,028 men; cost, £210,943. In 1872 there
                    were 215 Government and aided schools, attended by 9454 pupils, and maintained
                    at a total cost of £17,835, of which Government contributed £10,328. These are
                    exclusive of unaided schools. The census of 1872 returned the total number of
                    schools, aided and unaided, in the province at 4781. Bengali is the language in
                    the eastern part of the province; but Hindi, one of the dialects of Sanskrit, is
                    the language of the rest. The Mahometan population use Hindustâni or Urdu, a
                    language of modern origin, formed from the fusion of Persian and Arabic with
                    Hindi. The climate of Behar is very hot from the middle of March to the end of
                    June, when the rains set in, which continue till the end of September. The cold
                    season, from October to the first half of March, is the pleasantest time of the
                    year. The total rainfall in 1872 varied from 32 to 60 inches in different
                    localities; minimum temperature in December, 53°; maximum in May, 105°.</p>
                <p>In ancient times Behar comprised the dominions of the kings of Magadha, who at
                    one time were the lords paramount of India, and whose court is represented as
                    one of the most brilliant that ever existed. Alexander the Greal when he invaded
                    India intended to push his conquests tc Palibothra, the capital of Magadha,
                    whose monarch he heard could oppose him with 30,000 cavalry, 600,000 infantry,
                    and 9000 elephants. Their highest point of grandeur was supposed to have been
                    attained at the time of Seleucus Nicator, one of the immediate successors of
                    Alexander, whe invaded Magadha. According to the Greek historians he was
                    victorious, but this is doubtful, as he relinquished al] the Macedonian
                    conquests to the east of the Indus, and gave his daughter in marriage to Chandra
                    Gupta, the reigning king. At this time Magasthenes was appointed to represent
                    him at Magadha court. The Magadha monarchs encouraged arts and learning,
                    constructed roads, and sent their fleets across the Bay of Bengal to colonise
                    Java, Bali, and other islands in the Indian Archipelago. The Magadha kingdom
                    flourished from the 4th century before the Christian era to the 5th century
                    after it. But ancient Behar is far more celebrated in another respect. Six
                    centuries before the Christian era it was the cradle of Buddhism when that
                    religion was in its infant state. It sent its missionaries to Ceylon, China,
                    Thibet, and Tartary, and the religion they taught is still followed by 300
                    millions of people. Behar is a sacred spot in the eyes of the Chinese and other
                    Buddhist nations. In 1202 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> Behar fell into the
                    hands of the Mahometans without a struggle, and from this time it formed one of
                    the three subahs or provinces under the rulers of Bengal. In the time of Akbar
                    it comprised the seven <hi rend="italic">sarkars</hi> of Monghir, Champâran,
                    Hâjipur, Sâran, Tirhut, Rohtâs, and Behar. It came into the possession of the
                    East India Company with the acquisition of the Dïwâni in 1765, when the province
                    was united with Bengal. In 1857 two zamindârs, Umar Sinh and Kumâr Sinh,
                    rebelled against the British Government, and for some months held the ruinous
                    fort of Rohtâs against the English.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Behar,</hi> a magisterial subdivision, and a town of Patna
                    district. The <hi rend="smallcaps">Subdivision</hi> was formed in 1846. It has
                        <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n524/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0903-0524-0509"/> an area of 792 square miles, with a total
                    population of 570,888 souls, the average population per square mile being 721.
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Behar Town</hi> is situated in 25° 10' N. lat., and 85°
                    35' E. long. It was formerly the capital of a subah or governorship under the
                    Mahometans, but at present it is merely a subdivisional town. Population in 1872
                    :— Hindus, 31,006; Mahometans, 13,282; others, 7; total, 44,295. Municipal
                    income, £1100; expenditure, £1120; rate of taxation, 6d. per head of
                    population.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
