<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0559-0544-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BELLAY, Joachim du</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 3, page 544</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1026160">Morels</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1059232">Petrarchism</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:839665">Brothers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:922595">Felting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41n7xv2f">Pleiades</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4nv99f02">Felt</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41n7xp5n">Columbae</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n559/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BELLAY, <hi rend="smallcaps">Joachim du</hi></label>, an
                    eminent French poet and member of the Pleiad, was born late in 1524, at Lyré, on
                    the left bank of the Loire, not far from Angers. In the absence of documents we
                    are thrown upon the autobiographical passages in his poems for information about
                    the events of his life, and these, fortunately, are copious. From these, and
                    especially from the beautiful Latin elegy addressed to his friend Jean Morel, we
                    learn that, deprived early of both his parents, he was left to the mercy of an
                    elder brother, who allowed him to be brought up without other education than
                    what his own ardent spirit supplied. Before he reached manhood this brother also
                    died, and Joachim found himself at the head of the family, a vigorous, manly,
                    but half-cultured youth. Suddenly he was struck down by illness; and, confined
                    for many months to his bed, he softened the long hours of suffering by fervent
                    study; he now read the Latin and Greek poets for the first time, and felt a
                    passionate desire to imitate them in French. In 1548, having to a great measure
                    recovered his health, he happened to meet Ronsard in an inn in Poitiers, and a
                    friendship instantly sprang up between them that ceased only with Du Bellay’s
                    death. He joined the six poets, who, under Dorat, were forming a society, the
                    Pleiad, for the creation of a French school of Renaissance poetry; and his first
                    contribution to it was a prose volume, the famous <hi rend="italic"
                    >Deffence</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">Illustration de la
                    Langue</hi><hi rend="italic">française,</hi> which remains one of the earliest
                    and most perfect pieces of literary criticism in existence, and overweighs in
                    positive value much of his actual poetry. This appeared in 1549, and was
                    followed within a twelvemonth by two volumes in verse, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Recueil de Poésie,</hi> and the collection of lovesonnets called <hi
                    rend="italic">L</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">Olive.</hi> The latter celebrate, in
                    the manner of Petrarch, the loveliness of a semi-mythical mistress, understood
                    to be a Parisienne, and by name Viole, of which Olive is an anagram. The <hi
                    rend="italic">Recueil</hi> caused a quarrel with Ronsard, about which much
                    speculation has been wasted, and which still remains obscure. It seems that
                    Ronsard had invented a new form of the ode, which he allowed Du Bellay to see in
                    manuscript. Ronsard’s book was delayed in publication, and Du Bellay’s odes,
                    written after his metrical pattern, appeared first. Ronsard’s natural and
                    passing vexation has been exaggerated into a law-suit; but the friends were soon
                    on the old affectionate footing. In <hi rend="italic">L</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic"
                    >Olive</hi> Du Bellay was the first French writer to use the sonnet with
                    fluency. After he had translated two books of the Aeneid, which appeared in
                    1552, the yearning he had always felt to visit Italy was appeased by his being
                    sent to Rome in 1550 as secretary to his influential relative, Cardinal du
                    Bellay, and he remained in that city four years and a half. At first, however,
                    he was miserable enough. Everything around him was displeasing to him and jarred
                    on his refined and sometimes sickly nerves. At last he fell violently in love
                    with a lady, whose real name was Faustine, but whom he celebrates under the
                    poetical title of Columba and Columbelle. In his Latin poems this sincere and
                    absorbing passion burns like a clear flame, more veiled though no less burning
                    in his French <hi rend="italic">Regrets.</hi> Before he won her she was shut up
                    from his sight by her old and jealous husband. Frenzied with grief and desire,
                    burning with fever, exhausted with watching and physical suffering,—for his
                    health was still very delicate,·—Du Bellay walked day and night to and fro
                    before the house. At last, mysteriously enough, she is given to him; and the
                    Latin poems end in rapturous delight. At this point, however, and possibly for
                    this reason, he was hurried back to Paris, where he became canon of Nôtre Dame
                    in June 1555. He returned by Venice, the Grisons, and Geneva, and was received
                    by his friends in France with transport. He set himself to literary labour of
                    various kinds, publishing his Latin poems and his French sonnets called <hi
                    rend="italic">Les Antiquitez de Rome,</hi> in 1558, and his greatest lyrical
                    work, the <hi rend="italic">Regrets,</hi> in 1559. In the latter year, however,
                    a calumny deprived him of the protection of the -cardinal, and threw him into
                    the deepest distress and embarrassment. The nature of this charge is not known,
                    but it must have quickly passed away, for later on in that year we find him
                    preparing a new volume of poems, <hi rend="italic">Les Jeux Rustiques,</hi> for
                    the press, and nominated archbishop of Bordeaux. He did not live to enjoy this
                    distinction, for on the 1st of January 1560, he died of apoplexy, and was bαried
                    in Nôtre-Dame de Paris. Like Ronsard he was very deaf.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n560/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0560-0545"/>
                <p>His collected works did not appear until 1568. The early death of the French
                    Ovid, as he has been called, was a serious loss to European literature, for
                    Joachim du Bellay wa3 at the height of his power, and still rapidly advancing.
                    His poems have a force, an occasional sublimity, and a direct pathos for which
                    we look in vain among his contemporaries; and none but Ronsard excelled him in
                    facility and grace. His most famous poem, <hi rend="italic">Un Vanneur de
                    Blé</hi><hi rend="italic">aux Vents,</hi> one of the loveliest lyrics of the
                    age, was written shortly before his death, and appeared in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Jeux Rustiques</hi> in 1560; it is nominally a paraphrase from the Latin of
                    Naugerius. The standard edition of the French works of Joachim du Bellay is that
                    published in 2 vols, by Lemerre in 1866, and edited by Ch. Marty-Laveaux.
                    Spenser translated sixty of Du Bellay’s Roman sonnets into English, and
                    published them in 1591. A very delicate essay on the poet will be found in Mr W.
                    H. Pater’s <hi rend="italic">Studies in the History of the Renaissance,</hi>
                    1873.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
