<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0546-0531-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BELGRADE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 3, page 531</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:821579">Austrians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1131021">Spurs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:884187">Crosses</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1098511">Roads</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1159574">Turks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4h41jw08">Servians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pp2k">Cross</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x63bd91">Spurs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48s4jt2v">Heights</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204901">Austria</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n546/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BELGRADE</label> (in Servian, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Bielgorod,</hi> or White Town), the capital of the Servian principality,
                    situated at the confluence of the Save and the Danube, on the right bank of the
                    latter stream, opposite the Austrian town and fortress of Semlin. Lat. 44° 47'
                    N., long. 20° 28' E. It is built both on, and at the side of, a northern spur of
                    the Avala heights, the rocky summit being crowned by its ence famous citadel,
                    which still remains very much as it was left by Prince Eugene, except that on
                    the E., S., and W. the glacis has been changed into a promenade. The town was
                    formerly divided into three parts, namely, the Old Town, the Rassian Town <hi
                    rend="italic">{Sava mahala</hi> or Savedistrict), and the Turkish town <hi
                    rend="italic">{Dorcol,</hi> or Cross-road). A great change has, however, taken
                    place in the course of the present century, and the old divisions are only
                    partially applicable, while there has to be added the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n547/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0547-0532"/> Tirazia, an important recent suburban extension
                    along the line of the aqueduct or <hi rend="italic">Tirazi.</hi> Since 1869
                    great activity has been shown in building, and the Old Town is gradually being
                    regulated according to a definite plan. The general appearance of the place is
                    growing more and more European; its mosques and minarets, protected from actual
                    demolition by a Turkish treaty, are falling into ruin from neglect. As the seat
                    of the Servian Government, and the residence of the prince and the archbishop,
                    Belgrade possesses a royal and an episcopal palace, a foreign and a home office,
                    and other public buildings. Its educational institutions are remarkably
                    numerous, consisting of a high school, several normal schools, a gymnasium, a
                    theological seminary, a military academy, an industrial school, and an upper
                    school for girls. There is a theatre devoted to the development of the national
                    drama; and in the same building with the high school there is preserved a
                    valuable collection of national antiquities as well as an extensive library.
                    Besides the mosques, the ecclesiastical buildings include a cathedral and
                    several Greek churches, a Roman Catholic chapel in the Austrian embassy, and an
                    evangelical church. Among places of historical interest are the ruins of Prince
                    Eugene’s palace, and the monument in the Topjidere park on the spot where Prince
                    Michael was assassinated in 1868. · The citadel has been already mentioned; a
                    commandant’s residence, barracks, and a military hospital are among its
                    subsidiary buildings. Though its situation is highly conducive to mercantile
                    activity, the commerce of Belgrade is not so great as would naturally be
                    anticipated. It holds, however, direct commercial relations not only with Vienna
                    and Constantinople but with Manchester. There are only two monetary
                    establishments, one known as the “First Bank,” and the other a bank of credit.
                    The principal industrial products of the city are cotton-stuffs, carpets,
                    leather, and fire-arms. Belgrade is identified with the ancient <hi
                    rend="italic">Singi∙ dunum,</hi> and was the station of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Legio</hi><hi rend="italic">IV.</hi><hi rend="italic">Flavia</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Felix.</hi> It has from its earliest existence been a place of
                    military importance, and in modern times has sustained many sieges, and
                    repeatedly passed from the hands of the Austrians to those of the Turks. It was
                    taken by Soliman II. in 1521, and retaken by the Austrians in 1688, but again
                    lost in 1690. In 1717 it surrendered to Prince Eugene. The imperialists retained
                    it till 1739, when the Turks invested and reduced it. Austria again took it in
                    1789, but it was restored at the peace of 1791. In the year 1806 the Servian
                    insurgents succeeded in carrying it. In 1862 it was bombarded from the citadel
                    on account of a contest raging between the Turkish and Servian inhabitants, but
                    five years later it waβ completely evacuated by the foreign forces, and the
                    citadel received a garrison of Servian soldiere. The only mark of Turkish
                    occupation is the banner which continues to be shown from its walls along with
                    the national colours. Population in 1872, 26,674.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
