<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0854-0837-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BLOWPIPE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 3, page 837</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206830">Brazil</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="39" ref="fasttopic:926972">Flame</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:802066">Air</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:834188">Blasting</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:829151">Beads</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:833880">Blacks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:833576">Black</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4833n637">Rose</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b40k26c32">Brushes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20n29">Platinum</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="lcsh1910:b4jd4pp0f">Air</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="lcsh1910:b4b853j55">Blasting</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="lcsh1910:b4x05xc99">Beads</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4q52ff6p">Heat</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n854/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BLOWPIPE</label>, a tube for directing a jet of air into a
                    fire or into the flame of a lamp or gas jet, for the purpose of producing a high
                    temperature by complete and rapid combustion. The blowpipe has been in common
                    use from the earliest times for soldering metals and working glass; and since
                    1733, when Anton Swab first applied it to analysis of mineral substances,· it
                    has become a valuable auxiliary to the mineralogist and chemist, in the chemical
                    examination and analysis of minerals. Its application has been variously
                    improved at the hands of Cronstedt, Bergmann, Gahn, Berzelius, Plattner, and
                    others, but more especially by the two last-named chemists.</p>
                <p>The simplest and oldest form of blowpipe (still used by gasfitters, jewellers,
                    &amp;c.), is a conical brass tube, about 7 inches in length, curved at the small
                    end into a right angle, and terminating in a small round orifice, which is
                    applied to the flame, while the larger end is applied to the mouth. Where the
                    blast has to be kept up for only a few seconds, this instrument is quite
                    serviceable; but in longer chemical operations inconvenience arises from the
                    condensation of moisture exhaled by the lungs in the tube. Hence many blowpipes
                    are made with a cavity for retaining the moisture. Cronstedt placed a bulb in
                    the centre of his blowpipe. Dr Black’s convenient instrument consists of a
                    conical tube of tin plate, with a small brass tube, supporting the nozzle,
                    inserted near the wider end, and a mouthpiece at the narrow end. One of the most
                    suitable forms of blowpipe is that shown in fig. 1. It is Galin’s instrument as
                    improved by Plattner. The tube A is ground to fit accurately into a socket at
                    the top of the water-trap B, as is also the jet-pipe C. The nozzle D, of
                    platinum, is fitted in the same manner, so that it can be easily removed and
                    replaced while hot; <hi rend="italic">e.g.</hi> when it is desired to remove the
                    crust of soot which deposits upon the point when an oil lamp or candle is used.
                    The sizes of orifice recommended by Plattner are 0 4 and 0 <hi
                    rend="superscript"> -</hi> 5 millim. The trumpet mouthpiece, from the support it
                    gives to the cheeks when inflated, conduces to a more steady and long-continued
                    blast being kept up without fatigue than when the mouthpiece is inserted between
                    the lips. Mr David Forbes has suggested the use of a double jet-pipe in
                    connection with this instrument, so that a large or small orifice may be
                    obtained without stopping the point; but it is doubtful whether the advantage
                    gained is counterbalanced by the extra cost and complication. For the majority
                    of blowpipe workers, there is probably no better instrument than Dr Black’s, if
                    provided with a properly-shaped nozzle, if possible of platinum; but where it is
                    much used, the large-sized trumpet-mouthed instrument of Plattner is to be
                    preferred. The instrument should be held with the first and fourth fingers
                    passed round it, and the thumb laid along the side of the tube, the hold being
                    steadied by resting the elbow on the table. The mode of blowing is peculiar, and
                    requires some practice; an uninterrupted blast is kept up by the muscular action
                    of the cheeks, while the ordinary respiration goes on through the nostrils.</p>
                <p>If the flame of a candle or lamp be closely examined, it will be seen to consist
                    of four parts—(a) a deep blue ring at the base, (6) a dark cone in the centre,
                    (c) a luminous portion round this, and (&lt;7) an exterior pale blue envelope.
                    The blue ring is formed chiefly by combustion of carbonic oxide. In the central
                    cone the combustible vapours from the wick, though heated, are not burned,
                    atmospheric oxygen not reaching it. In the luminous portion the supply of oxygen
                    is not sufficient for complete combustion; the hydrogen takes up all or most of
                    it, and carbon is precipitated in solid particles and ignited. In the exterior
                    envelope, lastly, the temperature is highest, and combustion most
                    complete,—sufficient oxygen being supplied to convert the carbon and hydrogen
                    into water and carbonic acid..</p>
                <p>In blowpipe work only two of these four parts are. made use of, viz., the pale
                    envelope, for <hi rend="italic">oxidation,</hi> and. the luminous portion, for
                    <hi rend="italic">reduction.</hi> To obtain a good· <hi rend="italic">oxidizing
                    flame,</hi> the blowpipe is held with its nozzle inserted in the edge of the
                    flame close over the level of the wick, and blown into gently and evenly. A
                    conical jet is thus-produced, consisting of an inner cone, with an outer one
                    commencing near its apex:—the former, corresponding to (a) in the free flame,
                    blue and well defined; the latter, corresponding to (cZ), pale blue and vague.
                    The heat is greatest just beyond the point of the inner cone, combustion being
                    there most complete. Oxidation is better effected (if a very high temperature be
                    not required) the farther the substance is from the apex of the inner cone, so
                    far as the heat proves sufficient, for the air has thus freer access.</p>
                <p>To obtain a good <hi rend="italic">reducing flame</hi> (in which the combustible
                    matter, very hot, but not yet burned, is disposed to take oxygen from any
                    compound containing it), the nozzle, with smaller orifice, should just touch the
                    flame at a point higher above the wick, and a somewhat weaker current of air
                    should be blown. The flame then appears as a long, narrow, luminous cone,—the
                    end being enveloped by a dimly visible portion of flame corresponding to that
                    which surrounds the free flame, while there is also a dark nucleus about the
                    wick. The substance to be reduced is brought into the luminous portion, where
                    the reducing power is strongest.</p>
                <p>The flame of an oil-lamp is the best 'for blowpipe operations where gas is
                    wanting; candle flame may be used when great heat is not required. The blowpipe
                    lamp of Berzelius, supplied with colza oil, is probably the most suitable. The
                    wick, when in use, should be carefully trimmed and clean, so as to avoid a
                    smoking flame. The general introduction of gas has quite driven out the use of
                    oil-lamps for blowpipe purposes in laboratories.</p>
                <p>Various materials are used as supports for substances in the blowpipe flame; the
                    principal are charcoal, platinum, and glass. <hi rend="italic">Charcoal</hi> is
                    valuable for its infusibility and low conductivity for heat (allowing substances
                    to be strongly heated upon it), and for its powerful reducing agency by the
                    production of carbonic oxide when ignited; so that it is chiefly employed in
                    trying the fusibility of minerals, and in reduction. The best kind of charcoal
                    is that of close-grained pine or alder; it is cut in short prisms, having a flat
                    smooth surface at right angles to the rings of growth. In this a shallow hole is
                    made with a knife or borer, for receiving the substance to be held in the flame.
                    <hi rend="italic">Platinum</hi> is employed in oxidizing processes, and in
                    fusion of substances with fluxes with a view to try their solubility in them,
                    and note the phenomena of the bead; also in observing the colouring effect of
                    substances on the blowpipe flame (which effect is apt to be somewhat masked <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n855/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0855-0838"/> by charcoal). Most commonly it is used in the
                    form of wire, with a small bend or loop at the end. In flux experiments this
                    loop is dipped when ignited in the powdered flux <hi rend="italic">le.g.,</hi>
                    borax), then held in a lamp flame till the powder is fused; and the process is
                    repeated, if necessary, till the loop is quite filled with a bead of the flux;
                    to this is now added a little of the substance to be examined. Γlatinum is also
                    used in the form of foil and of spoons, and for the points of forceps. Metals
                    and easily reducible oxides, sulphides, or chlorides should not be treated upon
                    platinum, as these substances may combine with and damage it. Tubes of hard
                    German <hi rend="italic">glass,</hi> 5 to 6 inches long, about ⅜th inch
                    diameter, and open at both ends, are useful in the examination of substances
                    containing sulphur, selenium, arsenic, antimony, and tellurium; these, when
                    heated with access of air, evolve characteristic fumes. They are put in the tube
                    near one end (which is held slightly depressed), and subjected to the blowpipe
                    flame. The sublimates often condense on the cooler parts of the tube. Small
                    tubes, closed at one end, are used, where it is required to detect the presence
                    of water, mercury, or other bodies which are volatilized by heat without access
                    of air.</p>
                <p>The most important fluxes used in blowpipe analysis are carbonate of sodium,
                    borax, and microcosmic salt. The first (which must be anhydrous and quite free
                    from sulphates) serves chiefly in reducing metallic oxides aud sulphides on
                    charcoal, decomposing silicates, determining the presence of sulphur, and
                    discriminating between lime and other earthy bases in minerals. Pure <hi
                    rend="italic">borax,</hi> or acid borate of sodium deprived of its water of
                    crystallization by heating, is used for the purpose of dissolving up metallic
                    oxides, when in a state of fusion at a red heat, such fused masses usually
                    having characteristic colours when cold. In some cases the colour and
                    transparency change on cooling. <hi rend="italic">Microcosmic salts,</hi> or
                    ammonio-phosphate of sodium, is used on platinum wire in the same way as borax
                    j<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>In a paper to the
                    Royal Society, Captain Ross points out that it is better to use boric acid and
                    phosphoric acid, instead of borax and microcosmic salts, for various
                    analyses.</p></note> on heating, water and ammonia are given off. The following
                    are some other reagents for certain cases—nitrate of potash, bisulphate of
                    potash, nitrate of cobalt, silica, fluoride of calcium, oxide or oxalate of
                    nickel, protoxide of copper, tinfoil, fine silver, dry chloride of silver, bone
                    ash, and litmus and Brazil-wood paper.</p>
                <p>It may be useful here to pass briefly under review a few of the effects obtained
                    in qualitative examinations with the blowpipe. Beginning with the <hi
                    rend="italic">closed tube,</hi> organic substances may be revealed by the
                    empyreumatic odour given off, and by charring. Mercury condenses on the tube in
                    minute globules. Selenium gives a reddish-brown, tellurium a grey, arsenic a
                    black sublimate. Oxygen is sometimes given off. and will inflame an incandescent
                    splinter of wood when introduced; while ammonia may be detected by red litmus
                    paper, as also the acid or alkaline reaction of any liquid product. In the <hi
                    rend="italic">open tube,</hi> sulphur and sulphides give off pungent-smelling
                    sulphurous acid gas. Selenium gives a steel-grey deposit, and an odour
                    resembling that of horse radish. Arsenic, antimony, tellurium, yield their
                    respective acids, forming white sublimates. The deposit from arsenic is
                    crystalline, that from the others amorphous. In examination on <hi rend="italic"
                    >charcoal,</hi> it is useful, in practice, to commence with pure materials and
                    familiarize one’s self with their phenomena. Most of the metals fuse in the heat
                    of the blowpipe flame; and in the outer flame they oxidize. The noble metals do
                    not oxidize, but they fuse. The metals platinum, iridium, rhodium, and palladium
                    do not fuse. The incrustations (when such occur) are in each case
                    characteristic, both in aspect and in the effects they give before the blowpipe
                    flame. Among the most common oxides capable of reduction on charcoal alone, in
                    the inner flame, are those of zinc, silver, lead, copper, bismuth, and antimony.
                    The principal minerals that cannot be so reduced are those containing alkalies
                    and alkaline earths, and the oxides of iron, manganese, and chromium. Many
                    substances give a characteristic colour, when held by platinum forceps in the
                    oxidizing flame. For example, arsenic, antimony, lead, colour the flame <hi
                    rend="italic">blue;</hi> copper, baryta, zinc, <hi rend="italic">green;</hi>
                    lime, lithia, strontia, <hi rend="italic">red;</hi> potash, <hi rend="italic"
                    >violet.</hi> Heated with <hi rend="italic">borax,</hi> some bodies give a clear
                    bead, both while hot and cold, except when heated by the intermittent oxidizing
                    flame, or the flame of reduction, when the bead becomes opalescent, opaque, or
                    milky white. The alkaline earths, tantalic and titanic acids, yttria and
                    zirconia are examples of this. The oxides of most of the heavy metals give
                    coloured glasses with borax, similar to those obtained by their use in glass or
                    enamel painting. Thus oxide of cobalt gives a showy blue, and oxide of nickel a
                    reddish-brownish colour, both being very characteristic and delicate tests of
                    the presence of these metals. Ferric oxide gives a feeble yellow colour, which
                    is darker while hot; but when the bead so coloured is treated in the reducing
                    flame the iron passes into the state of ferrous oxide,giving an intensely green
                    or nearly black colour. This reaction may be more certainly brought about by
                    touching the bead while melted with a fragment of tin, when the ferric oxide is
                    probably reduced at the expense of the metal. With manganese the reverse effect
                    is produced. A bead containing a considerable quantity of manganous oxide, such
                    as is produced by a clean reducing flame, is colourless, but when treated in the
                    oxidizing flame the showy violet colour of the higher oxide is brought out. This
                    reaction is a very-delicate one, and is to be recommended to beginners as a test
                    exercise in blowing a clean flame, the bead being rendered alternately coloured
                    and colourless according as the oxidizing or reducing flame is used. Molybdic
                    acid, which gives a black bead in the reducing, and a clear bead in the
                    oxidizing flame, but requires more careful management, was usually recommended
                    by Plattner to his students for this kind of exercise. Copper salts give a green
                    bead in the oxidizing and a deep sealing-wax red in the reducing flame. This
                    latter indication is of value in detecting a trace of copper in the presence of
                    iron, which is done by reducing with tin as already described for iron. The
                    effects obtained with beads of microcosmic salt, or as it is more generally
                    called <hi rend="italic">salt of phosphorus,</hi> are generally similar to those
                    described for borax, but in certain cases it is to be preferred, especially in
                    the detection of silica, which remains undissolved, and titanic acid, which can
                    be made to assume the form of crystals similar to the natural mineral anatase by
                    particular treatment and microscopic examination. Several new phenomena, due to
                    the crystallization of titanic acid and similar bodies, have been described by
                    Gustav Rose.</p>
                <p>With <hi rend="italic">carbonate of sodium</hi> as flux (a paste of which and the
                    substance to be examined is made with water, and held on charcoal to the flame),
                    three reactions may occur. The substance may fuse with effervescence, or it may
                    be reduced, ox ’ the soda may sink into the charcoal, leaving the substance
                    intact on the surface. The first takes place with silica, and with titanic and
                    tungstic acids. The oxides of tungsten, antimony, arsenic, copper, mercury,
                    bismuth, tin, lead, zinc, iron, nickel, and cobalt are reduced. Lead, zinc,
                    antimony, bismuth, cadmium, and tellurium are volatilized partially, and form
                    sublimates on the charcoal. Mercury and arsenic are dissipated as soon as
                    reduced. Silica and titanic acid are the only two substances that produce a
                    clear bead. The bead in which silica is fused is sometimes rendered yellow by
                    the presence of sulphur. Carbonate of soda, with addition of a little nitrate of
                    potassa, is very useful for detecting minute quantities of manganese. The fused
                    mass, when clear, has, from the production of manganate<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n856/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0856-0839"/> of sodium, a fine green colour. (For particulars
                    of the behaviour of different minerals before the blowpipe, see the detailed
                    description in the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Mineralogy.)</hi> Of late years
                    the spectroscope has been successfully used in connection with blowpipe
                    operations, in the detection of certain of the rarer metallic elements.</p>
                <p>The blowpipe was first applied in the quantitative determination of metals by
                    Harkort in 1827, and wa3 brought to a high degree of perfection by Plattner. The
                    methods are substantially those adopted in the assay of ores on the large scale
                    in the wind furnace or muffle, thin capsules of clay or cavities in charcoal
                    blocks being substituted for crucibles, and steel basins faced with bone ash,
                    for cupels, in silver and gold assaying. From the small size of the beads
                    obtained, especially when the ores of the precious metals are operated upon, the
                    results are often such as cannot be weighed, and they are then measured by a
                    tangent scale, and the weight computed from the observed diameter. This method,
                    devised by Harkort, gives very accurate results when carefully used, but owing
                    to the difficulty of sampling the minute quantities operated upon so as to
                    represent the bulk of the mineral fairly, the quantitative blowpipe assay has
                    not made much progress. Perhaps the most useful quantitative application is in
                    the determination of nickel and cobalt. This depends upon the fact that when the
                    compounds of these metals, as well as those of copper and iron, with arsenic,
                    are melted in contact with an oxidizing flux, such as borax or salt of
                    phosphorus, iron is first taken up, then cobalt, and next nickel, and finally
                    copper; and as the oxides of these metals give very different colours to the
                    flux, we are enabled by examining the slag to detect the exact moment at which
                    each is removed. For the details of the process the reader is referred to
                    Plattner’s work.</p>
                <p>Among the various arrangements which have been contrived for supplying air to the
                    blowpipe otherwise than with the mouth, we may select that represented in the
                    annexed figure (2) as one which is generally sufficient for practical purposes
                    It will be seen that the jet <hi rend="italic">i</hi> is supported on a slide
                    which can be fixed by screwing in any direction and at any height on the rod <hi
                    rend="italic">s,</hi> which is jointed on the board <hi rend="italic">b.</hi>
                    The blast can thus be adjusted variously, according to the position given to the
                    blowpipe lamp <hi rend="italic">a,</hi> which is of the form devised by
                    Berzelius. The bellows B, the tube <hi rend="italic">k,</hi> and the reservoir
                    R, are of vulcanized india-rubber, <hi rend="italic">v</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">v</hi> are valves. The bellows being alternately compressed (with
                    hand or foot) and allowed to expand, air is driven into the reservoir, and a
                    fresh supply admitted into the bellows through <hi rend="italic">v.</hi> After a
                    few trials a constant blast may thus be maintained through the nozzle.</p>
                <p>For glass-blowing ordinary coal gas is the best combustible, as the flame can be
                    well controlled by a stopcock, and requires no trimming. The nature of the
                    apparatus will be understood from fig. 3, which shows the burner in horizontal
                    section. The tube <hi rend="italic">ab</hi> is screwed into another tube which
                    is connected with the gas pipe <hi rend="italic">ef mn</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">op</hi> are two annular disks which support the pipe <hi
                    rend="italic">ab;</hi> they have a series of openings round their edges, to
                    admit a uniform flow of gas to the narrow annular mouth between the two tubes
                    where it joins the blast. The stopcock <hi rend="italic">f</hi> regulates the
                    supply of gas. The wind, supplied by double bellows fixed under the table, is
                    sent through a lead pipe on which brass nozzles of various width can be screwed,
                    opening into <hi rend="italic">ab;</hi> the finer nozzles being pushed up nearly
                    to the end of this. Elastic tubing may sometimes be used with advantage for the
                    connections. A modified form of the apparatus is suitable for ordinary blowpipe
                    researches of the mineralogist or chemist (see Plattner’s work, 4th edition),
                    and the apparatus used in hand-soldering of metals and other operations of the
                    workshop is on the same principle. With suit- <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi>
                    able trunnions the blowpipe may be made to point in any direction as
                    required.</p>
                <p>The soldering lamp of tinners is an example of the aeolipile, an instrument which
                    deserves some notice here. The spirit lamp <hi rend="italic">a</hi> (fig. 4) is
                    inserted at the bottom of a sheet-iron cylinder M N, which is open on one side,
                    as shown. The upper part of the cylinder supports a strong cup of hammered
                    metal, with an opening for spirits at the top (closed by a screw or cock), and a
                    bent tube coming down from its upper part, through a slit in the cylinder to the
                    back of the flame. The weak spirits which are put in the cup are caused to boil
                    by the heat of the lamp, and the vapour, escaping through the bent tube,
                    produces a jet of very hot flame. (The cup is shown separately in fig. 5).
                    Similar advantage is gained by causing air to pass through a quantity of some
                    soluble hydrocarbon before it goes to the nozzle of a blowpipe.</p>
                <p>There are several forms of apparatus in which waterpressure is utilized for
                    supplying a steady blast to the blowpipe. One of these consists of a tin case,
                    with an oblique partition reaching nearly to the bottom. The case is filled
                    nearly three-fourths with water. Air is blown into the compartment which narrows
                    upwards (and with which the nozzle is connected above) by a pipe reaching nearly
                    to the bottom. This air rises through the water and accumulates above it,
                    forcing the water up into the other compartment, which communicates freely with
                    the outer air. The difference of water-level in the two chain-bers<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n857/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0857-0840"/> thus sustains a continuous blast through the
                    nozzle. Blowpipes have also been made on the principle of the blowing-machine
                    known as the <hi rend="italic">trompe.</hi> Again, the blast is sometimes
                    supplied from a chamber in which air is condensed by means of a syringe.</p>
                <p>The absorption of heat when an ordinary blast of cold air (with its large
                    proportion of nitrogen) is sent into a flame is considerable; and this has
                    suggested the employment of a hot blast for blowpipe work. Mr T. Fletcher has
                    constructed an apparatus on this principle, which yields a very intense flame,
                    sufficient to fuse platinum wire. The arrangement is represented in fig. 6. It
                    will be observed that the pipe conveying the blast is coiled several times round
                    the gas pipe (for ordinary coal-gas), and that both, coil and core are heated by
                    a row of burners placed below. The blast is furnished either with the mouth or
                    with india-rubber bellows.</p>
                <p>The power of the blowpipe flame may be greatly increased by supplying oxygen in
                    the place of atmospheric air; and a still greater heat is obtained by the
                    combination of pure oxygen and hydrogen. In the latter arrangement, which
                    constitutes the oxyhydrogen blowpipe, it is important that the oxygen and
                    hydrogen be kept in separate reservoirs, and be only allowed to mix at the jet,
                    otherwise explosion may occur through the flame running back through the jet to
                    the reservoir of mixed gases. There are various methods of effecting this, which
                    we do not stop to describe. The blue flame produced gives the most intense heat
                    that is obtainable by artificial means, except by the electric current. Thick
                    platinum wires are melted before it like wax in a candle flame; and earths, such
                    as lime, magnesia, or zirconia, are raised to intense incandescence. For the
                    application of the oxyhydrogen blowpipe to the fusion of the more refractory
                    metals, see <hi rend="smallcaps">Platinum.</hi></p>
                <p>The literature of the blowpipe is very extensive. The earlier notices of the
                    subject will be found in Berzelius’s original work, of which there are English
                    translations by Children, published in 1822, and by J. D. Whitney (of a later
                    edition), published in Boston in 1845. The most complete work, however, is
                    Plattner’s <hi rend="italic">Probirkunst</hi><hi rend="italic">mit</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">dem L'othrohre,</hi> of which there are several editions; the
                    fourth or latest, published since the author’s death, has been edited by his
                    pupil and successor, Professor Richter of Freiberg. An English translation, by
                    Professor H. B. Cornwall, has been published in New York. For the use of the
                    blowpipe in determining minerals, the best works are Scheerer’s <hi
                    rend="italic">L'oth-rohrbuch,</hi> translated by Professor H. B. Blanford, and a
                    <hi rend="italic">Manual of Determinative Mineralogy, with an Introduction to
                    Blowpipe Analysis,</hi> by Professor G. J. Brush of Yale College. In addition to
                    these works, notices, more or less extensive, will be found in most
                    mineralogical handbooks and works on chemical analysis. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a.
                    b. μ.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
