<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0190-0175-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BAAL</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 3, page 175</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:819237">Assyrians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1061214">Phoenicians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1141359">Syrians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:848005">Carthaginians</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1181450">Worship</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1093898">Religions</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1093763">Religion</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1093581">Relationism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1091272">Reason</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bg0t">Worship</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5cj23">Sun</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g8x">Religion</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bn4t">Religions</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r50f">Phoenicians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4np1wt1r">Syrians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n190/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BAAL</label> is a Semitic word, which primarily signifies <hi
                    rend="italic">lord</hi> or <hi rend="italic">owner,</hi> and then, in accordance
                    with the Semitic way of looking at family and religious relations, is specially
                    appropriated to express the relation of a <hi rend="italic">husband</hi> to his
                    wife, and of the <hi rend="italic">deity</hi> to his worshipper. In the latter
                    usage, which does not occur among the Arabian Semites, the word Baal seems at
                    first to have been a mere title of deity and not a proper name. In the Old
                    Testament it is regularly written with the article—“the Baal;” and the Baals of
                    different tribes or sanctuaries were not necessarily conceived as identical, so
                    that we find frequent mention of Baalim, or rather “the Baalim,” in the plural.
                    There is even reason to believe that at an early date the Israelites applied the
                    title of Baal to Jehovah himself, for one of Saul’s sons is named Esh-baal (1
                    Chron. viii. 33), while everything we know of Saul makes it most unlikely that
                    he was ever an idolater. Afterwards, when the name Baal was exclusively
                    appropriated to idolatrous worship (c∕. Hos. ii. 16, 17), abhorrence for the
                    unholy word was marked by writing <hi rend="italic">Bosheth</hi> (shameful
                    thing) for Baal in compound proper names, and thus we get the usual forms
                    Ishbosheth, Mephibosheth. <hi rend="italic">(Cf.</hi> Ewald, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Geschichte,</hi> ii. 537, and Wellhausen, <hi rend="italic">Text</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">der Bücher</hi><hi rend="italic">Samuelis,</hi> pp. xii. 30, where
                    more arguments are adduced for this view.)</p>
                <p>The great difficulty which has been felt by investigators in determining the
                    character and attributes of the god Baal mainly arises from the originally
                    appellative sense of the word, and many obscure points become clear if we
                    remember that when the title became a proper name it might be appropriated by
                    different nations to quite distinct deities, while traces of the wider use of
                    the word as a title for any god, might very well survive even after one god had
                    come to be known as Baal <hi rend="italic">par excellence.</hi> That Baal is not
                    always one and the same god was known even to the ancient mythologists, who were
                    very much disposed to fuse together distinct deities; for they distinguish an
                    “old” Baal or Belitan (Bel êthan) from a younger Baal, who is sometimes viewed
                    as the son of the other. The “old” Baal has sometimes been identified with the
                    planet Saturn, but it is more likely that he is the Baal (in Assyrian
                    pronunciation Bil) of the first triad of the Babylonian Pantheon, that is the
                    Bel, as distinct from the Baal, of the Old Testament. This Assyrian and
                    Babylonian Bel is no mere solar or planetary god, but is represented in Chaldean
                    cosmogony as the shaper of heaven and earth, the creator of men and beasts, and
                    of the luminaries of heaven <hi rend="italic">[Berosus,</hi> ed. Richter, p.
                    50). At the same time, we find that the inscriptions give the title of Bel to
                    other and inferior gods, especially to Merodach or the planet Jupiter. This
                    planet was, we know, the Baal (Bâl, Bil) of the heathen Mesopotamians (Sabians)
                    of later times, and of the Babylonian Mendeans.</p>
                <p>The Baal of the Syrians, Phoenicians, and heathen Hebrews is a much less elevated
                    conception than the Babylonian BeL He is properly the sun-god, Baal Shamem, Baal
                    (lord) of the heavens, the highest of the heavenly bodies, but still a mere
                    power of nature, born like the other luminaries from the primitive chaos <hi
                    rend="italic">(San-chσniathon,</hi> ed. Orelli, pp. 10, 14). As the sun-god he
                    is conceived as the male principle of life and reproduction in nature, and thus
                    in some forms of his worship is the patron of the grossest sensuality, and even
                    of systematic prostitution. An example of this is found in the worship of
                    Baal-Peor (Num. xxv.), and in general in the Canaanitish high places, where
                    Baal, the male principle, was worshipped in association with the unchaste
                    goddess Ashera, the female principle of nature. The frequent references to this
                    form of religion in the Old Testament are obscured in the English version by the
                    rendering “grove” for the word Ashera, which sometimes denotes the goddess,
                    sometimes the tree or post which was her symbol. Baal himself was represented on
                    the high places not by an image, but by obelisks or pillars <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Maççeboth,</hi> E. V. wrongly “<hi rend="italic">images</hi> sometimes called
                    <hi rend="italic">chammanim</hi> or sun-pillars, a name which is to be compared
                    with the title Baal-chamman, frequently given to the god on Phoenician
                    inscriptions. There is reason to believe that these symbols, in their earliest
                    form of the sacred tree and the sacred stone, were not specially appropriated to
                    Baal worship, but were the mark of any sanctuary, memorials of a place where the
                    worshipper had found God (see, for example, Gen. xxi. 33, where for <hi
                    rend="italic">grove</hi> read <hi rend="italic">tamarisk,</hi> Gen. xxviii. 18),
                    while the stone pillar was also a primitive altar. Gradually, however, they came
                    to be looked upon as phallic symbols, appropriate only to sensual nature
                    worship, and as such were attacked by the prophets (Micah v. 13, 14; Isa. xvii.
                    8, xxvii. 9, &lt;fcc.), and destroyed by such orthodox kings as Josiah. The
                    worship of Baal among the Hebrews has two distinct periods—one before the time
                    of Samuel, and a second from the introduction of the Tyrian worship of Baal by
                    Ahab, who married a Phoenician princess. The ritual of this new Baal, with his
                    long train of priests and prophets, his temple and sacred vestments (2 Kings
                    x.), was plainly much more splendid than the older Canaanitish worship. Of the
                    worship of the Tyrian Baal, who is also called Melkart (king of the city), and
                    is often identified with the Greek Heracles, but sometimes with the Olympian
                    Zeus, we have many accounts in ancient writers, from Herodotus downwards. He had
                    a magnificent temple in insular Tyre, founded by Hiram, to which gifts streamed
                    from all countries, especially at the great feasts. The solar character of this
                    deity appears especially in the annual feast of his awakening shortly after <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n191/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0191-0176"/> the winter solstice (Joseph., <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ant.,</hi> viii. 5). At Tyre, as among the Hebrews, Baal had his symbolical
                    pillars, one of gold and one of smaragdus, which, transported by phantasy to the
                    Farthest West, are still familiar to us as the pillars of Hercules. The worship
                    of the Tyrian Baal was carried to all the Phoenician colonies. His name occurs
                    as an element in Carthaginian proper names (Hanni6αZ, Asdruδα∕, &amp;c.), and a
                    tablet found at Marseilles still remains to inform us of the charges made by the
                    priests of the temple of Baal for offering sacrifices.</p>
                <p>A much-disputed question is the relation of the sun-god Baal to Moloch-Saturn.
                    Moloch is certainly called Baal in Jer. xix. 5, xxxii 35, but the word may here
                    retain its appellative force. It is, however, the theory of many scholars,
                    especially worked out by Movers, that Moloch is only a special development of
                    Baal, representing the destructive heat instead of the life-giving power of the
                    sun. Another question of some nicety concerns the precise character and mutual
                    relations of the female deities associated with Baal. In the Old Testament, as
                    we have seen, Baal is generally associated with Ashera, but sometimes with
                    Ashtoreth or Astarte (in the plural Ashtaroth, associated with the plural
                    Baalim, I Sam. vii. 4, &amp;c.) As Ashtoreth is constantly associated with the
                    Phoenician Baal, it was long customary to identify Ashera with her, a theory
                    opposed to the fact that Ashtoreth is represented as a chaste goddess. The key
                    to the difficulty is probably to be sought in the Assyrian mythology, where we
                    find that the planet Venus was worshipped as the chaste goddess Istar, when she
                    appeared as a morning star, and as the impure Bilit or Beltis, the Mylitta of
                    Herod, (i. 199), when she was an evening star. These two goddesses, associated
                    yet contrasted, seem to correspond respectively to the chaste Ashtoreth and the
                    foul Ashera, though the distinction between the rising and setting planet was
                    not kept up among the Western Semites, and the nobler deity came at length to be
                    viewed as the goddess of the moon.</p>
                <p>Finally, we may mention as a special form of Baal the Philistine Baal-zebub, or
                    “Baal of flies,” a conception which has more than one analogy in Greek religion,
                    especially the Zeυs ’ Από/mos at Olympia. The use of the word Beelzebub, or
                    rather, with a slight change, Beelzebul, by the later Jews, to denote the prince
                    of the devils (Mat. xii. 24), is easily understood on the principle laid down in
                    1 Cor. X. 20.</p>
                <p>For further information as to Baal, the reader may consult works on Syrian and
                    Phoenician religion. Of older books, the most celebrated is Selden’s <hi
                    rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">diis Syris</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi>
                    of recent books, Movers’s <hi rend="italic">Die</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Phönizier,</hi> i., a work full of learning, but deficient in method and logic.
                    The valuable contributions to the subject from Assyrian research are partly
                    brought together by Schrader in the <hi rend="italic">Stud,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">und</hi><hi rend="italic">Krit.</hi> for 1874, pp. 335, <hi
                    rend="italic">sqq.</hi> (w. <hi rend="smallcaps">r. s.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
