<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0419-0404-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BARUCH</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 3, page 404</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4np1wt1r">Syrians</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62f7n">Reading</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1090626">Reading</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1141359">Syrians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n419/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BARUCH</label>, son of Neriah, was the friend and amanuensis
                    of the prophet Jeremiah. After the temple at Jerusalem had been plundered by
                    Nebuchadnezzar, he wrote down Jeremiah’s prophecies respecting the return of the
                    Babylonians to destroy the state, and read them in the temple before the
                    assembled people at the risk of his life. The roll having been burned by the
                    king’s command, Jeremiah dictated the same again. When the temple was destroyed,
                    Baruch went to Egypt with Jeremiah, having been blamed as the prompter of the
                    threatening prophecies uttered by the latter. Nothing certain is known as to his
                    death,—some accounts representing him as dying in Egypt, others in Babylonia.
                    The Talmud adopts the latter opinion, making him the instructor of Ezra, to whom
                    he is said to have communicated the traditions he had received from
                    Jeremiah.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">Book of Baruch</hi> belongs to the Apocrypha, according
                    to Protestants, and to the deutero-canonical productions, according to Roman
                    Catholics.</p>
                <p>There is hardly sufficient cause for dividing the book, as some critics suggest,
                    between two writers. The author of iii. 9-v. 9 uses Isaiah as well as Jeremiah
                    in two places. A new paragraph undoubtedly begins at iii. 9, which has little
                    connection with the preceding context, and differs from it perceptibly both in
                    matter and form; yet it has the same general object. From reproof the language
                    passes to hope and Messianic happiness, and it becomes livelier and more
                    elevated. It is purer Greek without doubt. The supposed traces of Alexandrian
                    culture are somewhat indistinct. Wisdom is not spoken of in the Alexandrian
                    manner (iii. 24), but rather in the same way as in Sirach, which is
                    Palestinian.</p>
                <p>Much difference of opinion prevails regarding the original language. Some are for
                    a Greek original, others for a Hebrew one; while Fritzsche and Ruetschi think
                    that the first part was composed in Hebrevz, the second in Greek. The original
                    seems to have been Hebrew, though Jerome says that the Jews had not the book in
                    that language; and Epiphanius asserts the same thing. The testimony of the
                    former resolves itself into the fact that the original had been supplanted by
                    the Greek; and that of the latter is not of much value, since he gives Baruch,
                    along with Jeremiah and the Lamentations, in a second list of the canonical
                    books.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic"
                    >Hacres.,</hi> viii. 6; compare <hi rend="italic">De Mens.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >et</hi><hi rend="italic">Pond.,</hi> c. 23; <hi rend="italic">ibid.,</hi> c.
                    5.</p></note> We rely on the statement that the work was meant to be publicly
                    read in the temple (i. 14) as favourable to a Hebrew original, as well as on the
                    number and nature of the Hebraisms, which are sometimes so peculiar that they
                    cannot be resolved into the authorship of a Greek-speaking Jew. That the writer
                    was a Palestinian appears from various passages, such as ii. 17, “For the dead
                    that are in the graves, whose souls are taken from their bodies, will give unto
                    the Lord neither praise nor righteousness;” “Hearken, O ye that dwell about
                    Zion” (iv. 9); “Ye have forgotten the everlasting God that brought you up; and
                    ye have grieved Jerusalem that nursed you” (iv. 8). Both the latter passages
                    betray a Palestinian. Besides, the conception of Wisdom in iii. 12, &lt;fcc., is
                    Palestinian rather than Alexandrian; for the words in iii. 37 do not refer to
                    the incarnation of the Logos, but to personified Wisdom, as in Sirach xxiv. 10.
                    This points to a Hebrew original. The version seems to be free, especially in
                    the latter part.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n420/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0420-0405"/>
                <p>Who was the translator Î A comparison of the Septuagint translation of Jeremiah
                    with that of Baruch will suggest the answer. The agreement between the two is
                    remarkable. Constructions, phrases, and words are the same in them, so that we
                    may conjecture with Ewald and Hitzig that the same translator appears. The words
                    βαδtξω, <hi rend="italic">αποστολή, χαρμόσυνη, γαυρίαμα, δεσμώτης, άποικισμός,
                    δνομα μου επικαλεΐσθαι επί</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> tivl</hi> are common
                    to both. The LXX. version of Jeremiah was not made till the 1st century <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> or later; and Theodotion’s translation or recension
                    of it in the second. It is some confirmation of the opinion that Greek was not
                    the original when marginal notes are found in the Hexaplar-Syriac version
                    printed by Ceriani, in which the Hebrew is repeatedly referred to. Nothing seems
                    to disprove the assumption that Theodotion, from whose version that of Paul of
                    Tela was taken, had the Hebrew original before him.</p>
                <p>Though Baruch professes to have written the book, a later writer speaks in his
                    name. Jeremiah’s faithful friend is said to have composed it at Babylon. This
                    view is untenable on the following grounds :—</p>
                <p>1. The work contains historical inaccuracies. Jeremiah was living in the fifth
                    year after the destruction of Jerusalem, yet the epistle is dated that year at
                    Babylon. It is unlikely that Baruch left Jeremiah, since the two friends were so
                    united. According to Baruch i. 3, Jeconiah was present in the great assembly
                    before which the epistle was read, whereas we learn from 2 Kings xxv. 27 that he
                    was kept a prisoner as long as Nebuchadnezzar lived. Joakim is supposed to be
                    high priest at Jerusalem (i. 7). But we learn from 1 Chron. vi. 15 that
                    Jehozadak filled that office the fifth year after Jerusalem was destroyed. In i.
                    2 there is an error. The city was not burned when Jehoiachim was carried away.
                    And if the allusion be to the destruction of the city by Nebuchadnezzar, the
                    temple and its worship are supposed still to exist in i. 8-10. The particulars
                    narrated are put into the fifth year of the exile; yet we read, “Thou art waxen
                    old in a strange country” (iii. 10).</p>
                <p>2. Supposing Baruch himself to have been the writer, books later than his time
                    are used in the work. Nehemiah is followed, as in ii. 11 (comp. Nehem. ix. 10).
                    But Eichhorn’s language is too strong in calling the contents “a rhapsody
                    composed of various writings belonging to Hebrew antiquity, especially Daniel
                    and Nehemiah.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi
                    rend="italic">Einleitung</hi><hi rend="italic">in die</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >apokryphisch.cn</hi><hi rend="italic">Schriften</hi><hi rend="italic">des A.
                    T.,</hi> p. 382.</p></note></p>
                <p>The date of the work is given indefinitely in i. 2, <hi rend="italic">“In</hi>
                    the fifth year, and in the seventh day of the month, what time as the Chaldeans
                    took Jerusalem, and burnt it with fire.” The natural meaning of these words is,
                    “The fifth year after the destruction of Jerusalem by Nebuchadnezzar,” not “the
                    fifth year of Jehoiachim’s captivity.” The day is given, not the month; and
                    therefore De Wette conjectures that <hi rend="italic">ετει</hi> should be <hi
                    rend="italic">μηνί;</hi> but MS. authority is against him. It is probable that
                    the name of the month has dropped out, <hi rend="italic">i.e., Sivan.</hi> The
                    Palestinian abode of the writer is pretty clear, especially from the melancholy
                    view of death presented in ii. 17, iii. 19, resembling that in Psalms vi. 6,
                    lxxviii. 18, ciii. 29. In Alexandria the Jews had attained to a clear idea of
                    immortality, in Palestine not. The translation was made in Egypt, which accounts
                    for various expressions savouring of Alexandrianism, as in iii., 23, 24, 26.
                    There are evident points of contact between Daniel and Baruch, as appears from
                    Baruch i. 15-18, which agrees almost verbally with Daniel ix. 7-10. So ii 1, 2
                    coincide with Daniel ix. 12, 13; and ii. 7-17 with Daniel ix. 13-18. Hitzig
                    thinks the two authors were identical, but this can hardly be allowed; for the
                    tone and atmosphere of Baruch bear no perceptible trace of the</p>
                <p>Syrian persecutions or Maccabean struggle. Daniel borrowed from Baruch pretty
                    closely in some passages. We suppose that the translator was separated from the
                    author by a considerable period, probably 200 years. Perhaps the author lived
                    about 300-290 B.c.</p>
                <p>According to Jerome and Epiphanius, the Jews did not receive the book into their
                    canon; nor is it in the lists given by Josephus, Melito, and others. It has been
                    thought, however, that Origen considered it canonical, because in his catalogue
                    of sacred books he gives Lamentations and “the epistle” along with Jeremiah; and
                    Jeremiah’s epistle formed a part of Baruch. The testimony of Origen on this
                    point is perplexing; but it is conceivable that <hi rend="italic">some</hi> Jews
                    may have thought very highly of the book in his time, though its authority was
                    not generally admitted among their co-religionists.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See Welte’s note on this point in Herbst’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Einleitung, erster</hi><hi rend="italic">Theil</hi> pp. 14.
                    15.</p></note> From the position which the book occupied in the Septuagint, <hi
                    rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> either before or after Lamentations, it was often
                    considered an appendix to Jeremiah by the early Christians, and was regarded in
                    the same light, and of equal authority. Hence the words of it were often quoted
                    as Jeremiah’s by Irenaeus, Clemens Alexandrinus, and Tertullian. Cyril of
                    Jerusalem reckons it with the canonical books, among the <hi rend="italic"
                    >al</hi><hi rend="italic">θεόπνευστοι,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">θειaι
                    γρaφaι;</hi> and the epithets so applied cannot be explained away by
                    Protestants.</p>
                <p>The versions are the two Latin, a Syriac, and an Arabic. The Latin one in the
                    Vulgate belongs to a time prior to Jerome, and is tolerably literal. Another,
                    somewhat later, was first published by Jos. Maria Caro in 1688, and was
                    reprinted by Sabatier, side by side with the ante-Hieronymian one, in his <hi
                    rend="italic">Bibliorum</hi><hi rend="italic">Sacrorum Latinae</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Versiones Antiques.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>See vol. ii. p. 734, &amp;c.</p></note></hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 3</hi> It is founded upon the preceding one, and is less literal.
                    The Syriac and Arabic versions, printed in the London Polyglott, are literal.
                    The Hexaplar-Syriac version, made by Paul, bishop of Tela, in the beginning of
                    the 7th century, has been published by Ceriani.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Monumenta</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Sacra</hi><hi rend="italic">et Profana,</hi> tom. i. fascic.
                    1.</p></note> The most convenient editions of the Greek text are Tischendorf’s,
                    in the second volume of his Septuagint, and Fritzsche’s in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Libri Apocryphi Veteris Testamenti</hi><hi rend="italic">Greece,</hi> 1871.
                    (See Davidson’s <hi rend="italic">Introduction to the Old Testament,</hi> vol.
                    iii.; <hi rend="italic">Kurzgefasstes Exegetisches Handbuch zu den Apokryphen
                    des alten Testaments, erste Lieferung;</hi> Ewald’s <hi rend="italic">Geschichte
                    des Volkes Israel,</hi> vol. iv.; De Wette’s <hi rend="italic">Einleitung,</hi>
                    §§ 321-323; Weite’s <hi rend="italic">Einleitung in die heiligen Schriften
                    des</hi><hi rend="italic">A.</hi><hi rend="italic">T., zweyter Theil, dritte
                    Abtheilung.)</hi><hi rend="italic">Epistle of</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Jeremy.—</hi> An epistle of Jeremiah’s is often appended to Baruch, forming the
                    sixth chapter. According to the inscription, it was sent by the prophet by God’s
                    command to the Jews who were to be carried captive to Babylon. The writer
                    describes the folly and absurdity of idolatry in a declamatory style, with
                    repetitions somewhat like refrains. Thus, in verses 16, 23, 29, 65 occurs the
                    sentence, “Whereby they are known not to be gods; therefore fear them not;” “How
                    should a man then think and say that they are gods,” in 40, 44, 56, 64, 69; “How
                    then cannot men perceive that they be no gods,” in 49, 52. These and other
                    repetitions are unlike Jeremiah’s. The concluding verse is abrupt.</p>
                <p>All the relation this epistle has to Jeremiah is, that the contents and form are
                    derived from Jeremiah x. 1-16 and xxix. 4-23. Its combination with Baruch is
                    purely accidental. It could not have been written by Jeremiah, though many
                    Catholic theologians maintain that it was. The Hellenist betrays himself in a
                    few instances, as when he speaks of kings, verses 51, 53, 56, 59. Though Welte
                    tries to prove that the epistle was written in Hebrew, which is <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n421/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0421-0406"/> consistent with Jeremiah’s authorship, his
                    arguments are invalid. The original is pure Hellenistic Greek. The warning
                    ».gainst. idolatry bespeaks a foreigner living out of Palestine. The place of
                    its origin was probably Egypt; and the writer may have lived in the Maccabean
                    period, as we infer from his making the exile last for seven generations, <hi
                    rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> about 210 years. Jeremiah, on the contrary, gives the
                    time as 70 years in round numbers. The oldest allusion to the epistle is
                    commonly found in 2 Maccab. ii. 2, where a few words are similar to the fourth
                    verse of our epistle. But the appropriateness of the supposed reference is
                    doubtful.</p>
                <p>The old Latin version of the epistle, published by Sabatier, which is in the
                    Vulgate, is literal. The Syriac is freer. The Arabic is more literal than the
                    Latin. Both are in the London Polyglott. The Hexaplar-Syriac was published by
                    Ceriani. (s. υ.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
