<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0648-0631-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BHUTAN</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 3, page 631</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="19" ref="fastgeo:1207216">Bhutan</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206073">China</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="12" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:902429">Eden</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1140558">Swiss</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:840320">Buddhists</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:827603">Barley</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1028366">Mountains</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3m81r">Swiss</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bn9x31n">Tombs</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4n29p69w">Barley</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n648/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BHUTAN</label>, an independent kingdom in the Eastern
                    Timâlayas, between 26° and 28° N. lat., and 89° and 93° E. long. It is bounded
                    on the N. by Thibet; on the E. by a tract inhabited by various uncivilized
                    independent mountain tribes; on the S. by the British province of Assam, and the
                    district of Jalpâiguri; and on the W. by the independent native state of Sikim.
                    The whole of Bhutân presents a succession of lofty and rugged mountains
                    abounding in picturesque and sublime scenery. “The prospect,” says Captain
                    Turner, “between abrupt and lofty prominences is inconceivably grand; hills
                    clothed to their very summits with trees, dark and deep glens, and the high tops
                    of mountains lost in the clouds, constitute altogether a scene of extraordinary
                    magnificence and sublimity.” As might be expected from its physical structure,
                    this alpine region sends out numerous rivers in a southerly direction, which,
                    forcing their passage through narrow defiles, and precipitated in cataracts over
                    the precipices, eventually pour themselves into the Brahmaputra. One torrent is
                    mentioned by Turner as falling over so great a height that it is nearly
                    dissipated in mid-air, and looks from below like a jet of steam from boiling
                    water. Of the rivers traversing Bhutân, the most considerable is the Manâs,
                    flowing in its progress to the Brahmaputra under the walls of Tâsgâon, below
                    which it is unfordable. At the foot of Tâsgâon Hill it is crossed by a
                    suspension bridge. The other principal rivers are the Mâchu, Tchin-chu, Torshâ,
                    Mânchi, and Dharlâ.</p>
                <p>Previous to the British annexation of the Dwârs from Bhutân, the area of the
                    kingdom was reckoned at 20,000 sq. miles. The population of the country now
                    remaining to Bhutân was estimated in 1864 at 20,000 souls. Later information,
                    however, points to a larger figure. The people are industrious, and devote
                    themselves to agriculture, but from the geological structure of the country, and
                    from the insecurity of property, regular husbandry is limited to comparatively
                    few spots. The people are oppressed and poor. “Nothing that a Bhutiâ possesses
                    is his own,” wrote the British envoy in 1864; “he is at all times liable to lose
                    it if it attracts the cupidity of any one more powerful than himself. The lower
                    classes, whether villagers or public servants, are little better than the slaves
                    of higher officials. In regard to them no rights of property are observed, and
                    they have at once to surrender anything that is demanded of them. There never
                    was, I fancy, a country in which the doctrine of ‘ might is right* formed more
                    completely the whole and sole law and custom of the land than it does in Bhutân.
                    No official receives a salary; he has certain districts made over to him, and he
                    may get what he can out of them; a certain portion of his gains he is compelled
                    to send to the Darbâr; and the more he extorts and the more he sends to his
                    superior, the longer his tenure of office is likely to be.” Captain Pemberton
                    thus describes their moral condition— “I sometimes saw a few persons in whom the
                    demoralizing influences of such a state of society had yet left a trace of the
                    image in which they were originally created, and where the feelings of nature
                    still exercised their accustomed influence, but the exceptions were rare, and
                    although I have travelled and resided amongst various savage tribes on our
                    frontiers, I have never yet known a people so wholly degraded as the Bhutiâs.”
                    Physically the Bhutiâs are a fine race, although dirty in their habits and
                    persons. Their food consists of meat, chiefly pork, turnips, rice, barley-meal,
                    and tea made from the brick-tea of China. Their favourite drink is <hi
                    rend="italic">chong,</hi> distilled from rice or barley and millet, and <hi
                    rend="italic">Ματωά,</hi> beer made from fermented millet. A loose woollen coat
                    reaching to the knees, and bound round the waist by a thick fold of cotton
                    cloth, forms the dress of the men; the women’s dress is a long cloak with loose
                    sleeves. The houses of the Bhutiâs are of three and four stories; all the floors
                    are neatly boarded with deal; and on two sides of the house is a verandah
                    ornamented with carved work generally painted. The Bhutiâs are neat joiners, and
                    their doors, windows, and panelling are perfect in their way. No iron-work is
                    used; the doors open on ingenious wooden hinges. The appearance of the houses is
                    precisely that of Swiss chalets, picturesque and comfortable—the only drawback
                    being a want of chimneys, which the Bhutiâs do not know how to construct. The
                    people nominally profess the Buddhist religion, but in reality their religious
                    exercises are confined to the propitiation of evil spirits, and the mechanical
                    recital of a few sacred sentences. Around the cottages in the mountains the land
                    is cleared for cultivation, and produces thriving crops of barley, wheat,
                    buckwheat, millet, mustard, chillies, &amp;c. Turnips of excellent quality are
                    extensively grown; they are free from fibre and remarkably sweet. The wheat and
                    barley have a full round grain, and the climate is well adapted to the
                    production of both European and Asiatic vegetables. Potatoes have been
                    introduced. The Bhutiâs lay out their fields in a series of terraces cut out of
                    the sides of the hills; each terrace is rivetted and supported by stone
                    embankments, sometimes twenty feet high. Every field is carefully fenced with
                    pine branches, or protected by a stone wall. A complete system of irrigation
                    permeates the whole cultivated part of a village, the water being often brought
                    from a long distance by stone aqueducts. Bhutiâs do not care to extend their
                    cultivation, as an increased revenue is exacted in proportion to the land
                    cultivated, but devote their whole energies to make the land yield twice what it
                    is estimated to produce. The forests of Bhutân abound in many varieties of
                    stately trees. Among them are the beech, ash, birch, maple, cypress, and yew.
                    Firs and pines cover the mountain heights; and below these, but still at an
                    elevation of eight or nine thousand feet, is a zone of vegetation, consisting
                    principally of oaks and rhododendrons. The cinnamon tree is also found. Some <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n649/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0649-0632"/> of the roots and branches were examined by Turner
                    during his journey to Thibet; but the plant being neither in blossom nor bearing
                    fruit, it was impossible to decide whether it was the true cinnamon or an
                    inferior kind of cassia. The leaf, however, corresponded with the description
                    given of the true cinnamon by Linnaeus. The lower ranges of the hills abound in
                    animal life. Elephants are so numerous as to be dangerous to travellers; but
                    tigers are not common, except near the River Tistâ. Leopards abound in the Hah
                    valley; deer everywhere, some of them of a very large species. The musk deer is
                    found in the snows, and the barking deer on every hill side. Wild hogs are met
                    with even at great elevations. Large squirrels are common. Bears and rhinoceros
                    are also found. Pheasants, jungle fowls, pigeons, and other small game abound.
                    The Bhutiâs are no sportsmen. They have a superstitious objection to firing a
                    gun, thinking that it offends the deities of the woods and valleys, and brings
                    down rain. A species of horse, which seems indigenous to Bhutan, and is used as
                    a domestic animal, is called <hi rend="italic">tangan,</hi> from Tângastan, the
                    general appellation of that assemblage of mountains which constitutes the
                    territory of Bhutan. It is peculiar to this tract, not being found in any of the
                    neighbouring countries of Assam, Nepâl, Thibet, or Bengal, and unitee in an
                    eminent degree the two qualities of strength and beauty. The <hi rend="italic"
                    >tdngan</hi> horse usually stands about thirteen hands high, is short bodied,
                    clean-limbed, deep in the chest, and extremely active, his colour usually
                    inclining to piebald. In so barren and rude a country the manufacturing industry
                    of its people is, as might be expected, in a low stage, the few articles
                    produced being all destined for home consumption. These consist of coarse
                    blankets and cotton cloths made by the villagers inhabiting the southern tract.
                    Leather, from the hide of the buffalo, imperfectly tanned, furnishes the soles
                    of snow boots. Circular bowls are neatly turned from various woods. A small
                    quantity of paper is made from a plant described as the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Daphne</hi><hi rend="italic">papyrifera.</hi> Swords, iron spears, and
                    arrow-heads, and a few copper caldrons fabricated from the metal obtained in the
                    country, complete the list of manufactures. The foreign trade of Bhutan has
                    greatly declined. In 1809 the trade between Assam and Bhutan amounted to £20,000
                    per annum, the lac, madder, silk, <hi rend="italic">erendi</hi> cloth, and dried
                    fish of Assam, being exchanged for the woollens, gold-dust, salt, musk, horses,
                    and silk of Bhutan. At present very little trade is carried on by Bhutan with
                    the neighbouring countries. The military resources of the country are on an
                    insignificant scale. Beyond the guards for the defence of the various castles,
                    there is nothing like a standing army. The total military force was estimated by
                    the British envoy in 1864 at 6000. The climate of Bhutan varies according to the
                    difference of elevation. At the time when the inhabitants of Punâkhâ (the winter
                    residence of the Râjâs) are afraid of exposing themselves to the blazing sun,
                    those of Ghâsâ experience all the rigour of winter, and are chilled by perpetual
                    snows. Yet these places are within sight of each other. The rains descend in
                    floods upon the heights; but in the vicinity of Tâsi-sudon, the capital, they
                    are moderate; there are frequent showers, but nothing that can be compared to
                    the tropical rains of Bengal. Owing to the great elevation and steepness of the
                    mountains, dreadful storms arise among the hollows, often attended with fatal
                    results.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">History.—</hi> Bhutan formerly belonged to a tribe called by
                    the Bhutiâs Tephu, generally believed to have been the people of Kuch Behar.
                    About two hundred years ago some Thibetan soldiers subjugated the Tephus, took
                    possession of the country, and settled down in it. At the head of the Bhutan
                    government there are nominally two supreme authorities, the Dharm Râjâ, the
                    spiritual head, and the Deb Râjâ, the temporal ruler. To aid these Râjâs in
                    administering the country, there is a council of permanent ministers, called the
                    Lenehen. Practically, however, there is no government all. Subordinate officers
                    and rapacious governors of forts wield all the power of the state, and tyranny,
                    oppression, and anarchy reign over the whole country. The Dharm Râjâ succeeds as
                    an incarnation of the deity. On the death of a Dharm Râjâ a year or two elapses,
                    and the new incarnation then reappears in the shape of a child who generally
                    happens to be born in the family of a principal officer. The child establishes
                    his identity by recognizing the cooking utensils, &amp;c., of the late Dharm
                    Râjâ; he is then trained in a monastery, and on attaining his majority is
                    recognized as Râjâ, though he exercises no more real authority in his majority
                    than he did in his infancy. The Deb Râjâ is in theory elected by the council. In
                    practice he is merely the nominee of whichever of the two governors of East and
                    West Bhutan happens for the time to be the more powerful. The relations of the
                    British with Bhutan commenced in 1772, when the Bhutiâs invaded the principality
                    of Kuch Behar, a dependency of Bengal. The Kuch Behar Râjâ applied for aid, and
                    a force under Captain James was despatched to his assistance; the invaders were
                    expelled and pursued into their own territories. Upon the intercession of Teshu
                    Lama, then regent of Thibet, a treaty of peace was concluded in 1774 between the
                    East India Company and the ruler of Bhutan. In 1783 Captain Turner was deputed
                    to Bhutan, with a view of promoting commercial intercourse, but his mission
                    proved unsuccessful. From this period little intercourse took place with Bhutan,
                    until the occupation of Assam by the British in 1826. It was then discovered
                    that the Bhutiâs had usurped several tracts of low land lying at the foot of the
                    mountains, called the Dwârs or passes, and for these they agreed to pay a small
                    tribute. They failed to do so, however, and availed themselves of the command of
                    the passes to commit depredations within the British territory. Captain
                    Pemberton was accordingly deputed to Bhutan to adjust the points of difference.
                    But his negotiations yielded no definite result; and every other means of
                    obtaining redress and security proving unsuccessful, the Assam Dwârs were
                    wrested from the Bhutiâs, and the British Government consented to pay to Bhutan
                    a sum of £1000 per annum as compensation for the resumption of their tenure,
                    during the good behaviour of the Bhutiâs. Continued outrages and aggressions
                    were, however, committed by the Bhutiâs on British subjects in the Dwârs.
                    Notwithstanding repeated remonstrances and threats, scarcely a year passed
                    without the occurrence of several raids in British territory headed by Bhutiâ
                    officials, in which they plundered the inhabitants, massacred them, or carried
                    them away as slaves. In 1863 Mr Ashley Eden was sent as an envoy to Bhutan to
                    demand reparation for these outrages. He did not succeed in his mission; he was
                    subjected to the grossest insults; and under compulsion signed a treaty giving
                    over the disputed territory to Bhutan, and making other concessions which the
                    Bhutan Government demanded. On Mr Eden’s return the viceroy at once disavowed
                    his treaty, sternly stopped the former allowance for the Assam Dwârs, and
                    demanded the immediate restoration of all British subjects kidnapped during the
                    last five years. The Bhutiâs not complying with this demand, the
                    Governor-General issued a proclamation, dated the 12th November 1864, by which
                    the eleven Western or Bengal Dwârs were forthwith incorporated with the Queen’s
                    Indian dominions. No resistance was at first offered to the annexation; but,
                    suddenly, in January 1865, the Bhutiâs surprised the English garrison at
                    Diwângiri, and the post was abandoned with <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n650/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0650-0633"/> the loss of two mountain train guns. This
                    disaster was soon retrieved by General Tombs, and the Bhutiâs were compelled to
                    sue for peace, which was concluded on the 11th November 1865. The Bhutân
                    Government formally ceded all the eighteen Dwârs of Bengal and Assam, with the
                    rest of the territory taken from them, and agreed to liberate all kidnapped
                    British subjects. As the revenues of Bhutân mainly depended on these Dwârs, the
                    British Government, in return for these concessions, undertook to pay the Deb
                    and Dhârm Bâjâs annually, subject to the condition of their continued good
                    behaviour, an allowance beginning at £2500 and rising gradually to a maximum of
                    twice that amount. Since that time nothing of importance has occurred, and the
                    annexed territories have settled down into peaceful and prosperous British
                    districts.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
