<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0903-0749-0732-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BIRDS RECENTLY EXTIRPATED (9th edition, volume 3, page
                    732)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210572">Iceland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205795">Réunion</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1211575">Jamaica</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204558">Denmark</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205290">Greenland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:832970">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198488">Dodo</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1030128">Museums</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1012555">Mauritians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m9h">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b56d52v">Bones</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m03z08r">Doves</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ng4gv95">Fowling</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b853n1k">Fowls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4086371g">Huguenots</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n749/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BIRDS RECENTLY EXTIRPATED</label>.</p>
                <p>From the consideration of Fossil Birds we are naturally led to treat of those
                    which have been extirpated in modern times, and are made known to us by evidence
                    of various kinds, and more or less old. The most remarkable of these is the Dodo
                        <hi rend="italic">{Didus ineptus),</hi> which, on the discovery of Mauritius
                    by the Portuguese under Mascaregnas in the beginning of the 16 th century, was
                    found to inhabit that island. Voyagers have vied with each other in describing
                    or depicting its uncouth appearance, and its name has almost passed into a
                    byword expressive of all that is effete. Clumsy, flightless, and defenceless, it
                    soon succumbed, not so much to the human invaders of its realm as to the
                    domestic beasts which accompanied them, and there gaining their liberty,
                    unchecked by much of the wholesome discipline of nature, ran riot, to the utter
                    destruction (as will be seen) of no inconsiderable portion of the Mauritian
                    fauna. The latest known testimony of the Dodo’s existence is furnished by the
                    copy of a journal (now in the British Museum) kept by one Benjamin Harry, mate
                    of the ship “Berkley Castle,” which shews that it survived until July 1681. It
                    had its life most likely sometime longer, but of this there is no evidence
                    forthcoming. For a century and a half all that was known of it was derived from
                    the quaint and sometimes questionable accounts of early voyagers; certain
                    pictures, mostly by Dutch artists—for the bird was not unfrequently sent alive
                    to Europe, and the traffic of the East Indies w as then chiefly in the hands of
                    the Netherlanders—which pictures, however grotesque, were doubtless for the most
                    part faithful portraits; and a few scattered relics—a foot in the British
                    Museum, a head and foot at Oxford, a perfect skull at Copenhagen, and a
                    fragmentary one at Prague. Still these (or indeed the Danish specimen alone)
                    were enough to enable Professor Reinhardt to determine the affinity of the lost
                    bird to the Pigeons, an alliance not before surmised, but one which scarcely
                    anybody now disputes. In 1866, however, Mr George Clark of Mauritius discovered
                    in the peat of a pool (the Mare aux Songes) in that island an abundance of
                    Dodos’ bones <hi rend="italic">{Ibis,</hi> 1866, p. 141); and these, when
                    transmitted to Europe, informed naturalists as to nearly every part of its
                    osseous structure, which was soon after described in detail by Professor Owen
                        <hi rend="italic">{Trans. Zool. Soc..</hi> vi. p. 49).</p>
                <p>But the Dodo is not the only member of its family that has vanished. The little
                    island which has successively borne the name of Mascaregnas, England’s Forest,
                    Bourbon, and Réunion, and lies to the southward of Mauritius, had also an allied
                    Bird, now dead and gone. Of this not a relic has been handled by any naturalist.
                    The latest description of it, by Du Bois in 1674, is meagre in the extreme, and
                    though two figures—one by Bontekoe <hi rend="italic">{circa</hi> 1646), and
                    another by Pierre Witthoos <hi rend="italic">{ob.</hi> 1693) have been thought
                    to represent it <hi rend="italic">{Trans. Zool. Soc.</hi> vi. p. 373, plate 62),
                    their identification is but conjectural. Yet the existence of such a bird is
                    indubitable.</p>
                <p>Far to the eastward of these two sister islands lies a third—Rodriguez. Here
                    there formerly lived another Didine bird, sufficiently distinct from the Dodo of
                    Mauri tius to form a genus of its own— <hi rend="italic">Pezophaps</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">solitarius,</hi> the <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n750/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0903-0750-0733"/> Solitaire of Léguât, a Huguenot exile who,
                    passing some time in 1691-93 on that island, has left, with a very inferior
                    figure, a charmingly naive account of its appearance and habits, the general
                    truth of which has been amply substantiated by Mr Edward Newton’s discovery in
                    large numbers of its bones <hi rend="italic">{Phil. Trans.</hi> 1869, p. 327);
                    and a nearly complete skeleton of either sex may be seen in the museum of the
                    University of Cambridge, by the side of the most perfect specimen existing of
                    that of its bulkier relative, the Mauritian Dodo.</p>
                <p>Nor does this group of Didine birds contain all the lost forms of the Mascarene
                    islands. From Mauritius have disappeared at least two species of Parrot, a Dove,
                    a large Coot, and a second Ralline bird, abnormal, flightless, and long-billed—
                        <hi rend="italic">Aphanapteryx.</hi> A painting of this last was found by
                    Von Frauenfeld in the emperor’s library at Vienna, and some of its bones,
                    rescued by Mr Edward Newton from the peat of the Mare aux Songes, have been
                    fully described by Μ. A. Milne-Edwards. Remains of the Coot and one of the
                    extinct Parrots were found also in the same spot, while skins of the other
                    Parrot and of the Dove still exist in a few museums. Réunion, also, once had
                    other birds now lost, and so had Rodriguez. In the former, a somewhat abnormal
                    Starling <hi rend="italic">{Fregilupus)</hi> existed until some forty years ago
                        <hi rend="italic">{Proc. Zool. Soc.</hi> 1874, p. 474), and its skin and
                    skeleton are among the treasures of three or four museums. Perhaps, also, there
                    were other Ralline birds, but the evidence on this head is inconclusive. In
                    Rodriguez, the greater part of its original <hi rend="italic">avifauna</hi> has
                    vanished. There was a small but peculiar Owl <hi rend="italic">{Athene
                        murivora'),</hi> a big Parrot <hi rend="italic">{Necropsittacus
                        rodericanus^),</hi> a Dove <hi rend="italic">{Erythroena?</hi> sp. ign.), a
                    large brevipennate Heron <hi rend="italic">{Ardea megacephala),</hi> and a
                    singular Rail <hi rend="italic">{Miserythrus leguati)—</hi> in some respects
                    allied to the Mauritian <hi rend="italic">Aphanapteryx—</hi> besides other birds
                    of which we know from old voyagers,<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Proc. Zool. Soc.</hi> 1875, pp.
                            39-42.</p></note> though their remains have not yet been determined (as
                    those of the species above mentioned have been) from the numerous caverns of the
                    island. A second Parrot, or rather Parrakeet <hi rend="italic">{Palceornis
                        exsuΓ),</hi> still exists, but in very small numbers, and the unique
                    specimen known was obtained in the year 1871.</p>
                <p>With the examples of these Mascarene Islands before us, it is not without reason
                    that we suppose a like fate to have befallen many of the feathered inhabitants
                    of other places exposed to similar ravages. We cannot read the accounts not
                    merely of the earliest voyages to the Antilles, but even of those performed
                    within the last hundred years, without being aware that the writers met with
                    many Birds which are not now known to inhabit them. These lost species, there is
                    some ground for believing, were mainly; if not wholly, peculiar to the locality,
                    and after having made good their existence, maybe, for ages, fell easy and
                    helpless victims to the forces which European civilization brought into play.
                    Chief among these forces was fire. In all countries and at all times it has been
                    the habit of colonists to burn the woods surrounding their settlements — partly
                    to clear the ground for future crops, and partly (in tropical climates
                    especially) to promote the salubrity of their stations. When fire was set to the
                    forest and bush of a small island, the whole of which could be burnt at once,
                    the disastrous effect on its fauna can easily be conceived. Even the animals
                    which happened to escape the conflagration itself would speedily starve, owing
                    to the at least temporary destruction of the native flora whence, either
                    directly or indirectly, they derived their wonted sustenance. Thus in certain of
                    the Virgin Islands the “dead” shells of many species of terrestrial Gasteropods
                    are everywhere found in astounding numbers, while not a living individual of
                    several of the species has ever been met with by the conchologists <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n751/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0903-0751-0734"/> of our day. The only assignable cause of the
                    extinction of these creatures lies in the fact that these islands are known to
                    have been laid waste by fire. The shells have resisted destruction but how many
                    more animals must have perished without leaving a trace of their existence 1
                    Even at the present time, few parts of the world so overrun by people of
                    European descent are from a naturalist’s point of view so little known as the
                    West-India Islands. Still less is known of their state a century ago; and it
                    would be a long and wearisome task to collect from old voyages the meagre,
                    scattered, and often inaccurate information they contain as to the zoology of
                    these islands. One example may, perhaps, be sufficient. Ledru accompanied an
                    expedition sent out in 1796 by the French Government to the West Indies. In his
                    work he gives a list of the birds he found in the islands of St Thomas and St
                    Croix (<hi rend="italic">Voyage, aux Isles de Tenerife, dec.,</hi> Paris, 1810,
                    ii. p. 29). He enumerates <hi rend="italic">fourteen</hi> kinds of birds as
                    having occurred to him then. Of these there is now no trace of <hi rend="italic"
                        >eight</hi> of the number; and, if he is to be believed, it must be supposed
                    that within fifty or sixty years of his having been assured of their existence,
                    they have become extinct<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                            ><p>One of the survivors (a Parrakeet, <hi rend="italic">Conurus
                                xantholaεmus)</hi> was a few years ago restricted to a single
                            hill-top in St Thomas, and so reduced in numbers that the present writer
                            was ridiculed by many of the inhabitants for believing that such a bird
                            ever existed in the island. Found, however, it was at last, but it must
                            be regarded as verging upon extinction.</p></note> And yet the period
                    just mentioned was long subsequent to that in which the primeval woods of the
                    islands were burnt. What, then, must not have been the changes which tho
                    forest-fires produced?</p>
                <p>If this be not enough we may cite the case of the French islands of Guadeloupe
                    and Martinique, in which, according to Μ. Guyon <hi rend="italic">(Comptes
                        Rendus,</hi> lxiii. p. 589), there were once found <hi rend="italic"
                        >six</hi> species of <hi rend="italic">Psittaci,</hi> all now exterminated;
                    and it may possibly be that the Maccaws stated by Mr Gosse <hi rend="italic">(B.
                        Jamaica,</hi> p. 260) and Mr Marsh <hi rend="italic">(Proc. Acad. N^.S.
                        Philad.</hi> 1863, p. 283) to have formerly frequented certain parts of
                    Jamaica, but not apparently noticed there for some twenty-five or thirty years,
                    have fallen victims to colonization and its consequences.</p>
                <p>Mention has already been made of the Gare-fowl <hi rend="italic">(Alca
                        impennis),</hi> whose bones have been found in the kitchen-middens of
                    Denmark, and more lately in similar deposits in Caithness. This species, nearly
                    allied to our common Razor-bill <hi rend="italic">(A. torda),</hi> but
                    flightless and about twice as big, seems to have become extinct since 1844, in
                    which year the last two examples known to have lived were taken on a rocky
                    islet—one of a group called Fuglaskér, or Fowlskerries, off the south-west point
                    of [Iceland. Ten years before, one had been caught alive at the entrance of
                    Waterford harbour; and in 1821 or 1822 one was taken near St Hilda, to which
                    lonely island, as appears from old authors, the bird had been accustomed to
                    resort in the breeding season. In 1812 a pair were killed at Papa-Westray, which
                    was also a breeding station of the species, and the stuffed skin of one of them
                    is preserved in the British Museum, while that of the Waterford specimen may be
                    seen in the museum of Trinity College, Dublin. In the Faeroes the species was
                    formerly common, but it certainly ceased from appearing there about the
                    beginning of the present century. In the Iceland seas there are three localities
                    called after the bird’s name, but on only one of them has it been observed for
                    many years, having probably been as long extirpated in the rest as in the
                    Faeroes. On the locality where it continued latest, there is ample evidence to
                    show that it once was plentiful. There was a large skerry—the Geirfuglaskér
                    proper—on which, in 1813, the crew of a Faeroese vessel made a descent and
                    slaughtered a large number of Gare-fowls; but this, like the rest of the group,
                    was a place very difficult of access, and, in 1821, Faber, the well-known
                    faunist of Iceland, failed to land upon it, though some of his companions
                    reached the Geirfugladrângr, a smaller islet lying further to seaward. In 1830
                    the large skerry, through a submarine volcanic eruption, disappeared beneath the
                    λvaves, and immediately after a colony of Gare-fowls was discovered on another
                    rock lying nearer the mainland, and known as Eldey.<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Whether on the subsidence of the large
                            skerry another portion of the birds which frequented it colonized the
                            outermost islet is not known, for this spot does not seem to have been
                            visited by any human being since Faber’s time, more than fifty years
                            ago.</p></note> In the course of the next fourteen years, not fewer
                    probably than sixty birds were killed on this newly-chosen station, and a nearly
                    corresponding number of eggs were brought off; but the colony gradually dwindled
                    until, as above said, in 1844 the last two were taken <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Ibis,</hi> 1861, p. 374).</p>
                <p>In Greenland, for the last three hundred years, the Garefowl has only been known
                    as an occasional straggler, but it would appear that in 1574 a party of
                    Icelanders found it so plentiful at a spot on the east coast—since identified
                        <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n752/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0903-0752-0735"/> with DanelΓs or Graah’s Islands—that they
                    loaded one of their boats with their captives. All recent explorations of this
                    inhospitable coast prove the utter vanity of the notion that the Gare-fowl is
                    able there to find an asylum.</p>
                <p>But it was in the seas of Newfoundland that this species, known to the settlers
                    and fishermen as the “Penguin,”— a corruption of the words “pin-wing,”—was most
                    abundant, as a reference to Hakluyt’s and similar collections of voyages will
                    prove. In 1536, or forty years after the discovery of the country, we find an
                    island taking its name from the bird, and others are even now so called. English
                    and French mariners alike resorted to these spots, driving the helpless and
                    hapless birds on sails or planks into a boat, “as many as shall lade her,” and
                    salting them for provision. The French crews, indeed, trusted so much to this
                    supply of victual, as to take, it is said, but “small store of flesh with them.”
                    This practice, we learn from Cartwright <hi rend="italic">(Journal,</hi>
                    &lt;fcc., iii. p. 55), was carried on even in 1785, and he then foresaw the
                    speedy extirpation of the birds, which at that time had only one island left to
                    breed upon. In 1819, Anspach reported their entire disappearance, but it is
                    possible that some few yet lingered. On Funk Island, their last resort, rude
                    enclosures of stones are, or recently were, still to be seen, in which the
                    “Pinwings” were impounded before slaughter; and a large quantity of their bones,
                    and even natural mummies, preserved partly by the antiseptic property of the
                    peat and partly by the icy subsoil, have been discovered. One of the last has
                    furnished the chief materials from which the osteology of the species has been
                    described <hi rend="italic">(Trans. Zool.</hi><hi rend="italic">Soc.</hi> V. p.
                    317). Some 70 specimens of the bird’s skin, about as many eggs, and nearly
                    half-a-dozen more or less perfect skeletons, with detached bones of perhaps an
                    hundred individuals, are preserved in collections; but even if there be any
                    truth in the various reports of the appearance of the species since 1844 (some
                    of which seem to rest on fairly good testimony), so that it may still survive,
                    it is obvious that its rediscovery will most likely seal its fate.</p>
                <p>Far less commonly known, but apparently quite as certain, is the doom of a large
                    Duck which even fifty years ago was commonly found in summer about the mouth of
                    the St Lawrence and the coast of Labrador, migrating in winter to the shores of
                    Nova Scotia, New Brunswick, New England, and perhaps further southward. For many
                    years past, according to the best-informed American ornithologists, not a single
                    example has been met with in any of the markets of the United States, where
                    formerly it was not at all uncommon at the proper season, and the last known to
                    the writer to have lived was killed by Col. Wedderburn in Halifax harbour in the
                    autumn of 1852.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>It is
                            needless to observe that no one at that time had any notion of its
                            approaching extinction.</p></note> This bird, the <hi rend="italic">Anas
                        labradora</hi> of the older ornithologists, was nearly allied to the Eiders
                        <hi rend="italic">(Somateria},</hi> and like them used to breed on rocky
                    islets, where it was safe from the depredations of foxes and other carnivorous
                    quadrupeds. This safety was however unavailing when man began yearly to visit
                    its breeding-haunts, and, not content with plundering its nests, mercilessly to
                    shoot the birds. Most of such islets are, of course, easily ransacked and
                    depopulated. Having no asylum to turn to, for the shores of the mainland were
                    infested by the four-footed enemies just mentioned, and (unlike some of its
                    congeners) it had not a high northern range, its fate is easily understood. No
                    estimate has yet been made of the number of specimens existing in museums, but
                    it is believed to be not very great.</p>
                <p>Another bird which has become extinct within the last few years is one of a group
                    of Parrots <hi rend="italic">(Nestor}</hi> peculiar to the New-Zealand
                    Subregion, and though some of its congeners still exist in the less-frequented
                    and alpine parts of that country, this species <hi rend="italic">(N.</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">productus}</hi> seems to have been confined to Phillip Island.
                    The last known to have lived, according to information supplied to the writer by
                    Mr Gould, was seen by that gentleman in a cage in London about the year 1851.
                    Not much more than a dozen specimens are believed to exist in collections.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
