<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0288-0273-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BALBOA, Vasco Nunez de</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 3, page 273</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4707wx1r">Ships</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n5c">Shipping</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1205190">Peru</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1242151">Hispaniola</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1028366">Mountains</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1116352">Shipping</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1116439">Ships</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n288/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BALBOA, <hi rend="smallcaps">Vasco Nunez de</hi></label>, one
                    of the bravest and most successful of the Spanish discoverers of America, was
                    born at Xeres de los Caballeros, in Estremadura, about the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n289/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0289-0274"/> year 1475. Ile was by birth a <hi rend="italic"
                    >hidalgo,</hi> or gentleman, but was in poor circumstances. Little is known of
                    his life till the year 1501, when he was one of the company of adventurers who
                    followed Roderigo de Bastidas in his voyage of discovery to the western seas. He
                    appears to have settled in Hispaniola, and took to cultivating land in the
                    neighbourhood of Salvatierra, but with no great success, as his debts soon
                    became oppressive. In 1509 the famous Ojeda sailed from San Domingo with an
                    expedition, and founded the settlement of San Sebastian. He had left orders with
                    Enciso, an adventurous lawyer of the town, to fit out two ships and convey
                    provisions to the new settlement. Enciso set sail in 1510, and Balboa, whose
                    debts made the town unpleasant to him, managed to accompany him, by concealing
                    himself in a cask which was conveyed from Ins farm to the ship as if containing
                    provisions. The expedition, after various adventures, reached San Sebastian to
                    find Ojeda gone and the settlement in ruins. While Enciso was undecided how to
                    act, Vasco Nunez proposed that they should sail for Darien, on the Gulf of
                    Uraba, where he had touched when with Bastidas. His proposal was at once
                    accepted, and carried out. The new town was named Sta Maria de la Antigua del
                    Darien. Bitter quarrels soon broke out among the adventurers, caused chiefly by
                    Enciso prohibiting all private interchange for gold with the natives. Enciso was
                    deposed from the office of authority which he had assumed, but it was found no
                    easy matter to elect a successor. Nicuesa, in whose province they were, was
                    proposed by several, and was brought from Nombre de Dios by a ship which had
                    been sent out to bring assistance to him. The inhabitants of Darien, however,
                    would not receive him, and, in their wrath, seized him and placed him, with
                    seventeen companions, in a crazy bark with which to find his way back to
                    Hispaniola. The party of Vasco Nunez grew strong; Enciso was thrown into prison,
                    and finally sent off to Spain along with Vasco’s ally, the alcalde Zamudio.
                    Being thus left in authority, Balboa began to make excursions into the
                    surrounding country, and by his bravery and conciliatory manners gained the
                    friendship of several native chiefs. On one of these excursions he heard for the
                    first time of the great ocean that lay on the other side of the mountains, and
                    of the wondrous land of gold, afterwards called Peru. Soon after his return to
                    Darien he received letters from Zamudio, informing him that Enciso had
                    complained to the king, and had obtained a sentence condemning Balboa and
                    summoning him to Spain. In his despair at this message Vasco resolved to attempt
                    some great enterprise, the success of which he trusted would conciliate his
                    sovereign. On the 1st September 1513, he set out with about 190 men, well armed,
                    and sailed to Coyba, where he left half his forces to guard the canoes and
                    ships. With the remainder he started on his perilous journey across the isthmus.
                    On the 26th September they reached the summit of the range of mountains, and the
                    glorioue expanse of the Pacific was displayed to them. Three days later, they
                    began to descend the mountains on the western side, and Vasco, arriving at the
                    sea-shore, formally took possession of the ocean in the name of the Spanish
                    monarch. He remained on the coast for some time, heard again of Peru, had the
                    Pearl Islands pointed out to him, and set out for Darien. On the 18th January
                    1514 he reached the town, and was received with the utmost joy. He at once sent
                    messengers to Spain bearing presents, to give an account of his discoveries;
                    but, unfortunately, these did not arrive till an expedition had sailed from
                    Spain, under Don Pedro Arias de Avila (generally called Pedrarias, or Davila),
                    to replace Vasco Nunez, and to take possession of the colony. For some time
                    after Pedrarias reached Darien Vasco was in great straits, but at length letters
                    came from the king, announcing to him his satisfaction with his exploits, and
                    naming him <hi rend="italic">Adelantado,</hi> or admiral. Pedrarias was
                    prevailed upon to be reconciled with Vasco, and gave him one of his daughters in
                    marriage. Vasco then resolved to accomplish his grand project of exploring the
                    western sea. With infinite labour materials for building ships were conveyed
                    across the isthmus, and two brigantines were constructed. With these the
                    adventurers took possession of the Pearl Islands, and, had it not been for the
                    weather, would have reached the coast of Peru. This career of discovery was
                    stopped by the jealousy of Pedrarias, who feared that Balboa would throw off his
                    allegiance, and who enticed him to Acla by a crafty message. As soon as he had
                    him in his power, he threw him into prison, had him tried for treason, and
                    forced the judge to condemn him to death. The sentence, to the grief of all the
                    inhabitants, was carried into execution on the public square of Acla in
                    1517.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
