<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0879-0862-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BOIELDIEU, François</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 3, page 862</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1109393">Scribes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1046191">Operas</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1046145">Opera</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1030269">Music</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1030814">Musicals</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1137041">Success</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:817721">Arts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90251t">Opera</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2ch0v">Music</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9785q">Success</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n879/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BOIELDIEU, <hi rend="smallcaps">François</hi></label>- <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Adrien,</hi> is the chief representative of the national school
                    of comic opera in France, a branch of art in which everything that is most
                    lovable and at the same time most national in the French character has found its
                    full expression. He was born at Rouen in 1775, and received his first musical
                    education from M. Broche, the organist of the cathedral of that city. It is said
                    that, when quite a youth, in order to escape the punishment of a severe master
                    for a slight offence, he went off to Paris on foot, but was discovered and
                    brought back by his parents. He began composing songs and chamber music at a
                    very early age,—his first opera, <hi rend="italic">La Famille</hi> S⅛zsse,being
                    produced on the stage of Rouen in 1795, where it met with an enthusiastic
                    reception. Not satisfied with his local success he turned his eyes to that
                    loadstar of youthful ambition, Paris. He went to the capital in 1795, full of
                    hope and expectation. The score of his opera was submitted to the leading
                    musicians of the day, such as Cherubini, Méhul, and others, but met with little
                    approbation. Altogether the time was not favourable for the comic muse. The
                    heroic passions roused by the revolutionary events of the preceding years
                    required commensurate efforts of musical art; the grand opera was the order of
                    the day. Boieldieu had to fall back on his talent as a pianoforte-player for a
                    livelihood, and to wait for a chance of higher success in the meantime. This
                    success came at last from a source whence it was little expected, and, perhaps,
                    less desired. Garat, a fashionable singer of the period, admired Boieldieu’s
                    touch on the piano, and made him his accompanyist. He also sung in the
                    drawing-rooms of the Directoire the charming songs and ballads with which the
                    young composer supplied him but too willingly. In this manner Boieldieu’s
                    reputation gradually extended to wider circles. In 1797 his above-mentioned
                    opera appeared for the first time on a Paris stage, and was well received.
                    Several others followed in rapid succession, of which only the last, <hi
                    rend="italic">Le Calife</hi><hi rend="italic">de Bagdad</hi> (1799), has escaped
                    oblivion. It tends to show Boieldieu’s true artistic vocation, that, after the
                    enormous success of <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n880/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0880-0863"/> this work, he felt the want of a thorough musical
                    training, and voluntarily descended from the position of a successful <hi
                    rend="italic">maestro</hi> to that of a humble pupil. He took lessons from
                    Cherubini, and the influence of that great master is distinctly discernible in
                    the higher artistic finish of Boieldieu’s later compositions. In 1802 Boieldieu,
                    for the second time in his life, took to sudden flight, on this occasion in
                    order to escape the domestic troubles caused by his marriage with a celebrated
                    ballet-dancer of the Paris Opera. The frightened husband went to Russia, where
                    he was received with open arms by the Emperor Alexander. During his prolonged
                    stay at St Petersburg he composed a number of operas which it is unnecessary to
                    name. He also set to music the choruses of Racine’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Athalie,</hi> one of his few attempts at the tragic style of dramatic writing.
                    In 1811 he returned to his own country, where the following year witnessed the
                    production of one of his finest works, <hi rend="italic">Jean de Paris.</hi> The
                    charming coquetry of the queen of Navarre, the chivalrous <hi rend="italic"
                    >verve</hi> of the king, the officious pedantry of the seneschal, and the
                    amorous tenderness of the page—all this rendered in the finest touches that
                    music, and only French music, is capable of, will not soon be forgotten. We pass
                    over a number of other operas of lesser value, partly written in collaboration
                    with other composers, and turn at once to the second and greatest masterpiece of
                    Boieldieu’s genius, his <hi rend="italic">Dame Blanche</hi> (1825). The
                    libretto, written by Scribe, was partly suggested by Walter Scott’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Monastery,</hi> and several original Scotch tunes cleverly
                    introduced by the composer add not a little to the melodious charm and local
                    colour of the work. <hi rend="italic">La Dame Blanche</hi> marks the highest
                    development of the French school of comic opera. Grétry stood at the head of
                    this school; Cherubini with his <hi rend="italic">Deux Journées</hi> followed in
                    his wake; Boieldieu, greater than both (in this particular branch of art),
                    reached a perfection which was to some extent sustained by the works of Auber.
                    Boieldieu’s pupil, Adam, has in his <hi rend="italic">Derniers</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Souvenirs</hi><hi rend="italic">d'un Musicien</hi> left a charming
                    sketch of the genesis of Boieldieu’s masterpiece. The chief characteristics of
                    his style are an easy flow of graceful melodies, a refined though occasionally
                    somewhat meagre instrumentation, admirable phrasing, and a most distinct
                    enunciation of the words. The outer events of Boieldieu’s career may be summed
                    up in few words. For a long time he occupied the position of professor of
                    composition and pianoforte at the Conservatoire; in 1817 he was made a member of
                    the Institute. The <hi rend="italic">Dame Blanche</hi> was his last opera but
                    one. Soon after its production he was seized with a violent attack of pulmonary
                    disease. To stop the rapid progress of the illness he travelled in Italy and the
                    South of France, but fell a victim to it on October 8, 1834.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
