<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0589-0572-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BENIN</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 3, page 572</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f39x">Mouth</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v00z">Travelers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pw5q">Travels</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49p2wf9z">Travel</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:799938">Africans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:799932">Africanization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1028427">Mouth</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:890004">Deltas</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="9" ref="fastgeo:1206464">Benin</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1205480">Niger</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n589/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BENIN</label>, a country, city, and river of Western Africa,
                    to the west of the main channel of the Niger. The name was formerly applied to
                    the whole stretch of coast from the Volta, in 0° 40' E. long., to the Rio del
                    Rey or Riumbi, in 8° 40' E. long., including what is now known as the Slave
                    Coast, the whole delta of the Niger, and a small portion of the country to the
                    eastward; and some trace of this earlier application remains in the name of <hi
                    rend="italic">Bight of Benin,</hi> still given to that part of the sea which
                    washes the Slave Coast. The kingdom of Benin seems at one time to have been one
                    of the most powerful of Western Africa, and was known to Europeans in the 17th
                    century as the Great Benin. Budagry and Lagos, now British possessions, are both
                    Beninese colonies. Benin has now been long in a state of decline, and the
                    territory is broken up into independent states of no individual importance. Such
                    coherence, indeed, as still exists is rather ethnographical <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n590/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0590-0573"/> than territorial; but it may be regarded as
                    bounded on the E. by the Niger, N. by the Yoruba country, and W. by Egba. The
                    soil is highly fertile and produces palms, rice, beans, maize, kokos,plantains,
                    cotton, sugar, and Guinea pepper, in great abundance. The papaw and African plum
                    grow wild, and excellent tobacco can be raised. Many parts of the country are
                    covered with almost impenetrable forests and swamps, but towards the north there
                    is fine pasture land, in which the natives rear both cattle and horses of
                    considerable value. Of trees the cotton wood, the tamarind, and the mangrove are
                    the most frequent. The population is pretty dense, and it is said that in the
                    most flourishing state of the kingdom the king could collect 100,000 men. His
                    rule is absolute, and he is revered by his subjects as a species of divinity. It
                    is a crime to believe that the king either eats or sleeps; and all offences
                    against him are punished with the utmost severity. The religion and mythology
                    agree with the great system of Yoruba and Oro; the chief god is worshipped with
                    human sacrifices to an appalling extent. The people, at the same time, do not
                    indulge in wanton cruelty; they usually stupefy the victims before putting them
                    to death. The houses, at least of the better classes, are built on a plan
                    similar to that of the Romans, with a regular <hi rend="italic">atrium</hi> and
                    <hi rend="italic">impluvium.</hi> The Beninese weave their cotton into a fine
                    kind of muslin, which is worn in huge bulging petticoats by people of wealth,
                    while the lower orders are content with a simple <hi rend="italic">Beluko</hi>
                    or kilt. The capital of, the kingdom, or city of Benin, is situated about 73⅜
                    miles inland from the mouth of the Rio Formoso or Benin River, about 5° 35' E.
                    long, and 6° 25' N. lat. It covers a large extent of ground, but is so broken up
                    into separate portions by intervening spaces of jungle, that no proper estimate
                    can be formed of its population. The Obwe, or King’s quarter, alone is supposed
                    to have upwards of 15,000 inhabitants; but at the time of Burton’s visit in 1862
                    many of the houses were empty and falling to ruin. The next city in importance
                    is Wari (Owari, Awerri, or Owheyre, called Jakubythe natives), which is situated
                    about 130 miles S.S.E. of the capital, and some 7 or 10 miles from the sea, on
                    an island surrounded by a branch of the Niger distinguished by the same name. It
                    was formerly described as consisting of two parts about half a mile distant from
                    each other, but now consists of one long and straggling line along the shore.
                    The population previously stated at 5000 is reduced by Burton to 2000. The town,
                    however, has its own king, who has long asserted his independence of the monarch
                    of Benin. The houses are neatly built of clay, coloured with red ochre, and
                    frequently ornamented with rudely carved pillars. The port of Gwato (or as it is
                    variously called, Gato, Agatho, or Agatton) lies about 30 miles N.N.E. of the
                    mouth of the Benin River, is a place of some importance for the palm-oil trade,
                    and has a special interest as the place where Belzoni, the traveller, died and
                    was buried. Numerous factories are scattered along the creeks of the delta for
                    the purposes of trade, but all the larger European settlements have disappeared.
                    Since the abolition of the slave trade the chief export of the country is
                    palm-oil, in return for which salt, silk stuffs, guns and gunpowder, coral
                    (which is the official decoration of the higher dignities), beads, iron, brass,
                    and brandy are imported. The common internal currency is the cowrie-shelL</p>
                <p>The River Benin, called by the natives Uwo Ko Jakri, or Outlet of Jakri, is about
                    two miles broad at its mouth; but it is crossed by a very extensive bar of mud
                    and sand, on which there is only 12 feet of water at spring tides. Ships of 60
                    tons can ascend as far as Gwato.</p>
                <p>Benin was discovered by the Portuguese about the year 1485, and they carried on
                    for some time a brisk trade in slaves, who were carried to Elmina, and sold to
                    the natives of the Gold Coast. John III. of Portugal, however, prohibited this
                    traffic; and, as the situation was found very unhealthy, the settlement was
                    ordered to be withdrawn. Many traces of the Portuguese occupation are still to
                    be found, and one of the most striking proofs of their influence is the fact
                    that a corrupt Lusitanian dialect is still spoken by the older natives. The
                    Dutch afterwards established factories, and maintained them for a considerable
                    time, chiefly with a view to the slave trade. In 1788 Captain Landolphe founded
                    a factory called Barodo, near the native village of Obobi, for the French
                    Compagnie d’Oywheré; and it lasted till 1792, when it was destroyed by the
                    English. See Bosman’s <hi rend="italic">Description of the Coast of Guinea
                    in</hi> 1705 (in vol. xvi. of Pinkerton’s <hi rend="italic">Voyages)</hi>;
                    William Smith’s <hi rend="italic">New Voyage to Guinea,</hi> 1744; Adams’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Remarks on the West Coast of Africa,</hi> 1823; Clapperton’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Second Expedition,</hi> 1829; Lander’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Travels,</hi> 1832; Burton’s <hi rend="italic">My Wanderings in West
                    Africa,</hi> 1863.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
