<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0493-0478-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BECHWANA, or Betjuana</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 3, page 478</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b41j97809">Bechwanas</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7f28s">Zulus</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4154dt2t">Hottentots</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1242088">Sahara</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1170328">War</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1072687">Possessiveness</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:932562">Foresters</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1155984">Trees</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:799938">Africans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:799932">Africanization</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n493/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BECHWANA, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Betjuana</hi></label>, the
                    name of a nation extending over a large tract of the interior of South Africa,
                    lying between 22° and 28° S. lat. and 22° and 29’ E. long. There are remains as
                    well as traditions indicating that they once occupied lands further to the south
                    and north of their present boundaries. The country is bounded on the W. by what
                    may be called the southern Sahara; on the E. by the Limpopo, and on the N. by
                    the Matebele, a tribe which escaped the power of the Chaka, the bloody chief of
                    the Zulus. The country, though hilly and undulating, abounds in grassy plains
                    and considerable forests of acacia. Trees, however, are scarce, as the grass is
                    generally burned off every year; and the young wood is thus not allowed time to
                    grow. The nativeβ also, in order to get fresh garden ground and obtain branches
                    to raise their houses and make fences, are constantly destroying trees, and thus
                    increasing the dryness and sterility of the country. It is evident, from the dry
                    beds of what were once rivers and from remains of ancient forests, that, at an
                    early period, the country must have been abundantly watered. From the many
                    cattle folds and walls of defence scattered over the country, and ruins of
                    ancient towns, it is also evident that at that period stone-dykes were very
                    common.</p>
                <p>The number of the Bechwana has been variously estimated, and according to some
                    amounts to more than 200,000. Their language is copious, with but few slight
                    dialectic differences, being entirely free of the Hottentot elements found in
                    the Kaffre and Zulu. The power of the language which, like the Kaffre and Zulu,
                    belongs to the Ba-nta family, formerly unwritten, may be conceived when it is
                    known that, besides elementary and educational works, the whole of the Bible has
                    been translated into it and is now read by thousands.</p>
                <p>The Bechwana are divided into numerous tribes, all independent of each other, and
                    each governed by its own chiefs and councillors. The names of some of the
                    principal tribes are Batlapee, Barolong, Bangwaketse, Bakhatla, Bakuena,
                    Bamangwato, and Batauana, the last living near the lake Ngami, first visited by
                    Dr Livingstone. There are numerous minor divisione, with laws and customs very
                    similar. With the exception of the Balala (the poor inhabiting the country),
                    they are not nomadic, but live in towns of considerable size, containing from
                    5000 to 40,000. Doubtless, their former warlike habits had the tendency to
                    induce them to congregate for security; for latterly they live, for the sake of
                    agriculture and pasturage, in many formerly uninhabited places.</p>
                <p>Though from time immemorial they had been engaged in constant strife with each
                    other, and thus inured to warfare, they were no match for the warlike Kaffre and
                    butchering Zulu and Matebele. Since the introduction of Christianity among the
                    Bechwana, their clannish strifes have ceased; and, being a people of industrious
                    habits, and acute observers of whatever may increase their property and comfort,
                    they go in great numbers to Cape Colony and other parts where they can obtain
                    labour and wages, being prized as servants. This enables them to return enriched
                    to their homes in a few years.</p>
                <p>The government of the Bechwana may be said to be both monarchical and
                    patriarchal, ihd of a comparatively mild character, the king, as chief, seldom
                    exercising his individual authority independent of his councillors and
                    subordinate chiefs. They have their public assemblies (parliaments), but only
                    when circumstances, chiefly in reference to war, require. These are generally
                    characterized by great freedom of speech, and sometimes the king’s shortcomings
                    are unsparingly dealt with. All is taken in good part, and there is no
                    interruption of the speaker occupying the arena. The king generally closes the
                    meeting with a long speech, referring to the subjects which each speaker had
                    either supported or condemned, not forget-ing to endeavour to clear his own
                    character of any imputation. These public assemblies are now of very rare
                    occurrence.</p>
                <p>The Bechwana arc well formed, dark brown or bronze, and the majority handsome and
                    not assimilated to the negro type. In most the lower part of the face projects,
                    but the skull exhibits no difference from the European type, and many have broad
                    high foreheads, while there is nothing to be seen like the bent-out legs of the
                    negro. The lips are generally thicker than in Europeans, and many have the
                    nostrils wider. The hair is not wool, but simply hair curled and frizzled. They
                    possess the knowledge of smelting iron and copper ore, and make hoes for
                    husbandry, spears, battle-axes, tools, and a great variety of ornaments, chiefly
                    of brass and other alloys. They prepare the skins of animals, and fabricate a
                    variety of utensils. Agriculture and house-building (in which more skill and
                    labour are required than with African huts in general, the houses being always
                    round and admirably adapted to resist high and stormy winds) are the work of the
                    women, while the men make the garments, hunt, and go to war when required.</p>
                <p>The wealth of the Bechwana consists in their cattle, which they tend with the
                    greatest care, manifesting-a shrewd discrimination of localities and pasture
                    suited to oxen, sheep, and goats. Living in a warm climate, they require few
                    garments; but, though to a European they appear scantily dressed, both sexes are
                    strictly decent, and are disgusted by the comparative nudity of the Kaffre and
                    Matebele. Circumcision is practised, and for that purpose youths are selected
                    from 10 to 13 years of age; these retire from the towns, the place in which they
                    are being considered sacred till the season of seclusion, a month or more, is
                    over, when they are allowed to return to their friends, and are looked on as men
                    ready to go to war. The people have many ceremonies and superstitions, believing
                    in the influence of witchcraft and charms, but no one of these has the most
                    remote reference to religion. They have no knowledge whatever of idols, or
                    anything intended to represent an invisible power, and consequently have nothing
                    of a religious character. They do not possess a vestige of worship. With regard
                    to a divine Being their ideas are vague in the extreme. The name <hi
                    rend="italic">morimo,</hi> from <hi rend="italic">mo,</hi> a personal pronoun,
                    and <hi rend="italic">rimo,</hi> from <hi rend="italic">goτimo</hi> (above),
                    instead of being applied to something or some one heavenly—the Creator,
                    Upholder, and Ruler of all—is applied to something that does harm, that inflicts
                    death, or, according to some, a noxious creature that sometimes emerges from a
                    hole to do mischief. So little do the natives care about it, that it never
                    enters into their minds to have recourse to a charm, or anything of a fetish
                    character, to ward off the influence it might be thought to possess. They never
                    allow their thoughts to pierce beyond the moment of death, which is to them the
                    finale of man’s existence. Among some of the interior nations there is a belief
                    in the manes of dead kings of note, but not of the commonalty. Dr Moffat was
                    once present when Moselekatse, the king of the Matabele, in a meeting in the
                    midst of his nobles, in the dark, consulted the spirit of Machobane, his long
                    deceased father. Whatever worship the Bechwana of old may have had, they have
                    none now, not even of any of the animals—the fish, crocodile, monkey,
                    &amp;c.—from which some of the tribes are named. They have a superstitious dread
                    of some things, which, in most if not in all cases, originates with the
                    rainmaker. This is a notable character among all the interior tribes, and
                    possesses supreme influence over the native mind. He has only to speak and it is
                    done, whatever his orders may be. He pretends to give medicine to the clouds,
                    and has recourse to all sorts of tricks and demands on his impatient dupes in
                    order to gain time. Very frequently, when all fails, he falls a sacrifice to
                    their wrath.</p>
                <p>The country of the Bechwana south of the tropic of Capricorn is healthy, and
                    admirably suited for pulmonary complaints. The temperature ranges from zero to
                    105°, and when it exceeds this, as it sometimes does, heavy thunderstorms
                    follow, and not unfrequently hail falls of great size. The principal products
                    are a variety of species of millet <hi rend="italic">{Hotcus Sorghum),</hi>
                    kidney beans, pumpkins, water melons, sweet reed, &amp;c.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n494/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0494-0479"/>
                <p>The resources and capabilities of the country arc small. Hitherto the exports
                    have been principally ostrich feather≡, ivory, and cattle; but the first two are
                    become very scarce since the introduction of the horse and rifle. The elephant
                    is now found principally in the regions where the tsètse fly abounds, and where
                    horses cannct live, while the ostrich betakes itself to the deserts. (R. Μ.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
