<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0903-0435-0420-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BASILIDES (9th edition, volume 3, page 420)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:944037">God</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1012448">Matter</term>
                    <term ref="fast:943906">Gnosticism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:814120">Archons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx0636c">Matter</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rp1x">Gnosticism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4df6k36b">Earth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n102">Archons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208757">Syria</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n435/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BASILIDES</label>, one of the most celebrated of the
                    Gnostics, flourished probably about 120 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> Extremely
                    little is known of his life. He is said to have been born in Syria and to have
                    studied at Alexandria, and this is probably correct. There is, to some extent, a
                    corresponding uncertainty with regard to the precise doctrines held by him. Of
                    these there are two distinct expositions, the one given chiefly by Irenaeus,
                    which has been long before the world, the other contained in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Philosophoumena</hi> of Hippolytus, discovered in 1842.
                    According to Irenseus, the system of Basilides strongly resembled that of
                    Valentinus. The first principle or root of all things, was the supreme God, the
                    unknown and unborn Father. From Him emanated in succession <hi rend="italic"
                        >vovς,</hi><hi rend="italic">λόγος, φρόνησις, σοφία,</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">δύναμης.</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">:</hi> From the last,
                    according to Irenaeus, sprang the powers who created the first heaven; according
                    to Clemens Alex., however, from <hi rend="italic">δύναμις</hi> sprang <hi
                        rend="italic">δικαιοσύνη</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ειρήνη,</hi> and these
                    seven with the Father formed the first Ogdoad, or octave of existence. From them
                    emanated other powers, by whom the second heaven was made, and so on in
                    succession, each system being a more shadowy type or reflex of the original
                    ogdoad. The number of heavens was 365, whence the whole series was called.
                    Abraxas, or Abrasax, a name frequently applied to the lower deity, or even, as
                    by Tertullian, to the supreme God. The powers of the lowest heaven, of whom the
                    chief was called the <hi rend="italic">apχωv,</hi> created the earth. This <hi
                        rend="italic">apχωv</hi> is the God of the Jews, and against Him the other
                    powers were arrayed. To alleviate the misfortunes of the earth, the vois, or
                    first emanation, became incarnate and descended upon earth. The <hi
                        rend="italic">vovς</hi> as incorporeal could not suffer death; accordingly,
                    he changed forms with Simon of Cyrene, and stood by the cross, laughing at his
                    enemies, while Simon suffered in his place. Salvation is spiritual, pertains
                    only to the soul; outer actions are not in themselves good or bad. That
                    Basilides taught this doctrine of moral indifference is not perfectly clear, but
                    ïrenaeus reports that his disciples acted up to it.</p>
                <p>The exposition given by Hippolytus is widely different. According to the account
                    he gives, Basilides started neither with a dualism of God and matter or evil,
                    nor with a theory of emanation. His first principle was God, the unknown,
                    incomprehensible, unspeakable, non-existent one, of whom nothing can be
                    predicated, for no words are adequate to express His essence. This non-existent
                    God, by the exercise of what may be called volition, created the <hi
                        rend="italic">πανσπερμία,</hi> or seed, which contained in itself the germs
                    of all things. In this chaotic mass, which strongly resembles the <hi
                        rend="italic">ομοιομερή</hi> of Anaxagoras, there is a mixture of elements,—
                        <hi rend="italic">σύγχισις αρχική,</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> and at the
                    same time are embedded in it three degrees or kinds of divine sonship,
                    consubstantial with the Deity. The first kind is refined and pure, the second
                    gross, the third requiring purification. As all things naturally tend towards
                    God, the first sonship ascended and sat beside the Father. The second also
                    strove to ascend by means of the Spirit, which is to him as a wing, but he could
                    not rise quite to the Deity, and occupied an inferior position, while the wing
                    or spirit formed the firmament. The third sonship still remained immersed in
                    matter. Then from the world seed there burst forth the great <hi rend="italic"
                        >apχωv,</hi> or ruler, who ascended as far as the firmament, and, imagining
                    that there was nothing beyond, glorified himself as the brightest and strongest
                    of all beings. This ruler, who is sometimes called Abraxas, but whose true name
                    is ineffable, produced a son wiser and better than himself, by whose aid he laid
                    the foundations of the world. The seat of their rule is called the Ogdoad, and
                    it extends through all the ethereal region down to the moon’s sphere, <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n436/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0903-0436-0421"/> where the grosser air begins. This lower
                    dominion is ruled by a second and inferior <hi rend="italic">aρχωv,</hi> the God
                    of the Jews, who also had produced a son; and their seat is called the Hebdomad.
                    Meanwhile, the third sonship, which is truly the spiritual element in the elect,
                    is tied to matter, and is in need of deliverance. Freedom is given by the truth,
                        <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> by a knowledge of the true system of things,
                    and it is given by a series of illuminations. First the mind of the son of the
                    Great Archon is enlightened, and he instructs his father, who learns with fear
                    and repentance that there is a sphere of being higher than his own. The light
                    then passes to the son of the Archon of the Hebdomad, who likewise instructs his
                    father. Finally, the mind of Jesus is illuminated, and he instructs those of
                    mankind who are able to receive the truth. There are thus three great stages in
                    the world’s religious history, each being an advance on its predecessor. These
                    periods are the Ante-Jewish, the Jewish, and the Christian. All the souls
                    capable of receiving the light ascend upwards, while their bodies return to the
                    primeval chaos; the minds of all others are shrouded in eternal night, the
                    darkness of ignorance. For the relation of Basilides to other Gnostics, and for
                    the interpretation of his intensely symbolic expressions, see <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Gnostics.</hi></p>
                <p>The earlier accounts of Basilides, such as those of Neander, Baur (in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Christliche</hi><hi rend="italic">Gnosis'),</hi> and Matter,
                    were based for the most part on Irenaeus. The discovery of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Philosophoumena</hi> threw unexpected light on the subject, and the later
                    expositions generally follow Hippolytus as the exponent of the original system
                    of Basilides. Hilgenfeld still retains the older view. Full information is to be
                    found in Baur, <hi rend="italic">Kirchengeschichte,</hi> i.; L·ipsius, <hi
                        rend="italic">Gnostidsmτιs;</hi> Uhlhorn, <hi rend="italic">Das
                        Basilideanische System;</hi> Mansel, <hi rend="italic">Gnostic
                        Heresies.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
