<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0903-0599-0582-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BERAR (9th edition, volume 3, page 582)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20h7x">Valleys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g03">Cent</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17ss11">Trees</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zm20">Parsis</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:883965">Crops</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1163841">Valleys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:850620">Cent</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1155984">Trees</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n599/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BERAR</label>, a province of British India, forming a
                    Commissionership, is situated between 19° 30' and 21° 46' N. lat., and 76° and
                    79° 13' E. long. Area, about 17,500 square miles; population, <hi rend="italic"
                        >2⅛</hi> millions. The province consists of the districts assigned to the
                    British Government by his Highness the Nizâm of Haidarâbâd, under the treaties
                    of 1853 and 1861. These districts are Amrâotf, Elichpur, Wün, Akolâ, Buldânâ,
                    and Bâsim. Berar province is bounded on the N. and E. by the Central Provinces,
                    on the 8. by the Nizâm’s dominions, and on the W. by the Nizâm’s territory, the
                    Bombay district of Khandesh, and by the Central Provinces. The Ajantâ range
                    intersects the whole province from W. to E., and divides it into two distinct
                    sections—the Payanghât or lowland country, bounded on the N. by <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n600/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0903-0600-0583"/> the Gâwilgarh range of the Sâtpurâ hills,
                    which form the northern boundary between Berar and the Central Provinces, and on
                    the S. by the Ajantâ range, and the Bâlâghât or upland country of the Ajantâ
                    hills, occupying the whole southern part of the province. The Payanghât is a
                    wide valley running up eastward between the Ajantâ range and the Gâwilgarh
                    hills, from 40 to 50 miles in breadth. This tract contains all the best land in
                    Berar, it is full of deep, rich, black alluvial soil, called <hi rend="italic"
                        >regâr</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi> of almost inexhaustible fertility, and
                    it undulates just enough to maintain a natural system of drainage. Here and
                    there are barren tracts where the hills jut out far into the plain, covered with
                    stones and scrub jungle, or where a few isolated flat - topped hills occur.
                    There is nothing picturesque about this broad strip of alluvial country, it is
                    destitute of trees except near the villages close under the hills; and apart
                    from the Pùrnâ, which intersects it from east to west, it has hardly a perennial
                    stream. In the early autumn it is one sheet of cultivation, but after the
                    beginning of the hot season, when the crops have been gathered, its monotonous
                    plain is relieved by neither verdure, shade, nor water. The aspect of the
                    country above the passes which lead to the Bâlâghât is quite different. The
                    trees are finer and the groves more frequent than in the valley below; water is
                    more plentiful and nearer to the surface. The highlands fall southwards towards
                    the Nizâm’s country by a gradual series of ridges or steppes. The principal
                    rivers of the province are the Taptf, which forms a portion of its north-western
                    boundary; the Pùrnâ, which intersects the valley of the Payanghât; the Wardhâ,
                    forming the whole western boundary line; and the Pâin-gangâ, marking the
                    southern boundary for nearly its whole distance. The only natural lake is the
                    Salt Lake of Sunâr. There are no large tanks or artificial reservoirs.</p>
                <p>The total area of the province in 1869-70 was returned at between 17,000 and
                    18,000 square miles, of which about one-half is cultivated, one-fourth
                    cultivable but not cultivated, and the remaining one-fourth uncultivable waste.
                    The great crops are cotton of a superior quality, and <hi rend="italic"
                        >jodr</hi> or millet. The acreage under the different crops in 1869-70 is
                    thus returned— <hi rend="italic">Joar,</hi> 1,812,693 acres; cotton, 1,409,430;
                    wheat, 478,438; pulses, 493,009; <hi rend="italic">bajrd,</hi> 117,273; rice,
                    44,793; linseed, 61,394; hemp, 8978; <hi rend="italic">kardi,</hi> 57,192;
                    tobacco, 32,284; castor oil, 2605; sugar cane, 7947; opium, 247; other crops,
                    829,992; total, 5,356,275 acres, or 8369 square miles. The uncultivated products
                    consist of dyes, gums, fruits and roots of various trees and creepers, honey and
                    beeswax, and jungle fibres. The land settlement of the province is now being
                    made for a period of thirty years, based upon the Bombay system of survey and
                    settlement according to fields. Manufactures are very few, and consist
                    principally of cotton cloth, mostly of coarse quality, stout carpets, saddlery,
                    and a little silk weaving. In 1869-70 the total value of the imports was
                    returned at £7,350,085, and the exports at £5,755,399. For internal
                    communication six first-class roads have been constructed out of the general
                    revenues of the province :—(1), From Amrâoti to Elichpur, 31 miles; (2), from
                    Badnerâ to Morsi, 38 ⅜; (3), from Karinjâ to Murtizapur, 21; (4), from Badnerâ
                    to Amraoti, 5; (5), from Akolâ to Bâsim, 50; &lt;6), from Akolâ to Akot, 31
                    miles. The Nagpur branch of the Great Indian Peninsular Railway traverses the
                    province from east to west for about 150 miles, with short off-shoots to the
                    great cotton marts of Khamgâon and Amraoti.</p>
                <p>The census of 1867 returned the total population of Berar province at 2,231,565
                    souls, dwelling in 495,760 houses, comprising 5694 towns and villages; average
                    density of population, 128 per square mile; average number of persons per house,
                    4’5; proportion of males in total population, 51 ‘7 per cent. Classified
                    according to religion, the Hindus number 1,912,561, or 85 <hi rend="superscript"
                        > ,</hi> 70 per cent, of the total population; Mahometans, 154,951, or 6 94
                    per cent.; aborigines, 163,059, or 7'36 per cent.; Christians, 903; Parsis, 75;
                    and Jews, 16. The Mahometan population of the province is descended from the men
                    who originally accompanied from the north the Musalmân invaders of the Deccan.
                    Among the aboriginal tribes, the most numerous are the Gonds, Ands, Korkus,
                    Kolis, and Kolâms. The principal towns in the province are—(1.) Elichpur, the
                    capital of the old kingdom, and still the most populous town, although not a
                    place of any commercial importance, population 27,782; (2.) Amraoti, the richest
                    town in the province, and a rising and flourishing seat of commerce, pop.
                    23,410; (3.) Akolâ, pop. 12,236; (4.) Akot, a large cotton mart, pop, 14,606;
                    (5.) Karinjâ, pop. 11,750; (6.) Khamgaon, a large and prosperous cotton mart,
                    pop. 9432.</p>
                <p>The total imperial revenue of Berar province in 1869-70 amounted, to £704,109, of
                    which the land revenue gave £457,343; excise, £114,513; salt wells, £650;
                    miscellaneous, £39,413; stamps, £45,947; forests, £18,462; and customs (salt),
                    £27,780. Local funds and cesses amounted to £132,229, or a total revenue from
                    imperial and local sources for the province of £836,338. For the protection of
                    person and property Berar province contains 67 police stations, with 61
                    outposts—total strength of regular pofice, 2613 of all ranks, exclusive of the
                    village watch. The only troops located in the province are those of the
                    Haidarâbâd contingent. At Elichpur a regiment of infantry with a detachment of
                    cavalry and a battery of artillery is stationed; infantry detachments are also
                    stationed at Amraoti and Akolâ. The provision for education consisted in March
                    1870 of 341 schools, attended by 14,898 pupils. Of these 2 are high schools, one
                    at Akolâ and one at Amraoti, with 217 pupils; 44 middle-class schools with 3747
                    pupils; 267 primary schools with 10,148 pupils; 27 female schools with 730
                    pupils; and 1 Normal school for the training of masters.</p>
                <p>The climate of Berar differs very little from that of the Deccan generally,
                    except that in the Γayanghat valley the hot weather is exceptionally severe.
                    Here the freshness of the cold season vanishes after the crops have been taken
                    off the ground, but the heat does not very sensibly increase until the end of
                    March. From May 1st, until about the middle of June when the rains set in, the
                    sun is very powerful, but without the scorching winds of upper India. The nights
                    are comparatively cool. During the rains the air is moist and cool. In the
                    Bâlâghât country above the Ajantâ hills the thermometer always stands much lower
                    thau in the valley. The average rainfall for the whole province is said to be
                    about 27 inches in the valley, and above 30 inches in the Bâlâghât highlands. In
                    1869 the rainfall registered in each of the six districts averaged 33 inches for
                    the whole province. The average mean temperature registered at Akolâ in the-same
                    year was nearly 81° Fahr.</p>
                <p>The early history of Berar belongs to that of the Deccan. The province suffered
                    repeated invasions of Mahometans from the north, and on the collapse of the
                    Bâhmani dynasty in 1526, Berar formed one of the five kingdoms under independent
                    Mahometan princes, into' which the Deccan split up. In the beginning of the
                    seventeenth century the province was invaded by Prince Murad Mirza, son of the
                    Emperor Akbar, and annexed to the Dehli empire. It did not long enjoy the
                    blessings of tranquillity, for on the rise of the Marhattâ power about 1650, the
                    province became a favourite field of plunder. In 1671 the Marhattâ general,
                    Pratâp Râo, extended his ravages as far east as Karinjâ, and exacted from the
                    village officers a pledge to pay <hi rend="italic">chauth.</hi> In 1704 things
                    had reached their worst; the Marhattâs swarmed through Berar “like ants or
                    locusts,” and laid bare whole districts. They were expelled in 1704 by Zulfikâr
                    Khan, one of Aurangzeb’s best generals, but they returned incessantly, levying
                    black-mail in the shape of <hi rend="italic">chauth</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >sardeshmukhi,</hi> with the alternative of fire and sword. Upon the death
                    of Aurangzeb the Marhattâs consolidated their predominance in Berar, and in 1817
                    their demand for <hi rend="italic">chauth,</hi> or a fourth, and <hi
                        rend="italic">sardeshmukhi,</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> qt</hi> a tenth
                    of the revenue of the province, was conceded by the governor. But in 1720-24 the
                    viceroy of the Deccan, under the title of Nizâm-ul-mulk, gained his independence
                    by a series of victories over the imperial generals, and from that time till its
                    cession to England in 1853, Berar was always nominally subject to the Haidarâbâd
                    dynasty. The Mahrattâ rulers posted their officers all over the province, they
                    occupied it with their troops, they collected more than half the revenue, and
                    they fought among themselves for possession of the right to collect; but, with
                    the exception of a few <hi rend="italic">pargands</hi> ceded to the Peshwâ, the
                    Nizâm maintained his title as <hi rend="italic">de jure</hi> sovereign of the
                    country, and it was always admitted by the Marhattâs. In the Marhattâ war of
                    1803, the British under General Wellesley, afterwards the duke of Wellington,
                    assisted by the Nizâm, crushed the Marhattâ power in this part of the country,
                    by utterly defeating them at Argâon on the 28th November 1803, and a few days
                    afterwards at Gâwilgarh. On the 19 th December <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n601/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0903-0601-0584"/> 1803 the Marhattâ chief signed a treaty, in
                    which he resigned all claim to territory and revenue west of the Wardhâ, but
                    retained Narnâlâ and Gâwilgarh in his possession. By this treaty the whole of
                    Berar was made over in perpetual sovereignty to the Nizam. From that time till
                    1848 the history of the province consists of a long list of internal dissensions
                    and civil wars. These troubles reduced the state to the verge of bankruptcy. The
                    pay of the Nizâm’s irregular force, maintained under the treaty of 1800, fell
                    into arrears, and had to be advanced by the British Government. There were also
                    other unsatisfied claims of the Government on the Nizâm, and in 1853 his whole
                    debt amounted to £450,000. Accordingly, in that year a*new treaty was concluded
                    with the Nizâm, under which the existing Haidarâbâd contingent force is
                    maintained by the British Government, in lieu of the troops which the Nizâm had
                    been previously bound to furnish on demand in time of war; while for the payment
                    of this contingent and other claims on the Nizâm, districts then yielding a
                    gross revenue of £500,000 per annum, including the present province of Berar,
                    were assigned to our Government. By this treaty his highness was released from
                    the obligation of furnishing a large force in time of war; the contingent ceased
                    to be a part of the Nizâm’s army, and became an auxiliary force kept up by the
                    British Government for the Nizâm’s use. The treaty was revised in 1860, and as a
                    reward for services rendered by the Nizâm in 1857, two of the districts formerly
                    assigned to us were restored to him, and the territory of the Râjâ of Surâpur,
                    which had been confiscated in consequence of the rebellion of the chief, was
                    added to the Nizâm’s dominions.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
