<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0387-0372-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BARELÎ, or Bareilly</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 3, page 372</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4g15tg7r">Rates</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4zs2kn9v">Tracts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:952579">Head</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1153794">Tracts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1432098">Soul</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n387/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BARELÎ, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Bareilly</hi></label>, a
                    district of British India in the Rohilkhand division, under the jurisdiction of
                    the Lt.-Governor of the North-Western Provinces, situated between 28° 2' and 29°
                    2' N. lat., and 79° 2' 30" and 80° 13' 15" E. long. It is bounded on the N. by
                    Kumâon district and the independent state of Nepâl; on the E. by a portion of
                    the district of Shâhjahânpur, and the district of Lakhimpur in Oudh; on the S.
                    by the districts of Budâon and Shâhjahânpur; and on the W. by the native state
                    of Râmpur and Budâon. Bareli is a level country, watered by many streams, the
                    general slope being towards the south. The soil is fertile and highly
                    cultivated, groves of noble trees abound, and the villages have a neat,
                    prosperous look. A tract of forest jungle, called the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Tardi,</hi> stretches along the extreme north of the district, and teems with
                    large game, such as tigers, bears, deer, wild pigs, Ac.</p>
                <p>The River Sarda or Ghagrâ forms the eastern boundary of the district, and is the
                    principal stream. Next in importance is the Râmgangâ, which receives as its
                    tributaries most of the hill torrents of the Kumâon mountains; the principal
                    ones being the East Balιgιil, Nakatiyâ, Deuraniyâ, Saukhâ, Sidhâ, Dujaura,
                    Kichaha, West Bahgûl, Bhakrâ, Dhakrâ, and Dliùrâ. The Deohâ is another great
                    drainage artery, and receives many minor streams. The Gomati or Gumti also
                    passes through the district. Bareli district has an area of 2976'70 square
                    miles, of which 1845'28 square miles are under cultivation; 727'65 square miles
                    are cultivable, but not actually under cultivation; 25'16 square miles are held
                    revenue free; and 378'60 square miles are returned as uncultivable waste.</p>
                <p>The census of 1872 takes the area at 2982 square miles, and returns the
                    population at 1,507,139 souls, inhabiting 3548 villages or townships, and
                    296,441 houses; density of population per square mile, 505; villages or
                    townships per square mile, 1 '2; persons per village or township, 425; houses
                    per square mile, 99; persons per house, 5. Of the total population, 1,197,583,
                    or 79'5 per cent., are Hindus; 308,682, or 20'5 per cent., Mahometans; and 536
                    Christians, or others of unspecified religion. The Mahometans are chiefly the
                    descendants of Yusafzai Afghâns, called the Rohillâ Pathâns, who settled in the
                    country about the year 1720. The Rohillâswere formerly the ruling race of the
                    tract of country called Rohilkhand, and are men of a taller stature, a fairer
                    complexion, and a more arrogant air than the general inhabitants of the
                    district. Bishop Heber has described them as follows:— “The country is burdened
                    with a crowd of lazy, profligate, self-called sawârs (cavaliers), who, though
                    many of them are not worth a rupee, conceive it derogatory to their gentility
                    and Pathân blood to apply themselves to any honest industry, and obtain for the
                    most part a precarious livelihood by sponging on Hie industrious tradesmen and
                    farmers<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n388/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0388-0373"/>, on whom they levy a sort of blackmail, or as
                    hangers on to the few wealthy and noble families yet remaining in the province.
                    These men have no visible means of maintenance, and no visible occupation except
                    that of lounging up and down with their swords and shields, like the ancient
                    Highlanders, whom in many respects they much resemble.” The Rohillâs, after
                    fifty years’ precarious independence, were subjugated in 1774 by the confederacy
                    of British troops with the Nawâb of Oudh’s army, which formed so serious a
                    charge against Warren Hastings. Their territory was in that year annexed to
                    Oudh. In 1801 the Nawâb of Oudh ceded it to the Company in commutation of the
                    subsidy money. During the Sepoy Mutiny of 1857 the Rohillâs took a very active
                    part against the English, but since then they have been disarmed. Both before
                    and after that year, however, the Bareli Mahometans have distinguished
                    themselves by fanatical tumults against the Hindus.</p>
                <p>The inhabitants of the district are for the most part poor, but their condition
                    has improved under English rule. Sugar and rice, of which large quantities are
                    exported, form the principal agricultural products of the district Pilibhit
                    formed an independent district till its incorporation with Bareli in 1842; its
                    rice is celebrated all over the N.W. Provinces. Other agricultural
                    products—wheat, barley, cotton, tobacco, maize, millet, pulses, and fruit. The
                    jungle tract of the district produces fine timber, in which a large trade is
                    carried on. The total revenue of the district for 1870-71 amounted to £246,419,
                    and the civil expenditure to £80,978. By far the greater part of the revenue is
                    derived from the land; the new settlement for thirty years was concluded in
                    1872. Four towns contain a population of upwards of 5000 souls :—1. Bareli—area,
                    1280 acres, noticed below. 2. Pilibhit—area, 433 acres; population, 29,840;
                    municipal revenue (1872), £3291, 6s.; expenditure, £2698, 2s.; rate of taxation,
                    2s. 2⅛d. per head. 3. Bisâlpur—area, 142 acres; population, 9250; municipal
                    revenue, £282, 8s.; expenditure, £343, 18s.; rate of taxation, 7gd. per head. 4.
                    Anwlah—area, 128 acres; population, 11,153; municipal revenue, £183, 2s. 5⅜d.;
                    expenditure, £224, 15s. 10d.; rate of taxation, 4d. per head. Other minor towns:
                    Faridpur, population, 4940; Sarauli, 4585; Nawâbganj, 4418. There are 19 other
                    towns with a population of above 2000. Bareli shows a heavy criminal return, and
                    the police do not appear to be successful in grappling with crime. The regular
                    police consists of a force of 4218 men. In 1872 there were 518 schools in the
                    district, attended by 9265 pupils, besides those attending the university
                    college in the town of Bareli.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Barelî</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Bareilly</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi> the principal
                    place in the district of the same name, situated on the left bank of the Juâ, a
                    tributary of the Western Râmgangâ,in N. lat. 28° 23', E. long. 79° 28'. It is a
                    large town, with a brisk and lucrative commerce, and manufactures consisting
                    principally of house furnitures, such as chairs, tables, &amp;c. Mr Thornton
                    says, that “besides the hands engaged in this branch of handicraft, there are
                    cotton weavers, dressers, and twisters, manufacturers of muslins, and also of
                    silks and brocades, dyers and colour-makers, linen and cloth-plaiters, gold and
                    silver lace-makers, jewellers, goldsmiths, and silversmiths, blacksmiths,
                    coppersmiths, and tinmen, cutlers, armourers, sealmakers and engravers, turners,
                    saddlers, tailors, &lt;fcc., &amp;c.” In 1872 Bareli town contained a population
                    of 102,982, of whom 59,036 were Hindus, 43,463 Mahometans, and 483 of
                    unspecified religion. In 1872 the municipal revenue of the town amounted to
                    £6602, 8s.; expenditure, £7217, 12s.; rate of municipal taxation, Is. 3fd per
                    head of the population. The municipal revenue is derived from <hi rend="italic"
                    >octroi</hi> duties levied on articles of food brought for sale into the town.
                    The principal institution in the town is the Bareli college, intended as a seat
                    of upper class learning for the surrounding districts of the N.W. Provinces. It
                    is conducted by a staff of efficient professors from England, and its course
                    includes the subjects for degrees in the Calcutta University. In 1872-73 it was
                    attended by 310 pupils. The cost of the college department and upper school
                    amounted to £5836, of which Government contributed £5335.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
