<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0381-0366-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BARCELONA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 3, page 366</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68c45">Trinitarians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4fb4wr06">Hares</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4q52fm3g">Ports</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86q1x">Cotton</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:880858">Cotton</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1048190">Originality</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807488">Americans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206830">Brazil</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204901">Austria</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n381/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BARCELONA</label>, formerly the capital of the kingdom of
                    Catalonia, and now the chief town of the Spanish province to which it gives its
                    name, is a flourishing city and seaport on the shore of the Mediterranean, in
                    lat. 41° 22' N. and long. 2° 9' E., between the rivers Bésos <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Boetulo)</hi> on the north and the Llobregat <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Rubricatus)</hi> on the south. It stands on the sloping edge of a small but
                    fertile plain now covered w ith villas and gardens. Immediately to the
                    south-east rise the Montjuich hills to the height of 650 feet, crowned by an
                    important fortification; while on the west, the north, and the north-east, the
                    view is bounded by the heights of San Pedro Martio, Valcanca, and Moncada.
                    Barcelona was formerly surrounded by a strong line of ramparts, and defended,
                    or, more correctly, overawed by a citadel on the north-east, erected in 1715 by
                    Philip V. on Vauban’s principle; but these fortifications being felt as a
                    painful restriction on the natural development of the city, were, in spite of
                    the opposition of the central Government, finally abolished by the local
                    authorities in 1845. The walls of the moat were utilized for the cellars of the
                    houses which soon occupied the site of the ramparts, and the ground, which had
                    been covered by the citadel, was laid out in horticultural gardens. A rapid
                    extension of the city to the north-west took place, and in 1860 an elaborate
                    plan for the laying out of new districts received the royal sanction. Barcelona
                    thus comprises an old and a new town, differing from each other in many
                    important features, the former still consisting for the most part of irregular
                    and narrow streets, while the latter has all the symmetry and precision of a
                    premeditated scheme. The buildings of the old town are chiefly of brick, from
                    four to five stories in height, with flat roofs, and other Eastern
                    peculiarities; while in the new town hewn stone is very largely employed, and
                    the architecture is often of a modern English style. To the south-east, on the
                    tongue of land that helps to form the port, lies the suburb of Barceloneta. It
                    owes its origin to the marquis de la Mina, who, about 1754, did so much for the
                    city, and is regularly laid out, the houses being built of brick after a uniform
                    pattern. The main street or axis of the old town is the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Rambla,</hi> a favourite resort of the higher classes, which has a fine
                    promenade planted with plane-trees running down the middle, and contains the
                    principal hotels and theatres of the city. Among the most important of the
                    squares are the Plaza de Palacio, the Plaza Real, and the Plaza del Teatro. The
                    Paseo de San Juan and the Gardin del <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n382/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0382-0367"/> General to the north-east of the town are being
                    removed. The site of the former is to be occupied by a large market, while the
                    latter is to be absorbed into the Park. Barcelona is the see of a bishop, and,
                    like most Spanish towns, has a large number of ecclesiastical buildings, though
                    by no means so many as it once possessed. If Barceloneta on the one hand, and
                    Garcia, a suburban village, on the other, be included, the number of churches
                    amounts to twentyseven, and eighteen of these are <hi rend="italic">parroquias
                    ,</hi> while no fewer than eighteen convents were still standing in 1873. The
                    cathedral, erected between 1298 and 1448, but not yet finished, is a spacious
                    building in the Pointed style, and contains the tomb of Santa Eulalia, the
                    patron saint of the city. Its stained glass windows are among the finest in
                    Spain, and it possesses archives of great value. Santa Maria del Mar, Santos
                    Justo y Pastor, San Pedro de las Puellas, and San Pablo del Campo, are all
                    churches worthy of mention. San Miguel in Barceloneta, which preserved a curious
                    ancient mosaic and contained the tomb of the marquis de la Mina, has been taken
                    down.</p>
                <p>The educational institutions of Barcelona have from an early period been numerous
                    and important. The university <hi rend="italic">(Universidad Literaria·)</hi>
                    was originally founded in 1430 by the magistracy of the city, and received a
                    bull of confirma tion from Pope Nicholas V. in 1450, possessing at that time
                    four faculties and thirty-one chairs, all endowed by the corporation <hi
                    rend="italic">(vide</hi> Capmany ’ s <hi rend="italic">Memorias).</hi> It was
                    suppressed in 1714, but restored in 1841, and now occupies an extensive building
                    in the new town. There are, besides, an academy of natural sciences, a college
                    of medicine and surgery,—confirmed by a bull of Benedict XIII. in 1400,— an
                    academy of fine arts, a normal school, a theological seminary, an upper
                    industrial school, an institution for the education of deaf-mutes, a school of
                    navigation, and many minor establishments. Gratuitous instruction of a very high
                    order is afforded by the Board of Trade to upwards of two thousand pupils. The
                    principal charitable foundations are the <hi rend="italic">Casa de Caridad,</hi>
                    or House of Industry, the Hospital General, dating from 1401, and the Foundling
                    Hospital. The <hi rend="italic">Montes de Piedad</hi> are, in fact, mutual
                    benefit societies; and that of Nostra Senora de la Esperanza has this
                    peculiarity, that loans on deposits are made without interest to necessitous
                    persons, thousands of whom yearly avail themselves of its advantages. The
                    principal civic and commercial buildings are the <hi rend="italic">Casa
                    Consistorial,</hi> a fine Gothic hall, theLωy⅛, or Exchange, dating from 1383,
                    and the <hi rend="italic">Aduana, or</hi> Custom-house, built in 1792. At the
                    seaward end of the Rambla is a large ancient structure, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Atarazanas,</hi> or Arsenals, which was finished about 1243. A portion of it
                    was recently taken down to give a better view to the promenade. Remains of the
                    former royal state of Barcelona are found in the Palacio Real of the kings of
                    Aragon, and the Palacio de la Reina. At the highest part of the city, in the
                    Calle del Paradis, are some magnificent columns, and other Roman remains, which,
                    however, are hidden by the surrounding buildings.</p>
                <p>The inhabitants of Barcelona are not only an intelligent and industrious, but a
                    gay and pleasure-loving people. Means of public recreation are abundantly
                    supplied. There are no fewer than fourteen theatres of more or less pretension,
                    the two most important being the Teatro Principal and the Teatro del Liceo. The
                    latter is a very fine building, originally erected in 1845 on the site of a
                    convent of Trinitarian monks, and capable of containing 4000 spectators. A
                    striking feature in Barcelona society is the development of social life; and the
                    number of restaurants and similar places of evening resort is very great. A
                    pleasant promenade is furnished not only by the Rambla but by the Muralia del
                    Mar, or sea-wall, which was largely due to the marquis de la Mina, and is now
                    undergoing extensive alteration by the reclaiming of a strip of land from the
                    port.</p>
                <p>Barcelona has long been the industrial and commercial centre of Eastern Spain—a
                    pre-eminence which dates from the 12th and 13th centuries. It was the rival of
                    Genoa and Venice, and in renown its hardy mariners were second to none. The
                    origin of the famous code of maritime laws known as the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Consolado del mar</hi> is usually, though not with absolute certainty, ascribed
                    to its merchants; and it is pretty well established that they were the first to
                    employ the method of marine insurance. We find them at an early period trading,
                    not only with the ports of the Mediterranean, but with the Low Countries and
                    England, on the one hand, and with Constantinople and Damascus, Egypt and
                    Armenia, on the other,—entering into treaties with kings and magistracies, and
                    establishing in all important places consuls to look after their interests. The
                    prosperity so deeply rooted continued through numerous vicissitudes till the
                    emancipation of the Spanish American colonies, when a comparative decline set
                    in. This, however, proved only temporary, and, in spite of the disastrous
                    consequences of the French invasion, and the various revolutions of the country
                    since then. Barcelona has no need to look back with regret to the past. A great
                    variety of <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n383/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0383-0368"/> industries are now carried on—the most important
                    being the spinning and weaving of wool, cotton, and silk. Of the numerous guilds
                    that were anciently formed in the city an interesting list is to be found in Cap
                    many. It carries on a large shipping trade. In 1872 between 700 and 800 foreign
                    vessels, with a tonnage of 360,000 tons, discharged their cargoes in the port.
                    Of these 160 were British. The imports from the colonies are sugar, cotton,
                    tobacco, rum, wax, dye-wood, &amp;c.; machinery, coals, coke, cotton, wool,
                    thread, and other stuffs, are brought from England; articles of silk, chemical
                    preparations, pastes and flours of all sorts, objects of fashion, wines and
                    liquors, from France; petroleum, cotton, and staves from North America; cotton
                    from the Brazils and Smyrna; hides from the River Plate; salt-fish from the
                    North Sea. The export trade is not so extensive, consisting largely of fruits
                    and vegetables, oil, silk, wines, salt, Ac. The so-called port of Barcelona was
                    at first only an open beach, slightly sheltered by the neighbouring hills, but
                    at an early period the advantage of some artificial protection was felt. In 1438
                    we find Don Alphonso V. granting the magistracy a licence to build a mole; and
                    in 1474 the <hi rend="italic">Moll de Santa Creu</hi> was officially commenced.
                    Long after this, however, travellers speak of Barcelona as destitute of a
                    harbour; and it is only in the 17th century that satisfactory works were
                    undertaken. Down to a very recent period all the included area was shut off from
                    the open sea by a sandbank, which rendered the entrance of large vessels
                    impossible. An extension of the former mole, and the construction of another
                    from the foot of Montjuich, have embraced a portion of the sea outside of the
                    bank, and a convenient shelter is thus afforded for the heaviest men of war. The
                    depth in this part is about 40 feet, while within the sandbank it is from 18 to
                    20. Barcelona is well supplied with inland communication by rail, and the
                    traffic of its own streets is largely facilitated by tramway lines running from
                    the port as far as Garcia.</p>
                <p>According to traditions preserved by the Roman writers, Barcelona owed its
                    origin, or at least its first importance, to the Carthaginians under Hamilcar
                    Barca, after whom it was called <hi rend="italic">Barcino.</hi> It received a
                    Roman colony, and was known by the name of <hi rend="italic">Faventia.</hi>
                    After having shared in the various vicissitudes of the barbaric invasions, it
                    became the capital of a dukedom under Louis the Pious, and not long after began
                    to give the title of count to a family that soon made itself independent. In 985
                    the city was ^captured by the Moors, but not long after it was recovered by
                    Count Borell. In 1151 Raymund Berenguer married the daughter of Ramiro II. of
                    Aragon, and thus the countship of Barcelona was united to that kingdom by his
                    son. From the successive princes of the line the city received many privileges.
                    In 1640 Barcelona was the centre of the Catalonian rebellion against Philip IV.,
                    and threw itself under French protection. In 1652 it returned to its allegiance,
                    but was captured by the duke of Vendôme in 1697. At the peace of Ryswick, in the
                    same year, it was restored to the Spanish monarchy. During the War of the
                    Succession Barcelona adhered to the house of Austria. The seizure of Montjuich
                    in 1705 and the subsequent capture of the city by the earl of Peterborough
                    formed one of his most brilliant achievements. In 1714 it was taken after an
                    obstinate resistance by the duke of Berwick in the interests of Louis XIV., and
                    at the close of the war was reluctantly reconciled to the Bourbon dynasty. At
                    the commencement of Bonaparte’s attempt on the liberty of Spain, the French
                    troops obtained possession of the fortress, and kept the city in subjection.
                    Since then it has shared in most of the revolutionary movements that have swept
                    over Spain, and has frequently been distinguished by the violence of its civic
                    commotions. By the census of 1857 the population of the city amounted to
                    180,014, and by an enumeration in 1864 the city and suburbs were found to
                    contain 252,000 persons. (See <hi rend="italic">Manifestation de muichos</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">relevantes</hi><hi rend="italic">servicios de Barcelona,</hi>
                    Barcelona, 1697; Capmany, <hi rend="italic">Memorias historicas</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">sobre</hi><hi rend="italic">Barcelona,</hi> 1779-92; Chantreau,
                    <hi rend="italic">Lettres de</hi><hi rend="italic">Barcelonne,</hi> 1793; Hare,
                    <hi rend="italic">Wanderings in Spain.}</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
