<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0903-0867-0850-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BOECKH, August (9th edition, volume 3, page
                    850)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106924">Scholia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1030269">Music</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1030814">Musicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1052348">Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2ch0v">Music</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r785w31">Paper</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4df6k36b">Earth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fn10v74">Easter</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n867/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BOECKH, <hi rend="smallcaps">August</hi></label>, one of the
                    greatest scholars that Germany has produced in modern times, was bom in
                    Karlsruhe, November 24, 1785. He was sent to the gymnasium of his native city,
                    and remained there until he left for the University of Halle. There he devoted
                    himself to the study of theology, as his intention was to enter the church. He
                    had the privilege of listening to the lectures of Schleiermacher and other
                    eminent theologians; but at this time in Halle F. Wolf was exercising a spell
                    over the young men and creating an enthusiasm for classical studies. August
                    Boeckh felt the spell, passed from theology to philology, and became the
                    greatest of all Wolf’s scholars. At Easter of 1806 he went to Berlin to study in
                    the seminary for secondary teachers, conducted by Gedike; but the disturbances
                    which then agitated the country sent him home. In the summer of 1807 he came out
                    as privatdocent in the University of Heidelberg, and in the autumn of the same
                    year he was appointed a professor extraordinarius. Two years after (1809) he was
                    nominated ordinary professor. In 1811 he removed to Berlin, having been
                    appointed professor of eloquence and ancient literature in the university newly
                    established there. Here he remained till his death, which took place August 3,
                    1867. He was elected a member of the Academy of Sciences of Berlin in 1814, and
                    for a long time acted as its secretary. Many of the speeches contained in his
                        <hi rend="italic">Kleine Schriften</hi> were delivered in this latter
                    capacity.</p>
                <p>Boeckh worked out the ideas of Wolf in regard to philology, and illustrated them
                    by his practice. Discarding the old notion that philology lay in a minute
                    acquaintance with words and the exercise of the critical art, he believed it to
                    be the entire knowledge of antiquity, historical and philosophical <hi
                        rend="italic">(esse earn</hi><hi rend="italic">universoe</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">antiquitatis cognitionem</hi><pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n868/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0903-0868-0851"/><hi rend="italic">historicam et</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">p)hilosopham).</hi> He divides philology into five parts:
                    first, an inquiry into public acts, with a knowledge of times and places, into
                    civil institutions, and also into law; second, an inquiry into private affairs;
                    third, an exhibition of the religions and arts of the ancient nations; fourth, a
                    history of all their moral and physical speculations and beliefs, and of their
                    literatures; and fifth, a complete explanation of the language. These ideas in
                    regard to philology Boeckh gave out in a Latin oration delivered in 1822 <hi
                        rend="italic">(Gesammelte</hi><hi rend="italic">Kleine</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Schriften,</hi> vol. i. p. 104). He repeats them in somewhat different
                    language in the speech which he delivered at the opening of the congress of
                    German philologists in 1850. He there defines philology to be the historical
                    construction of the entire life,—therefore, of all forms of culture and all the
                    productions of a people in its practical and spiritual tendencies. He allows
                    that such a work is too great for any one man.; but the very infinity of
                    subjects is the stimulus to the pursuit of truth, and men strive because they
                    have not attained (vol. ii. p. 189). Even before Boeckh had published anything
                    on this subject, his oral expositions had become widely spread, and were much
                    discussed. (Lubker, “De Partitione Philologiae,” <hi rend="italic">Gesammelte
                        Schriften zur Philologie und</hi><hi rend="italic">Poedo-</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">gogik,</hi> vol. i. p. 8.) Freund gives the following account
                    of Boeckh’s division of philology :—</p>
                <p>“Boeckh distinguishes two chief parts of philological discipline—a formal and a
                    material part. To the formal part belong only interpretation and criticism; t©
                    the material all the other disciplines, even grammar. More particularly the
                    material part embraces—I. the practical life; II. the theoretical life of the
                    ancients. I. The practical, again, falls into the two divisions of—1. Public
                    life, including (1) political history, (2) political antiquities, (3)
                    chronology, and (4) geography; 2. Private life, which is considered as (1)
                    external life, in agriculture, commerce, trades, domestic economy, and
                    metrology; (2) internal life, including marriage, education, slaves, &amp;c. II.
                    Theoretical life is divided into two parts—1. The life in which the thought of
                    man is presented externally through a symbol—worship, plastic art, music, <hi
                        rend="italic">Orchestik;</hi> 2. Life in which the thought remains pure
                    within the mind—science. In the case of the last (1) the contents, and (2) the
                    form of acquisition are distinguished. The contents lie originally in mythology,
                    out of which philosophy developed itself, and out of philosophy came the other
                    sciences, which are partly physical, including mathematics, and partly ethical.
                    The form of knowledge is language, and it must be considered first in itself, in
                    its inner structure through grammar, and then in its formation and application
                    to the various artistic forms which the history of literature has to exhibit”
                        <hi rend="italic">(Wie</hi><hi rend="italic">studirt man</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Philologie,</hi> p. 29).</p>
                <p>From 1806 till the time of his death, Boeckh’s literary activity was unceasing.
                    His principal works were—(1.) An edition of Pindar, the first volume of which
                    (1811) contains the text of the Epinician odes; a treatise <hi rend="italic"
                        >De</hi><hi rend="italic">Metris Pindari,</hi> in three books; and <hi
                        rend="italic">Notoe Criticoe</hi><hi rend="italic">:</hi> the second (1819)
                    contains the <hi rend="italic">Scholia;</hi> and part ii. of volume ii. (1821)
                    contains a Latin translation, a commentary, the fragments, and indices. It is
                    the most complete edition of Pindar that we have. But it was especially the
                    treatise <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Metris Pindari</hi> in the
                    first volume which placed Boeckh in the first rank of scholars. This treatise
                    forms an epoch in the treatment of Greek metres. In it the author threw aside
                    all attempts to determine the Greek metres by mere subjective standards,
                    pointing out at the same time the clese connection between the music and the
                    poetry of the Greeks.; He investigated minutely the nature of Greek music as far
                    as it can be ascertained, <hi rend="superscript"> r</hi> as well as all the
                    details regarding Greek musical instruments; and he explained the statements of
                    the ancient Greek writers on rhythm. In this manner he laid the foundation for a
                    new treatment of Greek metres. (2.) <hi rend="italic">Die</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Staatsaushaltung der Athener,</hi> 2 vols., Berlin, 1817 (2d improved
                    edition, Berlin, 1851), translated into English by Sir George Cornewall Lewis, 2
                    vols., Lond., .828. Boeckh shows in this work an imperfect acquaintance with the
                    principles of the modern science of political economy. The book might have been
                    written by an ancient Greek. But this imperfection does not much impair its
                    great value and extraordinary merits. Boeckh has in it investigated a subject of
                    peculiar difficulty with profound learning. He has amassed information from the
                    whole range of Greek literature, he has carefully apprized the value of the
                    information given, and he shows throughout every portion of it rare critical
                    ability and insight. Similar and supplementary to his work on the political
                    economy of Athens, was his <hi rend="italic">Urkτιnden</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >über das Seewesen des Attischen Staats,</hi> Berlin, 1840. Allied to it
                    also was his work <hi rend="italic">Metrologische Untersuchungen</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">uber</hi><hi rend="italic">Gewichte, Münzfüsse, und Maasse des
                        Altertfvums,</hi> Berlin, 1838. (3.) His third great work arose out of his
                    second. In regard to the taxes and revenue of the Athenian state he derived a
                    great deal of his most trustworthy information from inscriptions, and many of
                    these inscriptions are given in his book. It was natural, therefore, that when
                    the Berlin Academy of Sciences projected the plan of a <hi rend="italic"
                        >Corpus</hi><hi rend="italic">Inscriptionum</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Groecarwm,</hi> Boeckh should be chosen as the principal editor. This great
                    work (1825-1859) is in four volumes, the last being incomplete.* Boeckh’s
                    resources as a scholar have full scope in the treatment of these inscriptions,
                    and though a new edition is now necessary and has been begun, Boeckh’s
                    explanations of them will form the basis of all subsequent commentaries.</p>
                <p>These were Boeckh’s great works; but his activity was continually digressing into
                    widely different fields. He has gained for himself a foremost position amongst
                    investigators into ancient chronology, and his name will occupy a parallel place
                    with those of Ideler and Mommsen. His principal work on this subject was called
                        <hi rend="italic">Zur Geschichte der</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Mondcyclen</hi><hi rend="italic">der Hellenen,</hi> Leipsic, 1855; but
                    another, <hi rend="italic">Epigraphisch-chronologische Studien,</hi> 1856, and
                    several papers which he published in the <hi rend="italic">Transactions of the
                        Berlin Academy,</hi> throw light on the subject. Boeckh also occupied
                    himself with philosophy. One of his earliest papers was on the Platonic doctrine
                    of the world <hi rend="italic">(De</hi><hi rend="italic">Platonica</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">corporis</hi><hi rend="italic">mundani fabrica,</hi> 1809),
                    and <hi rend="italic">De Plat. System,</hi><hi rend="italic">coelestium</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">globorum</hi><hi rend="italic">et de versa</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">indole</hi><hi rend="italic">astronomioe Philolaioe,</hi>
                    1810. In opposition to Gruppe he denied that Plato affirmed the diurnal rotation
                    of the earth, <hi rend="italic">Untersuchungen</hi><hi rend="italic">uber
                        das</hi><hi rend="italic">kosmische</hi><hi rend="italic">System des
                        Platon,</hi> Berlin, 1852, and when in opposition to him Grote published his
                    opinions on the subjects (Plato and the Rotation of the Earth) Boeckh was ready
                    with his reply. Another of his earlier papers, and one frequently referred to,
                    was <hi rend="italic">Commentatio Academica</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">simultate</hi><hi rend="italic">guoe</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Platoni cum Xenophonte intercessisse fertur</hi> (1811).</p>
                <p>Boeckh did not do much in the way of editing the classics. We have already
                    noticed his edition of Pindar. He. also published an edition of the Antigone of
                    Sophocles, with a poetical translation. <hi rend="italic">(Antigone,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Griechisch und</hi><hi rend="italic">Deutsch:</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Nebst Abhandlungen</hi><hi rend="italic">uber</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">diese Tragödie in Ganzen und über Einzelne Stellen
                        derselben,</hi> Berlin, 1843). He also collected and arranged the fragments
                    ascribed to Philolaus (Berlin, 1819), and endeavoured to show that they were
                    genuine. The force of his arguments in this direction has, however, been
                    recently weakened by Schaarschmidt, and the genuineness of the fragments is open
                    to grave doubt.</p>
                <p>The smaller writings of Boeckh began to be collected in his lifetime. Three of
                    the volumes were published before his death, and four after <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Gesammelte kleine Schriften,</hi><hi rend="italic">7</hi> vols.,
                    1859-1873). The first two consist of orations <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n869/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0903-0869-0852"/> delivered in the university or academy of
                    Berlin, or on public occasions. The third, fourth, fifth, and sixth contain his
                    contributions to the <hi rend="italic">Transactions of the Berlin Academy,</hi>
                    ⅞nd the seventh contains his critiques. The first two are valuable among other
                    excellences from an educational point of view, and contain an exposition of many
                    sound educational principles. In them Boeckh shows himself a man of wide heart,
                    interested in the most diverse forms of investigation, an ardent patriot, and a
                    lover of justice and truth. (j. D.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
