<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0903-0682-0665-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BICYCLE (9th edition, volume 3, page 665)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098511">Roads</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:995621">Leggings</term>
                    <term ref="fast:995328">Leg</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pp32">Roads</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vd0k">Leg</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p84454w">Wheels</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n682/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BICYCLE</label>. As the derivation of the term implies, the
                    chief component parts of this machine consist of two wheels. The word is applied
                    to those two-wheeled machines which have been brought to their present state of
                    perfection for human locomotion during the past five years. Shortly after the
                    close of the great Continental war in 1815, the first bicycle was introduced
                    into England from France. It was at the best an awkward affair, composed of a
                    couple of heavy wooden wheels of equal diameter, one behind the other, and
                    joined together by a longitudinal wooden bar on which the rider’s seat was
                    fixed, the mode of propulsion being the pushing the feet against the ground.
                    That such a cumbersome method of locomotion soon died a natural death is not to
                    be wondered at. For the next fifty years no real progress was made, as various
                    kinds of levers and other attempted appliances were found too intricate. In 1869
                    Μ. Michaux of Paris conceived the idea of making the front or driving wheel much
                    larger than the hind wheel; and very soon afterwards, Μ. Magee, another
                    Parisian, still further improved bicycles by making them entirely of steel and
                    iron. The principle of crank action attached to revolving axles having also
                    become developed, the pastime of bicycling was entirely revolutionized.
                    Indiarubber tyres and strong beaks were brought into requisition to relieve
                    jolting; and now-a-days a crack racing bicycle with a driving-wheel from 55 to
                    60 inches diameter does not exceed 50 lb in weight, or about half the weight of
                    one of the old wooden machines. Tricycles have been tried, but no great amount
                    of speed will ever be got out of them until the friction and weight can be
                    materially reduced.</p>
                <p>The diameter of the front or driving wheel of the modern bicycle varies from 2 j
                    to 5 feet, according to the length of the rider’s legs. When it is meant for
                    racing, most of the component parts are lighter, and the rest for relieving the
                    legs when going down hill is dispensed with. The rider sits astride a small
                    saddle, and the motive power is obtained from the feet working the crank
                    treadles attached to the revolving axle of the driving-wheel. There being no
                    lateral support to the machine, the first thing to be learnt is balancing, after
                    which it is best to begin riding down a gentle gradient without using the
                    treadles. Steering, which is managed by a transverse handle attached to the
                    driving-wheel and placed in front of the rider, should be mastered in the same
                    manner, after which the feet and legs may be brought into play on the treadles
                    and speed gradually acquired. Falls are inevitable at first, and they are best
                    avoided by slightly turning the driving-wheel in the direction the machine is
                    inclining, not the contrary way. Care must be taken to keep all bearings,
                    &lt;fcc., oiled from time to time, in order to prevent friction and so leesen
                    speed. With the exception of skating, bicycling is the quickest means of
                    locomotion that man possesses. A fair bicyclist can outstrip a horse in a day,
                    whilst an expert can do so in an hour. Bicycling has rapidly grown in favour
                    during the past two years; and long tours are now made with the greatest ease.
                    Where the roads are fairly level, and in a tolerably good state of repair, the
                    bicycle is unsurpassed as a means of self-locomotion. In hilly and mountainous
                    countries, where there are no made roads, or where they are much broken up and
                    heavy, it is next to useless, although india-rubber tyres to a certain extent
                    relieve the jolting over rough ground. Lightness, great strength, and the best
                    of workmanship are necessary’ in the manufacture of bicycles in order to prevent
                    serious accidents. It is in the two former requisites that steel and
                    india-rubber have such an advantage over iron and wood.</p>
                <p>As a proof of the perfection to which bicycle-riding has now been brought, the
                    following best performances on record, over a prepared cindeι <hi
                        rend="superscript"> ,</hi> path, may be mentioned, viz. :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Miles.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Hours.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Min.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Sec.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Miles.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Hours.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Mln.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Seo.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>∙⅜</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>32⅜</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>10</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>34</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>41</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>i</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>19⅛</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>20</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>12</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>38</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>30</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>52</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>48</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>2</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>6</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>31</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>40</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>31</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>48</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>3</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>9</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>58</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>50</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>9</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>21</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>4</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>13</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>19⅜</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>60</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>11</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>24</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>5</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>16</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>41</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>70</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>56</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>35</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>6</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>20</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>55</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>80</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>5</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>46</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>48</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>7</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>24</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>23</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>90</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>6</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>42</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>21</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>8</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>28</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>5</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>100</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>7</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>33</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>43</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>9</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>31</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>106</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>7</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>58</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>54⅜</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The last of these, as one of the London daily journals remarked, fairly ranks as
                    “the most extraordinary performance on record of any man, animal, or machine.”
                    The distance from Tunbridge to Liverpool, 234 miles, has been accomplished in 18
                    hours 35 minutes. A hundred miles a day, over fair roads, has often been
                    achieved for several days together, and many such journeys are recorded. A ride
                    of 800 miles, from London to John O’Groats, was made in 14 days, over
                    unexceptionally hilly and heavy roads, in June 1873.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
