<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0867-0842-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SHOVELER (9th edition, volume 21, page 842)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x05xc2x">Ana</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wd3q47s">Eye</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gm81p8d">Breast</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sx6497c">Wings</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n87327d">Ducks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:808411">Anas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:919113">Eye</term>
                    <term ref="fast:952579">Head</term>
                    <term ref="fast:838255">Breast</term>
                    <term ref="fast:825070">Back</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204543">Australia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n867/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SHOVELER</label>, formerly spelt <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Shovelar,</hi> and more anciently <hi rend="smallcaps">Shovelard,</hi> a word
                    by which used to be meant the bird now almost invariably called <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Spoonbill</hi><hi rend="italic">(q.v.),</hi> but in the latter
                    half of the 16th century transferred to one hitherto generally, and in these
                    days locally, known as the Spoon-billed Duck—the <hi rend="italic">Anas
                    clypeata</hi> of Linnaeus and <hi rend="italic">Spatula</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">Rhynchaspis clypeata</hi> of modern writers. All these names refer
                    to the shape of the bird’s bill, which, combined with the remarkably long <hi
                    rend="italic">lamellae</hi> (not wholly incomparable with the “whalebone” of the
                    toothless<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n868/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0868-0843"/> Cetaceans) that beset both maxilla and mandible,
                    has been thought sufficient to remove the species from the Linnaean genus <hi
                    rend="italic">Anas.</hi> Except for the extraordinary formation of this feature,
                    which carries with it a clumsy look, the male Shoveler would pass for one of the
                    most beautiful of this generally beautiful group of birds. As it is, for bright
                    and variegated colouring, there are few of his kindred to whom he is inferior.
                    His golden eye, his dark green head, surmounting a throat of pure white and
                    succeeded by a breast and flanks of rich bay, are conspicuous; while his deep
                    brown back, white scapulars, lesser wing-coverts (often miscalled shoulders) of
                    a glaucous blue, and glossy green speculum bordered with white present a
                    wonderful contrast of the richest tints, heightened again by his bright orange
                    feet. On the other hand, the female, excepting the blue wing-coverts she has in
                    common with her mate, is habited very like the ordinary Wild-Duck, <hi
                    rend="italic">A. boscas</hi> (see vol. vii. p. 505). The Shoveler is not an
                    abundant species, and in Great Britain its distribution is local; but its
                    numbers have remarkably increased since the passing of the WildFowl Protection
                    Act in 1876,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Prior to
                    that year there was perhaps only one district in England wherein the Shoveler
                    could he said to breed regularly, and thereto only a few pairs resorted. In 1885
                    there must have been a dozen counties in which it nested, and in some of them
                    the pairs breeding might be reckoned by the score.</p></note> so that in certain
                    districts it has regained its old position as an indigenous member of the Fauna.
                    It has not ordinarily a very high northern range, but inhabits the greater part
                    of Europe, Asia, and America, passing southwards, like most of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Anatidae</hi> towards winter, constantly reaching India, Ceylon,
                    Abyssinia, the Antilles, and Central America, while it is known to have occurred
                    at that season in New Granada, and, according to Gould, in Australia. Generally
                    resembling in its habits the other freshwater Ducks, the Shoveler has one
                    peculiarity that has been rarely, if ever, mentioned, and one that is perhaps
                    correlated with the structure of its bill. It seems to be especially given to
                    feeding on the surface of the water immediately above the spot where Diving
                    Ducks <hi rend="italic">(Fuligulinae)</hi> are employing themselves beneath. On
                    such occasions a pair of Shovelers may be watched, almost for the hour together,
                    swimming in a circle, about a yard in diameter, their heads turned inwards
                    towards its centre, their bills immersed vertically in the water, and engaged in
                    sifting, by means of the long <hi rend="italic">lamellae</hi> before mentioned,
                    the floating matters that are disturbed by their submerged allies and rise to
                    the top. These gyrations are executed with the greatest ease, each Shoveler of
                    the pair merely using the outer leg to impel it on its circular course, and to
                    the observer the prettiest part of the performance is the precision with which
                    each preserves its relative distance from its comrade.</p>
                <p>Four other species of the genus <hi rend="italic">Spatula,</hi> all possessing
                    the characteristic light blue “shoulders,” have been described:—one, <hi
                    rend="italic">S. platalea,</hi> from the southern parts of South America, having
                    the head, neck, and upper back of a pale reddish brown, freckled or closely
                    spotted with dark brown, and a dull bay breast with interrupted bars; a second,
                    <hi rend="italic">S. capensis,</hi> from South Africa, much lighter in colour
                    than the female of <hi rend="italic">S. clypeata</hi>; a third and a fourth, S.
                    <hi rend="italic">rhynchotis</hi> and <hi rend="italic">S. variegata,</hi> from
                    Australia and New Zealand respectively,—these last much darker in general
                    coloration, and the males possessing a white crescentic mark between the bill
                    and the eye, very like that which is found in the South-American Blue-winged
                    Teal <hi rend="italic">(Querquedula cyanoptera),</hi> but so much resembling
                    each other that their specific distinctness has been disputed by good authority.
                    In these last two the sexual difference is well marked by the plumage; but in
                    the South-American and SouthAfrican species it would seem that both male and
                    female have much the same appearance, as is the case with so many species of the
                    restricted genus <hi rend="italic">Anas,</hi> though this cannot yet be asserted
                    with certainty. (A. N. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
