<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0479-0458-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SCHUBERT, Franz Peter (9th edition, volume 21, page
                    458)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4086351k">Larks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pp6h">Conviction</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sn01992">Monarchs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3kb0r">Vines</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2ch0v">Music</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68967">Songs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r785w31">Paper</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90251t">Opera</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1030269">Music</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1030814">Musicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126120">Songs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:992706">Larks</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n479/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SCHUBERT, <hi rend="smallcaps">Franz Peter</hi></label>
                    (1797-1828), composer of vocal and instrumental music, was born at Vienna 31st
                    January 1797. For the foundation of his general education he was indebted to his
                    father, a schoolmaster in the Leopoldstadt; but the beauty of his voice
                    attracted so much attention that in 1808 he was received into the choir of the
                    imperial chapel, and during the five years which followed he was taught to sing
                    and to play the violin in the choristers’ school called the “Convict.” No
                    attempt seems to have been made to teach him composition, but, through the kind
                    intervention of an older chorister, he was supplied with music-paper, and
                    thenceforward he wrote incessantly, as his fancy dictated, without any help
                    whatever, always carefully signing and dating his MSS., which extend back as far
                    as 1810. When his voice broke in 1813 Schubert left the “Convict,” and, to avoid
                    the conscription, taught for three years in his father’s school. This, however,
                    in nowise damped his zeal for composition. Even at this early period his
                    invention was inexhaustible and the rapidity of his pen almost incredible. In
                    1815 he composed 2 symphonies, 5 operas, and no less than 137 songs (67 of which
                    have been published), besides a multitude of other important pieces. Yet so
                    little was his genius appreciated that when in 1816 he applied for an
                    appointment at a Government music school, with a salary equal to about twenty
                    guineas a year, he was rejected as “imperfectly qualified.”</p>
                <p>In 1818 Count Johann Eszterhazy secured the services of Schubert as resident
                    teacher of music to his daughters, for one of whom the young composer has been
                    supposed —on very insufficient authority—to have entertained a romantic, and of
                    course utterly hopeless, affection. The appointment was of great importance to
                    him, for he was poor, almost to starvation; yet it led to no permanent
                    improvement in his prospects: in fact his life was one long bitter
                    disappointment from beginning to end. He wrote on, year after year, producing
                    music of indescribable beauty in such enormous quantities that but for the dated
                    MSS. we should refuse to believe the accounts transmitted to us by his
                    biographers. He wrote because, when his genius inspired him with an idea, he
                    could not refrain. Yet he scarcely ever looked at his compositions after they
                    were finished, and very rarely heard any of them performed. Very little of his
                    dramatic music was given to the world. Two little operettas— <hi rend="italic"
                    >Die Zwillingsbrüder</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Die Zauberharfe—</hi> barely
                    escaped failure in 1820; and the beautiful incidental music to Madame von
                    Chezy’s <hi rend="italic">Rosamunde</hi> survived but two representations in
                    1823. Of his greater operas not one was placed upon the stage during his
                    lifetime. With his songs he was more fortunate. Many of them were published, and
                    their fresh bright melodies were irresistible. They were produced by hundreds,
                    and with a rapidity bordering upon the miraculous. Among the MSS. seven or eight
                    may be found dated on the same day; yet even in these he never repeated himself:
                    every one was the result of a new inspiration, committed to paper at the moment
                    of conception, laid aside immediately afterwards, and so completely forgotten
                    that he has been known to ask who was the composer of one of his own <hi
                    rend="italic">Lieder</hi> not very long after he had composed it. And this
                    wonderful facility of production led to no unworthy form of treatment. The
                    original MS. of <hi rend="italic">Hark, Hark, the Lark</hi> was written at a
                    “beer-garden,” on the back of a bill of fare, the moment after the composer had
                    read the words for the first time; and there are strong reasons for believing
                    that <hi rend="italic">Who is Sylvia?—</hi> one of the most perfectly finished
                    songs on record—and <hi rend="italic">Come, thou Monarch of the Vine,</hi> were
                    produced on the same occasion. But the success of the songs did not make
                    Schubert a prosperous man. All his life long he suffered from grinding poverty.
                    Though he received an actual commission to write his greatest dramatic work, <hi
                    rend="italic">Fierabras,</hi> for the court theatre at Vienna, it was rejected
                    in 1824 for the weakness of its <hi rend="italic">libretto.</hi> Once, and once
                    only, a chance seemed open to him. He was accepted in 1826 as a candidate for
                    the vacant post of conductor to the court theatre, and requested to compose some
                    music as a test of his powers. At the rehearsal the part he had designed for the
                    prima donna was found too trying for her voice, and he was requested to alter
                    it. “I will alter nothing,” said Schubert; and his refusal to listen to reason
                    cost him the coveted appointment.</p>
                <p>Of Schubert’s ten symphonies not one made its mark during his lifetime; yet the
                    stamp of genius is upon these as plainly as upon his songs. It is true that in
                    works of large dimensions genius loses half its power if unsupported by
                    learning; and Schubert was not learned enough to turn his inspirations to the
                    best account. His ideas came so quickly that the knowledge he possessed was not
                    sufficient to enable him to arrange them in that perfect order which forms the
                    chief charm of the symphonies of Mozart and Beethoven. And the same element of
                    weakness is discernible in his sonatas and other long pieces of chamber music.
                    But these are all true works of genius, precious and imperishable.</p>
                <p>It was not to be wondered at that under his heavy trials Schubert’s health failed
                    rapidly. After recovering from more than one serious attack of illness, he was
                    seized with a sudden access of delirium while at supper on 13th October 1828;
                    and on 19th November he died, leaving behind him a few clothes and other
                    possessions, which were officially valued at sixty-three Vienna florins ( = £2,
                    10s.). His grave at the Ortsfriedhof, bought by the scanty savings of his
                    brother Ferdinand, lies within a few feet of that of Beethoven.</p>
                <p>Schubert’s works, now (1886) in course of publication in a complete series by
                    Messrs Breitkopf &amp; Härtel of Leipsic, include 18 dramatic pieces, 8 sacred
                    compositions, 10 symphonies, 24 pianoforte sonatas, a vast collection of songs,
                    of which 457 are already published, and a multitude of other works which are too
                    numerous to mention.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
