<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0246-0227-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SALONICA, or Saloniki (9th edition, volume 21, page
                    227)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1103658">Saints</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1159314">Turkeys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:938950">Gates</term>
                    <term ref="fast:838614">Bricks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1155691">Travelers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1153279">Towers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1120771">Slavs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0399k">Towers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w669847">Slavs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4804xr51">Mohammedans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s756m31">Saints</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4222rc91">Turkey</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208963">Turkey</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1212489">Bulgaria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239717">Alps</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205085">Romania</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n246/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SALONICA, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Saloniki</hi></label>
                    (Ital. <hi rend="italic">Salonicco,</hi> Turkish <hi rend="italic">Selanik,</hi>
                    Slav. <hi rend="italic">Solun,</hi> the ancient <hi rend="italic"
                    >Thessalonica),</hi> during the Roman empire the capital of the province of
                    Macedonia, and still one of the most important cities of European Turkey, the
                    chief town of an extensive vilayet which includes the sanjaks of Salonica,
                    Serres, Drama, and Monastir, and has an aggregate population of 1,500,000.
                    Salonica lies on the west side of the Chalcidic peninsula, at the head of the
                    Gulf of Salonica <hi rend="italic">(Sinus Thermaicus),</hi> on a fine bay whose
                    southern edge is formed by the Calamerian heights, while its northern and
                    western side is the broad alluvial plain produced by the discharge of the Vardar
                    and the Inje-Karasu, the principal rivers of western Macedonia. Built partly on
                    the low ground along the edge of the bay and partly on the hill to the north (a
                    compact mass of mica schist), the city with its white houses enclosed by white
                    walls runs up along natural ravines to the castle of the Seven Towers
                    (Heptapyrgion), and is rendered picturesque by numerous domes and minarets and
                    the foliage of elms, cypresses, and mulberry trees. The hill of the</p>
                <p>Heptapyrgion is dominated by a second and that by a third eminence towards the
                    north. The commercial quarter of the town, lying naturally to the north-west,
                    towards the great valleys by which the inland traffic is conveyed, is now
                    pierced by broad and straight streets paved with lava; and the quay extends from
                    the north-west of the city for four-fifths of a mile to the Kauli-Kule (Tower of
                    Blood), or as it is now called Ak-Kule (White Tower). The old Via Egnatia
                    traverses the city from what is now the Vardar Gate to the Calamerian Gate. The
                    houses are for the most part insignificant wooden erections covered with lime or
                    mud. Two Roman triumphal arches used to span the Via Egnatia. The arch near the
                    Vardar Gate—a massive stone structure probably erected after the time of
                    Vespasian— was destroyed about 1867 to furnish material for repairing the city
                    walls; an imperfect inscription from it is now preserved in the British
                    Museum.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See <hi
                    rend="italic">Trans. Roy. Soc. Lit.,</hi> vol. viii., new series,
                    1878.</p></note> The other arch, popularly called the arch of Constantine, but
                    by Leake assigned to the reign of Theodosius, consisted of three archways built
                    of brick and faced with marble. It is now in a very dilapidated state.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See Newton’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Travels, &amp;c., in the Levant,</hi> vol. i. p. 122.</p></note> A
                    third example of Roman architecture —the remains of a white marble portico
                    supposed to have formed the entrance to the hippodrome—is known by the
                    Judaeo-Spanish designation of Las Incantadas, from the eight Caryatides in the
                    upper part of the structure.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>See Stuart’s <hi rend="italic">Athens,</hi> vol. iii. pl.
                    45, for engraving.</p></note> The conspicuous mosques of Salonica have nearly
                    all an early Christian origin; the remarkable preservation of their mural
                    decorations makes them very important for the history of Byzantine architecture.
                    The principal are those dedicated to St Sophia, St George, and St Demetrius.</p>
                <p>St Sophia (Aya Sofia), formerly the cathedral, and probably erected by
                    Justinian’s architect Anthemius, was converted into a mosque in 1589. It is
                    cased with slabs of white marble. The whole length of the interior is 110 feet.
                    The nave, forming a Greek cross, is surmounted by a hemispherical dome, the 600
                    square yards of which are covered with a rich mosaic representing the Ascension.
                    St Demetrius, which is probably older than the time of Justinian, consists of a
                    long nave (divided into three bays by massive square piers) and two side aisles,
                    each terminating eastward in an atrium the full height of the nave, in a style
                    not known to occur in any other church. The columns of the aisles are half the
                    height of those in the nave. The internal decoration is all produced by slabs of
                    different-coloured marbles. St George’s, conjecturally assigned by Messrs Pullan
                    and Texier to the reign of Constantine, is circular in plan, measuring
                    internally 80 feet in diameter. The external wall is 18 feet thick, and at the
                    angles of an inscribed octagon are chapels formed in the thickness of the wall,
                    and roofed with waggon-headed vaults visible on the exterior; the eastern
                    chapel, however, is enlarged and developed into a bema and apse projecting
                    beyond the circle, and the western and southern chapels constitute the two
                    entrances of the building. The dome, 72 yards in circumference, is covered
                    throughout its entire surface of 800 square yards with what is the largest work
                    in ancient mosaic that has come down to us, representing a series of fourteen
                    saints standing in the act of adoration in front of temples and colonnades. The
                    Eski Juma, or Old Mosque, is another interesting basilica, evidently later than
                    Constantine, with side aisles and. an apse without side chapels. The church of
                    the Holy Apostles and that of St Elias also deserve mention. Of the secular
                    buildings, the Caravanserai, usually attributed to Amurath II., probably dates
                    from Byzantine times.</p>
                <p>The prosperity of Salonica has all along been largely that of a commercial city.
                    During the Christian centuries before the Mohammedan conquest the patron saint
                    of the city was also the saint of a great market or fair to which merchants came
                    from all parts of the Mediterranean, and even from countries beyond the Alps. At
                    the beginning of the present century a large export trade was carried on in
                    woollen and cotton fabrics, white and red yarns, grain, wool, tobacco, yellow
                    berries, silk fabrics, sponges, &amp;c.; and silk gauze was manufactured in the
                    city. Direct British trade with Salonica began after the Greek war of
                    independence. Woven fabrics are at present imported from England, Austria,
                    Germany, Switzerland, and Italy; sugar mainly from Austria; coffee from South
                    America (partly direct); petroleum from America and Russia; soap from Greece and
                    Crete; metal goods from England, France, and Austria; and coal from England. The
                    exports com-<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n247/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0247-0228"/> prise cereals (wheat, barley, oats, maize, rye),
                    tobacco, wool, cotton, poppy seed, opium, cocoons, prunes, and timber. In 1884
                    the industrial establishments were steam flour-mills, a cottonspinning factory
                    (employing 500 hands and sending its goods to Constantinople, Smyrna, and
                    Beyrout), a distillery, several large soap-works, a nail factory, an
                    iron-bedstead factory, and a number of brick and tile works.</p>
                <p>In Salonica the several nationalities have schools of their own: the Greeks, for
                    example, have a normal school, a gymnasium, and nine other schools (one for
                    girls); and even the Bulgarians, though their members are comparatively small,
                    have two normal schools. The Jewish community (about 50,000) is of Spanish
                    origin, and still preserves its Judaeo-Spanish written in Hebrew characters.
                    Besides their own schools they have the advantage of a large school supported by
                    the Jewish Mission of the Established Church of Scotland (instituted about
                    1860). The total population of Salonica was estimated by Tozer about 1865 as
                    60,000. It has since increased probably to 90,000 or 100,000. The railway opened
                    to Kiuprili (136¾ miles) in 1873 is now extended 75 miles to Mitrovitza.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">History.—</hi> The older name of Thessalonica was Therma (in
                    allusion to the hot-springs of the neighbourhood). It was a military and
                    commercial station on a main line of communication between Rome and the East,
                    and had reached its zenith before the seat of empire was transferred to
                    Constantinople. It became a Roman <hi rend="italic">colonia</hi> in the middle
                    of the 3d century, and in the later defence of the ancient civilization against
                    the barbarian inroads it played a considerable part. In 390 Thessalonica was the
                    scene of the dreadful massacre perpetrated by command of Theodosius. Constantine
                    repaired the port, and probably enriched the town with some of its buildings.
                    During the iconoclastic reigns of terror it stood on the defensive, and
                    succeeded in saving the artistic treasures of its churches: in the 9th century
                    Joseph, one of its bishops, died in chains for his defence of image-worship. In
                    the 7th century the Slavonic tribes strove to capture the city, but in vain even
                    when it was thrown into confusion by a terrible earthquake which lasted several
                    days. It was the attempt made to transfer the whole Bulgarian trade to
                    Thessalonica that in the close of the 9th century caused the invasion of the
                    empire by Simeon of Bulgaria. In 904 the Saracens from the Cyrenaica took the
                    place by storm; the public buildings were grievously injured, and the
                    inhabitants to the number of 22,000 were carried off and sold as slaves
                    throughout the countries of the Mediterranean. In 1185 the Normans of Sicily,
                    having landed at Dyrrliachium and marched across country, took Thessalonica
                    after a ten days’ siege, and perpetrated endless barbarities, of which
                    Eustathius, then bishop of the see, has left us an account. In 1204 Baldwin,
                    conqueror of Constantinople, conferred the kingdom of Thessalonica on Boniface,
                    marquis of Montferrat; but eighteen years later Theodore, despot of Epirus, one
                    of the natural enemies of the new kingdom, took the city and had himself there
                    crowned by the patriarch of Macedonian Bulgaria. On the death of Demetrius (who
                    had been supported in his endeavour to recover his father’s throne by Pope
                    Honorius III.) the empty title of king of Salonica was adopted by several
                    claimants. In 1266 the house of Burgundy received a grant of the titular kingdom
                    from Baldwin II. when he was titular emperor, and it was sold by Eudes IV. to
                    Philip of Tarentum, titular emperor of Romania in 1320. The Venetians, to whom
                    the city was transferred by one of the Palaeologi, were in power when Sultan
                    Amurath appeared, and on the 1st of May 1430, in spite of the desperate
                    resistance of the inhabitants, took the city, which had thrice previously been
                    in the hands of the Turks. The body of St Demetrius, the patron saint, who from
                    the time of his death under Maximian in the 4th century had exercised a
                    marvellous influence on the popular imagination, was hacked to pieces, though
                    even the Mohammedans attributed virtue to the famous oil from which the saint
                    obtained the title of Myroblete. In 1876 the French and German consuls at
                    Thessalonica were massacred by the Turkish populace.</p>
                <p>Besides Tafel’s monograph, <hi rend="italic">Dissertatio de Thetsalonica</hi>
                    (Berlin, 1839), see Holland's <hi rend="italic">Travels</hi> (1815); Grisebaeh,
                    <hi rend="italic">Rumelien und Brussa,</hi> 1839; Bowen’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Mount Athos, Thessaly, and Epirus</hi> (1852); Boeckh, <hi rend="italic">C. I.
                    G.,</hi> vol. ii.; Texier and Fullan, <hi rend="italic">Byzantine
                    Architecture</hi> (1864); Tozer, <hi rend="italic">Highlands of Turkey,</hi>
                    1869.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
