<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0270-0251-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SAMOYEDES (9th edition, volume 21, page 251)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47p8tp2j">Ugrians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pg1hr5g">Motors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40p0x090">Tunguses</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4nv99d8g">Huns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h708690">Ostiaks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g08p">Groups</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1042778">Obi</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028189">Motors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:964118">Huns</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028366">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n270/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SAMOYEDES</label>, a Ural-Altaic stock, scattered in small
                    groups over an immense area, from the Altai Mountains down the basins of the Obi
                    and Yenisei, and along the shores of the Arctic Ocean from the mouth of the
                    latter river to the White Sea. They may be subdivided into two main groups. (A)
                    Those inhabiting the southern parts of the governments of Tomsk and Yeniseisk
                    have been so much under Tartar influence as to be with difficulty separated from
                    the Tartars; their sub-groups are the Kamasin Tartars, the Kaibals, the Motors,
                    the Beltirs, the Karagasses, and the Samoyedes of the middle Obi. (B) Those
                    inhabiting the subarctic region form three separate sub-groups:—(a) the Yuraks
                    in the coast-region from the Yenisei to the White Sea; (6) the Tavghi Samoyedes,
                    between the Yenisei and the Khatanga; (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) the Ostiak
                    Samoyedes, intermingled with Ostiaks, to the south of the others, in the forest
                    regions of Tobolsk and Yeniseisk. Their whole number may be estimated at from
                    20,000 to 25,000.</p>
                <p>The proper place of the Samoyedes among the Ural-Altaians is very difficult to
                    determine. As to their present name, signifying in its present Russian spelling
                    “self-eaters,” many ingenious theories have been advanced, but the current one,
                    proposed by Schrenk, who derived the name “Samo-yedes” from “Syroyadtsy,” or
                    “raw-eaters,” leaves much to be desired. Perhaps the etymology ought to be
                    sought in quite another direction, namely, in the likeness to Suomi. The names
                    assumed by the Samoyedes themselves are Hazovo and Nyänyäz. The Ostiaks know
                    them under the names of Orghoy, or Workho, both of which recall the Ugrians; the
                    name of Hui is also in use among the Ostiaks, and that of Yaron among the
                    Zyrians.</p>
                <p>The language now spoken by the Samoyedes is, like the Finnish languages,
                    agglutinative, but in both lexicon and grammar it differs so widely from these
                    that Prof. Ahlqvist does not regard the similarity as greater than, for
                    instance, that between Swedish and Persian. Much remains to be done for the
                    study of Samoyedic, but it may be regarded as the most remote cousin of the
                    Ugrian. It is a sonorous speech, pleasant to the ear. No fewer than three
                    separate dialects and a dozen sub-dialects are known in it.</p>
                <p>The conclusions deducible from their anthropological features— apart from the
                    general difficulty of arriving at safe conclusions on this ground alone, on
                    account of the variability of the ethnological type under various conditions of
                    life—are also rather indefinite. The Samoyedes are recognized as having the face
                    more flattened than undoubtedly Finnish stocks; their eyes are narrower, their
                    complexion and hair darker. Zuyeff describes them as like the Tunguses, with
                    flattened nose, thick lips, little beard, and black, hard hair. At first sight
                    they may be mistaken for Ostiaks,— especially on the obi; but they are
                    undoubtedly different. Castrén considers them as a mixture of Ugrians with
                    Mongolians, and M. Zograf as brachycephalic Mongolians. Quatrefages classes
                    them, together with the Voguls, as two families of the Ugrian sub-branch, this
                    last, together with the Sabmis (Laponians), forming part of the Ugrian or Boreal
                    branch of the yellow or Mongolic race.</p>
                <p>It is certain that formerly the Samoyedes occupied the Altai Mountains, whence
                    they were driven northwards by Turco-Tartars —probably at the time of the rise
                    of the empire of the Huns, that is, before the present era. Their further and
                    later migration towards the north may be said to be going on still. Thus, the
                    Kaibals left the Sayan Mountains and took possession of the Abakan steppe
                    (Minusinsk region), abandoned by the Kirghizes, in the earlier years of last
                    century, and in north-eastern Russia the Zyrians are still driving the Samoyedes
                    farther north, towards the Arctic coast. Since the researches of Schrenk it may
                    be considered as settled that in historical times the Samoyedes were inhabitants
                    of the so-called Ugria in the Northern Urals, while it would result from M.
                    Radloff’s extensive researches that the numberless graves containing remains of
                    the Bronze Period which are scattered throughout West Siberia, on the Altai, and
                    on the Yenisei in the Minusinsk region, are relics of a nation which he
                    considers as Ugro-Samoyedes. This nation, very numerous at that epoch,—which
                    preceded the Iron-Period civilization of the Turco-Tartars,—were pretty well
                    acquainted with mining; the remains of their mines, sometimes 50 feet deep, and
                    of the furnaces where they melted copper, tin, and gold, are very numerous;
                    their weapons of a hard bronze, their pots (one of which weighs 75 lb), and
                    their melted and polished bronze and golden decorations testify to a high
                    development of artistic feeling and industrial skill, strangely contrasting with
                    the low level reached by their earthenware. They were not nomads, but
                    husbandmen, and their irrigation canals are still to be seen. They kept horses
                    (though in small numbers), sheep, and goats, but no traces of their rearing
                    horned cattle have yet been found. The Turkish invasion of southern Siberia by
                    the Tukus, Khagases, and Uigurs, which took place in the 5th century, drove them
                    farther north and probably reduced most of them to slavery,—these slaves seeming
                    to have taught mining to their masters.</p>
                <p>At present they are disappearing, and have almost entirely lost their earlier
                    civilization. M. Polyakoff quite rightly observes that the Samoyedes, who now
                    maintain themselves by hunting and fishing on the lower obi, partly mixed in the
                    south with Ostiaks, recall the condition of the inhabitants of France and
                    Germany at the epoch of the reindeer. Clothed in skins, like the troglodytes of
                    the Weser, they make use of the same implements in bone and stone, eat
                    carnivorous animals—the wolf included—and cherish the same superstitions (of
                    which those regarding the teeth of the bear are perhaps the most characteristic)
                    as were current among the Stone-Period inhabitants of western Europe. Their
                    heaps of reindeer horns and skulls—memorials of religious ceremonies—are exactly
                    similar to those dating from the similar period of civilization in northern
                    Germany. Their huts often resemble the well-known stone huts of the Esquimaux;
                    their graves are mere boxes left in the tundra. The religion is fetichism mixed
                    with Shamanism, the shaman <hi rend="italic">(tadji-bei)</hi> being a
                    representative of the great divinity, the Num. The Yalmal peninsula, where they
                    find so great facilities for hunting, is especially venerated by the Obi Ostiak
                    Samoyedes, and there they have one of their chief idols, Khese. They are more
                    independent than the Ostiaks, less yielding in character, although as hospitable
                    as their neighbours. Reduced almost to slavery by Russian merchants, and brought
                    to the extreme of misery by the use of ardent spirits, they are disappearing
                    rapidly, small-pox completing the work of destruction. They still maintain the
                    high standard of honesty mentioned by historical documents; and, while the
                    Russians plunder even the stores of their shamans, the Samoyedes never will take
                    anything left in the tundra or about the houses by their “civilized” neighbours.
                    The Yurak Samoyedes are courageous and warlike; they offered armed resistance to
                    the Russian invaders, and it is only since the beginning of the century that
                    they have paid tribute. The exact number of the Ostiak Samoyedes is not known;
                    the Tavghi Samoyedes may number about 1000, and the Yuraks, mixed with the
                    former, are estimated at 6000 in obdorsk (about 150 settled), 5000 in European
                    Russia in the tundras of the Mezen, and about 350 in Yeniseisk.</p>
                <p>Of the southern Samoyedes, who are completely Tartarized, the Beltirs (3070 in
                    1859) live by agriculture and cattle-breeding in the Abakan steppe. They profess
                    Christianity, and speak a language closely resembling that of the Sagai Tartars.
                    The Kaibals, or Koibals, can hardly be distinguished from the Minusinsk Tartars,
                    and support themselves by rearing cattle. Castrén considers that three of their
                    stems are of Ostiak origin, the remainder being Samoyedic. The Kamasins, in the
                    Kansk district of Yeniseisk, are either herdsmen or agriculturists. They speak
                    the Samoyede language, with an admixture of Tartar words, and some of their
                    stems contain a large Tartar element. The very interesting nomadic tribe of
                    Karagasses, in the Sayan Mountains, is quite disappearing; the few
                    representatives of this formerly much more numerous stem are rapidly losing
                    their anthropological features, their Turkish language, and their distinctive
                    dress. The Motors are now little more than a memory. One portion of the tribe
                    emigrated to China and was there exterminated; the remainder have disappeared
                    among the Tuba Tartars and the Soyotes. The Samoyedes on the Obi in Tomsk may
                    number about 7000; they have adopted the Russian manner of life, but have
                    difficulty in carrying on agriculture, and are a poverty-stricken population
                    with little prospect of holding their own.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
