<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0410-0389-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SCHELDT, or Schelde (9th edition, volume 21, page
                    389)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:927691">Florin</term>
                    <term ref="fast:841533">Bulls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:845230">Canals</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r76k">Martins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tv2w">Canals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f39x">Mouth</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210278">Belgium</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n410/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SCHELDT, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Schelde</hi></label> (Fr.
                    <hi rend="italic">Escaut,</hi> Lat. <hi rend="italic">Scaldis,</hi> Ο. Dutch <hi
                    rend="italic">ScJιoude</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Schouwe),</hi> a river of
                    north-west Europe, belonging for 75 miles of its course to France, 137 to
                    Belgium, and 37 to the Netherlands. Rising at a height of 295 feet above the
                    sea, in a small lake (7 square miles) at the old abbey of St Martin, near
                    Catelet, in the French department of Aisne (Picardy), it becomes navigable by
                    the junction of the St Quentin Canal, below Catelet, and passes by Cambray,
                    Denain (where it receives the Selle), Valenciennes, at the mouth of the Rouelle,
                    Condé, at the mouth of the Haisne or Henne, and Chateau l’Abbaye, at the mouth
                    of the Scarpe. Entering Belgium between Mortagne and Hollain, it continues by
                    Fontenoy, Tournay, and Oudenarde to Ghent, where it is joined by the Lys from
                    the left, and by the canals which unite this town with Sas and Bruges. At Ghent
                    the tide rises 3 ½ feet and lasts for four hours; and it would ascend much
                    farther were it not for sluices. But the river, instead of proceeding straight
                    towards the sea, as it appears to have done perhaps as late as the time of
                    Charlemagne, makes a great bend towards the east to Dendermonde (the mouth of
                    the Dender) and Antwerp, whence it again turns northwest and loses itself in the
                    estuaries among the islands of</p>
                <p>Zealand. The whole of the lowlands to the north of Ghent are so intersected with
                    canals, and the natural channels are so intermingled with those partially or
                    entirely artificial, that it is impossible to discover with certainty what has
                    been the real history of the lower course of the Scheldt.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Bylandt, Belpaire, Renard, and Wauvermans
                    impugn, and Des Roches, Vifquain, Van Raemdonck and Verstraete maintain, the
                    existence within historic times of a direct main-river channel from Ghent
                    northward to the sea.</p></note> The Hont or Western Scheldt, the principal
                    estuary by which nearly all Belgium commerce is conveyed, was probably opened up
                    by a storm in 1173, and about 1058 must have been a mere narrow creek. The
                    Eastern Scheldt, which then received most of the river, has gradually diminished
                    in importance, and since the construction of the railway bridge across it
                    between the mainland and South Beveland in 1867 has become completely obstructed
                    with sands. At Antwerp the depth at high water is 49 feet.</p>
                <p>Between 1648 and 1792 the Dutch closed the mouths of the Scheldt against foreign
                    commerce. The emperor Joseph of Austria, at that time ruler of Antwerp,
                    protested against this action in 1783, but in 1784, by the treaty of
                    Fontainebleau, he recognized, in return for concessions of territory and 9⅜
                    million florins, the right of the Dutch to adhere to the terms of the peace of
                    Westphalia. In 1792 by conquest of Dumouriez, and in 1795 by treaty between
                    France and Holland, the Scheldt was declared open. During the union of Holland
                    and Belgium the question naturally lay in abeyance. When Belgium became
                    independent (1839) Holland so far resumed her exclusive policy, but in 1863 the
                    dues which she was allowed to levy by the treaty of separation were capitalized
                    by Belgium paying 17,141,640 florins, a sum which was largely repaid to Belgium
                    by twenty other countries who felt they had an interest in the free navigation
                    of the Scheldt. Great Britain’s share was 8,782,320 francs.</p>
                <p>See Vifquain, <hi rend="italic">Des Voies Navigables en Belgique,</hi> 1842;
                    Wauvermans, “Sur les Variations de l’Escaut au XVI. siècle,” in <hi
                    rend="italic">Bull. de la Soc. de Géogr. d’Anvers,</hi> vol. i.; Raemdonck,
                    “L’Hist. du Cours de l’Escaut,” and Verstraete, “Cours Primitif de l'Escaut,"
                    both in <hi rend="italic">Bull. de la Soc. Belge de Géogr.,</hi> 1878.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
