<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0159-0142-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SA'DÍ (9th edition, volume 21, page 142)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1025421">Mongols</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944037">God</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944223">Gods</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bg2hh25">Mongols</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w669j0w">Turkomans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4833n637">Rose</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bh84">Gardens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z196">Love</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208757">Syria</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n159/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SA'DÍ</label>, generally called <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Muṣliḥ-uddín</hi>, but more correctly <hi rend="smallcaps">Musharrif-iddín b.
                    Muṣliḥ-uddín</hi>, the greatest didactic poet and the most popular writer of
                    Persia, was born about 1184 (580 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.h.)</hi> in Shíráz,
                    where his father, 'Abdalláh, a man of practical religion and good common sense,
                    who impressed upon his son from early childhood the great maxims of doing good
                    and fearing nobody, was in the service of the Turkoman race of the Salgharides
                    or Atábegs of Fárs. The fifth ruler of this dynasty, Sa'd b. Zengí, who ascended
                    the throne in 1195 (591 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.h.),</hi> conceived a great
                    affection for young Musharrif-uddín and enabled him, after the premature death
                    of his father, to pursue his studies in the famous medreseh of Baghdad, the
                    Nizámiyyah, where he remained about thirty years (1196-1224). Strict college
                    discipline and severe theological studies repressed for a long time the inborn
                    cheerfulness and joviality of his nature; but his poetical genius, which rapidly
                    developed, kept alive in him, amid all the privations of an austere life, the
                    elasticity of youth, and some of his “early odes,” in which he praises the
                    pleasures of life and the sweetness of love, were no doubt composed during his
                    stay in Baghdad. At any rate his literary fame had already spread about 1210
                    (606 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.h.)</hi> as far as Kásh-gar in Turkistán, which the
                    young poet (who in honour of his patron had assumed the name of Sa'di) visited
                    in his twenty-sixth or twenty-seventh year. After mastering all the dogmatic
                    disciplines of the Islamitic faith he turned his attention first to practical
                    philosophy, and later on to the more ideal tenets of Sufic pantheism, under the
                    spiritual guidance of the famous sheikh Shiháb-uddín 'Umar Suhrawardí (died
                    1234; 632 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.h.).</hi> Between 1220 and 1225 he paid a visit
                    to a friend in Ispahán, went from there to Damascus, and returned to IspahAn
                    just at the time of the inroads of the Mongols, when the Atábeg Sa'd had been
                    deposed by the victorious ruler of Kirmán,<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n160/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0160-0143"/> Ghiyáth-uddín (1223). Sadly grieved by the
                    misfortune of his generous patron and disgusted with the miserable state to
                    which Persia had been reduced, Sa'di started in 1224 or 1225 on his way to
                    India, thus entering on the second period of his life—that of his wanderings
                    (1225- 1255). He proceeded <hi rend="italic">via</hi> Balkh, Ghazni, and the
                    Punjab to Gujrát, on the western coast of which he visited the famous shrine of
                    Síwa in Pattan-Sumanát, and met with a remarkable adventure. Having seen the
                    statue of the god lifting up its hands to heaven every morning at sunrise, he
                    discovered that a priest, hidden behind the image, wrought the miracle by means
                    of a cord; but, being caught in the very act of watching the performance, he had
                    no alternative but to hurl his pursuer into a deep well and to escape at full
                    speed,—not, however, until he had smashed the detested statue. After a prolonged
                    stay in Delhi, where he acquired the knowledge of Hindústání which he afterwards
                    turned to account in several of his poems—just as a number of excellent Arabic
                    kasídas bear witness to his fluency in that idiom which he had learnt in
                    Baghdad—he sailed for Yemen. In San'á, the capital of Yemen, the loss of a
                    beloved child (when he had married is not known) threw him into deep melancholy,
                    from which only a new adventurous expedition into Abyssinia on the opposite
                    African shore and a pilgrimage to Mecca and Medina could again rouse him. Thence
                    he directed his steps towards Syria and lived as a renowned sheikh for a
                    considerable time in Damascus, which he had once already visited. There and in
                    Baalbec he added to his literary renown that of a first-rate pulpit orator.
                    Specimens of his spiritual addresses are preserved in the five homilies (on the
                    fugitiveness of human life, on faith and fear of God, on love towards God, on
                    rest in God, and on the search for God) which usually form the second risálah or
                    prose treatise in Sa'di’s complete works. At last weary of Damascus he withdrew
                    into the desert near Jerusalem and led a solitary wandering life, till one day
                    he was taken captive by a troop of Frankish soldiers, brought to Tripoli, and
                    condemned to forced labour in the trenches of the fortress. After enduring
                    countless hardships, he was eventually rescued by a rich friend in Aleppo, who
                    paid his ransom, and moreover gave him his daughter in marriage. But Sa'di,
                    unable to live with his quarrelsome wife, set out on new travels, first to North
                    Africa and then through the length and breadth of Asia Minor and the adjoining
                    countries. Not until he had passed his seventieth year did he return to Shíráz
                    (about 1255; 653 A.H.). Finding the place of his birth tranquil and prosperous
                    under the wise rule of Abúbakr b. Sa'd, the son of his old patron (1226-1260;
                    623-658 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.h.),</hi> the aged poet took up his permanent
                    abode, interrupted only by repeated pilgrimages to Mecca, in a little hermitage
                    outside the town, in the midst of a charming garden, and devoted the remainder
                    of his life to Súfic contemplation and poetical composition. Sa'di died at
                    Shíráz in 1292 (691 A.H.) according to Hamdalláh Mustaufí (who wrote only forty
                    years later), or in December 1291 (690 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.h.),</hi> at the
                    age of 110 lunar years.</p>
                <p>The experience of the world gained during his travels, his intimate acquaintance
                    with the various countries he had visited, his insight into human character, its
                    grandeur and its littleness, which a thirty years’ intercourse with men of all
                    ranks and of many nationalities had fully matured, together with an inborn
                    loftiness of thought and the purest moral standard, made it easy for Sa'di to
                    compose in the short space of three years his two masterpieces, which have
                    immortalized his name, the <hi rend="italic">Bústán</hi> or “Fruit-garden”
                    (1257) and the <hi rend="italic">Gulistán</hi> or “Rose-garden” (1258), both
                    dedicated to the reigning Atábeg Abúbakr. The former, also called <hi
                    rend="italic">Sa'dínáma,</hi> is a kind of didactic epopee in ten chapters and
                    double-rhymed verses, which passes in review the highest philosophical and
                    religious questions, not seldom in the very spirit of Christianity, and abounds
                    with sound ethical maxims and matchless gems of transcendental speculation. The
                    latter is a prose work of a similar tendency in eight chapters, interspersed
                    with numerous verses and illustrated, like the <hi rend="italic">Bústán,</hi> by
                    a rich store of clever tales and charming anecdotes; it discusses more or less
                    the same topics as the larger work, but has acquired a much greater popularity
                    in both the East and the West, owing to its easier and more varied style, its
                    attractive lessons of practical wisdom, and its numerous bon-mots. But Sa'di’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Diwán,</hi> or collection of lyrical poetry, far surpasses the
                    <hi rend="italic">Bústán</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Gulistán,</hi> at any rate
                    in quantity, whether in quality also is a matter of taste. Other minor works are
                    the Arabic <hi rend="italic">kasídas,</hi> the first of which laments the
                    destruction of the Arabian caliphate by the Mongols in 1258 (656 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">a.h.)</hi>; the Persian <hi rend="italic">kasídas,</hi> partly
                    panegyrical, partly didactical; the <hi rend="italic">maráthí,</hi> or elegies,
                    beginning with one on the death of Abúbakr and ending with one on the defeat and
                    demise of the last caliph, Musta'sim; the <hi rend="italic">mulamma'át,</hi> or
                    poems with alternate Persian and Arabic verses, of a rather artificial
                    character; the <hi rend="italic">tarjí'át,</hi> or refrain-poems; the <hi
                    rend="italic">ghazals,</hi> or odes; the <hi rend="italic">sáhibiyyah</hi> and
                    <hi rend="italic">mιιkatta'át,</hi> or moral aphorisms and epigrams; the <hi
                    rend="italic">rubá'iyyát,</hi> or quatrains; and the <hi rend="italic"
                    >mufradát,</hi> or distichs. Sa'di’s lyrical poems possess neither the easy
                    grace and melodious charm of Hafiz’s songs nor the overpowering grandeur of
                    Jelál-uddín Rumi’s divine hymns, but they are nevertheless full of deep pathos
                    and show such a fearless love of truth as is seldom met with in Eastern poetry.
                    Even his panegyrics, although addressed in turn to almost all the rulers who in
                    those days of continually changing dynasties presided over the fate of Persia,
                    are free from that cringing servility so common in the effusions of Oriental
                    encomiasts.</p>
                <p>The first who collected and arranged his works was 'Alí b. Ahmad b. Bísutún
                    (1326-1334; 726-734 A.H.). The most exact information about Sa'di’s life and
                    works is found in the introduction to Dr W. Bacher’s <hi rend="italic">Sa'dî’s
                    Aphorismen und Sinngedichte,</hi> Strasburg, 1879 (a complete metrical
                    translation of the epigrammatic poems), and in the same author’s “Sa'di
                    Studien,” in <hi rend="italic">Z.D.M.G.,</hi> XXX. pp. 81-106. Sa'di’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Kulliyyát</hi> or complete works have been edited by Harington,
                    Calcutta, 1791-95 (with an English translation of some of the prose treatises
                    and of Daulat Shah’s notice on the poet, of which a German version is found in
                    Graf's <hi rend="italic">Rosengarten,</hi> Leipsic, 1846, p. 229 <hi
                    rend="italic">sq.)</hi>; for the numerous lithographed editions, see Rieu’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Pers. Cat. of the Brit. Mus.,</hi> ii. p. 596. The <hi
                    rend="italic">Bústán</hi> has been printed in Calcutta (1810 and 1828), as well
                    as in Lahore, Cawnpore, Tabriz, &amp;c.; a critical edition with Persian
                    commentary was published by K. II. Graf at Vienna in 1850 (German metrical
                    translations by the same, Jena, 1850, and by Schlechta-wssehrd, Vienna, 1852;
                    English translation by W. Clarke, London, 1879; French translation by Barbier de
                    Meynard, Paris, 1880). The best editions of the <hi rend="italic">Gulistan</hi>
                    are by A. Sprenger (Calcutta, 1851) and by Platts (London, 1874); the best
                    translations into English by Eastwick (1852) and by Platts (1873); into French
                    by Defrémery (1858); into German by Graf (1846); see also S. Robinson’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Persian Poetry for English Readers,</hi> 1883, pp. 245- 366.
                    Select kasídas, ghazals, elegies, quatrains, and distichs have been edited, with
                    a German metrical translation, by Graf, in the <hi rend="italic">Z.D.M.G.,</hi>
                    ix. p. 92 <hi rend="italic">sq.,</hi> xii. p. 82 <hi rend="italic">sq.,</hi>
                    xiii. p. 445 <hi rend="italic">sq.,</hi> xv. p. 541 <hi rend="italic">sq.,</hi>
                    and xviii. p. 570 <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi> On the Súfic character of Sa'di in
                    contrast to Hafiz and Jelál-uddín Rúmí, comp. Ethé, “Der Sûfismus und seine drei
                    Hauptvertreter,” in <hi rend="italic">Morgenländische Studien,</hi> Leipsic,
                    1870, pp. 95-124. (H. E.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
