<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0367-0348-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SAXE-MEININGEN (9th edition, volume 21, page
                    348)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g03">Cent</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n29pf6k">Sheep</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x63b58d">Kindness</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49w0934b">Germs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150508">Thuringians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1004072">Lutherans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:850620">Cent</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1115460">Sheep</term>
                    <term ref="fast:987598">Kindness</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204270">Maine</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n367/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SAXE-MEININGEN</label> (Germ. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Sachsen-Meiningen),</hi> a duchy in Thuringia, and an independent member of the
                    German empire, consists chiefly of an irregular crescentshaped territory, which,
                    with an average breadth of 10 miles, stretches for over 80 miles along the
                    south-west slope of the Thuringian Forest. The convex side rests upon the duchy
                    of Coburg, and is in part bounded by Bavaria, while the concave side, turned
                    towards the north, contains portions of four other Thuringian states and Prussia
                    be tween its horns, which are 46 miles apart. The districts of Kranichfeld, 15
                    miles north-west, and Kamburg, 22 miles due north of the eastern horn, together
                    with a number of smaller scattered exclaves, comprise 74 of the 953 square miles
                    now belonging to the duchy (about the size of county Down in Ireland). The
                    surface on the whole is hilly, and is partly occupied by offshoots of the
                    Thuringian Forest; the highest summits are the Kieserle (2851 feet) and the
                    Bless (2834 feet). The chief streams are the Werra, which traverses the south
                    and east of the duchy, and various tributaries of the Main and the Saale, so
                    that Saxe-Meiningen belongs to the basins of the three great rivers Weser,
                    Rhine, and Elbe.</p>
                <p>The soil is not very productive, although agriculture flourishes in the valleys
                    and on the level ground; grain has to be imported to meet the demand. In 1883
                    only 41 '8 per cent. of the total area (in 1878, 41·6) was devoted to
                    agriculture, while meadow land and pasture occupied 11 per cent. The chief grain
                    crops in 1883 were rye (44,442 acres, yielding 16,112 tons), oats (42,447 acres,
                    17,343 tons), wheat (25,252 acres, 9033 tons), and barley (19,015 acres, 94,456
                    tons). The cultivation of potatoes is very general (31,006 acres, 143,327 tons).
                    Tobacco, hops, and flax (in 1883, 997 acres) are also raised. The Werrathal and
                    the other fertile valleys produce large quantities of fruit. Sheep and cattle
                    raising is a tolerably important branch of industry throughout the duchy; horses
                    are bred in Kamburg. In 1883 Saxe-Meiningen contained 5174 horses, 66,733
                    cattle, 58,940 sheep, 45,136 pigs, and 26,817 goats. The extensive and valuable
                    forests, of which 75 per cent. are coniferous trees, occupy 41·9 per cent. of
                    the entire area. Nearly one half of the forests belong to the state and about
                    one-third to public bodies and institutions, leaving little more than a sixth
                    for private owners. The mineral wealth of the duchy is not inconsiderable. Iron,
                    coal, and slate are the chief minerals worked. There are salt-works at Salzungen
                    and Sulza, the former the most important in Thuringia; and the mineral water of
                    Friedrichshall is well known. The manufacturing industry of Saxe-Meiningen is
                    very active, especially in the districts of Sonneberg, Gräfenthal, and Saalfeld.
                    Iron goods of various kinds, glass and pottery, school-slates, marbles, &amp;c.,
                    are produced; the abundant timber fosters the manufacture of all kinds of wooden
                    articles, especially toys; and textile industry is also carried on to a slight
                    extent.</p>
                <p>The capital of the duchy is Meiningen (in 1881 11,227 inhabitants). Of the
                    sixteen other towns (Salzungen, Wasungen, Hildburghausen, Eisfeld, Sonneberg,
                    Saalfeld, Pössneck, Kamburg, &amp;c.) none has so many as 10,000 inhabitants.
                    There are 392 villages and hamlets. In 1880 the population was 207,075 (217 per
                    square mile), of whom 30 per cent. lived in communities of more than 2000. As in
                    the other Saxon duchies the population is almost exclusively Lutheran; in 1883
                    202,970 belonged to that confession, 2274 were Roman Catholics, 204 of other
                    Christian sects, and 1627 Jews.</p>
                <p>Saxe-Meiningen is a limited monarchy, its constitution resting on a law of 1829,
                    subsequently modified. The diet, elected for six years, consists of 24 members,
                    of whom 4 are elected by the largest landowners, 4 by those who pay the highest
                    personal taxes, and 16 by the other electors. The franchise is enjoyed by all
                    domiciled males over twenty-five years of age who pay at least a minimum of
                    taxes. The government is carried on by a ministry of five, with departments for
                    the ducal house and foreign affairs, home affairs, justice, education and public
                    worship, and finance. The returns of the state-lands and the ordinary
                    state-revenue are treated in separate budgets. The estimate for the period
                    1884-86 puts the annual income from the former at £105,340 and the annual
                    expenditure at £77,915, while the annual income and expenditure of the latter
                    are balanced at £145,148. Half of the surplus of £27,425 is credited to each
                    fund. The duke’s civil list of £19,714 (394,286 marks) is paid out of the
                    returns from the state-lands, at one time in the possession of the reigning
                    house. Saxe-Meiningen has one vote in the federal council and sends two deputies
                    to the reichstag.</p>
                <p>The original territory of the duchy of Saxe-Meiningen, founded in 1680 by
                    Bernhard, third son of Ernest the Pious, consisted of what is now the western
                    horn of the duchy, from Henneberg northwards. Bernhard was succeeded in 1706 by
                    his three sons; but by 1746 the only survivor was the youngest, Antony Ulrich,
                    who reigned alone until his death in 1763. The duchy had meanwhile been
                    considerably increased in extent; but contentions and petty wars with the other
                    Saxon principalities on questions of inheritance, the extravagance of the court,
                    and the hardships of the Seven Years’ War plunged it into bankruptcy and
                    distress. A happier time was enjoyed under Charlotte Amalie, Antony’s wife, who
                    ruled as regent for her two sons Charles (1775-1782) and George<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n368/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0368-0349"/> (1782-1803), and also under these princes
                    themselves. George, who had introduced the principle of primogeniture, was
                    succeeded by his infant son Bernhard Erich Freund, born in 1800. The war with
                    France at the beginning of the present century, with its attendant quartering of
                    troops, conscription, and levies of money, joined with cattle-disease and scanty
                    harvests in once more plunging the country into distress, from which it but
                    slowly recovered. Bernhard had already spontaneously granted a liberal
                    constitution to his subjects in 1824, when large additions (530 square miles)
                    consequent upon the redistribution of the Saxon lands in 1826 more than doubled
                    his possessions and rendered reorganization necessary. Among the additions to
                    Saxe-Meiningen were the duchy of Hildburghausen (whence the full title of the
                    present duchy is Saxe-Meiningen-Hildburghausen), which had been founded in 1680
                    by Ernest, the sixth son of Ernest the Pious; the principality of Saalfeld,
                    which, founded by John Ernest, Ernest’s seventh son, in 1680, had been united to
                    Coburg in 1735; and the districts of Themar, Kranichfeld, Kamburg, and other
                    smaller territories. Saxe-Meiningen, like the other Saxon duchies, entered the
                    Confederation of the Rhine in 1806; but in 1866, unlike its neighbours, it
                    declared for Austria in the war against Prussia. The land was at once occupied
                    by Prussian troops, and Bernhard abdicated (September 1866) in favour of his son
                    George, who made peace with Prussia and entered the North German Confederation.
                    In 1871 the dispute which had lasted since 1826 between the duke and the diet as
                    to the respective rights of each to the state-lands was terminated by a
                    compromise.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
