<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0685-0660-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SENEGAL (9th edition, volume 21, page 660)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j96094w">Seasons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6j916">Passes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94f0m">Negroes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1939238">Negroes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110447">Seasons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1066776">Plateaus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1095478">Reservoirs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205480">Niger</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1242088">Sahara</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207659">Cambodia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204591">Sudan</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n685/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SENEGAL</label>, a river of western Africa, which falls into
                    the Atlantic about 16° N. lat., 9 or 10 miles below St Louis. It is formed at
                    Bafulabé<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi
                    rend="italic">Bafulabé</hi> is a native word for “confluence.”</p></note> (13°
                    50' N. lat. and 10° 50' W. long.) by the junction of the Ba-fing or Black River
                    and the Ba-khoy or White River. The Ba-fing, which has a width at the confluence
                    of 1475 feet, descends from the highlands of Futa-Jallon by a northward course
                    of about 350 miles, during which it passes by a series of rapids from the
                    altitude of 2460 feet, at which it takes its rise, to that of 360 feet, and
                    receives from the right the Nunkolo and the Funkumah (with its tributary the
                    Boki). The Ba-khoy, 800 feet wide at the confluence, has been previously flowing
                    from east to west and gives that general direction to the Senegal, but its
                    source is away in the south-east behind the country of Buré. That of its
                    principal tributary, the Ba-ule (Red River), is more to the east and lies within
                    a few miles of the course of the Niger in the Mandingo plateau. Below Bafulabé
                    the Senegal, flowing north-west, passes a succession of falls—those of Guina
                    (160 feet) and of Felu (50 or 60)—and arrives at Médine, after having
                    accomplished 440 of its total course of 1000 miles. It receives only two
                    important affluents,—from the right the “marigot” of Kulu, which comes from
                    Kuniakhary, draining the slopes of the Kaarta plateau, and from the left the
                    Falemé, which rises in the Futa-Jallon between Labé and Timbo and flows
                    north-west in a permanent stream. Below Médine the Senegal presents a series of
                    great reaches, which become more and more navigable as they approach the
                    sea.</p>
                <p>From the 1st of August to the 1st of October it is open as far as Médine to
                    vessels not drawing more than 8 feet. Between Médine and Bakel (85 miles) there
                    are twenty-seven “narrows,” of which several, such as that at Kayes, are
                    difficult; it is on this account that a railway has been projected between Kayes
                    and the Niger. At Bakel below the confluence of the Falemé the river is
                    navigable till the 1st of December, from Bakel to Saldé between the 15th of July
                    and the 15th of December, and lastly from Mafu to the sea for a distance of 215
                    miles it is navigable all the year round. Outside the limits indicated
                    navigation between Mafu and Médine is often precarious even for barges drawing
                    little over a foot, and above Médine, though some reaches are deep enough,
                    troublesome transhipments are necessary between reach and reach. Between Mafu
                    and Saldé the Senegal changes its direction from north-west to west, and shortly
                    before reaching the sea to south-west. The bar at the mouth can usually be
                    crossed by vessels not drawing more than 10 feet, or at high tides a little
                    more. Below Bakel the river becomes tortuous and encloses the great island of
                    Morfil, 110 miles long, and a series of other islands, of which one is occupied
                    by St Louis. At this point the right branch of the river is only 500 feet from
                    the sea, but the dunes along the coast turn it south for other 9 miles. The
                    scantiness of its sources, the steepness of its upper course, and the rapid
                    evaporation which takes place after the short rainy season would soon dry up the
                    river-system of the Senegal, especially in the upper regions; but natural dams
                    cross the channel at intervals and the water accumulates behind them in deep
                    reaches, which thus act as reservoirs. In the rainy season the barriers are
                    submerged in succession, beginning with the farthest up, the reaches are filled,
                    and the plains of the lower Senegal are changed into immense marshes. Like Lake
                    Moeris in antiquity on the Nile and the lake of Cambodia at the present time on
                    the Me-kong, Lake Cayor on the right side of the lower Senegal and Lake Panieful
                    on the left constitute reserve basins, receiving the surplus waters of the river
                    during flood and restoring them in the dry season. For months together the
                    latter forms the only drinking pond for the wild beasts of the surrounding
                    country,—lions, elephants, leopards, panthers, ounces, cheetahs, hyaenas,
                    lynxes, giraffes, antelopes, gazelles, monkeys, jackals visiting it in crowds.
                    In the upper part of the river the reservoirs are successively emptied to the
                    level of the dams and receive no more water except from the permanent springs;
                    but they are partially protected by curtains of verdure from the effects of the
                    evaporation which makes itself so severely felt on the treeless seaboard. Owing
                    to these natural “locks,” similar to those of an artificial canal, the Senegal
                    river never discharges less than 1700 or 1800 cubic feet per second. The lower
                    Senegal forms the boundary between the dry and barren Sahara and the rich and
                    productive region of the western Sudan; the line of its inundations is an
                    ethnographic march between the nomadic Moor and the settled Negro.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
