<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0577-0552-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SCREW (9th edition, volume 21, page 552)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kw57r0g">Nuts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r47q">Cuttings</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mg7fz12">Cutting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4g15tk4n">Screws</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4js9hb31">Motion</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1042338">Nuts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:915038">Errors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:915026">Error</term>
                    <term ref="fast:885683">Cutting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1109382">Screws</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n577/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SCREW</label>. The screw is the simplest instrument for
                    converting a uniform motion of rotation into a uniform motion of translation
                    (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Mechanics,</hi> vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">xv.</hi> p.
                    754). Metal screws requiring no special accuracy are generally cut by taps and
                    dies. A tap is a cylindrical piece of steel having a screw on its exterior with
                    sharp cutting edges; by forcing this with a revolving motion into a hole of the
                    proper size, a screw is cut on its interior forming what is known as a nut or
                    female screw. The die is a nut with sharp cutting edges used to screw upon the
                    outside of round pieces of metal and thus produce male screws. More accurate
                    screws are cut in a lathe by causing the carriage carrying the tool to move
                    uniformly forward, thus a continuous spiral line is cut on the uniformly
                    revolving cylinder fixed between the lathe centres. The cutting t∞l may be an
                    ordinary form of lathe tool or a revolving saw-like disk. (See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Machine Tools,</hi> vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">xv.</hi> p.
                    153.)</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Errors of Screws.—</hi> For scientific purposes the screw must
                    be so regular that it moves forward in its nut exactly the same distance for
                    each given angular rotation around its axis. As the mountings of a screw
                    introduce many errors, the final and exact test of its accuracy can only be made
                    when it is finished and set up for use. A large screw can, however, be roughly
                    examined in the following manner. (1) Sea whether the surface of the threads has
                    a perfect polish. The more it departs from this, and approaches the rough torn
                    surface as cut by the lathe tool, the worse it is. A perfect screw has a perfect
                    polish. (2) Mount upon it between the centres of a lathe and the slip a short
                    nut which fits perfectly. If the nut moves from end to end with equal friction,
                    the screw is uniform in diameter. If the nut is long, unequal resistance may be
                    due to cither an error of run or a bend in the screw. (3) Fix a microscope on
                    the lathe carriage and focus its single cross-hair on the edge of the screw and
                    parallel to its axis. If the screw runs true at every point, its axis is
                    straight. (4) Observe whether the short nut runs from end to end of the screw
                    without a wabbling motion when the screw is turned and the nut kept from
                    revolving. If it wabbles the screw is said to be drunk. One can see this error
                    better by fixing a long pointer to the nut, or by attaching to it a minor and
                    observing an image in it with a telescope. The following experiment will also
                    detect this error. (5) Γut upon the screw two wellfitting and rather short nuts,
                    which are kept from revolving by arms bearing against a straight edge parallel
                    to the axis of the screw. Let one nut carry an arm which supports a microscope
                    focused on a line ruled on the other nut. Screw this combination to different
                    parts of the screw. If during one revolution the microscope remains in focus,
                    the screw is not drunk; and, if the cross-hairs bisect the line in every
                    position, there is no error of run.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Making Accurate Screws.—</hi> To produce a screw of a foot or
                    even a yard long with errors not exceeding <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1000</hi> th of an inch is not difficult. Professor William A.
                    Rogers of Harvard observatory has invented a process in which the tool of the
                    lathe while cutting the screw is moved so as to counteract the errors of the
                    lathe screw. The screw is then partly ground to get rid of local errors. But,
                    where the highest accuracy is needed, we must resort in the case of screws, as
                    in all other cases, to grinding. A long solid nut, tightly fitting the screw in
                    one position, cannot be moved freely to another position unless the screw is
                    very accurate. If grinding material is applied and the nut is constantly
                    tightened, it will grind out all errors of run, drunkenness, crookedness, and
                    irregularity of size. The condition is that the nut must be long, rigid, and
                    capable of being tightened as the grinding proceeds; also the screw must be
                    ground longer than it will finally be needed so that the imperfect ends may be
                    removed.</p>
                <p>The following process will produce a screw suitable for ruling<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n578/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0578-0553"/> gratings for optical purposes. Suppose it is our
                    purpose to produce a screw which is finally to be 9 inches long, not including
                    bearings, and 1 <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 8</hi>
                    inches in diameter. Select a bar of soft Bessemer steel, which has not the hard
                    spots usually found in cast steel, about 1 <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> / <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 8</hi> inches in diameter and 30 long. Put it between lathe
                    centres and turn it down to 1 inch diameter everywhere, except about 12 inches
                    in the centre, where it is left a little over 1 <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> /
                    <hi rend="subscript"> 8</hi> inches in diameter for cutting the screw. Now cut
                    the screw with a triangular thread a little sharper than 60°. Above all, avoid a
                    fine screw, using about 20 threads to the inch.</p>
                <p>The grinding nut, about 11 inches long, has now to be made. Fig. 1 represents a
                    section of the nut, which is made of brass, or better of Bessemer steel. It
                    consists of four segments,— <hi rend="italic">a</hi>, <hi rend="italic">a,</hi>
                    which can be drawn about the screw by two collars, <hi rend="italic">b, b,</hi>
                    and the screw c. Wedges between the segments prevent too great pressure on the
                    screw. The final clamping is effected by the rings and screws, <hi rend="italic"
                    >d, d,</hi> which enclose the flanges, <hi rend="italic">e,</hi> of the
                    segments. The screw is now placed in a lathe and surrounded by water whose
                    temperature can be kept constant to 1° C., and the nut placed on it. In order
                    that the weight of the nut may not make the ends too small, it must either be
                    counterbalanced by weights hung from a rope passing over pulleys in the ceiling,
                    or the screw must be vertical during the whole process. Emery and oil seem to be
                    the only available grinding materials, though a softer silica powder might be
                    used towards the end of the operation to clean off the emery and prevent future
                    wear. Now grind the screw in the nut, making the nut pass backwards and forwards
                    over the screw, its whole range being nearly 20 inches at first. Turn the nut
                    end for end every ten minutes and continue for two weeks, finally making the
                    range of the nut only about 10 inches, using finer washed emery and moving the
                    lathe slower to avoid heating. Finish with a fine silica powder or rouge. During
                    the process, if the thread becomes too blunt, recut the nut by a <hi
                    rend="italic">short</hi> tap so as not to change the pitch at any point. This
                    must of course not be done less than five days before the finish. Now cut to the
                    proper length; centre again in the lathe under a microscope; and turn the
                    bearings. A screw so ground has less errors than from any other system of
                    mounting. The periodic error especially will be too small to be discovered,
                    though the mountings and graduation and centering of the head will introduce it;
                    it must therefore finally be corrected.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Mounting of Screws.—</hi> The mounting must be devised most
                    carefully, and is indeed more difficult to make without error than the screw
                    itself. The principle which should be adopted is that no workmanship is perfect;
                    the design must make up for its imperfections. Thus the screw can never be made
                    to run true on its bearings, and hence the device of resting one end of the
                    carriage on the nut must be rejected. Also all rigid connexion between the nut
                    and the carriage must be avoided, as the screw can never be adjusted parallel to
                    the ways on which the carriage rests. For many purposes, such as ruling optical
                    gratings, the carriage must move accurately forward in a straight line as far as
                    the horizontal ’ plane is concerned, while a little curvature in the vertical
                    plane produces very little effect. These conditions can be satisfied by making
                    the ways V-shaped and grinding with a grinder somewhat shorter than the ways. By
                    constant reversals and by lengthening or shortening the stroke, they will
                    finally become nearly perfect. The vertical curvature can be sufficiently tested
                    by a short carriage carrying a delicate spirit level. Another and very efficient
                    form of ways is V-shaped with a flat top and nearly vertical sides. The carriage
                    rests on the flat top and is held by springs against one of the nearly vertical
                    sides. To determine with accuracy whether the ways are straight, fix a flat
                    piece of glass on the carriage and rule a line on it by moving it under a
                    diamond; reverse and rule another line near the first, and measure the distance
                    apart at the centre and at the two ends by a micrometer. If the centre
                    measurement is equal to the mean of the two end ones, the line is straight. This
                    is better than the method with a mirror mounted on the carriage and a telescope.
                    The screw itself must rest in bearings, and the end motion be prevented by a
                    point bearing against its flat end, which is protected by hardened steel or a
                    flat diamond. Collar bearings introduce periodic errors. The secret of success
                    is so to design the nut and its connexions as to eliminate all adjustments of
                    the screw and indeed all imperfect workmanship. The connexion must also be such
                    as to give means of correcting any residual periodic errors or errors of run
                    which may be introduced in the mountings or by the wear of the machine.</p>
                <p>The nut is shown in fig. 2. It is made in two halves, of wrought iron filled with
                    boxwood or lignum vitae plugs, on which the screw is cut. To each half a long
                    piece of sheet steel is fixed which bears against a guiding edge, to be
                    described presently. The two halves are held to the screw by springs, so that
                    each moves forward almost independently of the other.</p>
                <p>To join the nut to the carriage, a ring is attached to the latter, whose plane is
                    vertical and which can turn round a vertical axis.</p>
                <p>The bars fixed midway on the two halves of the nut bear against this ring at
                    points 90° distant from its axis.</p>
                <p>Hence each half does its share independently of the other in moving the carriage
                    forward. Any want of parallelism between the screw and the ways or eccentricity
                    in the screw mountings thus scarcely affects the forward motion of the carriage.
                    The guide against which the steel pieces of the nut rest can be made of such
                    form as to correct any small error of run due to wear of the screw. Also, by
                    causing it to move backwards and forwards periodically, the periodic error of
                    the head and mountings can be corrected.</p>
                <p>In making gratings for optical purposes the periodic error must be very perfectly
                    eliminated, since the periodic displacement of the lines only one-millionth of
                    an inch from their mean position will produce “ghosts”</p>
                <p>in the spectrum.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>In a
                    machine made by the present writer for ruling gratings the periodic error is
                    entirely due to the graduation and centering of the head. The uncorrected
                    periodic error from this cause displaces the lines/ <hi rend="subscript">
                    300000</hi> th of an inch, which is sufficient to entirely ruin all gratings
                    made without correcting it.</p></note> Indeed this is the most sensitive method
                    of detecting the existence of this error, and it is practically impossible to
                    mount the most perfect of screws without introducing it. A very practical method
                    of determining this error is to rule a short grating with very long lines on a
                    piece of common thin plate glass; cut it in two with a diamond and superimpose
                    the two halves with the rulings together and displaced sideways over each other
                    one-half the pitch of the screw. On now looking at the plates in a proper light
                    so as to have the spectral colours show through it, dark lines will appear,
                    which are wavy if there is a periodic error and straight if there is none. By
                    measuring the comparative amplitude of the waves and the distance apart of two
                    lines, the amount of the periodic error can be determined. The phase of the
                    periodic error is best found by a series of trials after setting the corrector
                    at the proper amplitude as determined above.</p>
                <p>A machine properly made as above and kept at a constant temperature should be
                    able to make a scale of 6 inches in length, with errors at no point exceeding
                    <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 100000</hi> th of an
                    inch. When, however, a grating of that length is attempted at the rate of 14,000
                    lines to the inch, four days and nights are required and the result is seldom
                    perfect, possibly on account of the wear of the machine or changes of
                    temperature. Gratings, however, less than 3 inches long are easy to make. (H. A.
                    R.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
