<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0268-0249-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SAMOS (9th edition, volume 21, page 249)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1151043">Time</term>
                    <term ref="fast:866649">Coins</term>
                    <term ref="fast:978609">Ionians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208757">Syria</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bk43">Levant</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n268/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SAMOS</label>, one of the principal and most fertile of the
                    islands in the Aegean Sea that closely adjoin the mainland of Asia Minor, from
                    which it is separated by a strait of only about a mile in width. It is about 27
                    miles in length, by about 14 in its greatest breadth, and is occupied throughout
                    the greater part of its extent by a range of mountains, of which the highest
                    summit, near its western extremity, called Mount Kerkis, attains to the height
                    of 4725 feet. This range is in fact a continuation of that of Mount Mycale on
                    the mainland, of which the promontory of Trogilium, immediately opposite to the
                    city of Samos, formed the extreme point. Various mythical legends were current
                    to account for the original settlement of the city of Samos, and to connect its
                    founders with the Greek heroic genealogies; but the earliest record that has any
                    claim to an historical character is that of the occupation of the island by a
                    colony of Ionian settlers under a leader named Procles, at the time of the great
                    Ionian emigration to Asia Minor (about 1050 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.).</hi> In
                    the historical period Samos figures as a purely Ionic city, and was one of the
                    most influential members of the Ionic confederacy. In the five centuries that
                    intervened from its first settlement to the reign of Polycrates, Samos had
                    rapidly attained to a great height of power and prosperity, had founded colonies
                    at Perinthus and other places on the Propontis, as well as at Nagidus and
                    Celenderis in Cilicia, and possessed a powerful navy, including, according to
                    Thucydides (i. 13), the first triremes that ever were constructed. It was a
                    Samian named Colaeus also who was the first Greek that ventured to penetrate
                    between the Pillars of Hercules into the ocean beyond, and brought back a vast
                    amount of wealth from these previously unknown regions (Herod., iv. 152).</p>
                <p>Samos was doubtless protected by its insular position from conquest by the
                    Persian general Harpagus; nor did it follow the example of the two other great
                    islands of Chios and Lesbos by voluntary submission to the Persian monarch. On
                    the contrary, it not only preserved its independence for a period of more than
                    twenty years longer, but it was precisely in this interval that it rose to the
                    highest pitch of power and prosperity under the enlightened and able, though
                    tyrannical, government of the despot <hi rend="smallcaps">Polycrates</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">(q.v.).</hi> Under his government Samos became “the first of all
                    cities Hellenic or barbaric,” and was adorned with three of the greatest public
                    works that had ever been executed by Greeks—an aqueduct tunnelled through a
                    mountain for a length of 7 stadia, a mole of more than 2 stadia in length for
                    the protection of the harbour, and a temple (that of Hera) exceeding all others
                    in size. How far these great works belong to the time of Polycrates cannot be
                    determined with certainty; but there is little doubt that they were enlarged and
                    completed, if not commenced, under his government. He was also the first to lay
                    claim to the sovereignty of the Aegean Sea, or thalassocraty, which at that time
                    there was none to dispute with him.</p>
                <p>After the death of Polycrates (522 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi>) Samos fell
                    under the power of his brother Syloson, who established himself in the
                    sovereignty with the support of a Persian army, but this revolution was not
                    accomplished without a massacre of the citizens, which must have given a heavy
                    blow to the prosperity of the island. Henceforth it continued to be tributary to
                    Persia till the great battle of Mycale (480), which not only freed the Samians
                    from the Persian yoke, but became the beginning of a fresh era of great
                    prosperity, during which they, like the neighbouring Chians and Lesbians, were
                    admitted as members of the Athenian confederacy, on free and equal terms,
                    without payment of tribute. An abrupt termination was, however, put to this
                    state of things in 439, when, the Samians having given offence to the Athenians,
                    their city was besieged and taken by Pericles, who compelled them to raze their
                    fortifications, to give up their ships of war, to furnish hostages, and to pay
                    the expenses of the war. From<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n269/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0269-0250"/> this time therefore Samos became a mere
                    dependency of Athens, and continued in this subordinate condition throughout the
                    Peloponnesian War; but after the victory of the Spartans at Aegospotami, the
                    city was besieged and taken by Lysander (404), and as usual an oligarchy was set
                    up under Spartan control. Other revolutions, however, quickly followed. The
                    victory of Conon at Cnidus in 394 restored the democracy, but the peace of
                    Antalcidas shortly afterwards (387) placed the island under the government of a
                    Persian satrap, and thus exposed it to the attacks of the Athenians, who sent an
                    expedition against it under Timotheus, one of their ablest generals, who after a
                    siege of eleven months reduced the whole island and took the capital city. A
                    large part of the inhabitants were expelled, and their place supplied by
                    Athenian emigrants (366).</p>
                <p>From this time we hear but little of Samos. It passed without resistance under
                    the yoke of Alexander the Great, and retained a position of nominal autonomy
                    under his successors, though practically dependent, sometimes on the kings of
                    Egypt, sometimes on those of Syria. After the defeat of Antiochus the Great at
                    the battle of Magnesia (190), it passed with the rest of Ionia to the kings of
                    Pergamum, but, having in an evil hour espoused the cause of the pretender
                    Aristonicus, it was deprived of its freedom, and was united with the Roman
                    province of Asia (129). Henceforth it of course held only a subordinate
                    position, but it seems to have always continued to be a flourishing and opulent
                    city. We find it selected by Antony as the headquarters of his fleet, and the
                    place where he spent his last winter with Cleopatra, and a few years later it
                    became the winter quarters of Augustus (21-20), who in return restored its
                    nominal freedom. Its autonomy, however, as in many other cases under the Roman
                    empire, was of a very fluctuating and uncertain character, and after 70 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> it lapsed into the ordinary condition of a Roman
                    provincial town. Its coins, however, attest its continued importance during more
                    than two centuries, and it was even able to contest with Smyrna and Ephesus the
                    proud title of the “first city of Ionia.” It still figures prominently in the
                    description of the Byzantine empire by Constantine Porphyrogenitus, but little
                    is known of it during the Middle Ages.</p>
                <p>During the Greek War of Independence Samos bore a conspicuous part, and it was in
                    the strait between the island and Mount Mycale that Canaris achieved one of his
                    most celebrated exploits by setting fire to and blowing up a Turkish frigate, in
                    the presence of the army that had been assembled for the invasion of the island,
                    a success that led to the abandonment of the enterprise, and Samos held its own
                    to the very end of the war. On the conclusion of peace the island was indeed
                    again handed over to the Turks, but since 1835 has held an exceptionally
                    advantageous position, being in fact self-governed, though tributary to the
                    Turkish empire, and ruled by a Greek governor nominated by the Porte, who bears
                    the title of “Prince of Samos,” but is supported and controlled by a Greek
                    council and assembly. The prosperity of the island bears witness to the wisdom
                    of this arrangement. It now contains a population of above 40,000 inhabitants,
                    and its trade has rapidly increased. Its principal article of export is its
                    wine, which was celebrated in ancient times, and still enjoys a high reputation
                    in the Levant. It exports also silk, oil, raisins, and other dried fruits.</p>
                <p>The ancient capital, which bore the name of the island, was situated on the south
                    coast, directly opposite to the promontory of Mycale, the town itself adjoining
                    the sea and having a large artificial port, the remains of which are still
                    visible, as are the ancient walls that surrounded the summit of a hill which
                    rises immediately above it, and now bears the name of Astypalaea. This formed
                    the acropolis of the ancient city, which in its flourishing times occupied a
                    wide extent, covering the slopes of Mount Ampelus down to the shore. From thence
                    a road led direct to the far-famed temple of Hera (Juno), which was situated
                    close to the shore, where its site is still marked by a single column, but even
                    that bereft of its capital. This miserable fragment, which has given to the
                    neighbouring headland the name of Capo Colonna, is all that remains of the
                    temple that was extolled by Herodotus as the largest he had ever seen, and which
                    vied in splendour as well as in celebrity with that of Diana at Ephesus. But,
                    like the Ephesian Artemis, the goddess worshipped at Samos was really a very
                    different divinity from the one that presided over Argos and other purely Greek
                    cities, and was unquestionably in the first instance a native Asiatic deity, who
                    was identified, on what grounds we know not, with the Hera of the olympic
                    mythology. Her image, as we learn from coins, much resembled that of the
                    Ephesian goddess, and was equally remote from any Greek conception of the
                    beautiful and stately Hera. Though so little of the temple remains, the plan of
                    it has been ascertained, and its dimensions found fully to verify the assertion
                    of Herodotus, as compared with all other Greek temples existing in his time,
                    though it was afterwards surpassed by the later temple at Ephesus.</p>
                <p>The modern capital of the island was, until a recent period, at a place called
                    Khora, about two miles from the sea, and the same distance from the site of the
                    ancient city; but since the change in the political condition of Samos the
                    capital has been transferred to Vathy, situated at the head of a deep bay on the
                    north coast, which has become the residence of the prince and the seat of
                    government. Here a new town has grown up, well built and paved, with a
                    convenient harbour, and already numbers a population of 6000.</p>
                <p>Samos was celebrated in ancient times as the birth-place of Pythagoras, who,
                    however, spent the greater part of his fife at a distance from his native
                    country. His name and figure are found on coins of the city of imperial date. It
                    was also conspicuous in the history of art, having produced in early times a
                    school of sculptors, commencing with Rhaecus and Theodoras, who are said to have
                    invented the art of casting statues in bronze, and to have introduced many other
                    technical improvements. The architect Rhaecus also, who built the temple of
                    Hera, was a native of the island. At a later period Samos was noted for the
                    manufacture of a particular kind of red earthenware, so much valued by the
                    Romans for domestic purposes that specimens of it generally occur wherever there
                    are remains of Roman settlements.</p>
                <p>All the particulars that are recorded concerning Samos in ancient times are
                    collected by Panofka <hi rend="italic">(Res Samiorum,</hi> Berlin, 1822). A full
                    description of the island, us it existed in his time, will be found in
                    Tournefort (<hi rend="italic">Voyage du Levant,</hi> 4to. Paris, 1717), and more
                    recent accounts in the works of Ross <hi rend="italic">(Reisen auf den
                    Griechischen Inseln,</hi> vol. ii., Stuttgart, 1843) and Guérin <hi
                    rend="italic">(Patmos et Samos,</hi> Paris, 1856). (E. H. B.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
