<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0635-0610-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SEA-SICKNESS (9th edition, volume 21, page 610)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1034747">Nausea</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1133761">Stomach</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1027064">Motion</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1137151">Suffering</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41z41s18">Stomach</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4js9hb31">Motion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gt5fn8v">Suffering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx0636c">Matter</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n635/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SEA-SICKNESS</label>, a peculiar set of symptoms experienced
                    by many persons when subjected to the pitching and rolling motion of a vessel at
                    sea, of which depression, giddiness, nausea, and vomiting are the most
                    prominent.</p>
                <p>Although the vast majority of persons appear to be liable to this ailment on
                    exposure to its exciting cause (the instances of complete and constant immunity
                    being rare), they do not all suffer alike. Many endure distress of a most acute
                    and even alarming kind, while others are simply conscious of transient feelings
                    of nausea and discomfort. In long voyages, while many are affected with
                    sea-sickness for the first few days only, others are tormented with it during
                    the entire period, especially on the occurrence of rough weather. In short
                    voyages, such as across the English Channel, not a few even of those susceptible
                    escape, while others suffer in an extreme degree, the sickness persisting long
                    after arrival on shore.</p>
                <p>The symptoms generally show themselves soon after the vessel has begun to roll by
                    the onset of giddiness and discomfort in the head, together with a sense of
                    nausea and sinking at the stomach, which soon develops into intense sickness and
                    vomiting. At first the contents of the stomach only are ejected; but thereafter
                    bilious matter, and occasionally even blood, are brought up by the violence of
                    the retching. The vomiting is liable to exacerbations according to the amount of
                    oscillation of the ship; but seasons of rest, sometimes admitting of sleep,
                    occasionally intervene. Along with the sickness there is great physical
                    prostration, as shown in the pallor of the skin, cold sweats, and feeble pulse,
                    accompanied with mental depression and wretchedness. In almost all instances the
                    attack has a favourable termination, and it is extremely rare that serious
                    results arise, except in the case of persons weakened by other diseases,
                    although occasionally the symptoms are for a time sufficiently alarming.</p>
                <p>The causes giving rise to sea-sickness have long been discussed, and a vast
                    number of theories have been proposed. The conditions concerned in the
                    production of the malady are apparently of complex character, embracing more
                    than one set of causes. In the first place, the rolling or heaving of the vessel
                    disturbs that feeling of the relation of the body to surrounding objects upon
                    which our sense of security rests. The nervous system being thus subjected to a
                    succession of shocks or surprises fails to effect the necessary adjustments for
                    equilibrium. Giddiness and with it nausea and vomiting follow, aided probably by
                    the profound vaso-motor disturbance which produces such manifest depression of
                    the circulation. Much has been made by some of the effects of the displacement
                    of the abdominal viscera, especially the stomach, by the rolling of the vessel;
                    but, while this may possibly operate to some extent, it can only be as an
                    accessory cause. The same may be said of the influence of the changing
                    impressions made upon the vision, which has been regarded by some as so powerful
                    in the matter, since attacks of seasickness occur also in the dark, and in the
                    case of blind persons. Other contributory causes may be mentioned, such as the
                    feeling that sickness is certain to come, which may bring on the attack in some
                    persons even before the vessel has begun to move; the sense of the body being in
                    a liquid or yielding medium as it descends with the vessel into the trough of
                    the sea, the varied odours to be met with on board ship, and circumstances of a
                    like nature tend also to precipitate or aggravate an attack. Dr Chapman’s view
                    is that the essential cause is an undue afflux of blood to the spinal cord. But,
                    in the few rare instances where sea-sickness has proved fatal, <hi rend="italic"
                    >post-mortem</hi> appearances have been almost entirely negative, and only such
                    as are met with in death from syncope.</p>
                <p>Innumerable preventives and remedies have been proposed; but most of them fall
                    far short of the success claimed for them. No means has yet been discovered
                    which can altogether prevent the occurrence of sea-sickness, nor is it likely
                    any will be found, since it is largely due to the pitching movements of the
                    vessel, which cannot be averted. Swinging couches or chambers have not proved of
                    any practical utility. No doubt there is less risk of sickness in a largo and
                    well-ballasted vessel than in a small one; but, even though the rolling may be
                    considerably modified, the ascending and descending movements which so readily
                    produce nausea continue. None of the medicinal agents proposed possess
                    infallible properties: a remedy which suits one person will often wholly fail
                    with another. There appears to be a wide concurrence of opinion that nerve
                    sedatives are among the most potent drugs which can be employed; and full
                    medicinal doses of bromide of potassium, chloral, or opium (the last two only
                    under strict medical direction) taken before sailing appear to act usefully in
                    the case of many persons. On the other hand, some high authorities have
                    recommended the employment of nerve stimulants, such as a small cupful of very
                    strong coffee to be taken about two hours before sailing, which will frequently
                    prevent or mitigate the sickness. When the vessel is in motion, or even before
                    starting, the recumbent position with the head low and the eyes closed should be
                    assumed by those at all likely to suffer, and, should the weather admit, on deck
                    rather than below,—the body, especially the extremities, being well covered.
                    Many persons, however, find comfort and relief from lying down in their berths
                    with a hot bottle to the feet, by which means sleep may be obtained, and with it
                    a temporary abatement of the distressing giddiness and nausea. Should sickness
                    supervene small quantities of some light food, such as thin arrowroot, gruel, or
                    soup, ought to be swallowed if possible, in order to lessen the sense of
                    exhaustion, which is often extreme. The vomiting may be mitigated by saline
                    effervescing drinks, ice, chloroform, hydrocyanic acid, or opium. Alcohol,
                    although occasionally useful in great prostration, is not generally found to be
                    of much service, but tends rather to aggravate the sickness. Dr Chapman, in
                    accordance with his view of the cause of the sickness, introduced a spinal
                    ice-bag, which has been extensively employed and recommended; but, like every
                    other plan of treatment, it has only occasional success. The more recently
                    proposed remedies, such as nitrite of amyl and cucaine, do not seem to yield any
                    better results than the agents already mentioned.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
