<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0318-0299-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SANTIAGO DE COMPOSTELLA (9th edition, volume 21, page
                    299)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xp6v395">Congregationalism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r76k">Martins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z892g7x">Chapels</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4057cr7r">Convents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0mz4b">Conventions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1067051">Plazas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1012869">Mayors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:875210">Congregationalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:852215">Chapels</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1072090">Porticoes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:877187">Convents</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n318/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SANTIAGO DE COMPOSTELLA</label>, the former capital of
                    Galicia, in the north-west of Spain, situated in 42° 52' 30" N. lat. and 8° 30'
                    6" W. long., 51½ miles westby-south from Lugo, and 32 miles south-by-west from
                    Corunna, in the province of that name. It lies on the eastern slope of the Monte
                    Pedroso, surrounded by mountains which draw down incessant rain that gives the
                    granite buildings of its deserted streets an extra tint of melancholy and decay.
                    The city is still the seat of a university and of an archbishopric, which lays
                    claim to the primacy of all Spain, but its former glories have quite departed.
                    In the Middle Ages its shrine, which contained the body of St James the Great,
                    was one of the most famous in Europe, and gathered crowds of pilgrims from all
                    parts. The city became, in fact, the focus of all the art and chivalry of
                    neighbouring Christendom, and a spot where conflicting interests could meet on
                    neutral ground. But the days of pilgrimages are past, and, though the
                    Congregation of Rites declared in 1884 that the cathedral still enshrines the
                    veritable body of the apostle, pilgrims are scarcely more often seen than in any
                    other cathedral town. The trade of Santiago can never have been otherwise than
                    dependent on the crowds of pilgrims who visited the shrine. It now only survives
                    in the silversmiths’ shops on the Plaza de los Plateros, which still have a
                    steady sale for artistic pieces of peasant jewellery. Otherwise it consists in
                    mere local traffic in cattle, linen, silk, leather, hats, and paper. There is
                    communication by rail with the little seaport of Carril on the west coast. The
                    population within the municipal boundaries was 23,000 in 1885.</p>
                <p>The relics of the saint were said to have been discovered in 835 by Theodomir,
                    bishop of Iria, who was guided to the spot by a star, whence the name <hi
                    rend="italic">(Campus Stellae).</hi> A chapel was forthwith erected, and the
                    bishopric was transferred thither by a special bull of Pope Leo III. A more
                    substantial building was begun in 868, but was totally destroyed in 997 by
                    Almanzor, who, however, respected the sacred relics. On the reconquest of the
                    city by Bermudo III. the roads which led to it were improved by that monarch,
                    and pilgrims began to flock to the shrine, which fast grew in reputation. In
                    1078 the erection of the present cathedral was begun during the episcopate of
                    Diego Pelaez, and was continued until 1188, when the western doorway was
                    completed. It is a cruciform building in the Romanesque style, 280 feet long, 60
                    feet wide, and 70 feet high, and keeps its original form in the interior, but is
                    disfigured externally by much poor late work. Besides the classic dome and
                    clock-tower, the two western towers have been raised to a height of 220 feet and
                    crowned with cupolas, and between them has been erected a classic portico, above
                    which is a niche containing a statue of St James. The façade was the work of
                    Casas y Noboa in 1738, and the statue was by Ventura Rodriguez in 1764. The
                    design is mediocre, and gains its chief effect from forming part of an extended
                    architectural composition on the Plaza Mayor, a grand square which is surrounded
                    on all sides by public buildings. The ground rises to the cathedral, which is
                    reached by a magnificent quadruple flight of steps, flanked by statues of David
                    and Solomon. Access to the staircase is given through some fine wrought-iron
                    gates, and in the centre, on the level of the Plaza, is the entrance to a
                    Romanesque chapel, La Iglesia Baja, constructed under the portico and
                    contemporary with the cathedral. To the north and south, and in a line with the
                    west front, are dependent buildings of the 18th century, grouping well with it.
                    Those to the south contain a light and elegant arcade to the upper windows, and
                    serve as a screen to the cloisters, built in 1533 by Fonseca, afterwards
                    archbishop of Toledo. They are said to be the largest in Spain, and are a fair
                    example of the latest Gothic. The delicate sculpture over the heads of the
                    windows and along the wall of the cloister is very noticeable. On the north of
                    the cathedral is the Plazuela S. Juan, where the peasants collect to do their
                    marketing. Here is the convent of S. Martin, built in 1636, which, after serving
                    as a barrack, is now used as an ecclesiastical seminary, restored to the church.
                    It has<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n319/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0319-0300"/> a tolerable cloister and bell-tower. The north
                    side of the cathedral is much overlaid by classical and Churrigueresque work;
                    and the same treatment has been applied to the east end, where is the Puerta
                    Santa, which is kept closed, except in jubilee years, when it is opened by the
                    archbishop. The corner of the south transept on the Plaza do los Plateros has
                    been mutilated by the erection of the clock-tower, but the façade is fortunately
                    preserved intact Perhaps the chief beauty of the cathedral, however, is the
                    Portico de la Gloria, behind the western classic portal. It is a work of the
                    12th century, and probably the utmost development of which round-arched Gothic
                    is capable. The shafts, tympana, and archivolts of the three doorways which open
                    on to the nave and aisles are a mass of strong and nervous sculpture. The design
                    is a general representation of the Last Judgment, and the subjects are all
                    treated with a quaint grace which shows the work of a real artist Faint traces
                    of colour remain and give a tone to the whole work. The cathedral is at such a
                    height from the ground that it is probable that, until the erection of the
                    present grand staircase, the portico could not be reached from the Plaza, but
                    stood open to the air. There are no marks of doors in the jambs, and the
                    entrance to the chapel beneath would have been blocked by any staircase which
                    differed much in plan from the present one. The interior of the church is one of
                    the purest and best examples of Romanesque work to be met with in Spain. The
                    absence of a clerestory throws an impressive gloom over the barrel-vaulted roof,
                    which makes the building seem larger than it is. A passage leads from the north
                    transept to the Parroquia of San Juan, or La Corticela, a small but interesting
                    portion of the original foundation. Many fine examples of metal work are in the
                    cathedral, as, for instance, the two bronze ambos in the choir by Juan B. Celma
                    of 1563, the gilt chandeliers of 1763, and the enamelled shrines of Sts Cucufato
                    and Fructuoso. In the Capilla del Relicario are a gold crucifix, dated 874,
                    containing a piece of the true cross, and a silver gilt custodia of 1544. The
                    Hospicio de los Reyes, on the north of the Plaza Mayor, for the reception of
                    pilgrims, was begun in 1504 by Enrique de Egas under Ferdinand and Isabella. It
                    consists of two Gothic and two classic court-yards with a chapel in the centre.
                    The gateway is fine, and there is some vigorous carving in the court-yards, one
                    of which contains a graceful fountain. The suppressed Colegio de Fonseca and the
                    adjoining convent of S. Geronimo have good Renaissance doorways. The university,
                    which was created in 1504 by a bull of Pope Julius IL, has fair Renaissance
                    buildings, which date from 1532. Those of the Seminario (1777) have no merit.
                    The chapel of the convent of S. Francisco, the cloisters of the half-ruined S.
                    Augustin, the belfry of S. Domingo, the church of S. Feliz de Celorio, which is
                    a modernized building of the 14th century, and the façades of several houses of
                    the 12th and 13th centuries are also good examples of different architectural
                    styles.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
