<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0707-0682-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SERPENTINE (9th edition, volume 21, page 682)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:964162">Hunting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1746444">Quart</term>
                    <term ref="fast:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1133812">Stone</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1133955">Stoning</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1099409">Rocks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1151398">Tinting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42r3nz3s">Hunting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b6k">Bohemianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kj6q">Canadians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vr13">Stone</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g6z">Rocks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h41jt0c">Tinting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n010039">Magnesium</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239717">Alps</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204598">Pennsylvania</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204928">California</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205688">Connecticut</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204310">Canada</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n707/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SERPENTINE</label>, a compact crypto-crystalline or fibrous
                    mineral substance, occurring in rock-masses which commonly present dark green
                    colours, variously mottled and fancifully compared to the markings on certain
                    serpents, whence the name “serpentine.” For a like reason it is sometimes called
                    “ophite,” while Italian sculptors have termed it “ranocchia,” in allusion to its
                    resemblance to the skin of a frog. In consequence of its variegated tints, the
                    stone is frequently cut and polished for ornamental purposes, and is hence
                    popularly called a marble. From true marble, however, it differs in chemical
                    composition, being essentially a hydrated silicate of magnesium, usually
                    associated with certain metallic oxides (such as those of iron, nickel, and
                    chromium) which confer upon the stone its characteristic tints. In some
                    localities serpentine is found in<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n708/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0708-0683"/> masses which are evidently intrusive among other
                    rocks, while elsewhere it occurs interbedded, usually in lenticular masses,
                    associated with gneiss and crystalline schists. It is noteworthy that the
                    serpentine is frequently crushed and brecciated, exhibiting polished slip-faces
                    which are sometimes striated. The surface of an exposed mass of serpentine is
                    generally barren, whence bosses of the rock are known in the Alps as “monts
                    morts.” The origin of serpentine has been a subject of much dispute. It was
                    pointed out by Sandberger and Tschermak that the alteration of olivine may give
                    rise to this product, and pseudomorphe of serpentine after chrysolite are well
                    known to mineralogists. Professor Bonney and many other geologists regard
                    serpentine as being generally an altered eruptive rock, due to the hydration of
                    peridotites, such as lherzolite; probably it may also result from the
                    decomposition of olivine-gabbro and other rocks rich in magnesian silicates.
                    Augite and hornblende may become altered to serpentine. On the contrary, Dr
                    Sterry Hunt and certain other chemical geologists believe that serpentine has
                    generally been formed as an aqueous sediment, probably precipitated by the
                    reaction of sulphate or chloride of magnesium upon the silicate of lime or
                    alkaline silicates derived from the disintegration of crystalline rocks and
                    found in solution in many natural waters. Serpentine is a rock of rather limited
                    occurrence. Its principal localities in England are Cornwall, especially in the
                    Lizard district, where it occupies a considerable area. The famous scenery of
                    Kynance Cove owes much of its beauty to the vivid colours and brilliant surface
                    of the serpentine. The rock is worked into vases, columns, mantelpieces,
                    &amp;c., and of late years has been used to a limited extent for the decoration
                    of shop-fronts in London. The beauty of the Lizard rock is heightened by the
                    white veins of steatite which traverse it, and in some cases by disseminated
                    crystals of bastite, which glisten with metallic lustre. Much of the Lizard
                    serpentine is of rich red and brown colour. Green serpentine is found near
                    Holyhead in Anglesea. A singularly beautiful variety of mottled red and green
                    tints, with veins of steatite, occurs near Portsoy in Banffshire, Scotland. It
                    is also found with chrome iron ore in the Shetland Islands. The green serpentine
                    of Galway occurs in intimate association with crystalline limestone, forming the
                    rock known as “ophicalcite” or “serpentinous marble.” Such an association is by
                    no means uncommon; but, though the beauty of the serpentine may thus be
                    enhanced, its durability seems to be impaired. On exposure to the weather the
                    carbonate of calcium decomposes more readily than the silicate of magnesium, and
                    hence the stone soon presents a rough eroded surface. The Galway rock comes into
                    the market under the name of “Irish green” or “Connemara marble.” Ophicalcites
                    also occur in Ayrshire, Scotland, and in various parts of the Scottish
                    Highlands; and the green pebbles found in Iona belong to this type of rock.</p>
                <p>On the Continent serpentines are largely worked at Zöblitz and at Waldheim in
                    Saxony. The famous rock of Zöblitz, mentioned by Agricola, is known to have been
                    wrought for between three and four centuries, and is still extensively explored
                    by open quarries and by subterranean galleries. The rock usually presents
                    various shades of green and brown, red being very rare; but its most interesting
                    feature is the frequent presence of pyrope, or Bohemian garnet, which occurs
                    scattered through the rock in dark red grains, that decompose on weathering to a
                    green chloritic product. Very little of the Zöblitz serpentine comes to England,
                    but it is common throughout Germany, and a good deal is sent to Russia and even
                    to the United States. It has been used in the construction of the mausoleum of
                    Prince Albert at Frogmore, and for Abraham Lincoln’s monument at Springfield,
                    Illinois. The best known of the Italian serpentines is the “verde Prato,” which
                    has been quarried for centuries at Monteferrato, near Prato in Tuscany.
                    According to Capacci this serpentine is probably of Eocene age. It has been
                    largely used as a decorative stone in ecclesiastical architecture in Prato,
                    Pistoia, and Florence. A good deal of serpentine is found near Genoa and
                    Levanto. The “verde di Pegli” is obtained from Pegli, not far from Genoa, while
                    the “verde di Genova” is a brecciated serpentinous limestone from Pietra
                    Lavezzara. Serpentine also occurs at various other points of the Apennines, in
                    Elba, and in Corsica. The term “ophiolite” has been vaguely used to include not
                    only serpentines but many of the rocks associated with the Italian serpentines.
                    In like manner the term “gabbro,” derived from a locality near Leghorn, was at
                    one time used as a general name for serpentine and its associates, though now
                    usually restricted to a rock composed essentially of plagioclase and diallage.
                    It is notable that this true gabbro is often found in company with
                    serpentine.</p>
                <p>Serpentine is found in numerous localities in the Alps and in France. An elegant
                    variety is quarried at Épinal in the Vosges, and a beautiful ophicalcite is
                    worked at St Véran and Maurins, in the department of Hautes-Alpes. The
                    serpentine of the Ronda Mountains in Spain has been described by Mr J.
                    Macpherson. In North America serpentine is so extensively distributed that only
                    a few localities can be mentioned. It is found at Syracuse in New York; on
                    Manhattan and Staten Islands; at Hoboken in New Jersey; at Newport, Rhode
                    Island; at Newburyport, Massachusetts; at Westchester, Chester county, and at
                    Texas, Lancaster county, in Pennsylvania. It also occurs between Clear Lake and
                    New Idrea in California. A fine ophicalcite has been obtained from near Milford
                    and New Haven in Connecticut, and a beautiful variety has been worked at Port
                    Henry, Essex county, New York (Dana). The Canadian eozoon occurs in a
                    serpentinous limestone.</p>
                <p>See <hi rend="smallcaps">Geology,</hi> vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">x.</hi> pp. 228,
                    232; <hi rend="smallcaps">Marble,</hi> vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">xv.</hi> p.
                    528; and <hi rend="smallcaps">Mineralogy,</hi> vol. xvi. p. 414. The literature
                    of the Italian and Saxon serpentines is rather voluminous. Of recent English
                    writings on serpentine reference may be made to Bonney, in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Quart. Journ. Geol. Soc.,</hi> London, xxxiii. p. 884, xxxiv. p. 769, xxxvii.
                    p. 40, xxxix. p. 21, and in <hi rend="italic">Geol Mag.,</hi> [2] vi. p. 362,
                    [3] i. p. 406; and to Collins, <hi rend="italic">Quart. Jοurn. Geol. Sοc.,</hi>
                    xl. p. 458, and <hi rend="italic">Geol. Mag.,</hi> [3] ii. p. 298. Sterry Hunt
                    has written an elaborate paper in <hi rend="italic">Proc. Roy. Soc. Canada,</hi>
                    1883, sect. iv. pp. 165-215. See also Teall, <hi rend="italic">British
                    Petrography,</hi> 1886, and Becker, in <hi rend="italic">Amer. Journ. of
                    Science,</hi> May 1886. (F. W. R*.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
