<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0157-0140-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SACY, Antoine Isaac, Baron Silvestre (9th edition,
                    volume 21, page 140)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812574">Arabists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1048144">Orientalists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:978818">Iranians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1104504">Samaritans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43f4kq99">Druses</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hd7p16n">Samaritans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n36h">Pentateuch</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fn1111w">Scholars</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n157/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SACY, <hi rend="smallcaps">Antoine Isaac, Baron
                    Silvestre</hi></label><note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>His father’s name was Silvestre, the addition De Sacy he took as a younger
                    son after a fashion then common with the Parisian <hi rend="italic"
                    >bourgeoisie.</hi></p></note><hi rend="smallcaps">de</hi> (1758- 1838), the
                    greatest of French Orientalists and the founder of the modern school of Arabic
                    scholarship, was the second son of a Parisian notary, and was born at Paris on
                    21st September 1758. From the age of seven years, when he lost his father, he
                    was educated in more than monastic seclusion in the house of his pious and
                    tender mother. Designed for the civil service, he studied jurisprudence, and in
                    1781 got a place as counsellor in the <hi rend="italic">cour des monnaies,</hi>
                    inwhich he continued till, in 1791, he was advanced to be a commissary-general
                    in the same department. De Sacy had a natural turn for business and liked
                    variety of work, while he seems to have had little or no need of absolute
                    repose. He had successively acquired all the Semitic languages while he was
                    following the usual course of school and professional training, and while he was
                    engaged in the civil service he found time to make himself a great name as an
                    Orientalist by a series of publications which, beginning with those Biblical
                    subjects to which his education and sympathies naturally directed his first
                    Semitic studies, gradually extended in range, and already displayed the
                    comprehensive scholar who had chosen the whole Semitic and Iranian East for his
                    domain.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>A communication
                    to Eichhorn on the Paris MS. of the Syro-Hexaplar version of IV. Kings formed
                    the basis of a paper in the latter’s <hi rend="italic">Repertorium,</hi> vol.
                    vii. (1780). This was De Sacy’s literary debut. It was followed by text and
                    translation of the letters of the Samaritans to Jos. Scaliger <hi rend="italic"
                    >(ibid.,</hi> vol. xiii., 1783) and by a series of essays on Arabian and Persian
                    history in the <hi rend="italic">Recueil</hi> of the Academy of Inscriptions and
                    in the <hi rend="italic">Notices et Extraits.</hi></p></note> The works of these
                    early years do not show the full maturity of his powers; his chief triumph was
                    an effective commencement of the decipherment of the Pahlaví inscriptions of the
                    Sasanian kings (1787-91). It was the French Revolution which gained De Sacy
                    wholly for letters. As a good Catholic and a staunch royalist he felt
                    constrained in 1792 to retire from the public service, and lived in close
                    seclusion in a cottage near Paris till in 1795 he was called to be professor of
                    Arabic in the newly founded school of living Eastern languages. The years of
                    retirement had not been fruitless; they were in part devoted to the study of the
                    religion of the Druses, which continued to occupy him throughout life and was
                    the subject of his last and unfinished work, the <hi rend="italic">Exposé de la
                    Religion des Druzes</hi> (2 vols., 1838). Nevertheless, when called to be a<pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n158/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0158-0141"/> teacher, he felt that he had himself much to
                    learn. Since the death of Reiske Arabic learning had been in a backward state,
                    the standard of philological knowledge was low, and the books for students
                    extremely defective. De Sacy set himself with characteristic thoroughness to
                    complete his own knowledge and supply the lacking helps to others, and he
                    accomplished this task on such a scale, with such width of range, precision of
                    thought, and scrupulous attention to details, that he became the founder of a
                    wholly new school and the father of all subsequent Arabists. His great
                    text-books, the <hi rend="italic">Grammaire Arabe</hi> (2 vols., 1st ed. 1810,
                    2d ed. 1831) and the <hi rend="italic">Chrestomathie</hi> (3 vols., 1st ed.
                    1806, 2d ed. 1826-31), together with its supplement, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Anthologie Grammaticale</hi> (1829), are works that can never become obsolete;
                    the luminous exposition of the grammar and the happy choice of the pieces in the
                    chrestomathy—all inedita—with the admirable notes, drawn from an enormous
                    reading in MS. sources, make them altogether different from ordinary text-books.
                    The whole powers of a great teacher, the whole wealth of knowledge of an
                    unrivalled scholar, are spent with absolute singleness of purpose for the
                    benefit of the learner, and the result is that the books are equally delightful
                    and instructive to the student and to the advanced scholar. A comparison of the
                    first and second editions shows how much toil and research it cost the author to
                    raise his own scholarship to the level which, thanks to his work, has become the
                    starting-place for all subsequent ascents of the Arabian Parnassus.</p>
                <p>De Sacy’s place as a teacher was threatened at the outset by his conscientious
                    refusal to take an oath of hatred to royalty. He tendered his resignation both
                    as professor and as member of the Institute; but he was allowed to continue to
                    teach, and rejoined the Institute on its reorganization in 1803. In 1805 he made
                    the only considerable journey of his life, being sent to Genoa on a vain search
                    for Arabic documents supposed to lie in the archives of that city. In 1806 he
                    added the duties of Persian professor to his old chair, and from this time
                    onwards—as, in spite of his royalist opinions, he was ready to do public service
                    under any stable government—his life, divided between his teaching, his literary
                    work, and a variety of public duties, was one of increasing honour and success,
                    broken only by a brief period of retreat during the Hundred Days. He found time
                    for everything: while his pen was ever at work on subjects of abstruse research,
                    he was one of the most active leaders in all the business which the French
                    system throws on the <hi rend="italic">savans</hi> of the capital, especially as
                    perpetual secretary of the Academy of Inscriptions (from 1832); in 1808 he
                    entered the <hi rend="italic">corps legislatif·,</hi> and in 1832, when quite an
                    old man, he became a peer of France and was regular in the duties of the
                    chamber.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The title of
                    baron he received from Napoleon in 1813.</p></note> In 1815 he became rector of
                    the university of Paris, and after the second restoration he was active on the
                    commission of public instruction. Of the <hi rend="italic">Société
                    Asiatique</hi> he was one of the founders, and when he was inspector of Oriental
                    types at the royal printing press he thought it his duty to read a proof of
                    every book printed in Arabic and Persian. With this he maintained a vast
                    correspondence and was accessible not only to every one who sought his advice on
                    matters of learning and business but to all the poor of his quarter, who came to
                    him as a member of the <hi rend="italic">bureau</hi> of charity. Yet he was
                    neither monk nor hermit: he enjoyed society and was happy in forty-eight years
                    of married life and in the care of a large family. Though small and to
                    appearance of delicate frame, De Sacy enjoyed unbroken health and worked on
                    without sign of failing powers till two days before his death (21st February
                    1838), when he suddenly fell down in the street and never rallied.</p>
                <p>De Sacy wrote so much that a list even of his larger essays, mostly communicated
                    to the Academy or in the <hi rend="italic">Notices et Extraits,</hi> is
                    impossible in this place, while his lesser papers and reviews in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Allg. Bib. f. biblische Litteratur,</hi> the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Mines de 1’Orient,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Magasin Encyclopédique,</hi> the
                    <hi rend="italic">Journal des Savants</hi> (of which he was an editor), and the
                    <hi rend="italic">Journal Asiatique</hi> are almost innumerable. Among the works
                    which he designed mainly for students may be classed his edition of Hariri
                    (1822, 2d edition by Reinaud, 1847, 1855), with a selected Arabic commentary,
                    and of the <hi rend="italic">Alfiya</hi> (1833), and his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Calila et Dimna</hi> (1816),—the Arabic version of that famous collection of
                    Buddhist animal tales which has been in various forms one of the most popular
                    books of the world. De Sacy’s enquiry into the wonderful history of these tales
                    forms one of his best services to letters and a good example of the way in which
                    he always made his work for the benefit of learners go hand in hand with
                    profound research. Of his continued interest in Biblical subjects he gave
                    evidence in his memoir on the Samaritan Arabic version of the Pentateuch (Mem.
                    <hi rend="italic">Acad, des Inscr.,</hi> vol. xlix.), and in the Arabic and
                    Syriac New Testaments edited for the British and Foreign Bible Society; among
                    works important for Eastern history, besides that on the Druses already named,
                    may be cited his version of Abd-Allatíf, <hi rend="italic">Relation Arabe sur
                    l’Égypte,</hi> and his essays on the <hi rend="italic">History of the Law of
                    Property in Egypt</hi> since the Arab conquest (1805-18). And, in conclusion, it
                    must not be forgotten that his oral teaching was not less influential than his
                    writings, and that, except Ewald, almost all Arabists of chief note in the first
                    half of this century, in Germany as well as in France, were his personal pupils.
                    Of the brilliant series of teachers who went out from his lecture-room one or
                    two veterans still survive, and Professor Fleischer’s elaborate notes and
                    corrections to the <hi rend="italic">Grammaire Arabe (Kleinere Sehriften,</hi>
                    vol. i., 1885) may be regarded as the latest tribute to the memory of the great
                    master by a disciple who is now the patriarch of living Arabists. (W. R. S.
                    )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
