<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0809-0784-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SHEEP (9th edition, volume 21, page 784)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206102">Nepal</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40k500">Ungulata</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4td9ng4n">Polo</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n29pf6k">Sheep</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r724">Presents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fs4j">Toes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4794135j">Tail</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1070244">Polo</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1115460">Sheep</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1152071">Toes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1142046">Tail</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n809/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SHEEP</label>. The animals commonly designated by this name
                    constitute the genus <hi rend="italic">Ovis</hi> of zoologists, a group
                    belonging to the Artiodactyle or paired-toed section of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ungulata</hi> or hoofed mammals (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Mammalia,</hi> vol.
                    xv. p. 432). They are ruminants, and belong to the hollowhorned section, <hi
                    rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> those having persistent horns composed of conical
                    epidermic sheaths, encasing and supported by processes of the frontal bone. This
                    section includes the various species of Oxen, Goats, and Antelopes, as well as
                    the Sheep, animals all so closely related structurally that it is by no means
                    easy to define the differences between them.</p>
                <p>In nearly all wild sheep the horns are present in both sexes, though smaller in
                    the female. They are trigonal in section, having always three more or less
                    distinctly marked surfaces, divided by edges running longitudinally to the axis
                    of the horn, sometimes sharply prominent and sometimes rounded off. They are
                    also marked by numerous transverse ridges and constrictions, and present a
                    strong more or less spiral curve, which varies in direction in different
                    species. The teeth resemble generally those of the other <hi rend="italic"
                    >Bovidae.</hi> The upper incisors and canines are entirely wanting, their place
                    being taken by a callous pad against which the lower front teeth bite. These are
                    eight in number, all much alike and in close contact; the outer pair represent
                    the canines, the rest the incisors. On each side of the mouth above and below
                    are six teeth close together, three of which are premolars (replacing milk
                    teeth) and three true molars, all markedly selenodont (the grinding surfaces
                    presenting crescent-like patterns) and hypsodont, or with long crowns and small
                    roots. The dental formula is thus—incisors <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> / <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 3</hi>, canines <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> / <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi>, premolars <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> / <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 3</hi>, molars <hi rend="superscript"> 3/</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> 3</hi>, = <hi rend="superscript"> 6</hi> / <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 10</hi>; total of both sides 32. The vertebral formula
                    is—cervical 7, dorsal 13, lumbar 6 or 7, sacral 4, caudal variable. In the feet
                    the hoofs of the two middle toes (third and fourth) only reach the ground, and
                    are equally developed. The outer toes (second and fifth) are very rudimentary,
                    represented only by small hoofs, without bony phalanges, and by the proximal or
                    upper ends of the slender splint-like metacarpal or metatarsal bones. Between
                    the two middle toes, in most species, is lodged a deep sac, having the form of a
                    retort and with a small external orifice, which secretes an unctuous and odorous
                    substance. This, tainting the herbage or stones over which the animal walks,
                    affords the means by which, through the powerfully developed sense of smell, the
                    neighbourhood of other individuals of the species is recognized. The crumen or
                    suborbital gland, which is so largely developed and probably performs the same
                    office in some antelopes and deer, is present, but in a comparatively
                    rudimentary form, though varying in different species. The tail, though long in
                    many varieties of domestic sheep, is' short in all the wild species, in which
                    also the external covering of the body is in the main hairy,—the fine fleecy
                    coats of wool, or hair so modified as to have the property of “felting” or
                    adhering together under pressure, which give such value to many breeds, having
                    been especially cultivated by selective breeding.</p>
                <p>The sheep was a domestic animal in Asia and Europe before the dawn of history,
                    though quite unknown as such in the New World until after the Spanish conquest.
                    It has now been introduced by man into almost all parts of the world where
                    settled agricultural operations are carried on, but flourishes especially in the
                    temperate regions of both hemispheres. Whether our well-known and useful animal
                    is derived from any one of the existing wild species, or from the crossing of
                    several, or from some now extinct species, is quite a matter of conjecture. The
                    variations of external characters seen in the different domestic breeds are very
                    great. They are chiefly manifested in the form and number of the horns, which
                    may be increased from the normal two to four or even eight, or may be altogether
                    absent in the female alone or in both sexes; in the form and length of the ears,
                    which often hang pendent by the side of the head; in the peculiar elevation or
                    arching of the nasal bones in some Eastern races; in the length of the tail, and
                    the development of great masses of fat at each side of its root or in the tail
                    itself; and in the colour and quality of the fleece. See <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Agriculture.</hi></p>
                <p>The distinction of the various permanent modifications under which wild sheep
                    occur is a matter of considerable difficulty. Trivial characters, such as size,
                    slight variations in colour, and especially the form and curvature of the horns,
                    are relied upon by different zoologists who have given attention to the subject
                    in the discrimination of species, but no complete accord has yet been
                    established. The most generally recognized forms are enumerated below.</p>
                <p>The geographical distribution of wild sheep is interesting. The immense mountain
                    ranges of Central Asia, the Pamir and Thian Shan of Turkestan, may be looked
                    upon as the centre of their habitat. Here, at an elevation of 16,000 feet above
                    the sea-level, is the home of the magnificent <hi rend="italic">Ovis poli,</hi>
                    named after the celebrated Venetian traveller Marco Polo, who met with it in his
                    adventurous travels through this region in the 13th century. It is remarkable
                    for the great size of the horns of the old rams and the wide open sweep of their
                    curve, so that the points stand boldly<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n810/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0810-0785"/> out on each side, far away from the animal’s
                    head, instead of curling round nearly in the same plane, as in most of the
                    allied species. A very similar if not identical species from the same origin, in
                    which the horns retain their more normal development, has received the name of
                    <hi rend="italic">O. karelini.</hi> Eastward and northward is found the argali
                    (<hi rend="italic">O</hi>. <hi rend="italic">ammon),</hi> with a wide and not
                    very well determined range. Still further north, in the Stanovoi Mountains and
                    Kamchatka, is <hi rend="italic">O. nivicola,</hi> and away on the other side of
                    Behring’s Strait, in the Rocky Mountains and adjacent high lands of western
                    North America, is the “bighorn” or mountain sheep (<hi rend="italic">O</hi>. <hi
                    rend="italic">montana),</hi> the only one of the genus found in that continent
                    and indeed—except the bison, the musk-ox <hi rend="italic">(Ovibos),</hi>
                    mountain goat <hi rend="italic">(Aploceras),</hi> and the prongbuck <hi
                    rend="italic">(Antilocaρra)—</hi> the only hollow-horned ruminant, being like
                    the rest obviously a straggler from the cradle of its race. Turning southward
                    from the point from which we started, and still a little to the east, in Nepal
                    and Little Tibet, is <hi rend="italic">O. hodgsoni,</hi> a species with large
                    and strongly curved horns, and another with smaller and more spreading horns,
                    the burrhel, <hi rend="italic">O. nahoor.</hi> Passing in a south-westerly
                    direction we find a series of smaller forms, <hi rend="italic">O. vignei</hi> of
                    Ladak, <hi rend="italic">O. cycloceros</hi> of northern India, Persia, and
                    Baluchistan, <hi rend="italic">O. gmelini</hi> of Asia Minor, O <hi
                    rend="italic">. ophian,</hi> confined to the elevated pine-clad Troodos
                    Mountains of the island of Cyprus, and said at the time of the British
                    occupation in 1878 to have been reduced to a flock of about twenty-five
                    individuals, and <hi rend="italic">O. musimon,</hi> the moufflon of Corsica and
                    Sardinia (see figure), believed to have been formerly also a native of Spain.
                    Lastly, we have the somewhat aberrant, goat-like aoudad, <hi rend="italic">O.
                    tragelaphus,</hi> of the great mountain ranges of North Africa.</p>
                <p>We thus find that sheep are essentially inhabitants of high mountainous parts of
                    the world, for dwelling among which their wonderful powers of climbing and
                    leaping give them special advantages. No species frequent by choice either level
                    deserts, open plains, dense forests, or swamps. By far the greater number of
                    species are inhabitants of the continent of Asia, one or perhaps two extending
                    into North America, one into Southern Europe, and one into North Africa. No wild
                    sheep occurs in any other part of the world, unless the so called musk-ox <hi
                    rend="italic">(Ovibos moschatus)</hi> of the Arctic regions, the nearest
                    existing ally to the true sheep, may be considered as one. Geologically
                    speaking, sheep appear to be very modern animals, or perhaps it would be safer
                    to say that no remains that can be with certainty referred to the genus have
                    been met with in the hitherto explored true Tertiary beds, which have yielded
                    such abundant modifications of antelopes and deer. They are apparently not
                    indigenous in the British Isles, but were probably introduced by man from the
                    East in prehistoric times. (W. H. F.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
