<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0487-0466-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SCIPIO (9th edition, volume 21, page 466)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c72h">Gauls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vb0p">Caesars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb7v">Consuls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx0652b">Consulates</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:848005">Carthaginians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n487/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SCIPIO</label>. The Scipios,<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The name means a “stick” or
                    “staff.”</p></note> a memorable name in Roman history, were a branch of the
                    ancient and noble family of the Cornelii. It was in Rome’s wars with Carthage
                    that they made themselves specially famous.</p>
                <p>1. <hi rend="smallcaps">Publius Cornelius Scipio,</hi> the father of the Elder
                    Africanus, was the first Roman general to encounter Hannibal in battle. He was
                    consul in 218 B.C., the first year of the Second Punic War, and, having Spain
                    for his province, he went with an army to Massilia (Marseilles) with the view of
                    arresting the Carthaginian’s advance on Italy. Failing, however, to meet his
                    enemy, he hastened back by sea to Cisalpine Gaul, leaving his army under the
                    command of his brother Cneius Scipio, who was to harass the Carthaginians in
                    Spain and hinder them from supporting Hannibal. In a sharp cavalry engagement in
                    the upper valley of the Po, on the Ticinus, he was defeated and severely
                    wounded, and it is said he owed his life to the bravery of his son, then a mere
                    stripling. Again, in the December of the same year, he witnessed the complete
                    defeat of the Roman army on the Trebia, his colleague Sempronius having insisted
                    on fighting contrary to his advice. But he still retained the confidence of the
                    Roman people, since his term of command was extended, and we find him with his
                    brother in Spain in the following year,<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n488/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0488-0467"/> winning victories over the Carthaginians and
                    strengthening Rome’s hold on that country, till 212 or 211. The details of these
                    campaigns are not accurately known to us, but it would seem that the ultimate
                    defeat and death of the Scipios were due to the desertion of the Celtiberi,
                    bribed by Hasdrubal, Hannibal’s brother.</p>
                <p>2. <hi rend="smallcaps">Publius Cornelius Scipio Africanus the Elder.—</hi> After
                    having been present at the disastrous battles of the Ticinus, the Trebia, and
                    Cannae, and having after that last crushing defeat had the spirit to remonstrate
                    with several Roman nobles who advocated giving up the struggle and quitting
                    Italy in despair, Scipio, at the age of twenty-four, offered to take the command
                    of the Roman army in Spain the year after his father’s death. The people already
                    had an intense belief in him, and he was unanimously elected. All Spain west of
                    the Ebro was in the year of his arrival (210) under Carthaginian control, but
                    fortunately for him the three Carthaginian generals, Hasdrubal (Hannibal’s
                    brother), Hasdrubal the son of Gisgo, and Mago (also Hannibal’s brother), were
                    not disposed to act in concert. Scipio was thus enabled to surprise and capture
                    New Carthage, the headquarters of the Carthaginian power in Spain, from which he
                    obtained a rich booty of war stores and supplies, with a particularly good
                    harbour. The native Spanish tribes now became friendly, and Scipio found useful
                    allies among them. In the following year he fought Hasdrubal somewhere in the
                    upper valley of the Guadalquivir, but the action could hardly have been a
                    decisive one, as soon afterwards the Carthaginian crossed the Pyrenees at the
                    head of a considerable army on his way to Italy. Next year another battle was
                    fought in the same neighbourhood, and Scipio’s success appears to have been
                    sufficiently decided to compel the Carthaginian commanders to fall back on
                    Gades, in the south-western corner of Spain. The country was now for the most
                    part under Roman influence, a result due even more to the statesmanlike tact of
                    Scipio than to his military ability. With the idea of striking a blow at
                    Carthage in Africa, the Roman general paid a short visit to the Numidian
                    princes, Syphax and Masinissa, but at the court of Syphax he was foiled by the
                    presence of Hasdrubal, the son of Gisgo, whose daughter Sophonisba was married
                    to the Numidian chief. On his return to Spain Scipio had to quell a mutiny which
                    had broken out among his troops. Hannibal’s brother Mago had meanwhile sailed
                    for Italy, and Scipio himself in 206, after having established the Roman
                    ascendency in Spain, gave up his command and returned to Rome to stand for the
                    consulship, to which he was unanimously elected the following year, the province
                    of Sicily being assigned to him. By this time Hasdrubal with his army had
                    perished on the Metaurus, and Hannibal’s movements were restricted to the
                    south-western extremity of Italy. For Rome the worst part of the struggle was
                    over. The war was now to be transferred by Scipio from Italy to Africa. He was
                    himself eagerly intent on this, and his great name drew to him a number of
                    volunteers from all parts of Italy. There was but one obstacle: the
                    old-fashioned aristocracy of Rome did not like him, as his taste for splendid
                    living and Greek culture was particularly offensive to them. A party in the
                    senate would have recalled him, but the popular enthusiasm was too strong for
                    them. A commission of inquiry was sent over to Sicily, and it found that he was
                    at the head of a well-equipped fleet and army. At the commissioners’ bidding he
                    sailed in 204 from Lilybaeum (Marsala) and landed on the coast of Africa near
                    Utica. Carthage meanwhile had secured the friendship of the powerful Numidian
                    chief Syphax, whose advance compelled Scipio to raise the siege of Utica and to
                    entrench himself on the shore between that place and Carthage. Next year he
                    surprised and utterly defeated Syphax and drove the Carthaginian army out of the
                    field. There was an attempt at negotiation, but the war party prevailed and
                    Hannibal was recalled from Italy. The decisive battle was fought near the
                    Numidian town of Zama in 202 and ended in Hannibal’s complete defeat. Peace was
                    concluded with the Carthaginians in the following year on terms which strictly
                    confined their dominion to a comparatively small territory in Africa, almost
                    annihilated their fleet, and exacted a heavy war contribution. In fact, the
                    independence of Carthage was destroyed, and it became simply a rich commercial
                    city. The old-fashioned and narrow-minded aristocrats who were in sympathy with
                    the “delenda est Carthago” policy subsequently announced by Cato thought these
                    terms too lenient; but Scipio was too great and too generous a man to lend
                    himself to the base work of utterly extinguishing an ancient and noble centre of
                    civilization. Rome was now perfectly safe from attack. It was a great
                    Mediterranean power: Spain and Sicily were Roman provinces, and the north of
                    Africa was under a Roman protectorate. Such was the end, after seventeen years,
                    of the Second Punic War. Scipio was welcomed back to Rome with the surname of
                    Africanus, and he had the moderation and good sense to refuse the many honours
                    which the people would have thrust upon him. For some years he lived quietly and
                    took no part in politics. In 190 his brother Lucius Scipio was consul and, on
                    the understanding that he should have the benefit of the military skill and
                    experience of Africanus, he was entrusted with the war in Asia against
                    Antiochus. The two brothers brought the war to a conclusion by a decisive
                    victory at Magnesia in the same year. Meanwhile Scipio’s political enemies had
                    gained ground, and on their return to Rome a prosecution was started against
                    Lucius on the ground of misappropriation of moneys received from Antiochus. As
                    Lucius was in the act of producing his account-books his brother wrested them
                    from his hands, tore them in pieces, and flung them on the floor of the
                    senate-house. He was then himself accused of having been bribed by Antiochus,
                    but he reminded his accusers that the day was ill chosen, as it happened to be
                    the anniversary of his great victory over Hannibal at Zama. There was an
                    outburst of enthusiasm, and Scipio was once again the hero and the darling of
                    the Roman people, who, it is said, crowded round him and followed him to the
                    Capitol. After all, however, he ended his days, as a voluntary exile in all
                    probability, at Liternum on the coast of Campania, dying, it would seem, in 183,
                    the year of Hannibal’s death, when a little above fifty years of age. Scipio’s
                    wife was Aemilia, daughter of the Aemilius Paullus who fell at Cannae and who
                    was the father of the conqueror of Macedonia. By her he had a daughter,
                    Cornelia, who became the mother of the two famous Gracchi.</p>
                <p>Spain, Northern Africa, the so-called province of Asia, were added to Rome’s
                    dominion during his life. Scipio lived to see Rome develop from a merely Italian
                    power to be in fact the mistress of the world, and he himself greatly
                    contributed to this result. Among Rome’s great generals we must rank him after
                    Caesar. He knew how to plan a campaign as well as how to fight a battle, and he
                    had the faculty of inspiring his soldiers with confidence and enthusiasm. He
                    never had to make head against such tremendous difficulties as his great
                    antagonist, and his achievements, great as they were, must be distinctly ranked
                    beneath the marvellous successes of Hannibal. Still the story was told that, in
                    a conversation between the two generals at the court of Antiochus, Hannibal, who
                    had named Alexander as the first and Pyrrhus as the second among military
                    commanders, confessed that had he beaten Scipio he should have put himself
                    before either of them. It seems to be at any rate certain that the two great men
                    respected and admired each other, and it is much to Scipio’s credit that he
                    withstood the mean persecution with which the Roman senate followed up the
                    Carthaginian. It may be that he had rather too much aristocratic <hi
                    rend="italic">hauteur</hi> for a statesman in time of peace, but against this we
                    must set the pleasing fact that he was a man of great intellectual culture and
                    could speak and write Greek just as well as his native Latin. He wrote his<pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n489/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0489-0468"/> own memoirs in Greek. There must indeed have been
                    a wonderful charm about the man, and there was a belief that he was a special
                    favourite of heaven and held actual communication with the gods. It is quite
                    possible too that he himself honestly shared this belief; and so it was that to
                    his political opponents he could be harsh and arrogant and towards others
                    singularly gracious and sympathetic. For a time he enjoyed a popularity at Rome
                    which no one but Caesar ever attained.</p>
                <p>3. <hi rend="smallcaps">Publius Cornelius Scipio Africanus the Younger.</hi>
                    —This Scipio, also one of Rome’s greatest generals, was the younger son of
                    Aemilius Paullus, and he fought when a youth of seventeen by his father’s side
                    at Pydna, 168,—the battle which decided the fate of Macedonia and made northern
                    Greece subject to Rome. He was adopted by the eldest son of Scipio Africanus the
                    Elder, and from him took the name Scipio with the surname Africanus. In 151, a
                    time of defeat and disaster for the Romans in Spain, which as yet had been but
                    very imperfectly subjugated, he served with credit in that country and obtained
                    an influence over the native tribes similar to that which the elder Scipio, his
                    grandfather by adoption, had acquired nearly sixty years before him. In the next
                    year an appeal was made to him by the Carthaginians to act as arbiter between
                    them and the Numidian prince Masinissa, who, backed up by a party at Rome, was
                    incessantly encroaching on Carthaginian territory. Rome’s policy in Africa was
                    to hold the balance between Masinissa and Carthage, and, when it was seen that
                    Carthage, as the result of several years of peace, was again becoming a
                    prosperous and powerful city, there grew up a feeling at Rome that the Numidian
                    king must be supported and their old rival thoroughly humiliated. Marcus Cato
                    and his party would hear of no compromise; Carthage, they said, must be
                    destroyed if Rome was to be safe. It was easy to find a pretext for war in the
                    disputes between Carthage and Masinissa. In 149 war was declared, and the
                    Carthaginians felt it to be a life-and-death struggle: every man and every woman
                    laboured to the uttermost for the defence of the city with a furious enthusiasm.
                    The Roman army, in which Scipio at first served in a subordinate capacity, was
                    utterly baffled. In the following year he was elected consul, while yet under
                    the legal age, for the express purpose of giving him the supreme command. After
                    two years of desperate fighting and splendid heroism on the part of the
                    defenders, the famished garrison could no longer hold the walls: Carthage was
                    captured, and the ruins of the city were burning for seventeen days; Rome
                    decreed that the place should be for ever desolate. On his return to Rome Scipio
                    became the subject of violent political attacks, against which he successfully
                    defended himself in speeches (no longer extant) that ranked as brilliant
                    specimens of oratory. In 134 he was again consul, with the province of Spain,
                    where a demoralized Roman army was vainly attempting the conquest of Numantia on
                    the Douro. Scipio, after devoting several months to the discipline of his
                    troops, reduced the city by blockade. The fall of Numantia, which was utterly
                    destroyed in 133, established the Roman dominion in the province of Hither or
                    Nearer Spain, the eastern portion of that country. Rome meanwhile was shaken by
                    the great political agitation of the Gracchi, whose sister Sempronia was
                    Scipio’s wife. Scipio himself, though not in sympathy with the extreme men of
                    the old conservative party, was decidedly opposed to the schemes of the Gracchi.
                    “Justly slain” (jure caesum) is said to have been his answer to the tribune
                    Carbo, who asked him before the people what he thought of the death of Tiberius
                    Gracchus. This gave dire offence to the popular party, which was now led by his
                    bitterest foes. Soon afterwards, in 129, he was found dead in bed on the morning
                    of a day on which he had intended to make a speech on a point connected with the
                    agrarian proposals of the Gracchi,—“<hi rend="italic">a</hi> victim of political
                    assassination” Mommsen confidently pronounces him. The mystery was never cleared
                    up, and there were political reasons for letting the matter drop.</p>
                <p>The Younger Scipio, great general and great man as he was, is for ever associated
                    with a hideous work of destruction at Carthage, which we feel he might have done
                    more to avert. Yet he was a man of culture and refinement; he gathered round him
                    such men as the Greek historian Polybius, the philosopher Panaetius, and the
                    poets Lucilius and Terence. And at the same time, according to Polybius and
                    Cicero, he had all the good sterling virtues of an old-fashioned Roman, and
                    steadily set his face against the increasing luxury and extravagance of his day.
                    As a speaker he seems to have been no less distinguished than as a soldier. He
                    spoke remarkably good and pure Latin, and he particularly enjoyed serious and
                    intellectual conversation. There seems to have been nothing mean or grasping
                    about him. After the capture of Carthage he gave back to the Greek cities of
                    Sicily the works of art of which Carthage had robbed them. He did not avail
                    himself of the many opportunities he must have had of amassing a fortune. Though
                    politically opposed to the Gracchi, he cannot be said to have been a foe to the
                    interests of the people. He was, in fact, a moderate man, in favour of
                    conciliation, and he was felt by the best men to be a safe political adviser,
                    while, as often happens in such cases, he could not help offending both
                    parties.</p>
                <p>4. Scipios are continually appearing in Roman history in more or less prominent
                    positions down to the time of the empire. One of them, <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Scipio Nasica</hi> (Nasica denoting an aquiline nose), contemporary of the
                    Younger Africanus, instigated the murder of Tiberius Gracchus, whom the people
                    were bent on re-electing (133) to the tribuneship. Though he was pontifex
                    maximus at the time, the senate, to save him, had to get him away from Rome, and
                    he left never to return, dying soon afterwards in Asia. (w. j. <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
