<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0415-0394-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SCHIEFNER, Franz Anton (9th edition, volume 21, page
                    394)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1150682">Tibetans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:986195">Karagasses</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:824449">Awareness</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1095153">Research</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:863557">Classicism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1156484">Tribes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1052348">Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k877">Research</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44b2x66s">Classicism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r785w31">Paper</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h708690">Ostiaks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n415/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SCHIEFNER, <hi rend="smallcaps">Franz Anton</hi></label>
                    (1817-1879), linguist, was born at Reval, in Russia, on the 18th July 1817. His
                    father was a merchant who had emigrated from Bohemia at the end of last century.
                    He received his education at the grammar school of his native place, where also
                    his subsequent colleague, the celebrated naturalist Karl Ernst von Baer, had
                    been brought up. He matriculated at St Petersburg as a law student in 1836, but
                    while qualifying for this profession he pursued with keen interest the study of
                    the classics, and subsequently devoted himself at Berlin, from 1840 to 1842,
                    exclusively to Eastern languages. On his return to St Petersburg in 1843 he was
                    employed in teaching the classics in the First Grammar School, and soon
                    afterwards received a post in the Imperial Academy, where in 1852 the
                    cultivation of the Tibetan language and literature was assigned to him as his
                    special function. Simultaneously he held from 1860 to 1873 the professorship of
                    classical languages in the Roman Catholic theological seminary. From 1854 till
                    his death he was an extraordinary member of the Imperial Academy. He died after
                    a fortnight’s illness on the 16th November 1879.</p>
                <p>Schiefner made bis mark in literary research in three directions. First, he
                    contributed to the <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Bulletin</hi> of the St Petersburg Academy, and brought out independently, a
                    number of valuable articles and larger publications on the language and
                    literature of Tibet. He possessed also a remarkable acquaintance with Mongolian,
                    and when death overtook him had just finished a revision of the New Testament in
                    that language with which the British and Foreign Bible Society had entrusted
                    him. Further, he was one of the greatest authorities on the philology and
                    ethnology of the Finnic tribes. He edited and translated the great Finnic epic
                    <hi rend="italic">Kalevala</hi>; he arranged, completed, and brought out in
                    twelve volumes the literary remains of Alexander Castrén, bearing on the
                    languages of the Samoyedic tribes, the Koibal, Karagass, Tungusian, Buryat,
                    Ostiak, and Kottic tongues, and prepared several valuable papers on Finnic
                    mythology for the Imperial Academy. In the third place, he made himself the
                    exponent of recent investigations into the languages of the Caucasus, which,
                    thanks to his lucid analyses, have now been placed within reach of European
                    philologists. Thus he gave a full analysis of the Tush language, and in quick
                    succession, from Baron P. Uslar’s investigations, comprehensive papers on the
                    Awar, Ude, Abkhasian, Tchetchenz, Kasi-Kumük, Hürkanian and Kürinian languages.
                    He had also completely mastered the Ossetic, and brought out a number of
                    translations from that language, several of them accompanied by the original
                    text. For many of his linguistical investigations he had, with as much tact as
                    patience, availed himself of the presence in St Petersburg of natives (soldiers
                    chiefly) of the districts on the languages of which he happened to be engaged.
                    The importance, however, of the vast mass of linguistical material thus opened
                    up by him, and of the results to which his investigations led, has not yet been
                    fully realized, except so far, perhaps, as his numerous contributions to our
                    knowledge of Eastern fables are concerned, for which branch of literature he
                    evinced throughout his works a keen appreciation.</p>
                <p>With a rare philological acumen, which with equal facility grasped the
                    morphological and idiomatic parts of a language, Schiefner combined an
                    indefatigable industry and a love of research which never flagged. He visited
                    England three times for purposes of research,—in 1863, 1867, and 1878,—when he
                    endeared himself to all who were brought in contact with him by his modesty and
                    single-heartedness, his animated and spirited conversation, and his unswerving
                    devotion to his various literary pursuits.<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n416/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0416-0395"/> The following list of his works has been drawn up
                    from biographical notices which appeared in the <hi rend="italic">Athenaeum
                    for</hi> 24th January 1880, and in the <hi rend="italic">Bulletin of</hi> the St
                    Petersburg Academy, xxvi. pp. 30-44 :— <hi rend="italic">Bemerkungen eum
                    Poley'schen Text des Devîmâhâtmyα,</hi> 1846; <hi rend="italic">Beiträge zur
                    Kritik des Bhartrihari aus Cârngadhara's Paddhati,</hi> 1847; (with A. Weber),
                    <hi rend="italic">Varix Lectiones ad Bohlenii editionem Bhartriharis
                    sententiarum pertinentes,</hi> 1850; <hi rend="italic">Ueber die logischen und
                    grammatischen Werke des Tandjur,</hi> 1847; <hi rend="italic">Ueber Indra's
                    Donnerkeil,</hi> 1848; <hi rend="italic">Nachträge zu den von 0. Böhtlingk und
                    J. Schmidt verfassten Verzeichnissen der auf Indien und Tibet bezüglichen
                    Handschriften und Holzdrucke im asiatischen Museum der k. Akademie der
                    Wissenschaften,</hi> 1848; <hi rend="italic">Bine tibetische Lebensbeschreibung
                    Çâkyamuni’s,</hi> 1848; <hi rend="italic">Ueber das Werk "Rgya tch'er rol
                    pa,"</hi> 1848-50; <hi rend="italic">Tibetische Studien,</hi> 1851-64; <hi
                    rend="italic">Ueber eine eigenthümliche Art der tibetischen Composita,</hi>
                    1856; <hi rend="italic">Ueber Pluralbezeichnungen im Tibetischen,</hi> 1877; <hi
                    rend="italic">Ueber die Verschlechterungs-Perioden der Menschheit nach
                    buddhistischer Anschauungsweise,</hi> 1851; <hi rend="italic">Bericht über die
                    neueste Büchersendung aus Peking,</hi> 1851; <hi rend="italic">Das buddhistische
                    Sûtra der</hi> 42 <hi rend="italic">Sätze aus dem Tibetischen übersetzt,</hi>
                    1851; <hi rend="italic">Ergänzungen und Berichtigungen zu J. Schmidt's Ausgabe
                    des Dsanglun,</hi> 1852; <hi rend="italic">Ueber das Werk “Histoire de la vie de
                    Hiouen-thsang,"</hi> 1853; <hi rend="italic">Bericht über die wissenschaftliche
                    Thätigkeit des Herrn Professors Wassiljew,</hi> 1854; <hi rend="italic">Uber die
                    nepalischen, assamischen, und ceylonischen Münzen des asiatischen Museums,</hi>
                    1854; <hi rend="italic">Ein kleiner Beitrag zur mongolischen Paläographie,</hi>
                    1856; <hi rend="italic">Sprachliche Bedenken gegen das Mongolenthum der
                    Skythen,</hi> 1856; <hi rend="italic">Bericht über Prof, Wassiljew’s Werk über
                    den Buddhismus,</hi> 1856; <hi rend="italic">Ueber die unter dem Namen
                    “Geschichte des Ardshi Bordshi Chan,” bekannte mongolische Märchensammlung,</hi>
                    1857; <hi rend="italic">Carminis indici Vimalapraçnottara ratnamâlâ versio
                    tibetica, mit deutscher Uebersetzung,</hi> 1856; <hi rend="italic">Buddhistische
                    Triglotte,</hi> 1859; <hi rend="italic">Ueber ein indisches Krähenorakel,</hi>
                    1859; <hi rend="italic">Ueber die hohen Zahlen der Buddhisten,</hi> 1862; <hi
                    rend="italic">Jäschke’s Bemühungen um eine Handschrift des Gesar,</hi> 1868; <hi
                    rend="italic">Târanâthae de doctrinae buddhicae in India propagatione narratio
                    tibetica,</hi> 1868 (German, 1869); <hi rend="italic">Ueber einige
                    morgenländische Fassungen der Rhampsinitsage,</hi> 1869; <hi rend="italic">Zur
                    buddhistischen Apokalyptik,</hi> 1874; <hi rend="italic">Bharatae responsa, tib.
                    et latine,</hi> 1874; <hi rend="italic">Mahâkâtjâjana und König
                    Tchanda-pradjota,</hi> 1875; <hi rend="italic">Indische Künstleranekdoten,</hi>
                    1875; <hi rend="italic">Indische Erzählungen,</hi> 1876-77 (an English
                    translation of these by W. R. S. Ralston appeared in 1882); <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ueber Vasubandhu’s Gâthâsangraha,</hi> 1878; <hi rend="italic">Ueber eine
                    tibetische Handschrift des India House,</hi> 1879; <hi rend="italic">Ueber das
                    Bonpo-Sùtra,</hi> 1880; <hi rend="italic">Zur Sampo-mythe,</hi> 1850; <hi
                    rend="italic">Kleine Beiträge zur finnischen Mythologie,</hi> 1852; <hi
                    rend="italic">Zur ehstnischen Mythologie,</hi> 1854; <hi rend="italic">Ueber den
                    Mythengehalt der finnischen Märchen,</hi> 1855; <hi rend="italic">Ueber die
                    Heldensagen der minussinischen Tataren,</hi> 1858; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Heldensagen, &amp;c., rhythmisch bearbeitet,</hi> 1859; <hi rend="italic">Zum
                    Mythus vom Weltuntergange,</hi> 1859; <hi rend="italic">Ueber die ehstnische
                    Sage vom Kalewi-poeg,</hi> 1860; <hi rend="italic">Zur russischen
                    Heldensage,</hi> 1861; <hi rend="italic">Ueber Kalewa und die Kalewingen,</hi>
                    1862; <hi rend="italic">Kalevala, deutsch in rhythmischer Form,</hi> 1852; <hi
                    rend="italic">Ueber das Thier “tarvas” im finnischen Epos,</hi> 1848-49; <hi
                    rend="italic">Die Lieder der Woten, metrisch übertragen,</hi> 1856; <hi
                    rend="italic">Ueber das Wort “sampo” im finnischen Epos,</hi> 1861; Versuch <hi
                    rend="italic">einer ostjakischen Sprachlehre,</hi> 1849-1856; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Grammatik und Wörterverzeichnisse der samojedischen Sprachen,</hi> 1854-1855;
                    <hi rend="italic">Grundzüge einer tungusischen Sprachlehre,</hi> 1856; <hi
                    rend="italic">Versuch einer burjätischen Sprachlehre,</hi> 1857; <hi
                    rend="italic">Versuch einer koibalischen und karagassischen Sprachlehre,</hi>
                    1857; <hi rend="italic">Versuch einer jenisei-osljakischen und kottischen
                    Sprachlehre,</hi> 1858; <hi rend="italic">Das 13-monatliche Jahr und die
                    Monatsnamen der sibirischen Völker,</hi> 1856; <hi rend="italic">Ueber die
                    Sprache der Jukagiren, 1859-71∙, Beiträge zur Kenntniss der tungusischen
                    Mundarten,</hi> 1859; <hi rend="italic">Tungusische Miscellen,</hi> 1874; <hi
                    rend="italic">Ueber die von G. von Maydell gesammelten tungusischen
                    Sprachproben,</hi> 1874; <hi rend="italic">A. Czekanowski’s tungusisches
                    Wörterverzeichniss,</hi> 1877; <hi rend="italic">Ueber sibirische
                    Eigenthumszeichen,</hi> 1855-1859; <hi rend="italic">Kurze Charakteristik der
                    Thuschsprache,</hi> 1854; <hi rend="italic">Versuch über die Thuschsprache,</hi>
                    1856; <hi rend="italic">Versuch über das Awarische,</hi> 1862; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ueber Baron Uslar's neuere linguistische Forschungen,</hi> 1863; <hi
                    rend="italic">Versuch über die Sprache der Uden,</hi> 1863; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ausführlicher Bericht über Baron Uslar’s abchasische Studien,</hi> 1863; <hi
                    rend="italic">Tschetschenzische Studien,</hi> 1864; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ausführlicher Bericht über Baron Uslar's Kasikumükische Studien,</hi> 1866; <hi
                    rend="italic">Hürkanische Studien,</hi> 1871; <hi rend="italic">Awarische
                    Studien,</hi> 1872; <hi rend="italic">Kürinisehe Studien,</hi> 1873; <hi
                    rend="italic">Awarische Texte,</hi> 1873; <hi rend="italic">Ossetische
                    Sprüchwörter,</hi> 1862; <hi rend="italic">Ossetische Texte,</hi> 1863; <hi
                    rend="italic">Zwei ossetische Thiermärchen,</hi> 1864; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ossetische Sagen und Märchen,</hi> 1867,</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
