<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0257-0238-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SALVIAN (9th edition, volume 21, page 238)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1053407">Parenting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1053451">Parents</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:939002">Gauls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f285">Parents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c72h">Gauls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4nv99d8g">Huns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34n208">Vandals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4599z56c">Goths</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n257/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SALVIAN</label>, a Christian writer of the 5th century, was
                    born in Gaul, and most probably in the neighbourhood of Treves or Cologne <hi
                    rend="italic">(De Gub. Dei,</hi> vi. 8, 13). His birth has been conjecturally
                    assigned to the period from 390 to 420. He was probably brought up as a
                    Christian, though of this there is no absolute proof. Zschimmer considers his
                    writings to show that he had made a special study of the law; and this is the
                    more likely as he appears to have been of noble birth and could describe one of
                    his relations as being “of no small account in her own district and not obscure
                    in family” (Ap. i.). He was already a Christian when he married Palladia, the
                    daughter of heathen parents, Hypatius and Quieta, whose displeasure he incurred
                    by persuading his wife to retire with him to a distant monastery, which is
                    almost certainly to be identified with that so lately founded by St Honoratus at
                    Lerins. For seven years there was no communication between the two branches of
                    the family, till at last, when Hypatius had become a Christian, Salvian wrote
                    him a most touching letter in his own name, his wife’s, and that of his little
                    daughter Auspiciola, begging for the renewal of the old affection <hi
                    rend="italic">(Ep.</hi> iv.). This whole letter is a most curious illustration
                    of Salvian’s reproach against his age that the noblest man at once forfeited all
                    esteem if he became a monk <hi rend="italic">(De Gub.,</hi> iv. 7 <hi
                    rend="italic">; cf.</hi> viii. 4).</p>
                <p>It was presumably at Lerins that Salvian made the acquaintance of St Honoratus
                    <hi rend="italic">(ob.</hi> 429), St Hilary of Arles <hi rend="italic">(ob.</hi>
                    449), and St Eucher of Lyons <hi rend="italic">(ob.</hi> 449). That he was a
                    friend of the former and wrote an account of his life we learn from St Hilary
                    (<hi rend="italic">Vita Hon.,</hi> ap. Migne, 1. 1260). To St Eucher’s two sons,
                    Salonius and Veranus, he acted as tutor in consort with St Vincent of Lerins. As
                    he succeeded St Honoratus and St Hilary in this office, this date cannot well be
                    later than the year 426 or 427, when the former was called to Arles, whither he
                    seems to have summoned Hilary before his death in 429 <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Eucherii Instructio ad Salonium,</hi> ap. Migne, 1. 773; Salv., <hi
                    rend="italic">Ep.</hi> ii.). Salvian continued his friendly intercourse with
                    both father and sons long after the latter had left his care; it was to Salonius
                    (then a bishop) that he wrote his explanatory letter just after the publication
                    of his treatise <hi rend="italic">Ad Ecclesiam</hi>; and to the same prelate a
                    few years later he dedicated his great work, the <hi rend="italic">De
                    Gubernatione Dei.</hi> The above facts, as will be seen, render it almost
                    certain that he must have been born a good deal before 420. If French scholars
                    are right in assigning Hilary’s <hi rend="italic">Vita Honorati</hi> to 430,
                    Salvian, who is there called a priest, had probably already left Lyons for
                    Marseilles, where he is known to have spent the last years of his life (Genn.,
                    ap. Migne, lviii. 1099). It was probably from Marseilles that he wrote his first
                    letter—presumably to Lerins—begging the community there to receive his kinsman,
                    the son of a widow of Cologne, who had been reduced to poverty by the barbarian
                    invasions. It seems a fair inference from this letter that Salvian, acting up to
                    the precepts of his own treatise <hi rend="italic">Ad Ecclesiam,</hi> had
                    divested himself of all his property in favour of that society and, having no
                    longer any possessions of his own, sent his relative to Lerins for assistance
                    <hi rend="italic">(Ep.</hi> i., with which compare <hi rend="italic">Ad
                    Eccles.,</hi> ii. 9, 10; iii. 5). It has been conjectured that Salvian paid a
                    visit to Carthage; but this is a mere inference based on the minute details he
                    gives of<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n258/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0258-0239"/> the state of this city just before its fall (De
                    <hi rend="italic">Gub.,</hi> vii., viii.). He seems to have been still living at
                    Marseilles when Gennadius wrote under the papacy of Gelasius (492-496).</p>
                <p>Of Salvian’s writings there are still extant two treatises, entitled respectively
                    <hi rend="italic">De Gubernatione Dei</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Ad
                    Ecclesiam,</hi> and a series of nine letters. The <hi rend="italic">De
                    Gubernatione,</hi> Salvian’s greatest work, was published after the capture of
                    Litorius at Toulouse (439), to which he plainly alludes in vii. 10, and after
                    the Vandal conquest of Carthage in the same year (vi. 12), but before Attila’s
                    invasion (450), as Salvian speaks of the Huns, not as enemies of the empire, but
                    as serving in the Roman armies (vii. 9). The words “proximum bellum” seem to
                    denote a year very soon after 439. In this work Salvian deals with the same
                    problem that had moved the eloquence of St Augustine and Orosius. Why were these
                    miseries falling on the empire? Could it be, as the pagans said, because the age
                    had forsaken its old gods? or, as the semi-pagan creed of some Christians
                    taught, that God did not constantly overrule the world he had created (i. 1)?
                    With the former Salvian will not argue (iii. 1). To the latter he replies by
                    asserting that, “just as the navigating steersman never looses the helm, so does
                    God never remove his care from the world.” Hence the title of the treatise. In
                    books i. and ii. Salvian sets himself to prove God’s constant guidance, first by
                    the facts of Scripture history, and secondly by the enumeration of special texts
                    declaring this truth. Having thus “laid the foundations” of his work, he
                    declares in book iii. that the misery of the Roman world is all due to the
                    neglect of God’s commandments and the terrible sins of every class of society.
                    It is not merely that the slaves are thieves and runaways, wine-bibbers and
                    gluttons,—the rich are worse (iv. 3). It is their harshness and greed that drive
                    the poor to join the Bagaudae and fly for shelter to the barbarian invaders (v.
                    5 and 6). Everywhere the taxes are heaped upon the needy, while the rich, who
                    have the apportioning of the impost, escape comparatively free (v. 7). The great
                    towns are wholly given up to the abominations of the circus and the theatre,
                    where decency is wholly set at nought, and Minerva, Mars, Neptune, and the old
                    gods are still worshipped (vi. 11; <hi rend="italic">cf. vi. 2</hi> and viii.
                    2). Treves was almost destroyed by the barbarians; yet the first petition of its
                    few surviving nobles was that the emperor would re-establish the circus games as
                    a remedy for the ruined city (vi. 15). And this was the prayer of Christians,
                    whose baptismal oath pledged them to renounce "the devil and his works . . . the
                    pomps and shows (spectacula)” of this wicked world (vi. 6). Darker still were
                    the iniquities of Carthage, surpassing even the unconcealed licentiousness of
                    Gaul and Spain (iv. 5); and more fearful to Salvian than all else was it to hear
                    men swear “by Christ” that they would commit a crime (iv. 15). It would be the
                    atheist’s strongest argument if God left such a state of society unpunished (iv.
                    12),— especially among Christians, whose sin, since they alone had the
                    Scriptures, was worse than that of barbarians, even if equally wicked, would be
                    (v. 2). But, as a matter of fact, the latter had at least some shining virtues
                    mingled with their vices, whereas the Romans were wholly corrupt (vii. 15, iv.
                    14). With this iniquity of the Romans Salvian contrasts the chastity of the
                    Vandals, the piety of the Goths, and the ruder virtues of the Franks, the
                    Saxons, and the other tribes to whom, though heretic Arians or unbelievers, God
                    is giving in reward the inheritance of the empire (vii. 9, 11, 21). It is
                    curious that Salvian shows no such hatred of the heterodox barbarians as was
                    rife in Gaul seventy years later.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ad Ecclesiam</hi> is sufficiently explained by its common
                    title, <hi rend="italic">Contra Avaritiam.</hi> It is quoted more than once in
                    the <hi rend="italic">De Gubernatione.</hi> Salvian published it under the name
                    of Timothy, and explained his motives for so doing in a letter to his old pupil,
                    Bishop Salonius <hi rend="italic">(Ep.</hi> ix. ). This work is chiefly
                    remarkable because in some places it seems to recommend parents not to bequeath
                    anything to their children, on the plea that it is better for the children to
                    suffer want in this world than that their parents should be damned in the next
                    (iii. 4). Salvian is very clear on the duty of absolute selfdenial in the case
                    of sacred virgins, priests, and monks (ii. 8-10). Several works mentioned by
                    Gennadius, notably a poem “in morem Graecorum” on the six days of creation
                    (hexaemeron), and certain homilies composed for bishops, are now lost (Genn.,
                    67).</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Ad Ecclesiam</hi> was first printed in Sichard’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Antidoton</hi> (Basel, 1528); the <hi rend="italic">Re
                    Gubernatione</hi> by Brassican (Basel, 1530). The two appeared in one volume at
                    Paris in 1575. Pithoeus added variae lectiones and the first seven letters
                    (Paris, 1580); Ritterhusius made various conjectural emendations (Altorf, 1611),
                    and Baluze many more based on MS. authority (Paris, 1663-1669). Numerous other
                    editions appeared from the 16th to the 18th century, all of which are now
                    superseded by the excellent ones of C. Halm (Berlin, 1877) and F. Pauly (Vienna,
                    1883). The two oldest MSS. of the <hi rend="italic">Re Gubernatione</hi> belong
                    to the 10th century (Cod. Paris, No. 13,385) and the 13th (Brussels, 10,628); of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Ad Ecclesiam</hi> to the 10th (Paris, 2172) and the 11th
                    (Paris, 2785); of <hi rend="italic">Epistle IX.</hi> to the 9th (Paris, 2785);
                    of <hi rend="italic">Epistle VIII.</hi> to the 7th or 8th century (Paris,
                    95,559) and to the 9th or 10th century (Paris, 12,237,12,236). Of the first
                    seven epistles there is only one MS. extant, of which one part is now at Bern
                    (No. 219), the other at Paris (No. 3791). See <hi rend="italic">Histoire
                    Littéraire de France,</hi> vol. ii.; Zschimmer’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Salvianus</hi> (Halle, 1875). Salvian’s works are reprinted (after Baluze) in
                    Migne’s <hi rend="italic">Cursus Patrologiae,</hi> vol. liii. For bibliography
                    see T. G. Schoenemann’s <hi rend="italic">Bibliotheca Patrum</hi> (ii. 823) and
                    the prefaces to the editions of Halm and Pauly. Gennadius, St Hilary, and St
                    Eucher may be consulted in Migne, vols, lviii. and 1. (T. A. A.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
