<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0145-0128-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SABINES (9th edition, volume 21, page 128)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1048190">Originality</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1033832">Nationalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:814541">Arm</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1048651">Oscans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w922">Writers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49s1kk48">Arm</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20h7x">Valleys</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n145/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SABINES</label>. The Sabines (Sabini) were a people of
                    Central Italy, who played an important part in the early history of Rome.
                    According to all old writers they were one of the most ancient nations of Italy,
                    and the parent stock from which many of the other tribes that occupied the
                    central and southern regions of the peninsula derived their origin. Of their own
                    origin and affinities we know very little. Strabo calls them a very ancient race
                    and “autochthonous,” which may be taken as signifying that there was no
                    authentic tradition of their immigration, or of the quarter from whence they
                    came. The story of their Laconian descent may be safely rejected as one of those
                    fictions by which a certain class of the later Greek writers sought to derive
                    every people in Italy from a Greek origin. But the evidence concerning their
                    language, scanty as it is, is sufficient to prove that they were a cognate race
                    with the neighbouring Umbrians and Oscans, as well as, more remotely, with the
                    Latins. Cato, the best authority among the Roman writers with respect to the
                    different races of Italy, affirmed that the Sabines originally occupied the
                    country about Amiternum, in the upper valley of the Aternus, at the foot of the
                    loftiest group of the Apennines. From thence they gradually extended themselves
                    into the fertile valleys about Reate, where we find them established in
                    historical times, and occupied the tract from thence to the Tiber and the Anio.
                    But even in its widest extension the region held by the Sabines was of small
                    dimensions, and for the most part of a rugged and mountainous character. Hence
                    it was natural that they should seek a place for their superfluous population by
                    repeated emigrations into the neighbouring districts, and the general tradition
                    among Roman writers ascribed the origin of several of the more powerful and
                    populous nations of the peninsula to such emigrations. This result was
                    especially promoted by a custom which, though not unknown to the other nations
                    of Italy, appears to have been peculiarly characteristic of the Sabines—that of
                    a Ver Sacrum, or “sacred spring,” when everything born in that year was
                    consecrated to some local divinity, most frequently to Mamers or Mars. All the
                    cattle were duly sacrificed, while the young men were allowed to grow up to
                    manhood, and then sent forth in a body to seek for themselves new abodes beyond
                    the limits of their native land. To such colonies is ascribed the foundation of
                    the Picentes or people of Picenum, the Samnites, and the Hirpini. Of these the
                    last-mentioned derived their name from <hi rend="italic">hirpus,</hi> the Sabine
                    name for a wolf, an animal of that description being supposed to have been
                    divinely sent as the leader of the colony, as a woodpecker <hi rend="italic"
                    >(picus),</hi> also sacred to Mars, became that of the Piceni. The Peligni also,
                    as we learn from Ovid, himself a native of the district, claimed a Sabine
                    origin, and the same was probably the case with the smaller kindred tribes of
                    the Marsi, Marrucini, and Vestini. The Samnites, again, in their turn sent forth
                    the Frentani and the Lucanians, who extended their dominion throughout the
                    mountainous regions of<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n146/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0146-0129"/> Southern Italy and carried their arms from the
                    Adriatic to the Sicilian Straits.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile the Sabines themselves were confined within comparatively narrow
                    limits, and their extension towards the south was checked by the growing power
                    of the Latins. Here their power appears to have attained its highest point about
                    the time of the foundation of Rome, and the legendary history, familiar to every
                    schoolboy, of the contests between Romulus and Tatius, the divided sovereignty
                    at one time established between them, and the peaceful reign and legislation of
                    the Sabine king Numa may be taken as representing the historical fact that the
                    population of Rome really contained an important Sabine element, and that Sabine
                    influences were largely intermixed with those of Latin origin, both in the civil
                    institutions and still more in the religious rites and ceremonies of the rising
                    republic. Beyond this it is impossible to pronounce with certainty as to the
                    real value and significance of the traditions preserved to us in the poetical
                    legends transmitted in the garb of history; and it is impossible in an article
                    like the present to give even an outline of the various theories that have been
                    devised by modern writers to put an historical interpretation upon the records
                    thus preserved to us. It is clear, however, that the power of the Sabines was by
                    no means broken, even by the establishment of the more powerful monarchy at Rome
                    under the Tarquins, and for a period of more than fifty years after the fall of
                    the monarchy we find the Romans engaged in almost perpetual hostilities against
                    the Sabines on the one side and the AEquians and Volscians on the other. At
                    length in the year 449 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> the Sabines were defeated
                    by the consul M. Horatius, in an action which appears to have been of so
                    decisive a character that we do not find them again appearing in arms against
                    the Romans for a period of more than 160 years. Their quiescence is the more
                    singular as during this interval the republic was engaged in the long series of
                    the Samnite Wars, in which their adversaries were the direct descendants of the
                    Sabines, and had therefore every claim on their support. Still more
                    unaccountable is it that, after looking on with apparent neutrality for so long,
                    we find the Sabines in the year 290 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> once more in
                    arms against Rome, and that at a period when the Third Samnite War had for a
                    time crushed all the hopes of their natural allies. The result was, as might
                    have been expected, that they found themselves wholly unequal to contend
                    single-handed against the power of Rome, and the consul M’. Curius Dentatus
                    reduced them to submission in a single campaign. They were severely punished for
                    this defection; and henceforth their national existence was at an end. Those who
                    survived the slaughter of the war were admitted to the position of Roman
                    citizens, though at first without the right of suffrage, but twenty years after
                    this also was granted them, and they were to all intents and purposes
                    incorporated in the Roman state. Thus separated from all the tribes of kindred
                    origin, they never again appear in history, and, like the Campanians and Latins,
                    were content to swell the ranks of the Roman legions even in the fierce struggle
                    of the Social War (91- 88 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.).</hi> Under the
                    arrangements of the Roman empire their very name was lost as a territorial
                    designation, but it always continued in popular use, and was revived in the
                    Middle Ages as that of an ecclesiastical province. Even at the present day every
                    peasant in the neighbourhood of Rome will point to La Sabina as the familiar
                    appellation of the lofty mountain tract to the north of the city.</p>
                <p>The limits of the territory occupied by the Sabines do not appear to have varied
                    much from a very early period till the days of Strabo. That geographer describes
                    them as extending as far south as Eretum near the Tiber, on the road to Rome,
                    and a few miles only from Cures, the reputed birthplace of Tatius and Numa, but
                    which in his time had become a mere village. The principal town of the Sabines
                    was Reate (still called Rieti), in the midst of the beautiful and fertile valley
                    of the Velino, and from thence they occupied the upper valley of that river to
                    its sources in the Monte della Sibilla and the rugged mountain valleys which
                    connected it with that of the Aternus. Here was found Amiternum, the original
                    capital of the tribe, near the modern Aquila, and between that and Reate lay
                    Interocrea (Antrodoco), in a pass that has always formed one of the leading
                    lines of communication through the central Apennines. In the extreme north was
                    Nursia (Norcia), noted for the coldness of its climate, and celebrated in
                    ecclesiastical history as the birthplace of St Benedict. These were the only
                    towns of any importance in the territory of the Sabines; but they lived for the
                    most part scattered in villages about the mountains, a circumstance absurdly
                    alleged by some Roman writers as a proof of their Laconian origin. It was
                    doubtless owing to this habit, as well as to the rugged mountainous character of
                    the country in which they dwelt, that the Sabines owed the primitive simplicity
                    of their manners and the frugal and severe character which distinguished them
                    even in the days of Augustus. All readers of Horace must be familiar with his
                    frequent allusions to the moral purity and frugal manners of the people that
                    surrounded his Sabine villa, which was situated on the reverse of Mount
                    Lucretilis, only about 15 miles from the rich and luxurious Tibur (Tivoli). The
                    small town of Varia (Vicovaro), in its immediate neighbourhood, seems to have
                    marked the frontier on this side.</p>
                <p>No remains of the Sabine language are extant in the form of inscriptions, but
                    coins struck during the Social War with the inscription “Safinim” show that the
                    native appellation was the same as that in use among the Latins. The form
                    “Sabellus” is frequently found in Latin writers as an ethnic adjective
                    equivalent to Sabine; but the practice adopted by modern writers, of employing
                    the term “Sabellian” to designate all the tribes of Sabine origin, including
                    Samnites, Lucanians, &amp;c., was first introduced by Niebuhr, and is not
                    supported by any ancient authority, <hi rend="smallcaps">(e. h. b.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
