<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0174-0157-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ST ANDREWS (9th edition, volume 21, page 157)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170190">Walls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1153279">Towers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:852215">Chapels</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1134794">Streets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1039127">Normans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1109058">Scones</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47s7ht9n">Walls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zv9m">Streets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s53t">Normans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4125q963">Dominicans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gm81p0j">Bells</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n174/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ST ANDREWS</label>, a city, royal burgh, university town, and
                    seaport of Scotland, in the county of Fife, is situated on a bay of the German
                    Ocean and on a branch of the North British Railway, 9 miles east of Cupar and 11
                    south-south-east of Dundee. It occupies a platform of sandstone rock about 50
                    feet in height, running east and west and presenting to the sea a precipitous
                    wall, which has been much encroached on by its action within recent years. The
                    principal streets (North Street, Market Street, and South Street) diverge from
                    the cathedral and run east and west, and Queen Street runs south from the centre
                    of South Street. Many new houses and villas have been recently erected towards
                    the south, north, and west. The prosperity of the city depends primarily on its
                    educational institutions, especially the university. The golf links, which are
                    considered the best in Scotland, and sea-bathing attract many residents and
                    visitors. In the 16th century St Andrews was one of the most important ports
                    north of the Forth, and is said to have numbered 14,000 inhabitants; but it fell
                    into decay after the Civil War, and, although it has much increased in the
                    present century, its trade has not revived to any extent. The harbour, protected
                    by a pier 630 feet in length, affords entrance to vessels of 100 tons burden.
                    The principal imports are wood and coals and the principal exports agricultural
                    pro duce. The herring and deep-sea fishing is carried on by about 170 fishermen.
                    The evidences of antiquity in the dwelling-houses are comparatively few. The
                    city was never surrounded by walls, but had several gates, of which that called
                    the West Port still remains. The most prominent ruins are those of the cathedral
                    and the castle (see below). Among the modern public buildings are the townhall
                    (1858) in the Scottish baronial style, the golf clubhouse, the Gibson and fever
                    hospitals, and the recreation hall (1884). The population of St Andrews in 1801
                    'was only 3263, but by 1881 it had nearly doubled, being 6406. The parliamentary
                    burgh in 1881 numbered 6458.</p>
                <p>The cathedral originated partly in the priory of Canons Regular founded to the
                    south-east of the town by Bishop Robert (1122-1159). Martine, who wrote in the
                    end of the 17th century, states that in his time some of the buildings were
                    entire and that considerable remains of others existed, but nearly all traces
                    have now disappeared, with the exception of portions of the abbey wall and the
                    archways, now known as the “Pends,” forming the main entrance from the city. The
                    wall is about three-quarters of a mile long and bears turrets at intervals. The
                    cathedral was founded by Bishop Arnold (1159-1162), to supply more ample
                    accommodation for the canons and for the celebration of the worship of the see
                    than was afforded by the church of St Regulus. Of this older building in the
                    Romanesque style, probably dating from the 10th century, there remain the square
                    tower, 108 feet in height, and the choir, of very diminutive proportions. O11 a
                    plan of the town <hi rend="italic">c</hi>. 1530 a chancel appears beyond, and on
                    seals affixed to the city and college charters there are representations of
                    other buildings attached. The cathedral which succeeded the church of St Regulus
                    is represented in full outline in the plan of the town of 1530. It was
                    constructed in the form of a Latin cross, the total length of the building
                    inside the walls being 355 feet, the length of the nave 200, of the choir and
                    lateral aisles 62, and of the lady chapel at the eastern extremity 50. The width
                    at the transepts was 166 feet and of the nave and choir 62. According to Fordun
                    the building was founded in 1159; but before it was finished the see witnessed
                    the succession of eleven bishops, the consecration taking place in the time of
                    Bishop Lamberton (1297-1328) in 1318, when the ceremony was witnessed by Robert
                    the Bruce. When entire it had, besides a central tower, six turrets, of which
                    two at the eastern and one of the two at the western extremity rising to a
                    height of 100 feet still remain. The building was partly destroyed by fire in
                    1378, and the restoration and further embellishment were completed in 1440. It
                    was stripped of its altars and images in 1559 by the magistrates and inhabitants
                    of the city. It is believed that about the end of the 16th century the central
                    tower gave way, carrying with it the north wall. Since then large portions of
                    the ruins have been taken away for building purposes, and nothing was done to
                    preserve them till 1826. The principal portions now remaining, partly Norman and
                    partly Early English, are the eastern and western gables, the greater part of
                    the southern wall of the nave, and the western wall of the south transept.</p>
                <p>Closely connected with the fortunes of the cathedral are those of the castle, the
                    picturesque ruins of which are situated about 250 yards north-west of the
                    cathedral, on a rocky promontory now much worn away by the sea. It is supposed
                    to have been erected by Bishop Roger about the beginning of the 13th century as
                    an episcopal residence, and was strongly fortified. It was frequently taken by
                    the English, and after it had been captured by the Scottish regent in 1336-37
                    was destroyed lest it should fall into their hands. Towards the close of the
                    century it was rebuilt by Bishop Trail in the form of a massive fortification
                    with a moat on the south and west sides. James I. spent some of his early years
                    within it under the care of Bishop Wardlaw, and it is supposed to have been the
                    birthplace of James III. From a window in the castle Cardinal David Beaton
                    witnessed the burning of Wishart in front of the gate, and shortly afterwards he
                    was murdered within it in his bedroom by a party of Reformers. The castle was
                    taken from the conspirators by the French, among the prisoners captured being
                    John Knox. Some years afterwards it was repaired by Archbishop Hamilton, but in
                    a less massive and substantial form. It had in 1656 fallen into such disrepair
                    that the town council ordered its “sleatts and timmer, redd and lumps” to be
                    devoted to the repair of the pier at the harbour. The principal remains are a
                    portion of the south wall enclosing a square tower, the bottle dungeon below the
                    north-west tower, the kitchen tower, and a curious subterranean passage.</p>
                <p>The town church, formerly the church of the Holy Trinity, was originally founded
                    in 1112 by Bishop Turgot. The early building was a beautiful Norman structure,
                    but at the close of the 18th century the whole, with the exception of little
                    else than the square tower and spire, was re-erected in a plain and ungainly
                    style. Within the church Knox preached the sermon which led to the stripping of
                    the cathedral and the destruction of the monastic<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n175/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0175-0158"/> buildings. It contains an elaborate monument to
                    Archbishop Sharp. Near the south-west of the town is the ruined northern
                    transept of the chapel of the Dominican monastery founded by Bishop Wishart in
                    1274; but all traces of the Observantine monastery founded about 1450 by Bishop
                    Kennedy have disappeared, except the well. The church of St Alary on the rock
                    erected by the Culdees is supposed to have stood on the Lady’s Craig now covered
                    by the sea; and the foundations of another, also dedicated to the Virgin, to the
                    west of the harbour were discovered in 1860, giving the full outline of the
                    ground-plan of the building.</p>
                <p>The university was possibly a development of the “schools” which were in
                    existence as early as the beginning of the 12th century, and were endowed by
                    certain “rents and kune” payable to them from lands in the neighbourhood. Its
                    immediate origin was due to a society formed in 1410 by Lawrence of Lindores,
                    abbot of Scone, Richard Cornwall, archdeacon of Lothian, William Stephen,
                    afterwards archbishop of Dunblane, and a few others, for the instruction of all
                    who chose to attend their lectures. A charter was granted in 1411 by Bishop
                    Wardlaw, who attracted the most learned men in Scotland as professors, and bulls
                    were obtained from the pope in 1413 confirming the charter and constituting it a
                    <hi rend="italic">studium generate</hi> or university. The lectures were
                    delivered in various parts of the town until 1430, when a building called the
                    “pedagogy” to the Faculty of Arts was granted by the founder of the university.
                    St Salvator’s College was founded and richly endowed by Bishop Kennedy in 1456;
                    twelve years later it was granted the power to confer degrees in theology and
                    philosophy, and by the end of the century was regarded as a constituent part of
                    the university. In 1512 the university received a further addition by the
                    foundation of St Leonard’s College by Prior John Hepburn and Archbishop
                    Alexander Stuart on the site of buildings which at one time were used as a
                    hospital for pilgrims. In the same year Archbishop Stuart nominally changed the
                    original “pedagogy” into a college and annexed to it the parish church of St
                    Michael of Tarvet; but its actual erection into a college did not take place
                    until 1537. By a bull obtained from Paul III. it was dedicated to the Blessed
                    Virgin Mary of the Assumption. The outline of the ancient structure is
                    preserved, but the general character of the buildings has been much altered by
                    various restorations. They form two sides of a quadrangle, the library and
                    principal’s residence being on the north and the lecture-rooms and old
                    dining-hall on the west. The university library, which now includes the older
                    college libraries, was founded about the middle of the 17th century, rebuilt in
                    1764, and improved in 1829. The lower hall in the older part of the building has
                    been used as a provincial meeting-place for the Scottish parliament. When the
                    constitution of the colleges was remodelled in 1579 St Mary’s was set apart to
                    theology; and in 1747 the colleges of St Salvator and St Leonard were formed
                    into the United College. The buildings of St Leonard’s are now occupied as a
                    high class school for girls. The college chapel is in ruins. The United College
                    occupies the site of St Salvator’s College, but the old buildings have been
                    removed, with the exception of the college chapel, now used as the university
                    chapel and the parish church of St Leonard’s, a fine Gothic structure containing
                    an elaborate tomb of Bishop Kennedy; the entrance gateway with the square clock
                    tower rising to a height of 152 feet; and the janitor’s house, with some
                    class-rooms above. The modern building, in the Elizabethan style, forming two
                    sides of a quadrangle, was erected between the years 1827 and 1847. The Madras
                    College was founded and endowed by Dr Andrew Bell. It is attended by about 700
                    pupils. There are also several large boarding and day schools.</p>
                <p>St Andrews (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Scotland)</hi> is said to have been made a
                    bishopric in the 9th century, and when in 908 the Pictish and Scottish Churches
                    were united the primacy was transferred to it from Dunkeld, its bishops being
                    henceforth known as bishops of Alban. Turgot, who was appointed in 1109, was the
                    first bishop who really filled the see. It became an archbishopric during the
                    primacy of Patrick Graham (1466-78). This ceased in 1688. It was created a royal
                    burgh by David I. in 1124. The St Andrews district of burghs returns one member
                    to the House of Commons.</p>
                <p>Martine, <hi rend="italic">History and Antiquities of St Rule’s Chapel, St
                    Andrews,</hi> 1787; Grierson, <hi rend="italic">Delineatlons of St Andrews,</hi>
                    1807, 3d ed. 1838; <hi rend="italic">Reliquiae Divi Andreae, 1797</hi>; <hi
                    rend="italic">Liber Cartarum Sancti Andreae,</hi> Bannatyne Club, 1841; Skene,
                    “Ecclesiastical Settlements in Scotland,” in P <hi rend="italic">roc. Soc.
                    Antiq. Scot.,</hi> 1862-63; <hi rend="italic">Histories</hi> of St Andrews by
                    Lyon (1843) and Rogers (1849); Skene, <hi rend="italic">Celtic Scotland..</hi>
                    (T. F. H.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
