<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0655-0630-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SELDEN, John</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 21, page 630</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0399k">Towers</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4s46hf7s">Talking</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86q1x">Cotton</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s347">Trials</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:869839">Commons</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1153279">Towers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:950637">Halls</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198642">Conquest</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:881747">Courts</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n655/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SELDEN, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi></label> (1584-1654),
                    jurist, legal antiquary, and Oriental scholar, was born on 16th December 1584 at
                    Salvington, in the parish of West Tarring, near Worthing, Sussex. His father,
                    also named John Selden, held a small farm, and seems to have occasionally added
                    to his livelihood by his labour as a wheelwright and his skill as a musician. It
                    is said that his accomplishments as a violin-player gained him his wife, whose
                    social position was somewhat superior to his own. She was Margaret, the only
                    child of Thomas Baker of Rustington, a village in the vicinity of West Tarring,
                    and was more or less remotely descended from a knightly family of the same name
                    in Kent. John Selden commenced his education at the free grammar-school at
                    Chichester, whence he proceeded in his sixteenth year with an exhibition to Hart
                    Hall at Oxford. In 1603 he was admitted a member of Clifford’s Inn, London, and
                    in 1604 migrated to the Inner Temple, and in due course he was called to the
                    bar. While still a student he appears to have been on terms of friendship with
                    Ben Jonson, Drayton, and Camden; and among his more intimate companions were
                    Edward Littleton, afterwards lord keeper; Henry Rolle, afterwards lord
                    chief-justice; Edward Herbert, afterwards solicitorgeneral; and Thomas Gardener,
                    afterwards recorder of London. His earliest patron was Sir Robert Cotton, the
                    antiquary, by whom he seems to have been employed in copying and abridging
                    certain of the parliamentary records then preserved in the Tower. For some
                    reason which has not been explained, Selden never went into court as an
                    advocate, save on rare and exceptional occasions. But his practice in chambers
                    as a conveyancer and consulting counsel is stated to have been large, and, if we
                    may judge from the considerable fortune he accumulated, it must also have been
                    lucrative.</p>
                <p>It was, however, as a scholar and writer that Selden won his reputation both
                    amongst his contemporaries and with posterity. His first work, an account of the
                    civil administration of England before the Norman Conquest, is said to have been
                    completed when he was only two-or three-and-twenty years of age. But if this was
                    the <hi rend="italic">Analecton Anglo-Britannicon,</hi> as is generally
                    supposed, he withheld it from the world until 1615. In 1610 appeared his <hi
                    rend="italic">England's Epinomis</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Janus Anglorum,
                    Facies Altera,</hi> which dealt with the progress of English law down to Henry
                    II., and <hi rend="italic">The Duello, or Single Combat,</hi> in which he traced
                    the history of trial by battle in England from the Norman Conquest. In 1613 he
                    supplied a series of notes, enriched by an immense number of quotations and
                    references, to the first eighteen cantos of Drayton’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Polyolbion.</hi> In 1614 he published <hi rend="italic">Titles of Honour,</hi>
                    which, in spite of some obvious defects and omissions, has remained to the
                    present day the most comprehensive and trustworthy work of its kind that we
                    possess; and in 1616 his notes on Fortescue’s <hi rend="italic">De Laudibus
                    Legum Angliae</hi> and Hengham’s <hi rend="italic">Summae Magna et Parva.</hi>
                    In 1617 his <hi rend="italic">De Diis Syriis</hi> was issued from the press, and
                    immediately established his fame as an Oriental scholar among the learned in all
                    parts of Europe. After two centuries and a half, indeed, it is still not only
                    the fundamental but also in many respects the best book which has been written
                    on Semitic mythology. In 1618 his <hi rend="italic">History of Tithes,</hi>
                    although only published after it had been submitted to the censorship and duly
                    licensed, nevertheless aroused the apprehension of the bishops and provoked the
                    intervention of the king. The author was summoned before the privy council and
                    compelled to retract his opinions, or at any rate what were held to be his
                    opinions. Moreover, his work was suppressed and himself forbidden to reply to
                    any of the controversialists who had come or might come forward to answer
                    it.</p>
                <p>This seems to have introduced Selden to the practical side of political affairs.
                    The discontents which a few years later broke out into civil war were already
                    forcing themselves on public attention, and it is pretty certain that, although
                    he was not in parliament, he was the instigator and perhaps the draftsman of the
                    memorable protestation on the rights and privileges of the House affirmed by the
                    Commons on the 18th of December 1621. He was with several of the members
                    committed to prison, at first in the Tower and subsequently under the charge of
                    Sir Robert Ducie, sheriff of London. During his detention, which only lasted a
                    short time, he occupied himself in preparing an edition of Eadmer’s <hi
                    rend="italic">History</hi> from a manuscript lent to him by his host or jailor,
                    which he published two years afterwards. In 1623 he was returned to the House of
                    Commons for the borough of Lancaster, and sat with Coke, Noy, and Pym on
                    Sergeant Glanville’s election committee. He was also nominated reader of Lyon’s
                    Inn, an office which he declined to undertake. For this the benchers of the
                    Inner Temple, by whom he had been appointed, fined him £20 and disqualified him
                    from being chosen one of their number. But he was relieved from this incapacity
                    after a few years, and became a master of the bench. In the first parliament of
                    Charles I. (1625), it appears from the “returns of members” printed in 1878
                    that, contrary to the assertion of all his biographers, he had no seat. In
                    Charles’s second parliament (1626) he was elected for Great Bedwin in Wiltshire,
                    and took a prominent part in the impeachment of George Villiers, duke of
                    Buckingham. In the following year, in the “benevolence” case, he was counsel for
                    Sir Edmund Hampden in the Court of King’s Bench. In 1628 he was returned to the
                    third parliament of Charles for Ludgers-<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n656/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0656-0631"/> hall in Wiltshire, and had a large and important
                    share in drawing up and carrying the Petition of Right. In the session of 1629
                    he was one of the members mainly responsible for the tumultuous passage in the
                    House of Commons of the resolution against the illegal levy of tonnage and
                    poundage, and, along with Eliot, Hoiles, Long, Valentine, Strode, and the rest,
                    he was sent once more to the Tower. There he remained for eight months, deprived
                    for a part of the time of the use of books and writing materials. He was then
                    removed, under less rigorous conditions, to the Marshalsea, until not long
                    afterwards owing to the good offices of Archbishop Laud he was liberated. Some
                    years before he had been appointed steward to the earl of Kent, to whose seat,
                    Wrest in Bedfordshire, he now retired. In 1628 at the suggestion of Sir Robert
                    Cotton he had compiled, with the assistance of two learned coadjutors, Patrick
                    Young and Richard James, a catalogue of the Arundel marbles. He employed his
                    leisure at Wrest in writing <hi rend="italic">De Successionibus in Bona Defuncti
                    secundum Leges Ebraeorum</hi> and <hi rend="italic">De Successione in
                    Pontificatum Ebraeorum,</hi> published in 1631. About this period he seems to
                    have inclined towards the court rather than the popular party, and even to have
                    secured the personal favour of the king. To him in 1635 he dedicated his <hi
                    rend="italic">Mare Clausum,</hi> and under the royal patronage it was put forth
                    as a kind of state paper. It had been written sixteen or seventeen years before;
                    but James I. had prohibited its publication for political reasons; hence it
                    appeared a quarter of a century after Grotius’s <hi rend="italic">Mare
                    Liberum,</hi> to which it was intended to be a rejoinder, and the pretensions
                    advanced in which on behalf of the Dutch fishermen to poach in the waters off
                    the British coasts it was its purpose to explode. The fact that Selden was not
                    retained in the great case of ship money in 1637 by John Hampden, the cousin of
                    his former client, may be accepted as additional evidence that his zeal in the
                    popular cause was not so warm and unsuspected as it had once been. During the
                    progress of this momentous constitutional conflict, indeed, he seems to have
                    been absorbed in his Oriental researches, publishing <hi rend="italic">De Jure
                    Naturali et Gentium juxta Disciplinam Ebraeorum</hi> in 1640. He was not elected
                    to the Short Parliament of 1640; but to the Long Parliament, summoned in the
                    autumn, he was returned without opposition for the university of Oxford.
                    Immediately after the opening of the session he was nominated a member of the
                    committee of twenty-four appointed to draw up a remonstrance on the state of the
                    nation. He was also a member of the committees entrusted with the preliminary
                    arrangements for the impeachment of Strafford. But he was not one of the
                    managers at the trial, and he voted against the Bill for his attainder. He was,
                    moreover, a member of the committees nominated to search for precedents and
                    frame the articles of impeachment against Archbishop Laud, although it does not
                    appear that he was implicated in the later stages of the prosecution against
                    him. He opposed the resolution against Episcopacy which led to the exclusion of
                    the bishops from the House of Lords, and printed an answer to the arguments used
                    by Sir Harbottle Grimston on that occasion. He joined in the protestation of the
                    Commons for the maintenance of the Protestant religion according to the
                    doctrines of the Church of England, the authority of the crown, and the liberty
                    of the subject. He was equally opposed to the court on the question of the
                    commissions of lieutenancy of array and to the parliament on the question of the
                    militia ordinance. In 1643, however, he became a member and participated in the
                    discussions of the assembly of divines at Westminster, and was appointed shortly
                    afterwards keeper of the rolls and records in the Tower. In 1645 he was named
                    one of the parliamentary commissioners of the admiralty, and was elected master
                    of Trinity Hall in Cambridge,—an office he declined to accept. In 1646 he
                    subscribed the Solemn League and Covenant, and in 1647 was voted £5000 by the
                    parliament as compensation for his sufferings in the evil days of the monarchy.
                    He had not, however, relaxed his literary exertions during these years. He
                    published in 1642 <hi rend="italic">Privileges of the Baronage of England when
                    they sit in Parliament</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Discourse concerning the
                    Rights and Privileges of the Subject',</hi> in 1644 <hi rend="italic"
                    >Dissertatio de Anno Civili et Calendario Reipublicae Judaicae',</hi> in 1646
                    his treatise on marriage and divorce among the Jews entitled <hi rend="italic"
                    >Uxor Ebraica∙,</hi> and in 1647 the earliest printed edition of the old and
                    curious English law-book <hi rend="italic">Fleta.</hi> What course he adopted
                    with regard to the trial and execution of the king is unknown; but it is said
                    that he refused to answer the <hi rend="italic">Eikon Basilike,</hi> although
                    Cromwell was anxious he should do so, the task which he declined being
                    afterwards performed by Milton in his <hi rend="italic">Iconoclastes.</hi> In
                    1650 Selden passed the first part of <hi rend="italic">De Synedriis et
                    Prefecturis Juridicis Veterum Ebraeorum</hi> through the press, the second and
                    third parts being severally published in 1653 and 1655, and in 1652 he wrote a
                    preface and collated some of the manuscripts for Sir Roger Twysden’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Historiae Anglicae Scriptores Decem.</hi> His last publication was
                    a vindication of himself from certain charges advanced against him and his <hi
                    rend="italic">Mare Clausum</hi> in 1653 by Theodore Graswinckel, a Dutch
                    jurist.</p>
                <p>After the death of the earl of Kent in 1639 Selden lived permanently under the
                    same roof with his widow. It is believed that he was married to her, although
                    their marriage does not seem to have ever been publicly acknowledged. He died at
                    Friary House in Whitefriars on 30th November 1654, and was buried in the Temple
                    Church, London. Within the last few years a brass tablet has been erected to his
                    memory by the benchers of the Inner Temple in the parish church of West
                    Tarring.</p>
                <p>Several of Selden’s minor productions were printed for the first time after his
                    death, and a collective edition of his writings was published by Archdeacon
                    Wilkins in 3 vols. folio in 1725, and again in 1726. His <hi rend="italic">Table
                    Talk,</hi> by which he is perhaps best known, did not appear until 1689. It was
                    edited by his amanuensis, Richard Milward, who affirms that “the sense and
                    notion is wholly Selden’s,” and that “most of the words” are his also. Its
                    genuineness has sometimes been questioned, although on insufficient grounds. In
                    Hallam’s opinion it “gives perhaps a more exalted notion of Selden’s natural
                    talents than any of his learned writings,” and in Coleridge’s it contains “more
                    weighty bullion sense” than he had “ever found in the same number of pages of
                    any uninspired writer.”</p>
                <p>See Bliss, Wood’s <hi rend="italic">Athenae Oxonienses</hi> (London, 1817, vol.
                    iv.); Aikin, <hi rend="italic">Lives of John Selden and Archbishop Usher</hi>
                    (London, 1812); Johnson, <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of John Selden,</hi> &amp;c.
                    (London, 1835); Singer, <hi rend="italic">Table Talk of John Selden</hi>
                    (London, 1847); and Wilkins, <hi rend="italic">Johannis Seldeni Opera
                    Omnia,</hi> &amp;c. (London, 1725). (F. DR.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
