<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0220-0201-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ST VITUS’S DANCE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 21, page 201</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0v30g">Symptoms</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4pz51n7n">Chorea</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rp3w">Health</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4xp6v41r">Heart</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2th4x">Resultants</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1140998">Symptoms</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:953493">Heart</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:858594">Chorea</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:952743">Health</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:796146">Acting</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n220/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ST VITUS’S DANCE</label>,<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>This name was originally employed in connexion with those
                    remarkable epidemic outbursts of combined mental and physical excitement which
                    for a time prevailed among the inhabitants of some parts of Germany in the
                    Middle Ages. It is stated that sufferers from <pb corresp="kp-eb0921-0221-0202"
                    xml:id="pbn9202"/> this dancing mania were wont to resort to the chapels of St
                    Vitus (more than one in Swabia), the saint being believed to possess the power
                    of curing them. The transference of the name to the disease now under
                    consideration was a manifest error, but so closely has the association now
                    become that the original application of the term has been comparatively
                    obscured.</p></note> or <hi rend="smallcaps">Chorea,</hi> a disorder of the<pb
                    corresp="pbn9202" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n221/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0221-0202"/> nervous system occurring for the most part in
                    children, and characterized mainly by involuntary jerking movements of the
                    muscles throughout almost the entire body. It is to be regarded as a functional
                    nervous disorder of wide extent, the manifestations of which appear not merely
                    in disturbance affecting the motor apparatus but in various associated morbid
                    phenomena of cerebral origin. Among the predisposing causes age is important,
                    chorea being essentially an ailment of childhood and more particularly of the
                    period in which the second dentition is taking place. The greater number of the
                    cases occur between the ages of nine and twelve. It is not often seen in very
                    young children nor after puberty; but there are many exceptions to this rule. It
                    is twice as frequent with girls as with boys. Hereditary predisposition to
                    nervous troubles is apt to find expression in this malady in youth, more
                    especially if the general health becomes lowered. Of exciting causes strong
                    emotions, such as fright, ill-usage or hardship of any kind, insufficient
                    feeding, overwork or anxiety, are among the most common; while, again, some
                    distant source of irritation, such as teething or intestinal worms, appears
                    capable of giving rise to an attack. It is an occasional but rare complication
                    of pregnancy. The connexion of chorea with rheumatism is now universally
                    recognized, and is shown not merely by its frequent occurrence before, after, or
                    during the course of attacks of rheumatic fever in young persons, but even
                    independently of this by the liability of the heart to suffer in a similar way
                    in the two diseases.</p>
                <p>The symptoms of St Vitus’s dance are in some instances developed suddenly as the
                    result of fright, but much more frequently they come on insidiously. They are
                    usually preceded by changes in the temper and disposition, the child becoming
                    sad, irritable, and emotional, while at the same time the general health is
                    somewhat impaired. The first thing indicative of the disease is a certain
                    awkwardness or fidgetiness of manner together with restlessness, the child being
                    evidently unable to continue quiet, but frequently moving the limbs into
                    different positions. In walking, too, slight dragging of one limb may be
                    noticed. The convulsive muscular movements usually first show themselves in one
                    part, such as an arm or a leg, and in some instances they may remain localized
                    to that limited extent, while in all cases there is a tendency for the
                    disorderly symptoms to be more marked on one side than on the other. When fully
                    developed the phenomena of the disease are very characteristic. The child when
                    standing or sitting is never still, but is constantly changing the position of
                    the body or limbs in consequence of the sudden and incoordinate action of
                    muscles or groups of them. The shoulder is jerked up, the head and trunk twisted
                    about, the limbs crossed suddenly and changed again, the fingers keep moving
                    restlessly, while the face is distorted with grimaces, frowning and smiling
                    irregularly. These symptoms are aggravated when purposive movements are
                    attempted or when the child is watched. Speech is affected both from the
                    incoordinate movements of the tongue and from phonation sometimes taking place
                    during an act of inspiration. The taking of food becomes a matter of difficulty,
                    since much of it is lost in the attempts to convey it to the mouth, while
                    swallowing is also interfered with owing to the irregular action of the
                    pharyngeal muscles. When the tongue is protruded it comes out in a jerky manner
                    and is immediately withdrawn, the jaws at the same time closing suddenly and
                    sometimes with con siderable force. In locomotion the muscles of the limbs act
                    incoordinately and there is a marked alteration of the gait, which is now
                    halting and now leaping, and the child may be tripped by one limb being suddenly
                    jerked in front of the other. In short, whether at rest or in motion the whole
                    muscular system is seen to be deranged in its operations, and the term “insanity
                    of the muscles” not inaptly expresses the condition, for they no longer act in
                    harmony or with purpose, but seem, as Trousseau expresses it, each to have a
                    will of its own and to be exercising this for different objects at one time. The
                    muscles of organic life (involuntary muscles) appear scarcely, if at all,
                    affected in this disease, as, for example, the heart, the rhythmic movements of
                    which are not as a rule impaired. But the heart may suffer in other ways,
                    especially from inflammatory conditions similar to those which attend upon
                    rheumatism and which frequently lay the foundation of permanent heart disease.
                    In severe cases of St Vitus’s dance the child comes to present a distressing
                    appearance from the constant restlessness and disorderly movement, and the
                    physical health declines. Usually, however, there is a remission of the symptoms
                    during sleep. The mental condition of the patient is more or less affected, as
                    shown in emotional tendencies, irritability, and a somewhat fatuous expression
                    and bearing, but this change is in general of transient character and ceases
                    with convalescence.</p>
                <p>This disease occasionally assumes a very acute and aggravated form, in which the
                    disorderly movements are so violent as to render the patient liable to be
                    injured and to necessitate forcible control of the limbs or the employment of
                    anaesthetics to produce unconsciousness. Such cases are of very grave character,
                    if, as is common, they are accompanied with sleeplessness, and they may prove
                    rapidly fatal by exhaustion. In the great majority of cases of St Vitus’s dance,
                    however, complete recovery is to be anticipated sooner or later, the symptoms
                    usually continuing for from one to two months, or even sometimes much
                    longer.</p>
                <p>The nature of this disease has given rise to much discussion and there still
                    remains considerable difference of opinion as to its true pathology. The fact
                    that the vast majority of cases recover would seem to show that there could have
                    been no profound change in the structural integrity of the nerve-centres, while
                    in those instances where a fatal result takes place <hi rend="italic"
                    >post-mortem</hi> examination reveals no constant morbid condition. A theory
                    supported by high authority has referred the cause of the malady to the plugging
                    up of minute blood-vessels in the motor centres of the brain (a condition not
                    unlikely to occur in rheumatic inflammation affecting the lining membrane of the
                    heart), and such a change has been seen in a few instances. In a still larger
                    number, however, no appearances of this kind have been observed, but simply
                    vascular changes of a congestive character widely diffused throughout the
                    central nervous system, accompanied with evidences of slight inflammatory
                    action. Dr Dickinson, whose views, founded upon carefully conducted
                    investigations, are those most widely accepted, concludes as follows: “We see in
                    chorea a widely distributed hyperaemia [ <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi>
                    congestion] of the nervous centres, not due to any mechanical mischance, but
                    produced mainly by causes of two kinds,—one a morbid, probably a humoral
                    influence, which may affect the nervous centres as it affects other organs and
                    tissues; the other, irritation in some mode usually mental but sometimes what is
                    called reflex, which especially belongs to and disturbs the nervous system, and
                    affects persons differently, according to the inherent mobility of their
                    nature.”</p>
                <p>For the treatment of St Vitus’s dance the remedies proposed have been
                    innumerable, but it is doubtful whether any of them have much control over the
                    disease, which<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n222/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0222-0203"/> under suitable hygienic conditions tends to
                    recover of itself. These conditions, however, are all-important, and embrace the
                    proper feeding of the child with nutritious light diet, the absence of all
                    sources of excitement and annoyance, such as being laughed at or mocked by other
                    children, and the rectification of any causes of irritation and of
                    irregularities in the general health. For a time, and especially if the symptoms
                    are severe, confinement to the house or even to bed may be necessary, but as
                    soon as possible the child should be taken out into the open air and gently
                    exercised by walking. Of medicinal remedies the most serviceable appear to be
                    zinc, arsenic, and iron, especially the last two, which act as tonics to the
                    system and improve the condition of the blood. They should be continued during
                    the whole course of the disease and convalescence, if they do not disagree. As
                    sedatives in cases of sleeplessness, bromide of potassium and chloral are of
                    use. Many other agents, such as conium, belladonna, strychnia, the salts of
                    silver, &amp;c., have been recommended, but they do not seem to possess any
                    special advantages. In long-continued cases of the disease much benefit will be
                    obtained by a change of air as well as by the employment of moderate gymnastic
                    exercises. Bearing in mind the weakened condition of the muscles as the result
                    of the choreic movements, the employment of friction and of electricity is also
                    likely to be beneficial. After recovery the general health of the child should
                    for a long time receive attention, and care should be taken to guard against
                    excitement, excessive study, or any exhausting condition, physical or mental,
                    from the fact that the disease is apt to recur and that other nervous disorders
                    still more serious may be developed from it.</p>
                <p>In the rare instances of the acute form of this malady, where the convulsive
                    movements are unceasing and violent, the only measures available are the use of
                    chloral or chloroform inhalation to produce insensibility and muscular
                    relaxation, but the effect is only palliative and does not prevent the fatal
                    result which in most such cases quickly supervenes. (<hi rend="smallcaps">j. o.
                    a.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
