<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0320-0301-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SAÔNE, Haute-</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 21, page 301</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:946934">Gray</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1046191">Operas</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1104198">Salons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1046145">Opera</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:979089">Iron</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1002458">Looms</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49k45x1d">Salons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90251t">Opera</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zz70">Iron</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4t727j1r">Copper</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43r0pw3g">Looms</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n320/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SAÔNE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Haute-</hi></label>, a department
                    in the north-east of France, formed in 1790 from the northern portion of Franche
                    Comté, and traversed by the river Saône. Situated between 47° 14' and 48° 1' N.
                    lat. and between 5° 21 and 6° 49' E. long., it is bounded N. by the department
                    of the Vosges, E. by the territory of Belfort, S. by Doubs and Jura, and W. by
                    Côte-d’Or and Haute-Marne. On the north-east, where they are formed by the
                    Vosges, and to the south along the course of the Ognon the limits are natural.
                    The highest point of the department is the Ballon de Servance (3900 feet), and
                    the lowest the confluence of the Saône and Ognon (610 feet). The general slope
                    is from north-east to south-west, the direction followed by those two streams.
                    In the north-east the department belongs to the Vosgian formation, consisting of
                    pine-clad mountains of sandstone and granite; but throughout the greater part of
                    its extent it is composed of limestone plateaus 800 to 1000 feet high pierced
                    with crevasses and subterranean caves, into which the rain water disappears to
                    issue again as springs in the valleys 200 feet lower down. In its passage
                    through the department the Saône receives from the right the Amance and the
                    Salon from the Langres plateau, and from the left the Coney, the Lanterne
                    (augmented by the Breuchin which passes by Luxeuil), the Durgeon (passing
                    Vesoul), and the Ognon. The north-eastern districts are cold in climate and have
                    an annual rainfall ranging from 36 to 48 inches. Towards the south-west the
                    characteristics become those of the Rhone valley generally. At Vesoul and Gray
                    the rainfall only reaches 24 inches per annum.</p>
                <p>Out of a total of 1,319,570 acres 664,846 are arable, 375,999 under forest,
                    153,278 natural meadows and orchards, and 31,752 vineyards. The agricultural
                    population numbers 180,893 out of a total of 295,905. They possess 22,331
                    horses, 152,609 cattle, 63,000 sheep, 72,678 pigs, 7094 goats, more than 19,000
                    dogs, and 15,915 beehives (40 tons 15 cwts. of honey in 1881). Wheat is the
                    staple crop—2,727,425 bushels in 1883; next come oats, 3,188,322 bushels;
                    potatoes, 8,175,673 bushels; wine, mostly of middling quality, 4,887,652 gallons
                    (average vintage for the last ten years 6,086,652 gallons); rye, 449,308
                    bushels; barley, 396,940; meslin, 276,251; buckwheat, 63,945; maize, 64,924;
                    millet, 154; colza, 456 tons; beetroot, 26,365 tons; pulse, 5662 bushels; hemp,
                    linen, tobacco, hops. The woods, which cover more than a quarter of the
                    department, are composed of firs in the Vosges and beech trees, oaks, wych elms,
                    and aspens in the other districts. Kirschwasser is manufactured at Fougerolles
                    from the native cherries. The industrial population number 51,477; 550 workmen
                    raise 143,842 tons of iron-ore yearly; copper, silver, and manganese exist in
                    the department, and gold occurs in the bed of the Ognon. Rock-salt mines yield
                    annually 11,000 tons of salt and the materials for a considerable manufacture of
                    sulphuric, hydrochloric, and nitric acids, sulphate of soda, chloride of lime,
                    and Epsom and Glauber salts. Coal mines, with their principal centre at
                    Ronchamp, give employment to more than 2000 workmen, and in 1883 yielded 212,680
                    tons of coal. Peat, limestone, plaster, building-stone, marble, porphyry,
                    granite, syenite, and sandstone are all worked in the department. The green
                    porphyry pedestal of Napoleon’s sarcophagus at Les Invalides and the syenite
                    columns of the Grand Opera in Paris were cut at Servance. Οf the many mineral
                    waters of Haute-Saône the best known are the hot springs of Luxeuil, which, with
                    their sixteen saline and two chalybeate sources, discharge over 127,000 gallons
                    in the 24 hours and are used for bathing and drinking. Besides forty-seven
                    iron-working establishments (smelting furnaces, foundries, and wire-drawing
                    mills, producing in 1883 4875 tons of iron smelted by wood-fuel, 286 tons of
                    refined iron and 1040 tons of sheet-iron, &amp;c.), Haute-Saône possesses
                    copper-foundries, engineering works, steel-foundries, and factories for
                    producing tin plate, nails, pins, files, saws, screws, shot, chains,
                    agricultural implements, locks, spinning machinery, edge tools, &amp;c.
                    Window-glass is manufactured by 105 workmen and glass wares by 300, pottery and
                    earthenware by 220 to 230. There are also about 100 brick and tile works; the
                    paper-mills employ 329 hands, and the 21 cotton-mills (66,700 spindles and 2518
                    looms, of which 154 are hand-looms) upwards of 2000. Printworks, fulling mills,
                    hosiery factories, and straw-hat factories are also of some account; as well as
                    sugar-works, dye-works, saw-mills, starch-works, chemical works, oil-mills,
                    tanyards, and flour-mills. The department exports wheat (893,000 bushels),
                    cattle, iron, wood, pottery, kirschwasser, and cooper’s wares. The Saône
                    provides a navigable channel of 40 miles, which is about to be connected with
                    the Moselle and the Meuse by the Canal de l’Est in course of construction along
                    the valley of the Coney. Gray is the great emporium of the water-borne trade,
                    estimated at 200,000 tons per annum. The department has 186 miles of national
                    roads, 3313 miles of other roads, and 235 miles of railway—the Paris-Mulhouse
                    and Nancy-Gray railways, crossing at Vesoul, and various other lines. There are
                    three arrondissements,—Vesoul, Gray (7254 inhabitants in the town), Lure
                    (4360),—28 cantons, 583 communes. Haute-Saône is in the district of the 7th
                    corps d’armée, and in its legal, ecclesiastical, and educational relations
                    depends on Besançon. Luxeuil (4376 inhabitants), the most important place after
                    the subprefectures, is celebrated for its abbey, founded by St Columban in
                    590.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
