<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0205-0186-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ST MALO</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 21, page 186</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205190">Peru</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204310">Canada</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795c7h">Republicanism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4qr4nq8b">Tides</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:839694">Broussaisism</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1150792">Tides</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1130905">Spring</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1099409">Rocks</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n205/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ST MALO</label>, a seaport town of France, on the English
                    Channel, on the right bank of the estuary of the Rance, is situated in 48° 39'
                    N. lat., 51 miles by rail north-northwest of Rennes. It is the administrative
                    centre of an arrondissement in the department of Ille-et-Vilaine and a
                    first-class garrison town, surrounded by ramparts of the 13th, 16th, and 17th
                    centuries, which are strengthened with great towers at the principal gates. The
                    granite island on which St Malo stands communicates with the mainland only on
                    the north-east by a causeway known as the “Sillon” (furrow), 650 feet long, and
                    at one time only 46 feet broad, though now three times that breadth. This
                    causeway forms part of the site of Rocabey, an industrial suburb more extensive,
                    though less populous, than the town itself. In the sea round about lie other
                    granite rocks, which have been turned to account in the defences of the coast;
                    on the islet of the Grand Bey is the tomb (1848) of Chateaubriand. The rocks and
                    beach in the circuit of St Malo are continually changing their appearance, owing
                    to the violence of the tides. Equinoctial spring-tides sometimes rise 50 feet
                    above low-water level, and during storms the sea sometimes washes over the
                    ramparts. The harbour of St Malo lies south of the town in the creek separating
                    it from the neighbouring town of St Servan. It has a wet dock with from 20 to 25
                    feet of water (30 feet in spring-tides), and a mile of quays. Additional works
                    are projected, to make the area of the dock 42 acres and the length of quays 1½
                    miles. Among French seaports St Malo stands twelfth in commercial importance,
                    but first in the number of seamen on its register. The annual imports and
                    exports together amount to 184,000 tons, and 3000 tons of shipping are built
                    yearly. Besides fitting out fishing-boats for Newfoundland, St Malo exports
                    grain, colza-seed, cider, butter, tobacco, and various kinds of provisions to
                    the Channel Islands, with which it is connected by a regular steamboat service.
                    The coasting vessels have a tonnage of about 30,000. Communication between St
                    Malo and St Servan is maintained by a revolving bridge. St Malo is largely
                    frequented for sea-bathing, but not so much as Dinard, on the opposite side of
                    the Rance. Paramé, to the east of</p>
                <p>St Malo, has recently sprung into importance. The interior of St Malo presents a
                    tortuous maze of narrow streets and of small squares lined with high and
                    sometimes quaint buildings. The old house in which Duguay-Trouin was born
                    deserves to be noted. Above all rises the stone spire which since 1859
                    terminates the central tower of the cathedral. The castle, which defends the
                    town towards the “Sillon,” is flanked with four towers, and in the centre rises
                    the great keep, an older and loftier structure, which was breached in 1378 by
                    the duke of Lancaster. St Malo has statues to Chateaubriand and Duguay-Trouin.
                    The museum contains remains of the ship “La Petite Hermine,” in which Jacques
                    Cartier sailed for the discovery of Canada; and the natural history museum
                    possesses a remarkable collection of from 6000 to 7000 European birds. The
                    population of St Malo in 1881 was 10,891 (commune, 11,212).</p>
                <p>In the 6th century the granite island on which St Malo now stands was the retreat
                    of Abbot Aaron, who gave asylum in his monastery to Malo (Maclovius or
                    Malovius), a Cambrian priest, who came hither to escape the episcopal dignity,
                    but afterwards became bishop of Aleth (now St Servan); the see was transferred
                    to St Malo only in the 12th century. Jealous of their independence, the
                    inhabitants of St Malo played off against each other the dukes of Brittany and
                    the kings of France, who alternately sought to bring them under subjection.
                    During the troubles of the League they hoped to establish a republican
                    government in their city, and on the night of 11th March 1590 they exterminated
                    the royal garrison and imprisoned their bishop and the canons. But four years
                    later they surrendered to Henry IV. of France. During the following century the
                    maritime power of St Malo attained some importance. In November 1693 the English
                    vainly bombarded St Malo for four consecutive days. In July 1695 they renewed
                    the attempt, but were equally unsuccessful. The people of St Malo had in the
                    course of a single war captured upwards of 1500 vessels (several of them laden
                    with gold and other treasure) and burned a considerable number more. Enriched by
                    these successes and by the wealth they drew from Peru, the shipowners of the
                    town not only supplied the king with the means necessary for the famous Rio de
                    Janeiro expedition conducted by Duguay-Trouin in 1711, but also lent him
                    £1,200,000 for carrying on the War of the Spanish Succession. In June 1758 the
                    English sent a third expedition against St Malo under the command of
                    Marlborough, and inflicted a loss of £480,000 in the harbour. But another
                    expedition undertaken in the following September received a complete check. In
                    1778 and during the wars of the empire the St Malo privateers resumed their
                    activity. In 1789 St Servan was separated from St Malo and in 1790 St Malo lost
                    its bishopric. During the Reign of Terror the town was the scene of sanguinary
                    executions. Among the celebrities born in St Malo are Jacques Cartier,
                    Duguay-Trouin, Surcouf, and Mahé de la Bourdonnais—all four of naval fame—
                    Maupertuis, Chateaubriand, the Abbé de Lamennais, and Broussais.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
