<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0921-0640-0615-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SEBASTIANO DEL PIOMBO (9th edition, volume 21, page
                    615)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1050530">Painters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1103658">Saints</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110522">Sebastianism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1063919">Pietà</term>
                    <term ref="fast:884187">Crosses</term>
                    <term ref="fast:984609">Judgments</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9qc3b">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93k3f">Madonna</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pp2k">Cross</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f45m">Judgments</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n640/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SEBASTIANO DEL PIOMBO</label> (1485-1547), painter, was born
                    at Venice in 1485, and belongs to the Venetian school, exceptionally modified by
                    the Florentine or Roman. His family name was Luciani. He was at first a
                    musician, chiefly a solo-player on the lute, and was in great request among the
                    Venetian nobility. He soon showed a turn for painting, and became a pupil of
                    Giovanni Bellini and afterwards of Giorgione. His first painting of note was
                    done for the church of St John Chrysostom in Venice, and is so closely modelled
                    on the style of Giorgione that in its author’s time it often passed for the work
                    of that master. It represents Chrysostom reading aloud at a desk, a grand
                    Magdalene in front, and two other female and three male saints. Towards 1512
                    Sebastiano was invited to Rome by the wealthy Sienese merchant Agostino Chigi,
                    who occupied a villa by the Tiber, since named the Farnesina; he executed some
                    frescos here, other leading artists being employed at the same time. The
                    Venetian mode of colour was then a startling novelty in Rome. Michelangelo saw
                    and approved the work of Luciani, became his personal friend, and entered into a
                    peculiar arrangement with him. At this period the pictorial ability of
                    Michelangelo (apart from his general power as an artist, regarding which there
                    arose no question) was somewhat decried in Rome, the rival faculty of Raphael
                    being invidiously exalted in comparison; in especial it was contended that
                    Buonarroti fell short as a colourist. He therefore thought that he might try
                    whether, by furnishing designs for pictures and leaving to Sebastiano the
                    execution of them in colour, he could not maintain at its highest level his own
                    general supremacy in the art, leaving Raphael to sustain the competition as he
                    best might. In this there seems to have been nothing particularly unfair, always
                    assuming that the compact was not fraudulently concealed; and the facts are so
                    openly stated by Michelangelo’s friend Vasari (not to speak of other writers)
                    that there appears to have been little or no disguise in the matter. Besides,
                    the pictures are there to speak for themselves; and connoisseurs have always
                    acknowledged that the quality of Michelangelo’s unmatched design is patent on
                    the face of them. Of late years, however, some writers, unnecessarily jealous
                    for Buonarroti’s personal rectitude, have denied that his handiwork is to be
                    traced in the pictures bearing the name of Sebastiano. Four leading pictures
                    which Sebastiano painted in pursuance of his league with Buonarroti are the
                    Pietà (earliest of the four), in the church of the Conventuali, Viterbo; the
                    Transfiguration and the Flagellation, in the church of S. Pietro in Montorio,
                    Rome; and, most celebrated of all, the Raising of Lazarus, now in the London
                    National Gallery. This grand work—more remarkable for general strength of
                    pictorial perception than for qualities of detailed intellectual or emotional
                    expression—is more than 12 by 9 feet in dimensions, with the principal figures
                    of the natural size; it is inscribed “Sebastianus Venetus faciebat,” and was
                    transferred from wood to canvas in 1771. It was painted in 1517-19 for Giulio
                    de’ Medici, then bishop of Narbonne, afterwards Pope Clement VII.; and it
                    remained in Narbonne cathedral until purchased by the duke of Orleans early in
                    the 18th century,—coming to England with the Orleans gallery in 1792. It is
                    generally admitted that the design of Michelangelo appears in the figure of
                    Lazarus and of those who are busied about him (the British Museum contains two
                    sketches of the Lazarus regarded as Michelangelo’s handiwork); but whether he
                    actually touched the panel, as has often been said, appears more than doubtful,
                    as he left Rome about the time when the picture was commenced. Raphael’s
                    Transfiguration was painted for the same patron and the same destination. The
                    two works were exhibited together, and some admirers did not scruple to give the
                    preference to Sebastiano’s. The third of the four pictures above mentioned, the
                    Flagellation of Christ, though ordinarily termed a fresco, is, according to
                    Vasari, painted in oil upon the wall. This was a method first practised by
                    Domenico Veneziano, and afterwards by some other artists; but Sebastiano alone
                    succeeded in preventing the blackening of the colours. The contour of the figure
                    of Christ in this picture is supposed by many to have been supplied by
                    Buonarroti’s own hand. Sebastiano, always a tardy worker, was occupied about six
                    years upon this work, along with its companion the Transfiguration, and the
                    allied figures of saints.</p>
                <p>After the elevation of Giulio de’ Medici to the pontificate, the office of the
                    “piombo” or leaden seal—that is, the office of sealer of briefs of the apostolic
                    chamber—became vacant; two painters competed for it, Sebastiano Luciani,
                    hitherto a comparatively poor man, and Giovanni da Udine. Finally Sebastiano,
                    assuming the habit of a friar, secured the very lucrative appointment,—with the
                    proviso, however, that he should pay out of his emoluments 300 scudi per annum
                    to Giovanni. If he had heretofore been slow in painting, he became now supine
                    and indifferent in a marked degree. He lived on the fat of the land, cultivated
                    sprightly literary and other society, to which he contributed his own full quota
                    of amusement, and would scarcely handle a brush, saying jocularly that he
                    benefited the profession by leaving all the more work for other artists to do.
                    Berni, one of his intimates, addressed a <hi rend="italic">capitolo</hi> to him,
                    and Sebastiano responded in like versified form. One of the few subjectpictures
                    which he executed after taking office was Christ carrying the Cross for the
                    patriarch of Aquileia, also a Madonna with the body of Christ. The former
                    painting is done on stone, a method invented by Sebastiano himself. He likewise
                    painted at times on slate,—as in the instance of Christ on the Cross, now in the
                    Berlin gallery, where the slate constitutes the background. In the same method,
                    and also in the same gallery, is the Dead Christ supported by Joseph of
                    Arimathea, with a weeping Magdalene,— colossal half-length figures. Late in life
                    Sebastiano had a serious disagreement with Michelangelo with reference to the
                    Florentine’s great picture of the Last Judgment. Sebastiano encouraged the pope
                    to insist that this picture should be executed in oil. Michelangelo, determined
                    from the first upon nothing but fresco, tartly replied to his holiness that oil
                    was only fit for women and for sluggards like Friar Sebastian; and the coolness
                    between the two painters lasted almost up to the friar’s death. This event,
                    consequent upon a violent fever acting rapidly upon a<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n641/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0921-0641-0616"/> very sanguine temperament, took place at Rome
                    in 1547. Sebastiano directed that his burial, in the church of S. Maria del
                    Popolo, should be conducted without ceremony of priests, friars, or lights, and
                    that the cost thus saved should go to the poor; in this he was obeyed.</p>
                <p>Numerous pupils sought training from Sebastiano del Piombo; but, owing to his
                    dilatory and self-indulgent habits, they learned little from him, with the
                    exception of Tommaso Laureti. Sebastiano, conscious of his deficiency in the
                    higher sphere of invention, made himself especially celebrated as a portrait
                    painter: the likeness of Andrea Doria, in the Doria Palace, Rome, is one of the
                    most renowned. In the London National Gallery are two fine specimens: one canvas
                    represents the friar himself, along with Cardinal Ippolito de' Medici; the
                    other, a portrait of a lady in the character of St Agatha, used to be identified
                    with one of Sebastiano’s prime works, the likeness of Julia Gonzaga (painted for
                    her lover, the aforenamed cardinal), but this assumption is now discredited.
                    There were also portraits of Marcantonio Colonna, Vittoria Colonna, Ferdinand
                    marquis of Pescara, Popes Adrian VI., Clement VII. (Studj Gallery, Naples), and
                    Paul III., Sanmicheli, Anton Francesco degli Albizzi, and Pietro Aretino. One
                    likeness of the last-named sitter is in Arezzo and another in the Berlin
                    gallery.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
