<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0345-0326-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SAVIGNY, Friedrich Carl von</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 21, page 326</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xw47w7c">Bavarians</term>
                    <term n="18" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4rv0d77h">Protestants</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1080735">Prussians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="18" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1079934">Protestants</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n345/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SAVIGNY, <hi rend="smallcaps">Friedrich Carl von</hi></label>
                    (1779-1861), was born at Frankfort-on-the-Main on February 21, 1779. He was
                    descended from an ancient family, which figures in the history of Lorraine, and
                    which derived its name from the castle of Savigny near Charmes in the valley of
                    the Moselle. When Lorraine passed into the possession of France, his family
                    attached itself to Germany, and his ancestors filled important official posts in
                    Nassau and other German states. His great-grandfather wrote a work, <hi
                    rend="italic">La Dissolution de la Reunion,</hi> as a protest against the
                    conquests of Louis XIV.; his grandfather was “Regierungsdirector” at
                    Zweibriicken, and his father was a noble of the empire and “Kreisgesandter” of
                    several princes of the diet of the circle of the Upper Rhine. His father, Carl
                    Ludwig von Savigny, died in 1791, his mother in 1792, and he was brought up and
                    educated by his guardian, Herr von Neurath, assessor of the Reichskammergericht
                    or imperial chamber at Wetzlar, a master of the “Staatsrecht” of the time.</p>
                <p>In 1795 Savigny went to study at Marburg, and derived great advantage, as is
                    gratefully recorded by him, from the teaching and friendship of Professors Weis
                    and Bauer. For six months he studied at Gottingen. It is noted as a curious
                    circumstance that, though Hugo, the great civilian, was there lecturing, Savigny
                    did not attend his course. He suffered much for two or three years from
                    ill-health. Savigny visited, after the fashion of German students, Jena,
                    Leipsic, and Halle; and he returned to Marburg, where, on December 31, 1800, he
                    took his doctor’s degree. His inaugural dissertation was entitled <hi
                    rend="italic">De Concursu Delictorum Formali.</hi><note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The object of his investigation is thus
                    described: “Delicta concurrere dicuntur, ubi de pluribus legum violationibus,
                    quarum nonnisi unus est reus, in eodem judicio puniendis agitur.”</p></note> At
                    Marburg he lectured as privat-docent on criminal law, the pandects, the law of
                    succession, obligations, and the methodology of law. In 1803 he published his
                    famous treatise, <hi rend="italic">Das Recht des Besitzes,</hi> or the right of
                    possession. It was at once hailed by Thibaut as a masterpiece; jurists
                    recognized that the old uncritical study of Roman law was at an end. It quickly
                    obtained a European reputation, and still remains a prominent landmark in the
                    history of jurisprudence. It was the fountain-head of a stream of literature
                    which has not yet ceased to flow. Austin, no partial judge, pronounced it to be
                    “of all books upon law, the most consummate and masterly.” In 1804 Savigny
                    married Kunigunde Brentano, the sister of Bettina von Arnim and Clemens Brentano
                    the poet. In that year he visited Paris, chiefly with a view to make researches
                    in the National Library into the life of the jurist Cujas, whom he greatly
                    admired. In a letter to be found in his miscellaneous works he explains the
                    ground of his admiration. “Dans l’histoire de la jurisprudence moderne, il n’y a
                    pas d’époque plus brilliante que celle du 16 <hi rend="superscript"> me</hi>
                    siècle. C’est alors que la science du droit eut véritablement un grand et noble
                    caractère qu’elle n’a pas retrouvé depuis.” A story not without significance as
                    to his character relates to this period of his life. On his way to Paris, a box
                    containing papers in which were the results of laborious researches was stolen
                    from his carriage. He bore the loss with equanimity, and managed with the
                    assistance of Jacob Grimm, his wife, and one of her sisters to do much to repair
                    the loss.</p>
                <p>In 1808 he was appointed by the Bavarian Government ordinary professor of Roman
                    law at Landshut, where he remained a year and a half, and where he left many
                    pleasant memories. In 1810 he was called, chiefly at the instance of William von
                    Humboldt, to Berlin to fill the chair of Roman law, and assist in organizing the
                    new university. One of his services was to create, in con-</p>
                <p>nexion with the law faculty, a “Spruch-Collegium,” or university court, competent
                    to deal with cases remitted to it by the ordinary courts; and he took an active
                    part in its labours. This was the busiest time of his life. He was engaged in
                    lecturing, in the government of the university (of which he was the third
                    rector), and as tutor to the crown prince in Roman, criminal, and Prussian law.
                    Not the least important consequence of his residence in Berlin was his
                    friendship with Niebuhr and Eichhorn. In 1814 appeared his pamphlet <hi
                    rend="italic">Vom Beruf unserer Zeit für Gesetzgebung und
                    Rechtswissenschaft.</hi> It was a protest against the demand for codification,
                    and in particular against the extension of the Code Napoléon to Germany. Fired
                    with the hope that a day of resurrection for the national life of Germany was at
                    hand, Thibaut had written a pamphlet urging the necessity of forming a code for
                    Germany. Savigny wrote a reply, in which were laid down some principles with
                    which wise advocates of codification might well agree. “I regard,” he said, “the
                    law of each country as a member of its body, not as a garment merely which has
                    been made to please the fancy, and can be taken off at pleasure and exchanged
                    for another.” He laid stress upon the connexion of the present and the past and
                    the consequent limitations of the power of legislation. But in the course of his
                    argument he confounded the errors of codifiers in France, Austria, and Prussia,
                    and especially the defects in the Code Napoléon, with the necessary incidents of
                    codification. Put at its highest, his argument comes to little more than others
                    had before crudely expressed by saying, “We are not wise enough to compose a
                    code.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See Austin’s
                    criticisms in <hi rend="italic">Lectures,</hi> ii. 698.</p></note></p>
                <p>In 1815 he founded, with Eichhorn and Göschen, the <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift
                    für geschichtliche Rechtswissenschaft,</hi> the organ of the new historical
                    school, of which he was the representative. In 1816, while on his way to Rome as
                    envoy of Prussia, Niebuhr made at Verona the celebrated discovery of the lost
                    text of Gaius. He communicated to Savigny the fact, and also his conjecture that
                    it was the work of Ulpian. Savigny made known the discovery to the world in an
                    article in the <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift,</hi> and pointed out Gaius as the
                    real author. Göschen, Bekker, and Hollweg actually deciphered the manuscript;
                    but there is some truth in Hugo’s saying, “Without Savigny one would not have
                    had Gaius.”</p>
                <p>The record of the remainder of Savigny’s life consists of little else than a list
                    of the merited honours which he received at the hands of his sovereign, and of
                    the works which he published with indefatigable activity.</p>
                <p>In 1815 appeared the first volume of his <hi rend="italic">Geschichte des
                    Römischen Rechts im Mittelalter;</hi> the last did not appear until 1831. This
                    work, to which his early instructor, Weis, had first prompted him, was
                    originally intended to be a literary history of Roman law from Irnerius to the
                    present time. His design was in some respect narrowed; in others it was widened.
                    He saw fit not to continue the narrative beyond the 16th century, when the
                    separation of nationalities disturbed the foundations of the science of law. His
                    treatment of the subject was not merely that of a bibliographer; it was
                    philosophical. It revealed the continuity in the history of Roman law; and it
                    was an emphatic protest against the habit of viewing the law of a nation as an
                    arbitrary creation, not connected with its history and condition. It was the
                    parent of many valuable works which continued Savigny’s investigations.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See Von Mohl’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Staatswissenschaft,</hi> vol. iii. p. 55. For a somewhat less
                    favourable view, see Gans’s <hi rend="italic">Vermischte
                    Schriften.</hi></p></note> In 1817 he was appointed a member of the commission
                    for organizing the Prussian provincial estates, and also a member of the
                    department of justice in the Staatsrath, and in 1819 he<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n346/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0346-0327"/> became a member of the supreme court of cassation
                    and revision for the Rhine Provinces. In 1820 he was made a member of the
                    commission for revising the Prussian code. In 1822 a serious nervous illness
                    attacked Savigny, and compelled him to seek relief in travel. He always
                    considered that he had benefited much by the homoeopathic treatment of Dr
                    Necker, and he remained a firm believer in homoeopathy. In 1835 he began his
                    elaborate work on the modern system of Roman law. The eighth and last volume
                    appeared in 1849.</p>
                <p>In March 1842 he ceased to perform his duties as professor in order to become
                    “Grosskanzler” of Prussia; and in that position he carried out several important
                    law reforms in regard to bills of exchange and divorce (a subject on which he
                    had meditated much). He held that office until 1848, when he resigned, not
                    altogether to the regret of his friends, who had seen his energies withdrawn
                    from jurisprudence without being able to flatter themselves that he was a great
                    statesman. In 1850, on the occasion of the jubilee of his obtaining his doctor’s
                    degree, appeared in five volumes his <hi rend="italic">Vermischte
                    Schriften,</hi> consisting of a collection of his minor works published between
                    1800 and 1844. This event gave rise to much enthusiasm throughout Germany in
                    honour of “the great master” and founder of modern jurisprudence. Professor
                    Scheurl, in his <hi rend="italic">Einige Worte über Savigny,</hi> notes the fact
                    that on the 31st of October Luther first revealed to the world the light of
                    evangelical truth, and Savigny on that day began his work as a law reformer. In
                    1853 he published his treatise on <hi rend="italic">Obligations,</hi> a
                    supplement to his system of modern Roman law. Savigny died at Berlin on October
                    25, 1861. His son, Carl Friedrich von Savigny, born September 19, 1814, was
                    Prussian minister of foreign affairs in 1849. He represented Prussia in
                    important diplomatic transactions, especially in 1866, and died February 11,
                    1875.</p>
                <p>In the history of jurisprudence Savigny’s great works are the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Rccht des Besitzes</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Beruf unserer Zcit für
                    Gesctzgebung.</hi> The former marked an epoch in jurisprudence. Prof. Ihering
                    says: “With the <hi rend="italic">Recht des Besitzes</hi> was the juridical
                    method of the Romans regained, and modern jurisprudence born.” It marked a great
                    advance both in results and method, and it tendered obsolete a large literature.
                    Savigny sought to prove that in Roman law possession had always reference to
                    usucapion or to interdicts, that it is not a right to continue in possession,
                    but to immunity from violence, and that possession is based on the consciousness
                    of unlimited power. These and other propositions were maintained with great
                    acuteness and unequalled ingenuity in interpreting and harmonizing the Roman
                    jurists. The book also seeks to solve the problem of general interest, common to
                    almost every system of jurisprudence, why possession, rightful or wrongful, as
                    distinguished from property, should be protected. This general problem suffers
                    by being almost solely discussed with reference to Roman law. His leading
                    principle, that every “exercise of force” is illegal, is not incontestible, and,
                    if true, it does not clear up the whole problem. The attempt to treat the
                    historical accidents of Roman aw as juridical necessities is the weak side of a
                    work in other respects masterly; and there is a difficulty in understanding
                    Austin’s eulogy that it was of all books he knew “the least alloyed with error
                    and imperfection.” The controversy which has been carried on in Germany by
                    Ihering, Baron, Gans, and Bruns shows that many of Savigny’s conclusions have
                    not been accepted.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See
                    Windscheid, <hi rend="italic">Lehrbuch des Pandektenrechts,</hi> i.
                    439,</p></note> The <hi rend="italic">Beruf unserer Zeit</hi> expresses the
                    idea, unfamiliar in 1814, that law is part and parcel of national life, and
                    combats the notion, too much assumed by French jurists, especially in last
                    century, and countenanced in practice by Bentham, that law might be arbitrarily
                    imposed on a country irrespective of its state of civilization and past history.
                    Of even greater value than his services in founding or consolidating “the
                    historical school of jurisprudence” is the emphatic recognition in his works of
                    the fact that the practice and theory of jurisprudence cannot be divorced
                    without injury to both. Writing at a time when the influence of Hegel was in the
                    ascendant, and in a city where he was official philosopher, Savigny was not
                    carried away by metaphysical theories. In all his writings there is not a word
                    betraying acquaintance with the labours of his great contemporary, Bentham; nor
                    had Bentham more than the most superficial knowledge of him (see Gans’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Rückblicke auf Personen).</hi> Perhaps a study of both would do
                    more than anything else to aid in the construction of a true science of
                    jurisprudence, consisting neither of platitudes and logomachies nor of a
                    worthless catalogue of legal curiosities. (J. M+. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
