<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0162-0145-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SAFFRON</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 21, page 145</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bg2hh25">Mongols</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4q52fd7q">Butter</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k224">Baths</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1025421">Mongols</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1199318">Crocuses</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:843083">Butter</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1151043">Time</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1137272">Sugar</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206073">China</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n162/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SAFFRON</label> (Arab, <hi rend="italic">za'farān)</hi> is
                    manufactured from the dried stigmas and part of the style of the saffron crocus,
                    a cultivated form of <hi rend="italic">Crocus sativus,</hi> L., the precise
                    origin of which is unknown; for, though some of the wild forms (var. <hi
                    rend="italic">Thomasii, Cartwrightianus)</hi> are also employed for the
                    manufacture of saffron, they differ in character from the cultivated type and
                    are somewhat restricted in geographical range, while the cultivated form extends
                    with little or no change through nearly ninety degrees of ongitude (Spain to
                    Kashmir) and twenty-five degrees of latitude (England to Persia). It is
                    invariably sterile, unless artificially fertilized with the pollen of some of
                    the wild varieties. The purple flower, which blooms late in autumn, is very
                    similar to that of the common spring crocus, and the stigmas, which are
                    protruded from the perianth, are of a characteristic orange-red colour. The
                    Egyptians, though acquainted with the bastard safflower (see preceding article),
                    do not seem to have possessed saffron; but it is named in Canticles iv. 14 among
                    other sweet-smelling herbs. It is also repeatedly mentioned (<hi rend="italic"
                    >κρόκος</hi>) by Homer, Hippocrates, and other Greek writers; and the word
                    “crocodile” was long supposed to have been derived from κρόκος and δειλός,
                    whence we have such stories as that “the crocodile’s tears are never true save
                    when he is forced where saffron groweth” (Fuller’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Worthies).</hi> It has long been cultivated in Persia and Kashmir, and is
                    supposed to have been introduced into China by the Mongol invasion. It is
                    mentioned in the Chinese materia medica <hi rend="italic">(Pun tsaou,</hi>
                    1552-78). The chief seat of cultivation in early times, however, was the town of
                    Corycus (modern Korghoz) in Cilicia, and from this central point of distribution
                    it may not improbably have spread east and west. According to Hehn, the town
                    derived its name from the crocus; Reymond, on the other hand, with more
                    probability, holds that the name of the drug arose from that of the town. It was
                    cultivated by the Arabs in Spain about 961, and is mentioned in an English
                    leech-book of the 10th century, but seems to have disappeared from western
                    Europe till reintroduced by the crusaders. According to Hakluyt, it was brought
                    into England from Tripoli by a pilgrim, who hid a stolen corm in the hollow of
                    his staff. It was especially cultivated near Hinton in Cambridgeshire and in
                    Essex at Saffron Walden <hi rend="italic">(i.e.,</hi> Saffron Woods, not Saffron
                    Walled-in, as the canting crest of the town would imply), its cultivators being
                    called “crokers.” This industry, though very important in the 15th century, when
                    English saffron commanded the highest prices on the Continent, appears to have
                    died out about 1768.</p>
                <p>Saffron was used as an ingredient in many of the complicated medicines of early
                    times. According to Gerard “the moderate use of it is good for the head and
                    maketh the sences more quicke and lively. It shaketh off heavie and drowsy sleep
                    and maketh a man mery.” It appears to be really a stimulant and antispasmodic,
                    though its powers are slight. It is scarcely ever employed by modern pharmacists
                    unless for the mere coloration of other tinctures, or at most as a cordial
                    adjunct to other medicines. That it was very largely used in cookery is
                    evidenced by many writers; thus Laurenbergius <hi rend="italic">(Apparatus
                    Plantarum,</hi> 1632) makes the large assertion “In re familiare vix ullus est
                    telluris habitatus angulus ubi non sit croci quotidiana usurpatio aspersi vel
                    incocti cibis.” The Chinese used also to employ it largely, and the Persians and
                    Spaniards<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n163/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0163-0146"/> still <hi rend="italic">m</hi> ix it with their
                    rice. As a perfume it was strewn in Greek halls, courts, and theatres, and in
                    the Roman baths. The streets of Rome were sprinkled with saffron when Nero made
                    his entry into the city.</p>
                <p>It was, however, mainly used as a dye. It was a royal colour in early Greek
                    times, though afterwards perhaps from its abundant use in the baths, and as a
                    scented salve, it was especially appropriated by the hetairae. In ancient
                    Ireland a king’s mantle was dyed with saffron, and even down to the 17th century
                    the “lein-croich,” or saffron-dyed shirt, was worn by persons of rank in the
                    Hebrides. In mediaeval illumination it furnished, as a glaze upon burnished
                    tinfoil, a cheap and effective substitute for gold. The sacred spot on the
                    forehead of a Hindu pundit is also partly composed of it. Its main use in
                    England was to colour pastry and confectionery,—hence “I must have saffron to
                    colour the Warden pies” (<hi rend="italic">Winter’s Tale,</hi> act iv. sc.
                    i.),—and it is still often added to butter and cheese. One grain of saffron
                    rubbed to powder with sugar and a little water imparts a distinctly yellow tint
                    to ten gallons of water. This colouring power is due to the presence of
                    polychlorite, a substance whose chemical formula appears to be C <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 48</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 60</hi> O <hi rend="subscript"
                    > 18</hi>, and which may be obtained by treating saffron with ether, and
                    afterwards exhausting with water. Under acids it yields the following
                    reaction—</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">C</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps"> 48</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">H</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps"> 60</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">O</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps"> 18</hi> + H <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O = <hi rend="smallcaps">2(C</hi><hi rend="subscript
                    smallcaps"> 16</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">H</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps">
                    18</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">O</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps"> 6</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">) + c</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps"> 10</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">h</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps"> 14</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">o + c</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps"> 6</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">h</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps"> 12</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">o</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps"> 6</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">·</hi></p>
                <p>Polj’clilorite. Crocin. Essential oil. Sugar.</p>
                <p>Crocin, according to Watts, <hi rend="italic">Dict, of Chem.,</hi> has a
                    composition of C <hi rend="subscript"> 29</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 42</hi> O
                    <hi rend="subscript"> 15</hi> or C <hi rend="subscript"> 58</hi> H <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 42</hi> O <hi rend="subscript"> 30</hi>. This crocin is a red
                    colouring matter, and it is surmised that the red colour of the stigmas is due
                    to this reaction taking place in nature.</p>
                <p>At present saffron is chiefly cultivated in Spain, France, Sicily, on the lower
                    spurs of the Apennines, and in Persia and Kashmir. The ground has to be
                    thoroughly cleared of stones, manured, and trenched, and the corms are planted
                    in ridges. The flowers are gathered at the end of October, in the early morning,
                    just when they are beginning to open after the night. The stigmas and a part of
                    the style are carefully picked out, and the wet saffron is then scattered on
                    sheets of paper to a depth of 2 or 3 inches; over this a cloth is laid, and next
                    a board with a heavy weight. A strong heat is applied for about two hours so as
                    to make the saffron “sweat,” and a gentler temperature for a further period of
                    twenty-four hours, the cake being turned every hour so that every part is
                    thoroughly dried. It is calculated that the stigmas of about 4300 flowers are
                    required to give an ounce of saffron; but the experiments of Chappellier
                    indicate a possibility of greatly increasing the yield by the cultivation of
                    monstrous forms.</p>
                <p>The drug has naturally always been liable to great adulteration in spite of
                    penalties, the severity of which suggests the surviving tradition of its sacred
                    character. Thus in Nuremberg a regular saffron inspection was held, and in the
                    15th century we read of men being burned in the market-place along with their
                    adulterated saffron, while on another occasion three persons convicted of the
                    same crime were buried alive. Grease and butter are still very frequently mixed
                    with the cake and shreds of beef dipped in saffron water are also used. Good
                    saffron is distinguished by its deep orange-red colour; if it is light yellow or
                    blackish, it is bad or too old. It should also have a peculiar and rather
                    powerful odour, and a bitter pungent taste. If oily it is probably adulterated
                    with butter or grease.</p>
                <p>See Flückiger and Hanbury, <hi rend="italic">Pharmocographia,</hi> and Maw, <hi
                    rend="italic">Monograph of the genus Crocus,</hi> upon which the preceding
                    account is essentially based; also Pereira, <hi rend="italic">Materia
                    Medica,</hi> and the pharmacopoeias.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
