<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0184-0167-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ST ÉTIENNE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 21, page 167</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1118724">Silk</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:865087">Coal</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:865671">Coaling</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1093898">Religions</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1170328">War</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g8x">Religion</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bn4t">Religions</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4fb4wm7s">Coal</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4js9h942">Coaling</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n184/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ST ÉTIENNE</label>, an industrial and manufacturing town of
                    France, chef-lieu of the department of Loire, 312 miles south-south-east of
                    Paris and 36 miles south-south-west of Lyons by rail, with a branch line to Le
                    Puy. The coal-field of St Étienne is the richest in France after that of
                    Valenciennes and Pas de Calais, giving employment to 12,000 miners and 5000
                    workmen at the pit-heads. There are 64 concessions worked by 28 companies,
                    extending over an area 20 miles long by 5 in width; the mineral is of two
                    kinds,—smelting coal (said to be the best in France) and gas coal; the yearly
                    output is between 3,000,000 and 4,000,000 tons, but with a tendency to decrease.
                    In the metallurgic establishments of the arrondissement, which extend all the
                    way along the railway from Firminy to Rive-de-Gier, 5540 workmen are employed,
                    and in 1882 61,127 tons of cast metal, 58,445 tons of iron, 10,815 tons of
                    sheet-iron, and 131,563 tons of steel of all kinds were manu factured. The
                    last-</p>
                <p>named industry, carried on accord ing to the Besse mer and Martin processes,
                    yields nearly a third of the whole French production of steel.</p>
                <p>Military and naval material, railway plant, and articles of general mer chandise
                    are all madeat St Étienne, and its name is especially associ ated with large
                    castings, bomb proof plates, ship-</p>
                <p>armour, masts, and pieces of machin ery. The national gun-factory, under the
                    direction of artillery officers and employing 4300 workmen, is almost
                    exclusively devoted to the production of rifles and revolvers for the army. A
                    certain number of gun-makers not engaged in the factory turn out from 80,000 to
                    90,000 firearms (hunting-pieces, revolvers, &amp;c.) per annum. Hardware is
                    manufactured by 60 firms, employing 7000 workmen (who are not, however,
                    exclusively occupied with this department); leading articles are locks (known as
                    Forez locks), common cutlery, files, nails, bolts, anvils, vices. Hemp cables
                    for mines,<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n185/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0185-0168"/> hats, pottery, and lime are among the
                    miscellaneous manufactured products of the town, which is besides a great centre
                    of the ribbon trade, with a testing-house <hi rend="italic">(condition)</hi> for
                    examining the silk. From 500 to 600 tons of silk, valued at £1,200,000 to
                    £1,400,000, are used per annum, and the manufactured articles reach a value
                    ranging from £2,800,000 to £3,200,000. The ribbons, laces, trimmings (in silk,
                    cotton, and india-rubber) produced in the arrondissement of St Étienne are
                    valued at £4,000,000, and form four-fifths of the total French production. With
                    the exception of a few factories where machinery is employed, the whole
                    manufacture is carried on by persons with small means. About 5000 looms
                    (Jacquard’s permitting thirty-six pieces to be woven at once) and 40,000 workmen
                    are employed. Besides the old abbey church of Valbenoîte (outside of the town)
                    with its nave dating from the 13th century, the public buildings comprise a
                    Protestant church, a synagogue, a town-house (finished under the second empire
                    and decorated with statues of the ribbon trade and metallurgy), a school of
                    mines (1816), with a mineralogical and geological collection, and a “palace of
                    the arts,” with a museum and library rich in old MSS. and collections in
                    connexion with artillery and natural history. Near Valbenoîte in the wooded
                    gorge of the Furens is the reservoir of Gouffre d’Enfer, formed by a dam
                    (1861-1866) 328 feet long, 131 high, and 131 wide at the base, and capable of
                    storing about 70,000,000 cubic feet of water. The population of the town was
                    28,000 in 1764; by 1876 it was 126,019, but it had decreased to 114,962 (123,813
                    in the commune) in 1881.</p>
                <p>At the close of the 12th century St Etienne was only a parish of the Pays de Gier
                    belonging to the abbey of Valbenoîte. By the middle of the 14th century the coal
                    trade had reached a certain development, and by the close of the century the
                    town was surrounded with walls and had consuls. A hundred years later it had
                    three growing suburbs. The Wars of Religion stimulated the manufacture of arms,
                    and about the same period the ribbon trade sprang into existence. It was not
                    till the 18th century, however, that the town entered on its era of prosperity.
                    The royal manufactory of arms was established in 1764. In 1789 they were
                    producing at the rate of 12,000 muskets per annum; between September 1794 and
                    May 1796 they delivered 170,858; and 100,000 was the annual average throughout
                    the whole period of the empire. The first railways opened in France were the
                    line between St Étienne and Andrezieu on the Loire in 1828 and that between St
                    Etienne and Lyons in 1831. In 1856 St Étienne became the administrative centre
                    of the department instead of Montbrison. Among the local celebrities are Francis
                    Garnier, who conquered Tongking in 1873, and several engravers who have given
                    eminence to the St Étienne school of engraving.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
