<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0921-0222-0203-05" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SALAMANCA (9th edition, volume 21, page 203)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p843z58">Domes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4057cr7r">Convents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0mz4b">Conventions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4599z56c">Goths</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ww7759r">Moors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f45m">Judgments</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g68c">Virginal</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44m91m0x">Virginity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:896536">Domes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:877187">Convents</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1151043">Time</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:945091">Goths</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:984609">Judgments</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n222/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SALAMANCA</label><hi rend="italic">(Salmantica,
                        Elmantica),</hi> the capital of the above province, lies on the banks of the
                    Tormes, 172 miles north-west of Madrid by rail. The river is here crossed by a
                    bridge 500 feet in length built on twenty-six arches, fifteen of which are of
                    Roman origin, while the remainder date from the 16th century. The town was of
                    importance in times as remote as 222 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> when it was
                    captured by Hannibal from the Vettones; and it afterwards became under the
                    Romans the ninth station on the Via Lata from Merida to Zaragoza. It passed
                    successively under the rule of the Goths and the Moors, till the latter were
                    finally driven out about 1055. The city is still much the same in outward
                    appearance as when its tortuous streets were thronged with students. The
                    university was naturally the chief source of wealth to the town, the population
                    of which in the 16th century numbered 50,000. Its decay of course reacted on the
                    townsfolk, but it fortunately also arrested the process of modernization, so
                    that the city retains most of its old features and is now one of the most
                    picturesque in Spain. The ravages of war alone have wrought serious damage, for
                    the French in their defensive operations at the siege almost destroyed the
                    western quarter. The ruins still remain, and give an air of desolation which is
                    not borne out by the real condition of the inhabitants, however poverty-stricken
                    they may appear. The magnificent Plaza Mayor, built by Andres Garcia de Quiñones
                    at the beginning of the 18th century, and capable of holding 20,000 people to
                    witness a bullfight, is one of the finest squares in Europe. It is surrounded by
                    an arcade of ninety arches on Corinthian columns, one side of the square being
                    occupied by the municipal buildings. The decorations of the façades are in the
                    Renaissance style, and the plaza as a whole is a fine sample of plateresque
                    architecture. But the old and new cathedrals (see below) are the chief objects
                    of interest in the city.</p>
                <p>In the Middle Ages the trade of Salamanca was not insignificant, and the stamped
                    leather-work produced there is still sought after. Its manufactures are now of
                    little consequence, and consist of china, cloth, and leather. The transport
                    trade of the town is, however, of more importance, and shows signs of
                    increasing. But any great revival can only take place when communication with
                    the coast is considerably improved, a result which will no doubt be promoted by
                    the recent opening of the line to the coast of Portugal. The population within
                    the municipal boundaries in 1877 was 18,007, and in 1886 was estimated at about
                    20,000.</p>
                <p>The old cathedral is a cruciform building of the 12th century, begun by Bishop
                    Geronimo, the confessor of the Cid. Its style of architecture is that Late
                    Romanesque which prevailed in the south of France, but the builder showed much
                    originality in the construction of the dome, which covers the crossing of the
                    nave and transepts. The inner dome is made to spring, not from immediately above
                    the arches, but from a higher stage of a double arcade pierced<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n223/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0921-0223-0204"/> with windows. The thrust of the vaulting is
                    borne by four massive pinnacles, and over the inner dome is an outer pointed one
                    covered with tiles. The whole forms a most effective and graceful group. On the
                    vault of the apse is a fresco of Our Lord in Judgment by Nicolas Florentino. The
                    reredos, which has the peculiarity of fitting the curve of the apse, contains
                    fifty-five panels with paintings mostly by the same artist. There are many fine
                    monuments in the south transept and cloister chapels. An adjoining building, the
                    Capilla de Talavera, is used as a chapel for service according to the Mozarabic
                    rite, which is celebrated there six times a year. On the north of and adjoining
                    the old church stands the new cathedral, built from designs by Juan Gil de
                    Ontañon. Begun in 1513 under Bishop Francisco de Bobadilla, but not finished
                    until 1734, it is a notable example of the late Gothic and Plateresque styles.
                    Its length is 340 feet and its breadth 160 feet. The interior is fairly Gothic
                    in character, but on the outside the Renaissance spirit shows itself more
                    clearly, and is fully developed in the dome. Everywhere the attempt at mere
                    novelty or richness results in feebleness. The main arch of the great portal
                    consists of a simple trefoil, but the label above takes an ogee line, and the
                    inner arches are elliptical. Above the doors are bas-reliefs, foliage, &amp;c.,
                    which in exuberance of design and quality of workmanship are good examples of
                    the latest efforts of Spanish Gothic. The church contains paintings by
                    Navarrete, Becerra, and Morales, and some overrated statues by Juan de Juni. The
                    treasury is very rich, and amongst other articles possesses a custodia which is
                    a masterpiece of goldsmith’s work, and a bronze crucifix, of undoubted
                    authenticity, which was borne before the Cid in battle. The tower is too unsafe
                    to allow of the ringing of its great bell, which weighs over 23 tons. The
                    interest of Salamanca centred in its university, founded by Alfonso IX. about
                    1200 and for four centuries one of the chief seats of European learning. Of the
                    university buildings the façade of the library (80,000 volumes, exclusive of
                    MSS.) is a peculiarly rich example of late 15th-century Gothic. The cloisters
                    are light and elegant; the grand staircase ascending from them has a fine
                    balustrade of foliage and figures. The Colegio de Nobles Irlandeses, formerly
                    Colegio de Santiago Apostol, was built in 1521 from designs by Ibarra. The
                    double arcaded cloister is a fine piece of work of the best period of the
                    Renaissance. The Jesuit College is an immense and ugly Renaissance building
                    begun in 1614 by Juan Gomez de Mora. The Colegio Viejo, also called San
                    Bartolomé, was rebuilt in the 18th century, and now serves as the governor’s
                    palace. The convent of Santo Domingo, sometimes called San Esteban, shows a
                    mixture of styles from the 13th century onwards. The church is Gothic with a
                    plateresque façade of great lightness and delicacy. It is of purer design than
                    that of the cathedral; nevertheless it shows the tendency of the period. The
                    reredos, one of the finest Renaissance works in Spain, contains statues by
                    Salvador Carmona, and a curious bronze statuette of the Virgin and Child on a
                    throne of champlevé enamel of the 12th century. The chapter-house, built by Juan
                    Moreno in 1637, and the staircase and sacristy arc good examples of later work.
                    The convent of the Augustinas Recoletas, begun by Fontana in 1616, is in better
                    taste than any other Renaissance building in the city. The church is rich in
                    marble fittings and contains several fine pictures of the Neapolitan school,
                    especially the Conception by Ribera over the altar. The convent of the Sancti
                    Spiritu has a good door by Berruguete. There is also a rather effective portal
                    to the convent of Las Duenas. The church of S. Marcos is a curious circular
                    building with three eastern apses; and the churches of S. Martin and S. Matteo
                    have good early doorways. Many of the private houses are untouched examples of
                    the domestic architecture of the prosperous times in which they were built. Such
                    are the Casa de las Conchas, the finest example of its period in Spain; the Casa
                    de la Sal, with a magnificent courtyard and sculptured gallery; and the palaces
                    of Maldonado, Monterey, and Espinosa. (H. B. B.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
