<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0329-0310-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SARDIS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 21, page 310</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4hd7ns44">Mounds</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4k931f29">Ruins</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ww7712k">Wealth</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1111954">Seljuks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1159574">Turks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1028233">Mounds</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1172973">Wealth</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n329/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SARDIS</label> (οί Σάρςϵις), the capital of the kingdom of
                    Lydia, the seat of a <hi rend="italic">conventus</hi> under the Roman empire,
                    and the metropolis of the province Lydia in later Roman and Byzantine times, was
                    situated in the middle Hermus valley, at the foot of Mount Tmolus, a steep and
                    lofty spur of which formed the citadel. It was about 20 stadia (2½ miles) south
                    of the Hermus. The earliest reference to Sardis is in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Persae</hi> of AEschylus (472 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi>); in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Iliad</hi> the name Hyde seems to be given to the city of the
                    Maeonian (<hi rend="italic">i.e</hi>., Lydian) chiefs, and in later times Hyde
                    was said to be the older name of Sardis, or the name of its citadel. It is,
                    however, more probable that Sardis was not the original capital of the
                    Maeonians, but that it became so amid the changes which produced a powerful
                    Lydian empire in the 8th century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> The city, but
                    not the citadel, was destroyed by the Cimmerians in the 7th century, by the
                    Athenians in the 6th, and by Antiochus the Great in the 3d century; once at
                    least, under the emperor Tiberius, it was destroyed by an earthquake; but it was
                    always rebuilt, and continued to be one of the great cities of western Asia
                    Minor till the later Byzantine time. Its importance was due, first to its
                    military strength, secondly to its situation on an important highway leading
                    from the interior to the AEgean coast, and thirdly to its commanding the wide
                    and fertile plain of the Hermus. The early Lydian kingdom was far advanced in
                    the industrial arts (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Lydia),</hi> and Sardis was the
                    chief seat of its manufactures. The most important of these trades was the
                    manufacture and dyeing of delicate woollen stuffs and carpets. The statement
                    that the little stream Pactolus which flowed through the market-place rolled
                    over golden sands is probably little more than a metaphor, due to the wealth of
                    the city to which the Greeks of the 6th century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi>
                    resorted for supplies of gold; but trade and the practical organization of
                    commerce were the real sources of this wealth. After Constantinople became the
                    capital of the East a new road system grew up connecting the provinces with the
                    capital. Sardis then lay rather apart from the great lines of communication and
                    lost some of its importance. It still, however, retained its titular supremacy,
                    and continued to be the seat of the metropolitan bishop of the province. It is
                    enumerated as third, after Ephesus and Smyrna, in the list of cities of the
                    Thracesian thema given by Constantine Porphyrogenitus in the 10th century; but
                    in the actual history of the next four centuries it plays a part very inferior
                    to Magnesia ad Sipylum and Philadelphia, which have to the present day retained
                    their pre-eminence in the district. The Hermus valley began to suffer from the
                    inroads of the Seljuk Turks about the end of the 11th century; but the successes
                    of the Greek general Philocales in 1118 relieved the district for the time, and
                    the ability of the Comneni, together with the gradual decay of the Seljuk power,
                    retained it in the Byzantine dominions. The country round Sardis was frequently
                    ravaged both by Christians and by Greeks during the 13th century. Soon after
                    1301 the Seljuk emirs overran the whole of the Hermus and Cayster valleys, and a
                    fort on the citadel of Sardis was handed over to them by treaty. Finally in 1390
                    Philadelphia, which had for some time been an independent Christian city,
                    surrendered to Sultan Bayazid’s mixed army of Ottoman Turks and Byzantine
                    Christians, and the Seljuk power in the Hermus valley was merged in the Ottoman
                    empire. The latest reference to the city of Sardis relates its capture (and
                    probable destruction) by Timur in 1402. Its site is now absolutely deserted,
                    except that a tiny village, Sart, merely a few huts inhabited by semi-nomadic
                    Yuruks, exists beside the Pactolus, and that there is a station of the Smyrna
                    and Cassaba Railway a mile north of the principal ruins.</p>
                <p>The ruins of Sardis, so far as they are now visible, are chiefly of the Roman
                    time; but probably few ancient sites would more richly reward the excavator with
                    remains of all periods from the early pre-Hellenic time downwards. O11 the banks
                    of the Pactolus two columns of a temple of the Greek period, probably the great
                    temple of Cybele, are still standing. More than one attempt to excavate this
                    temple, the last by Mr G. Dennis in 1882, have been made and prematurely brought
                    to an end by lack of funds. The necropolis of the old Lydian city, a vast series
                    of mounds, some of enormous size, lies on the north side of the Hermus, four or
                    five miles from Sardis, a little south of the sacred lake Coloe; here the
                    Maeonian chiefs, sons, according to Homer, of the lake, were brought to sleep
                    beside their mother. The series of mounds is now called Bin Tepe (Thousand
                    Mounds). Several of them have been opened by modern excavators, but in every
                    case it was found that treasure-seekers of an earlier time had removed any
                    articles of value that had been deposited in the sepulchral chambers.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
