<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0236-0217-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SALICYLIC ACID</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 21, page 217</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4g737640">Pharmacopoeias</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4028pp4g">Viola</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pr1n">Phenols</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04032">Alcohol</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b41z41s37">Alcoholates</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b40z70w4g">Alcohols</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1075502">Preparedness</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1060501">Phenols</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1060490">Phenol</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:804631">Alcohols</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:804414">Alcoholics</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1060283">Pharmacopoeias</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1152983">Torula</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1167119">Viola</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n236/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SALICYLIC ACID</label>, an organic acid found in nature, in
                    the free state, in the flowers of the meadow-sweet <hi rend="italic">(Spiraea
                    Ulmaria,</hi> L.) and, combined with methylic ether, in the leaves of the
                    wintergreen <hi rend="italic">(Gaultheria procumbens,</hi> L.) and <hi
                    rend="italic">Andromeda Leschenaultii,</hi> in the bark of the sweet birch <hi
                    rend="italic">(Betula lenta,</hi> L.), and in several species of <hi
                    rend="italic">Viola.</hi> It was discovered in 1838 by Piria, who prepared it
                    artificially by the decomposition of <hi rend="smallcaps">Salicin</hi> (<hi
                    rend="italic">q.v</hi>.). It is remarkable as being the first organic compound
                    occurring in nature which has been prepared artificially on the large scale as a
                    commercial article. During the last few years it has been extensively used in
                    medicine as a remedy for acute rheumatism, either alone or in the form of its
                    sodium salt. Possessing powerful antiseptic properties and being poisonous only
                    in large doses (the medicinal dose being from 5 to 30 grains), it is capable of
                    manifold uses in the arts and manufactures. In the proportion of from 1 to 10
                    per cent. it prevents the development of bacteria in fluids containing them, and
                    if added to the extent of 1 part in 60 it will destroy their life. It also kills
                    <hi rend="italic">Torula,</hi> and prevents the souring of beer and milk. It
                    hinders the chemical changes brought about by the action of vegetable ferments
                    or enzymes such as amygdalin and sinnigrin, and consequently can prevent the
                    formation of essential oil of almonds or of oil of mustard, &amp;c. Plants
                    watered with its solution speedily die. The addition of a little of the acid to
                    glue renders it more tenacious; skins to be used for making leather do not
                    undergo decomposition if steeped in a dilute solution; butter containing a small
                    quantity of it may be kept sweet for months even in the hottest weather. It also
                    prevents the mouldiness of preserved fruits and has been found useful in the
                    manufacture of vinegar. Unless the perfectly pure acid be employed the addition
                    of salicylic acid to articles of food must be considered dangerous, some persons
                    being peculiarly susceptible to its action.</p>
                <p>Salicylic acid is met with in commerce in two forms, “natural” and “artificial.”
                    The former occurs as handsome prismatic crystals resembling those of strychnin,
                    but considerably larger, usually about half an inch in length; the latter is met
                    with as light minute crystals bearing some resemblance to sulphate of quinine,
                    but smaller. The natural acid is prepared by decomposing the volatile oil of
                    wintergreen or of the sweet birch by a strong solution of potassium hydrate, and
                    treating the resulting potassium salicylate with hydrochloric acid, which
                    liberates the salicylic acid. The artificial acid is prepared according to
                    Robbe’s patent process by passing carbonic anhydride through sodium phenoxide
                    (carbolate) heated in a retort, with certain precautions respecting temperature
                    to prevent the formation of para-hydroxybenzoic acid. It is subsequently
                    purified and recrystallized. An improvement has recently been made on this
                    process by substituting sodium phenol for sodium phenoxide, the whole of the
                    phenol being in this case converted into salicylic acid. Formerly this acid was
                    met with in commerce contaminated with phenol, rosolic, and para-oxybenzoic
                    acids, but is now prepared in a perfectly pure condition. The presence of the
                    first-named impurity may be detected by its odour and by the melting-point being
                    lower than when pure, the second by the pink tinge it communicates to the acid,
                    and the third by its comparative insolubility in boiling chloroform, by the
                    greater solubility of its calcium salt, and by its giving a yellow precipitate
                    with ferric chloride. Salicylic acid when pure should be free from odour and
                    should dissolve completely in alcohol, and its solution, when spontaneously
                    evaporated without contact with air, should yield crystals having colourless
                    points. It has a specific gravity of 1·45 and fuses at 155° C. (311° Fahr.);
                    above that temperature it is converted into phenol and carbonic anhydride. Its
                    chemical formula is C <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi> H <hi rend="subscript">
                    4</hi> (OH)Co <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> H. It is soluble in 760 parts of cold
                    water, in 4 of rectified spirits of wine, and in 200 of glycerin, also in olive
                    and castor oils, in melted fats and vaseline. Alkaline salts of citric, acetic,
                    and phosphoric acids render it more soluble in water, possibly from the base
                    combining with it. An aqueous solution of salicylic acid gives a deep violet
                    colour with ferric salts. The methyl, ethyl, and amyl ethers of the acid are
                    used in perfumery, and the calcium salt if kept for some time and then distilled
                    with water yields a liquid which has a strong odour of roses (Dingler, <hi
                    rend="italic">Polytechn. Journ.,</hi> ccxvii. p. 136).</p>
                <p>When administered internally salicylic acid rapidly lowers the bodily temperature
                    and reduces the pulse rate, blood pressure, and rapidity of respiration, causing
                    death when given in excessive doses by paralysis of the respiratory organs. It
                    is excreted in the urine partly as salicylic and partly as salicyluric acid,
                    communicating to it a brown colour by reflected and a green one by transmitted
                    light. When taken for some time it produces deafness, giddiness, headache, and
                    noises in the ears, like quinine. Taken internally in medicinal doses it
                    possesses the same properties as salicin and sodium salicylate (see below), but
                    is much less used in medicine. Applied externally, it has a marked action on
                    thickened epidermis, and is hence used for the cure of corns and warts, to
                    relieve pain and destroy fetor in ulcerated cancer, and also in certain skin
                    diseases in which an antiseptic is useful, as in psoriasis, eczema, intertrigo,
                    lupus, and ringworm. Taken as snuff it relieves hay fever.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Salicylate of sodium</hi> (NaC <hi rend="subscript"> 7</hi> H
                    <hi rend="subscript"> 5</hi> O <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>) is more frequently
                    used in medicine than salicylic acid because less irritating to the mucous
                    membranes. It is prepared by neutralizing a solution of sodium carbonate with
                    salicylic acid. It occurs in commerce as small white crystalline plates with a
                    slight pearly lustre, having a sweetish saline taste and mildly alkaline
                    reaction. It is soluble in 1·5 parts of water and 6 of alcohol at 15° C. (59°
                    Fahr.), but much more so in boiling water and alcohol. It is chiefly employed
                    medicinally as a remedy for acute rheumatism, in which it lowers the temperature
                    and allays pain. It is also useful in headache and in phlegmasia alba; its
                    cholagogic action and its power of rendering the bile more fluid indicate its
                    usefulness in the treatment of gall stones. It has been found of service in
                    Meniere’s disease. Alcohol or other stimulants are often given with it to
                    prevent the depressing influence on the heart’s action which is caused by large
                    doses. Ammonia is, however, unfit for this purpose (Martindale, <hi
                    rend="italic">Extra Pharmacopoeia,</hi> 3d ed., p. 57). Like salicylic acid, it
                    produces when given in full doses subjective auditory phenomena, but these
                    symptoms are relieved by the use of ergot and hydrobromic acid. In a few persons
                    it causes most disagreeable visions whenever the eyes are shut, and in others it
                    has even produced delirium. In its action on bacteria it is about one-third less
                    powerful than salicylic acid.<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n237/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0237-0218"/></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
