<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0921-0214-0195-04" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SAINT-PIERRE, Jacques Henri Bernardin de (9th edition,
                    volume 21, page 195)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1103658">Saints</term>
                    <term ref="fast:825070">Back</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942866">Girls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1207170">Malta</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s756m31">Saints</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9789n">Girls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r76k">Martins</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n214/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SAINT-PIERRE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Jacques Henri Bernardin
                            de</hi></label> (1737- 1814), French man-of-letters, was born at Havre
                    on 19th January 1737 and was educated at Caen. After a fashion commoner with
                    English than with French boys, he took an early fancy to the sea, and his uncle,
                    a ship captain, gave him the opportunity of gratifying it. But a single voyage
                    to Martinique was enough for him and he went back to school. He next wanted to
                    be a missionary; but his parents, who had probably taken the measure of his
                    enthusiasms from his sea experiences, objected, and he became an engineer. He
                    served in the army, but was dismissed for insubordination, and, after
                    quarrelling with his family, was in some difficulty. But in 1761 he obtained an
                    appointment at Malta, which also he did not hold long. The most rolling of
                    stones, he appears at St Petersburg, at Warsaw, at Dresden, at Berlin, holding
                    brief commissions as an engineer and rejoicing in romantic adventures. But he
                    came back to Paris at the age of thirty even poorer than he set out. He then
                    passed two years in literary work, supporting himself in an unknown fashion, and
                    in 1768 (for he seems to have been as successful in obtaining appointments as in
                    losing them) he set out for the Isle of France (Mauritius) with a Government
                    commission and remained there three years, returning home in 1771. These
                    wanderings supplied Bernardin with the whole of what may be called his
                    stock-in-trade, for, though he lived more than forty years longer, he never
                    again quitted France. He was very poor, and indeed it is not easy to discover
                    from his biographers what he lived upon, for, though he was an unwearied
                    solicitor of employments and “gratifications,” he received but little, and his
                    touchy and sensitive temperament frequently caused him to quarrel with what
                    little he did receive. On his return from Mauritius he was introduced to the
                    society of D’Alembert and his friends, and continued to frequent it. But he took
                    no great pleasure in the company of any literary man except Rousseau, of whom in
                    Jean Jacques’s last years he saw much, and on whom he formed both his own
                    character and still more his style to a considerable degree. His first work of
                    any importance, the <hi rend="italic">Voyage à l’Ile de France,</hi> appeared in
                    1773 and gained him some reputation. It is the soberest and therefore the least
                    characteristic of his books. The <hi rend="italic">Études de la Nature,</hi>
                    which made his fame and assured him of literary success, did not appear till ten
                    years later, his masterpiece <hi rend="italic">Paid et Virginie</hi> not till
                    1787, and his other masterpiece (which, as much less sentimental and showing not
                    a little humour, some persons may be allowed to prefer), the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Chaumière Indienne,</hi> not till 1790. In 1792 he married<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n215/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0921-0215-0196"/> a very young girl, Félicité Didot. For a
                    short time in 1792 he was superintendent of the Jardin des Plantes and again for
                    a short time professor of morals at the École Normale in 1794. Next year he
                    became a member of the Institute. After his first wife’s death he married, in
                    1800, when he was sixty-three, another young girl, Désirée de Pelleport, and is
                    said to have been very happy with her. He still continued to publish, and was
                    something of a favourite with Napoleon. On the 21st of January 1814 he died at
                    Éragny near Pontoise, where he had in his last years chiefly lived and where he
                    had a house, so that he cannot have been ill off.</p>
                <p>It has been hinted that Bernardin de Saint-Pierre’s personal character was not
                    entirely amiable; it may be added that his literary character has not in all
                    English eyes sufficed to atone for it. Englishmen, and not Englishmen only, have
                    been found to pronounce <hi rend="italic">Paid et Virginie</hi> gaudy in style
                    and unhealthy, not to say unwholesome, in tone. Perhaps Bernardin is not fairly
                    to be judged by this famous story, in which the exuberant sensibility of the
                    time finds equally exuberant expression. The <hi rend="italic">Chaumière</hi>
                    and some passages in the <hi rend="italic">Études de la Nature</hi> proper may
                    be thought to exhibit the real merits of his style to greater advantage. The
                    historic estimate (the sole estimate that is of much worth in comparative
                    literary criticism) at once disengages the question from its difficulties. Where
                    Bernardin is of merit and importance is in his breaking away from the dull and
                    arid vocabulary and phrase which more than a century of classical writing had
                    brought upon France, in his genuine and vigorous preference of the beauties of
                    nature to the mere charms of drawing-room society, and in the attempt which he
                    made, with as much sincerity as could fairly be expected from a man of his day,
                    to reproduce the aspects of the natural world faithfully. After Rousseau, and
                    even more than Rousseau, Bernardin was in French literature the apostle of the
                    return to nature, and, though in him and his immediate follower, Chateaubriand,
                    there is still much mannerism and unreality, he should not and will not lack the
                    credit due.</p>
                <p>Aimé Martin, disciple of Bernardin and the second husband of his second wife,
                    published a complete edition of his works in 18 volumes (Paris, 1818-20),
                    afterwards increased by additional correspondence, &amp;c. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Paul et Virginie,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Chaumière Indienne,</hi>
                    &amp;c., have been separately reprinted in innumerable forms.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
