<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0164-0147-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SAGHALIN, or Sakhalin</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 21, page 147</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1204082">Japan</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204480">Alaska</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210278">Belgium</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:832891">Birch</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1134302">Straits</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:981987">Japanning</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1028427">Mouth</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="13" ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3m35f">Fauna</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4c824k75">Japanning</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4rv0d79g">Riches</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n164/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SAGHALIN, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Sakhalin</hi></label>, is
                    the name improperly given to a large elongated island in the North Pacific,
                    lying between 45° 57' and 54° 24' N. lat. and 141° 30' and 144° 50' E. long.,
                    off the coast of Russian Manchuria. Its proper name is <hi rend="italic"
                    >Karaftu,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Karafuto.</hi> It is separated from the
                    mainland by the narrow and shallow Strait of Tartary, which often freezes in
                    winter in its narrower part, and from Yezo (Japan) by the Strait of La Pérouse.
                    This island (670 miles long, 20 to 150 broad, with an area of 24,560 square
                    miles), about equal in size to Belgium and Holland together, must be considered
                    as a continuation of the mountains bordering the Manchurian littoral. Its
                    orography is still imperfectly known. The present maps represent it as formed of
                    two parallel ridges, running north and south and reaching from 2000 to 4000 or
                    5000 feet (Mounts Berniget and Ktöus-pal) high, with two or more wide
                    depressions, not exceeding 600 feet above the sea. The general configuration of
                    the littoral and the island, however, renders it more probable that there are
                    three chains running south-west to north-east, forming continuations of those of
                    the mainland. The geological structure of the island is also imperfectly known.
                    A few crystalline rocks are found at several capes; Cretaceous limestones
                    containing a rich and specific fauna of gigantic ammonites occur at Dui; and
                    Tertiary conglomerates, sandstones, marls, and clays, folded by subsequent
                    upheavals, are widely spread. The clays, which contain layers of good coal and a
                    rich fossil vegetation, show that during the Miocene period Saghalin was part of
                    a continent which comprised both north Asia, Alaska, and Japan, and enjoyed a
                    much warmer climate than now. The Pliocene deposits contain a mollusc fauna more
                    arctic than the present, and probably indicating that the connexion between the
                    Pacific and Arctic Oceans was broader than now. Only two rivers, the Tym and the
                    Poronai, are worthy of mention. The former, 250 miles long, and navigable by
                    rafts and light boats for 50 miles from its mouth, flows north and north-east
                    with numerous (about 100) rapids and shallows, in a wild valley suitable only
                    for fishing or hunting settlements, and enters the Sea of Okhotsk at the Bay of
                    Nyi. The Poronai flows north and then south to the Gulf of Patience, a wide bay
                    on the south-east coast. Three other small streams enter the wide semicircular
                    Gulf of Aniva at the southern extremity of the island.</p>
                <p>Owing to the cooling influence of the Sea of Okhotsk, the climate is very cold.
                    At Dui the average yearly temperature is only 33°·0 Fahr. (January, 3°·4; July,
                    61°·0), 35 <hi rend="superscript"> o·</hi> 0 at Kusunai, and 37°·6 at Aniva
                    (January, 9°·5; July, 60°·2). A dense covering of clouds for the most part shuts
                    out the rays of the sun; while the cold current issuing from the Sea of Okhotsk,
                    aided by north-east winds, in summer brings immense ice-floes to the east coast.
                    The whole of the island is covered with dense forests (mostly coniferous). The
                    Ayan fir <hi rend="italic">(Abies ayanensis),</hi> the Saghalin pichta, and the
                    Daurian larch are the chief trees; and the upper parts of the mountains have the
                    Siberian rampant cedar <hi rend="italic">(Cembra pumila)</hi> and the Curilian
                    bamboo <hi rend="italic">(Arundinaria kurilense),</hi> 4 feet high and half an
                    inch thick. Birch, both European and Kamchatkan <hi rend="italic">(B. alba</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">B. Ermani),</hi> elder, poplar, elm, wild cherry <hi
                    rend="italic">(Prunus padus), Taxus baceata,</hi> and several willows are mixed
                    with the Conifers; while farther south the maple, the ash, and the oak, as also
                    the Japanese <hi rend="italic">Panax ricinifolium</hi> and the Amur cork <hi
                    rend="italic">(Philodendron amurense),</hi> make their appearance. The number of
                    phanerogamous species known reaches 590 and may reach 700, of which only 20 are
                    peculiar to Saghalin, the remainder belonging to the Amur and partly to the
                    Japanese flora. The fauna of Saghalin closely resembles that of the Amur region,
                    and in fact the Siberian. Bears, foxes, and sables are still numerous, as also
                    the reindeer in the north and the antelope; and tigers are occasionally met with
                    in the south. The avifauna is the common Siberian; and the rivers are
                    exceedingly rich in fish, especially species of salmon <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Oncorhynchus),</hi> which make their way up the rivers in vast numbers to
                    spawn. The lower marine fauna, explored by Schrenck, is also rich, while
                    numerous whales, not in high esteem with whalers, are met with on the sea-coast.
                    Otarias, seals, and dolphins are a source of profit.</p>
                <p>Saghalin has been inhabited since at least the Neolithic Stone Age. Flint
                    implements, exactly like those of Siberia and Russia, have been found at Dui and
                    Kusunai in great numbers, as well as polished hatchets (of trap, diorite, and
                    argillaceous schists)—also like the European ones—primitive pottery with
                    decorations like those of Olonetz, and stone weights for nets. Afterwards came a
                    population to whom bronze was known; they have left their traces in earthen
                    walls and kitchen-middens (in the Bay of Aniva). The present inhabitants consist
                    of some 2000 Gilyaks, 2500 Ainos, 500 Oroks, as many Japanese, and about 6000
                    Russians. The Gilyaks, who do not differ from those of the Amur, inhabit the
                    northern part of the island. They support themselves by fishing and partly by
                    hunting, but suffer from competition with the Japanese, who take possession of
                    the best fishing-grounds. The Oroks, of Tungus origin, resemble the Orotchons of
                    the Amur; they live by hunting. The Ainos, who are still the subject of so much
                    discussion among ethnologists, are the aborigines of the island; they are
                    closely akin to the Curilians, and, like these, differ from all other Mongolian
                    races by their luxuriance of hair and beard. They now inhabit only the south
                    part of the island, and have been brought into a condition of slavery by the
                    Japanese, by whom they have been driven out of Yezo and Nippon, in both of which
                    they were the aborigines. The Japanese have several colonies on Saghalin and
                    force the Ainos to fish and to collect seaweed for exportation. They send their
                    ships to the south part of the island and have colonies there, and also on the
                    east coast, at the mouth of the Tym. The Russians began to settle permanently on
                    Saghalin in 1857; and, though next year posts were established in the southern
                    part of the island, it still continued to belong to Japan, which definitely
                    ceded it to Russia in 1875. A scheme having been lately formed for colonizing
                    the island with convicts, several thousands have been transported thither,
                    especially to Dui (Alexandrovsk), where they are employed in coal-mining (annual
                    output from 3000 to 30,000 cwts.), or make some attempt at agriculture; they are
                    either kept in the Alexandrovsk prison, or permitted to build houses and to
                    settle with their families. These efforts towards colonization, however,
                    encounter great difficulties from the quality of the soil, the cultivable
                    patches occurring here and there in the marshy valley of the Duika river, on the
                    upper course of the Tym, and in the bays of Patience and Aniva. The only crops
                    that thrive are various kinds of kitchen produce. The Russian settlements are at
                    Dui on the west coast, Malo-Tymovsk and Rykovsk on the upper Tym, Korsakoff and
                    Muravieff on the Bay of Aniva.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">History.—</hi> Saghalin, which was under Chinese dominion until
                    the present century, became known to Europeans from the travels of Martin
                    Gerrits in the 17th century, and still better from those of La Pérouse (1787)
                    and Krusenstern (1805), who described large parts of its coasts. Both, however,
                    regarded it as a mere appendage of the continent, and were unaware of the
                    existence of the Strait of<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n165/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0165-0148"/> Tartary, which was discovered a few years later
                    by a Japanese, Mamia Rinso, whose discovery is embodied in Siebold’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Nippon.</hi> The Russian navigator Nevelskoi, in 1849,
                    definitively established the existence and navigability of this strait; since
                    that time the Russian expeditious of Boshnyak (1851) and Rimskiy-Korsakoff
                    (1853) continued the explorations, and in the latter year a Russian post was
                    temporarily established at Aniva Bay. L. Schrenck in 1855-56, and MM. Schmidt,
                    Glehn, Brvlkin, and Shebunin in 1860, explored the geology, fauna, flora, and
                    ethnology of the island; M. Lopatin in 1867 explored, on foot, the cast coast;
                    MM. Dobrotvorsky published (1869 and onwards) interesting data as to the
                    inhabitants, and M. Polyakoff was entrusted in 1881-82 with a detailed
                    exploration, and returned with rich ethnological and zoological collections,
                    with regard to which only preliminary reports have as yet been published. (P. A.
                    K.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
