<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0380-0359-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SAXONY, Prussian</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 21, page 359</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1080735">Prussians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1150508">Thuringians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1137272">Sugar</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1104215">Salt</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1137549">Sugars</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:850620">Cent</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1104337">Salts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b43b5w92m">Salts</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zn7v">Sugar</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b43x83n13">Sugars</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b47h1dq72">Salt</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g03">Cent</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n380/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SAXONY, <hi rend="smallcaps">Prussian</hi></label> (Germ. <hi
                    rend="italic">Provinz Sachsen),</hi> one of the central provinces of the kingdom
                    of Prussia, consists mainly of what was formerly the northern part of the
                    kingdom of Saxony (ceded to Prussia in 1815), but also comprises the duchy of
                    Magdeburg, the Altmark, and other districts, the connexion of which with Prussia
                    is of earlier date. The area of the province is 9750 square miles. On the W. it
                    is bounded by Hesse-Nassau, Hanover, and Brunswick, on the N. by Hanover and
                    Brandenburg, on the E. by Brandenburg and Silesia, and on the S. by the kingdom
                    of Saxony and the small Thuringian states. It is, however, very irregular in
                    form, entirely surrounding parts of Brunswick and the Thuringian states, and
                    itself possessing several “exclaves,” while the northern portion of the province
                    is almost entirely severed from the southern by the duchy of Anhalt. The major
                    part of the province is flat and belongs to the great North-German plain, but
                    the western and south-western districts are hilly, including parts of the Harz
                    (with the Brocken, 3417 feet) and the Thuringian Forest. About nine-tenths of
                    Prussian Saxony belongs to the system of the Elbe, the chief feeders of which
                    within the province are the Saale and the Mulde, but a small district on the
                    west drains into the Weser. The saltwater lakes between Halle and Eisleben are
                    the only lakes of the kind in Prussia.</p>
                <p>Saxony is on the whole the most fertile province of Prussia, and excels all the
                    others in its produce of wheat and beetroot sugar (as well as in salt, brown
                    coal, and copper), but the nature of its soil is very unequal. The best
                    crop-producing districts lie near the base of the Harz Mountains, such as the
                    “Magdeburger Börde” and the “Goldene Aue,” and rich pasture lands occur in the
                    river valleys, but the sandy plains of the Altmark, in the north part of the
                    province, yield but a scanty return for the husbandman’s toil.</p>
                <p>Of the total area of the province 61 per cent. is occupied by arable land, 13 per
                    cent. by meadows and pastures, and 20·5 per cent. by forests. Wheat and rye are
                    raised in such abundance as to allow of a considerable export, while the other
                    grain crops meet the local demand. The beetroot for sugar is grown chiefly in
                    the district to the north of the Harz, as far as the obre, and on the banks of
                    the Saale; and the amount of sugar produced (upwards of 400,000 tons in 1883-84)
                    is nearly as much as that of all the rest of Prussia together. Flax, hops, and
                    seeds for oil are also cultivated to some extent, and large quantities of
                    excellent fruit are grown at the foot of the Harz and in the valleys of the
                    Unstrut and the Saale. The market-gardening of Erfurt is well-known throughout
                    Germany. Wine, of indifferent quality, is produced in the vicinity of Naumburg.
                    Saxony is comparatively poor in timber, though there are some fine forests in
                    the Harz and other hilly districts. Cattle-rearing is carried on with success in
                    the river valleys, and more goats are met with here than in any other part of
                    Prussia. The live-stock census for 1883 gave the following figures :—horses,
                    182,485; cattle, 624,973; sheep, 1,390,915; pigs, 719,627; goats, 261,225.
                    (Compare the tables under <hi rend="smallcaps">Prussia,</hi> vol. xx. p.
                    14.)</p>
                <p>The principal underground wealth of Prussian Saxony consists of its salt and its
                    brown coal, of both of which it possesses larger stores than any other part of
                    the German empire. The rock-salt mines and brine springs (the chief of which are
                    at Stassfurt, Schönebeck, Halle, &amp;c.) produced in 1883-4 no less than
                    256,000 tons of salt, while the annual output of brown coal amounts to about 8
                    million tons, or more than the entire yield of the rest of Germany. Prussian
                    Saxony also possesses three-fourths of the wealth of Germany in copper, the
                    yield in 1883 amounting to 445,000 tons of ore and 11,000 tons of the pure
                    metal. The copper mines are found chiefly in the Harz district.. The other
                    mineral resources include silver (one-third of the total German yield),
                    pit-coal, pyrites, alum, plaster of Paris, sulphur, alabaster, and several
                    varieties of good building-stone. Numerous mineral springs occur in the
                    Harz.</p>
                <p>In addition to the production of sugar already noted, the most important
                    industries are the manufactures of cloth, leather, iron and steel wares (chiefly
                    at Suhl and Sömmerda), spirits (Nord<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n381/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0381-0360"/> hausen), chemicals (Stassfurt), and starch. Beer
                    is also brewed extensively in Prussian Saxony, where the annual consumption per
                    head (107 quarts) is considerably in excess of the average for the kingdom.
                    Trade is much facilitated by the great waterway of the Elbe, as well as by a
                    very complete system of railways. The chief articles are wool, grain, sugar,
                    salt, lignite, and the principal manufactured products named above.</p>
                <p>The population of the province of Saxony in 1880 was 2,312,007, including
                    2,154,663 Protestants, 145,518 Roman Catholics, and 6700 Jews; in 1885,
                    according to provisional census returns, the population was 2,427,968. The great
                    bulk of the inhabitants are of unmixed German stock, but many of those in the
                    east part of the province have Wendish blood in their veins. The province
                    belongs to the more thickly populated parts of Germany, the average being 237
                    persons to the square mile, and the ratio of the urban population to the rural
                    is about as 4½ to 5½. The occupation census of 1882 gives the following
                    percentages for the different classes of the population :—agricultural, 36 78;
                    industrial, 3578; trade, 875; domestic servants and day labourers, 8 70;
                    official and professional, 572.</p>
                <p>Prussian Saxony is divided into the three government districts of Magdeburg,
                    Merseburg, and Erfurt. Magdeburg is the most important town and the headquarters
                    of an army corps, but the provincial chambers meet at Merseburg. The province
                    sends twenty members to the reichstag and thirty-eight to the Prussian house of
                    representatives. The religious control of the district is in the hands of a
                    consistory at Magdeburg; the Roman Catholics belong to the diocese of Paderborn.
                    The university of Halle holds a high rank among German seats of learning, and
                    the other educational requirements of the province are adequately provided for.
                    The illiterate recruits of this province in 1883-4 numbered only 13 out of a
                    total of 7868, equivalent to 077 per cent. The principal towns are Magdeburg
                    (about 150,000 inhabitants, including Neustadt and Buckau), Halle (81,869),
                    Erfurt (58,307), Halberstadt (34,048), Nordhausen, Mühlhausen, and
                    Aschersleben.</p>
                <p>The history of the present Prussian province of Saxony as such dates only from
                    1815, and is, of course, merely of local interest. The previous history of its
                    constituent parts, of considerable more interest and importance, must be sought
                    for under the various headings that will suggest themselves, such as <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Saxony</hi><hi rend="italic">(supra),</hi><hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Prussia, Magdeburg, Erfurt,</hi> &amp;c. It is, however, worth noting that the
                    province comprises the Altmark or old North Mark that formed the kernel of the
                    Prussian state (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Prussia,</hi> vol. xx. p. 2), and also
                    the old bishoprics on the Elbe and Saale, from which as a centre the
                    Christianization of Germany mainly spread. And the leading position of this part
                    of Germany in promoting the Reformation should also be remembered.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
