<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0603-0578-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SEA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 21, page 578</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="17" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:829042">Bays</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:795379">Accounting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1211700">Mexico</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n603/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SEA</label>. Any part of the ocean marked off from the
                    general mass of water may be called a sea. In geography the name is loosely
                    applied: for instance, the Arabian Sea is an open bay, Hudson’s Bay is an
                    enclosed sea. Seas proper lie within the transitional area which divides the
                    permanent continental masses from the permanent ocean basins, and their
                    boundaries are consequently subject to geological change, and to alteration by
                    subsidence and elevation occurring in historic times.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Inland Seas</hi> are seas entirely surrounded by land (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Caspian Sea, Dead Sea,</hi> and, for general discussion, <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Lake).</hi><hi rend="italic">Enclosed Seas</hi> have
                    communication with the ocean restricted to one opening, which may take the form
                    of one, two, or more straits close to each other. The best known are the White
                    Sea of the Arctic Ocean; the Baltic, Zuyder Zee, Hudson’s Bay, Gulf of Mexico,
                    and Mediterranean, with the Adriatic and Black Sea, of the Atlantic; the Red Sea
                    and Persian Gulf of the Indian Ocean; and the Yellow Sea and Sea of Okhotsk of
                    the Pacific.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The
                    prevalence of colour names for these seas is noteworthy.</p></note> They are all
                    cut off from general oceanic circulation and very largely from tides, but the
                    result is not stagnation. The Baltic and Black Sea are but slightly saline on
                    account of the number of large rivers falling into them, and the fresh
                    surface-water flows out as a regular current, liable indeed to be checked, and
                    even reversed for a time, but in the main persistent; while the salt water flows
                    in uniformly as an undercurrent. A state of equilibrium is arrived at, so that
                    periodical fluctuations of salinity do not affect the average of a number of
                    years. The water of the Mediterranean and Red Sea is much salter than that of
                    the ocean, which therefore flows in as a surface-current, while the dense very
                    salt water escapes below. In the case of the Baltic and Black Sea dilution by
                    rivers, in that of the Mediterranean and Red Sea concentration by evaporation
                    maintains a circu-<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n604/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0604-0579"/> lation. Winds and differences of barometric
                    pressure are, as in inland seas, great factors in producing variable currents.
                    (See <hi rend="smallcaps">Baltic Sea, Black Sea, Mediterranean Sea, Red Sea,
                    &amp;c.)</hi><hi rend="italic">Partially Enclosed Seas</hi> may be (<hi
                    rend="italic">a</hi>) comparatively shallow irregular channels through which
                    strong tides sweep, or (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) ocean basins cut off by
                    barriers barely rising to the surface, or remaining permanently submerged, in
                    which case there may be no break of continuity in the ocean surface to indicate
                    the sea. Seas of the first description are related to shallow enclosed seas, but
                    are much affected by tides and ocean currents; the principal are the Kara Sea of
                    the Arctic Ocean, Baffin Bay and North Sea of the Atlantic, Behring Sea and
                    Japan Sea of the Pacific. They are subject to considerable temperature changes
                    owing to their proximity to land. Seas coming under the second category combine
                    the peculiarities of the open ocean and of deep inland seas. The Caribbean Sea
                    of the Atlantic, the China Sea, Java Sea, and numerous small seas of the eastern
                    archipelago of the Pacific are the best examples. Their chief peculiarity is
                    that the temperature of the water instead of falling uniformly to the bottom
                    becomes stationary at some intermediate position corresponding to the top of the
                    barrier. They are usually very deep. (See <hi rend="smallcaps">North Sea,
                    Norwegian Sea,</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Pacific Ocean.)</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Other Seas.—</hi> Coral Sea, Arabian Sea, Sea of Bengal, are
                    names, now dropping out of use, to designate parts of the ocean. “Sargasso Sea”
                    is an expression devoid of geographical meaning (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Atlantic Ocean,</hi> vol. iii. p. 20).</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Firths and Estuaries.—</hi> A river entering the sea by a short
                    estuary flows over the surface, freshening it to a considerable extent, and, if
                    the force of its current is not too great, the rising tide slowly forces a wedge
                    of sea water up between river and river bed, withdrawing it rapidly when ebb
                    sets in. In a firth that is large compared with the river falling into it,
                    judging from results recently obtained in the Firth of Forth,<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Mill, <hi rend="italic">Proc.
                    Roy. Soc. Ed.,</hi> xiii. 29, 137, and 347.</p></note> a state of equilibrium is
                    arrived at, the water increasing in salinity more and more gradually as it
                    proceeds seawards, the disturbing influence of the tide becoming less and less,
                    and the vertical distribution of salinity more and more uniform until the river
                    water meets the sea, diffused through a nearly homogeneous mass with a density
                    little inferior to that of the ocean. Between the extreme cases there are
                    numerous gradations of estuary depending on the ratio of river to sea inlet.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Deposits.—</hi> All seas within about 300 miles of continental
                    land, whatever may be their depth, are paved with terrigenous débris, and all at
                    a greater distance from shore are carpeted with true pelagic deposits (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Pacific Ocean).</hi><hi rend="italic">Marine Fauna and
                    Flora.—</hi> The mixing of river with sea water produces a marked difference in
                    the fauna and flora of seas. Where low salinity prevails diatoms abound,
                    probably on account of the greater amount of silica dissolved in river water,
                    and they form food for minute pelagic animals and larvae, which are in turn
                    preyed upon by larger creatures. In some seas, such as the North Sea, there are
                    many celebrated fishing beds on the shallow banks of which innumerable
                    invertebrate animals live and form an inexhaustible food-supply for edible
                    fishes. Naturalists have remarked that in temperate seas enormous shoals of
                    relatively few species are met with, while in tropical seas species are very
                    numerous and individuals comparatively few. Organisms, such as the corals, which
                    secrete carbonate of lime appear to flourish more luxuriantly in warmer and
                    salter seas than in those which are colder and fresher.</p>
                <p>The geological and dynamic aspects of seas are treated of in <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Geology</hi> (vol. x. p. 284 <hi rend="italic">sq.)</hi> and <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Geography (Physical);</hi> and in <hi rend="smallcaps">Atlantic
                    Ocean, Baltic Sea, Black Sea, Indian</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Ocean,
                    Mediterranean Sea, North Sea, Norwegian Sea, Pacific Ocean, Polar Regions,</hi>
                    and <hi rend="smallcaps">Red Sea</hi> the general geographical and physical
                    characters of oceans and seas are described. In <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Meteorology</hi> some account is given of the influence of the sea on climate,
                    and chemical problems connected with the ocean are discussed in <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Sea Water.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
