<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0663-0638-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SELKIRK</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 21, page 638</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:999328">Lions</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1734554">Lion</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1057037">Pens</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1199090">Yarrow</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:932562">Foresters</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1098312">Rivers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4t14tp94">Oats</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t32v">Lion</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zm3g">Pens</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ww7759r">Moors</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b47p8tc5z">Abbeys</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n663/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SELKIRK</label>, a lowland county of Scotland, of tortuous
                    outline, is bounded by Midlothian on the N., by Peebles on the N. and W., by
                    Dumfries on the S., and by Roxburgh on the E. Its extreme length from south-west
                    to northeast is 28 miles, its greatest breadth from east to west 17, and its
                    total area 260 square miles or 166,524 acres, of which 1997 are water. This
                    includes two detached portions, one to the north-west, surrounded by Peebles,
                    and another on the east, the estate and barony of Sinton, separated from
                    Roxburgh in the reign of William the Lion on the appointment of Andrew de Synton
                    to the sheriffship of Selkirk. From its lowest altitude (300 feet) at the
                    junction of the Gala and the Tweed the surface rises to 2433 feet at Dun Rig, a
                    wild and desolate summit on the western boundary. Level haughs, beds of ancient
                    lakes, occur in the courses of the rivers; but the county is otherwise wholly
                    mountainous and only a small proportion of it arable. Of its principal summits,
                    Ettrick Pen (2269), Capel Fell (2223), Deer Law (2064), Herman Law (2014), are
                    in the south, and Windlestrae Law (2161) in the north, about a mile from the
                    borders of Midlothian. Broadly speaking, Selkirk may be said to consist of the
                    two entire valleys of Ettrick and Yarrow and a section of the valley of Tweed,
                    the first two sloping from the south until they merge in the last, which forms
                    the northern portion of the county. Besides St Mary’s Loch and its adjunct the
                    Loch of the Lowes, together about 4 1/2 miles long, there are several others of
                    considerable size, mostly in the eastern uplands between Ettrick and
                    Teviotdale—the two lochs of Shaws, Clearburn Loch, Kingside Loch, Hellmuir Loch,
                    Alemuir Loch, and Akermuir Loch. These, with the larger rivers and the mountain
                    “burns,” attract anglers to Selkirk from all parts of the kingdom.</p>
                <p>Geologically, the Selkirk rocks are a portion of that great Silurian mass which
                    occupies the south of Scotland from Wigtown to the north-east coast of Berwick.
                    At no part are they known to be covered by rocks of later formation; but here
                    and there (at Windlestrae Law and Priest-hope, for example) igneous rocks
                    protrude in massive outcrops, almost granitic, one measuring over 100 feet in
                    thickness. The hillsides yield inexhaustible supplies of blue-grey whinstone,
                    suitable for building; but repeated efforts to establish slate-quarries and
                    lead-mines have ended in failure. According to records of the 16 th century,
                    gold was found at Mount Benger, Douglas Craig, and Linglie Burn,—“an ingenious
                    gentleman” named Bevis Bulmer having been “most successful upon Henderland Moor
                    in Ettrick Forest, where he got the greatest gold—the like to it in no other
                    place before of Scotland.”</p>
                <p>Corresponding with the high average altitude, the prevailing climate is cold and
                    wet, and, as the soil is mostly thin, over a close subsoil of clayey “till,”
                    agriculture is carried on at a disadvantage. About the middle of the 19th
                    century large areas of virgin soil were brought under tillage; but the prudence
                    of the “improvement” is now greatly doubted, in regard to a large proportion at
                    least, —its restoration to permanent pasture being now found almost
                    impracticable.</p>
                <p>In 1884 23,263 acres, or nearly a seventh of the whole, were under cultivation
                    and 3228 under wood. The rotation of crops most commonly followed is a
                    six-course shift of (1) turnips, (2) barley or oats, (3), (4), (5) grass or
                    pasture, and (6) oats. Horses in 1884 numbered 580, cattle 2657, sheep 165,061;
                    Till about a century ago the upper farms of the county were stocked exclusively
                    with sheep of the blackfaced breed, and in high heathery tracts these still
                    predominate. But as altitude diminishes sheep improve in quality, from pure
                    Cheviot to half-bred and three-quarters-bred Leicester-Cheviot Upwards of 60,000
                    acres, more than a third of the county, belong to the duke of Buccleuch, whose
                    title is derived from an ancient possession of his family in the vale of
                    Rankleburn. Other principal landowners are Mr Maxwell-Stuart of Traquair (9765
                    acres) and Lord Napier and Ettrick (6988 acres).</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Manufactures.—</hi> So early as the beginning of the 17th
                    century the village of Galashiels did a considerable local trade in woollen
                    cloth, then or shortly afterwards known as “Galashiels grey,” and towards the
                    end of the 18th century this industry was greatly stimulated by judicious grants
                    from “the equivalent” paid by England at the Union. About the end of the first
                    quarter of the 19th century a few novelties in pattern (mostly accidental) led
                    to the opening up of what has now become a vast industry—the Tweed trade, which
                    still has its acknowledged centre in Selkirk.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Administration and Population.—</hi> Selkirkshire with
                    Peeblesshire forms one parliamentary constituency. Of entire civil parishes it
                    contains only two, with parts of nine others; there are also, taken from these,
                    three <hi rend="italic">quoad sacra</hi> parishes and part of a fourth. The
                    population, 4937 in 1755 and 9809 in 1851, was in 1881 returned at 25,564,—an
                    increase partly due to the annexation of a portion of Galashiels formerly
                    reckoned in Roxburgh. Outside the two towns of Galashiels (population 9140 in
                    1881) and Selkirk population has been almost stationary for more than a century,
                    that of the landward parishes in 1755 and 1881 being respectively as follows
                    :—Ashkirk, 200 and 138; Innerleithen, 60 and 61; Ettrick, 397 and 397; Stow, 260
                    and 441; Yarrow, 1180 and 611; Roberton, 250 and 250.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Antiquities and History.—</hi> The shire is not rich in
                    antiquities, although its hillsides here and there reveal earthen enclosures
                    known as “British camps,” as well as tumuli yielding human remains and the usual
                    fragments of rude pottery. A mysterious ditch, known as “the Catrail,” beginning
                    at the north end of the county, traverses its entire extent before entering
                    Roxburgh on its way to the English border. Besides smaller redoubts, there is on
                    its line, at Rink in Galashiels parish, a well-preserved circular fort of
                    formidable strength and dimensions. Near Minchmoor the Catrail is crossed by
                    “Wallace's trench.” where, according to an historical document recently
                    published, the Scottish patriot defied for a while the generals of Edward I.
                    Close by is the hill-track by which Montrose escaped from the disastrous field
                    of Philiphaugh in 1645. Newark Castle, built by James II., still stands in fair
                    preservation, notable enough historically, but more familiar as the recital-hall
                    of the “last minstrel’s” immortal lay. The county is dotted over with other
                    towers of smaller size, in various stages of decay. Around them cluster those
                    traditions which, sung in ballads full of simple force and tenderness, have made
                    Selkirk the poet’s chosen haunt. Yarrow, “garlanded with rhyme,” has, without
                    hyperbole, been termed “the Tempe of the West.” Selkirk was long known
                    officially as the “shire of the Forest,” an appellation its famous sheriff Sir
                    Walter Scott loved to recall. Except the burgh of Selkirk, its lands, and a
                    large tract in upper Ettrick belonging to Melrose Abbey, the county remained
                    long under the jurisdiction of a forest court, and its forest-steadings were
                    held by tack from the crown till the time of Queen Mary. It was a favourite
                    hunting-ground of Scottish monarchs and formed the dowry-land of at least two
                    foreign princesses who became queens of Scotland. See T. Craig-Brown, <hi
                    rend="italic">Hist. of Selkirkshire.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
