<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0486-0465-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SCIO</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 21, page 465</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1116352">Shipping</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1116439">Ships</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1175881">Wine</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:978609">Ionians</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1159574">Turks</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:965486">Hymns</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4707wx1r">Ships</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n5c">Shipping</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4qb9vd72">Scythians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49k45v4z">Hymns</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xp6v99v">Pelasgi</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n486/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SCIO</label>, the Italian name of an island on the west coast
                    of Asia Minor, called by the Greeks Chios <hi rend="italic">(η Χίος,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> ,</hi><hi rend="italic">ς τη</hi> Xto) and by the
                    Turks Saki Adasi; the soft pronunciation of χ before ι in Modern Greek,
                    approximating to <hi rend="italic">sk,</hi> caused Xto to be Italianized as
                    Scio. Scio, which is about 30 miles long from north to south, and varies in
                    breadth from 8 to 15 miles, is divided into a larger northern part and a smaller
                    southern part, called respectively <hi rend="italic">apanomeria,</hi><pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n487/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0487-0466"/> and <hi rend="italic">katomeria.</hi> The island
                    is rugged and well deserves the epithet “craggy” (πrαt7rαλocσσα) applied to it
                    in the Homeric hymn. The southern part is less rocky than the northern, and the
                    wealth of the island is concentrated there. The figs of Chios were noted in
                    ancient times, but wine and gum mastic have always been its most important
                    products. The climate is almost perfect, the atmosphere delightful and healthy;
                    oranges, olives, and even palms grow freely. The finest wine was grown on the
                    northwestern coast, in the district called by Strabo Ariusia, and was known in
                    Italy as <hi rend="italic">vinum Arvisium.</hi> The population of Chios has
                    always been far greater than its resources could feed; the people have therefore
                    been forced to import the necessaries of life in exchange for their wine and
                    mastic and fruit, and alike in ancient and modern times they have been known as
                    merchants and traders. Pottery of Chios and Thasos was exported to Illyria
                    (Strab., p. 317) and doubtless elsewhere; it formed or contained the cargo of
                    outward-bound trading ships. Thasian ware is familiar in museums, where the
                    stamped handles of Thasian amphorae have been collected in thousands; but no
                    pottery has yet been identified as of Chian manufacture. An incidental proof of
                    the importance of Chian handicrafts lies in the fact that early in the 7th
                    century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> Glaucus of Chios discovered the process
                    of soldering iron, and the iron stand of a large crater whose parts were all
                    connected by this process was constructed by him, and preserved as one of the
                    most interesting relics of antiquity at Delphi. The long line of Chian sculptors
                    in marble, Bupalus and Athenis, sons of Archermus, son of Micciades, son of
                    Melas, bears witness to the fame of Chian art in the period 660 to 540 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> The Winged Victory of Micciades and Archermus, which
                    was dedicated at Delos, is still preserved,—the most important attested work
                    extant of archaic Greek art. Marble quarries also were worked in the island. In
                    literature the chief glory of Chios was the school of epic poets called
                    Homeridae, who carried on and gave an Ionic tone to the traditional art of the
                    older Aeolic bards. Cinaethus is said to have written the Homeric <hi
                    rend="italic">Hymn to Apollo of Delos,</hi> and is believed by some modern
                    critics to have exercised great influence on the text of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Iliad</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Odyssey.</hi> The Chian recension of these
                    poems (Χία "Eκδoσts) was in later times one of the standard texts. Ion the
                    tragic poet, Theopompus the historian, and other writers maintained the position
                    of Chios in literature during the classical period.</p>
                <p>The chief city of Chios has always borne the same name as the island. It is
                    situated near the middle of the eastern coast, and at the present day contains
                    about 17,000 inhabitants. A theatre and a temple of Athena Poliuchus existed in
                    the ancient city. About 6 miles north of the city there is a curious monument of
                    antiquity, commonly called “the school of Homer”; it is a very ancient sanctuary
                    of Cybele, with an altar and a figure of the goddess with her two lions, cut out
                    of the native rock on the summit of a hill. On the west coast there is a
                    monastery of great wealth with a church founded by Constantine IX. (1042-54).
                    Starting from the city and encompassing the island, one passes in succession the
                    promontory Posidium; Cape Phanae, the southern extremity of Chios, with a
                    harbour and a temple of Apollo; Notium, probably the south-western point of the
                    island; Laii, opposite the city of Chios, where the island is narrowest; the
                    town Bolissus (now Volisso), the home of the Homerid poets; Melaena, the
                    north-western point; the wine-growing district Ariusia; Cardamyle (now
                    Cardhamili); the north-eastern promontory was probably named Phlium, and the
                    mountains that cross the northern part of the island Pelinaeus or Pellenaeus.
                    The situation of the small towns Leuconium, Delphinium, Caucasa, Coela, and
                    Polichne is uncertain; probably most of them were in the southern part. The
                    island is subject to earthquakes; a very destructive shock occurred in March
                    1881.</p>
                <p>The history of Chios is very obscure. According to Pherecydes, the original
                    inhabitants were Leleges, while according to other accounts Thessalian Pelasgi
                    possessed the island before it became an Ionian state. The name Aethalia, common
                    to Chios and Lemnos in very early time, suggests the original existence of a
                    homogeneous population in these anil other neighbouring islands. (Enopium, a
                    mythical hero, son of Dionysus or of Rhadamanthus, was an early king of Chios.
                    His successor in the fourth generation, Hector, united the island to the Ionian
                    confederacy (Pausan., vii. 4), though Strabo (p. 633) implies an actual conquest
                    by Ionian settlers. The name Hector and the fountain Helene (probably at the
                    modern Thelena in the north) might be expected in the island of the Homeridae.
                    The regal government was at a later time exchanged for an oligarchy or a
                    democracy, but nothing is known as to the manner and date of the change. As in
                    most other states of Greece, tyrants sometimes ruled in Chios; the names of
                    Amphiclus and Polytecnus are mentioned. The early relations of Chios with other
                    states are very obscure, but it seems to have been an ally of Miletus, and to
                    have been at enmity with the Phocaeo-Samian alliance, to which the neighbouring
                    Erythrø belonged. The same form of the Ionian dialect was spoken in Chios and in
                    Erythrae.</p>
                <p>When the Persians appeared on the Ionian coast Chios willingly submitted, refused
                    to their old enemies the Phocaeans, who were fleeing from the Persian yoke, a
                    refuge on their islands Oenussae, and even surrendered the Lydian fugitive
                    Pactyes in defiance of all religious scruples. Strattis, tyrant of Chios,
                    followed Darius in his Scythian expedition. The Chians joined in the Ionian
                    rebellion against the Persians (500-495) and supplied 100 ships. After the
                    Persian victory at Lade the island was most severely treated, the towns and
                    temples burned, and many of the people enslaved. At Salamis (480) the Chian
                    ships, led by the tyrant Strattis, served in the Persian fleet. After the battle
                    of Mycale (479) the island became free and a democratic government no doubt took
                    the place of the tyranny. Chios was the most powerful state after Athens in the
                    Delian confederacy, and it was an ally on equal terms of the Athenian empire,
                    paying no tribute, but furnishing ships in case of war. It remained a faithful
                    ally of the Athenians till the year 412, when, encouraged by the weakness caused
                    in Athens by the Sicilian disasters, it joined the Lacedaemonians. Its fleet
                    then consisted of fifty ships. The Athenians defeated them in three battles, at
                    Bolissus, Phanae, and Leuconium, but could not reconquer the island. Finding the
                    Spartan hegemony more oppressive than the Athenian, Chios returned to the
                    Athenian connexion in 394, but soon afterwards deserted and joined the Thebans.
                    In the wars of Alexander the Great, Memnon, supported by the oligarchical party,
                    held the island for the Persians. It was afterwards involved in the rapid
                    vicissitudes of Ionian history, falling under the power of various dynasties
                    among the <hi rend="italic">diadochi.</hi> In the Mithradatic wars it favoured
                    the Roman alliance, and the king’s general Zenobius fined the island 2000
                    talents and carried off a great number of the population into slavery in Pontus.
                    It had many centuries of peaceful prosperity under Roman and Byzantine rule. The
                    Genoese held it from the 14th century till in 1566 the Turks conquered it and
                    the third great Chian disaster and massacre occurred. Except for a brief
                    Venetian occupation in 1694, Chios has remained in Turkish hands till the
                    present day. A fourth massacre afflicted the island in 1822, when the Turks
                    repressed with fire and sword the attempted Greek insurrection. Till this
                    terrible event the island was ruled very leniently by the Turks; the internal
                    government was left in the hands of five archons, three Greek and two Catholic,
                    while two resident Turkish officials represented the sultan and received through
                    the archons the stipulated tribute. (W. M. RA. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
