<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0165-0148-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SAGITTA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 21, page 148</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4bz6186h">Cells</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g08p">Groups</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4vq2s959">Annelida</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:850250">Cells</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:952579">Head</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1103449">Sagitta</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:851703">Chaetognatha</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1170190">Walls</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n165/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SAGITTA</label>. The name “Sagitta” was given by Martin
                    Slabber in 1775 to a small marine worm which is now known as the type of a
                    distinct group, the <hi rend="italic">Chaetognatha</hi> (Leuckart). The group
                    comprises two genera <hi rend="italic">(Sagitta</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Spodella)</hi> and a considerable number of species; they are small transparent
                    pelagic animals, varying in length from a few lines up to two inches, and are
                    universally distributed. The body (see fig.) is elongated and furnished with a
                    tail and lateral fins, which are prolongations of the chitinous cuticle; the
                    head is provided with a great number of variously shaped chitinous setae. The
                    body is divided by transverse septa into three distinct segments: the first
                    septum is placed just behind the head <hi rend="italic">(st),</hi> the second
                    (<hi rend="italic">st)</hi> about the middle of the body, separating the ovaries
                    and testes. The body-cavity is likewise separated into right and left halves by
                    a continuous vertical mesentery, 'which suspends the gut. The alimentary canal
                    is a simple straight tube of uniform structure passing from the mouth to the
                    anus, which is placed ventrally and at the second transverse septum; the
                    alimentary tube is ciliated and is unprovided with glands of any kind. The
                    body-wall is composed of (1) an outer layer of epidermis, which secretes the
                    chitinous cuticle already referred to,—the thickness of the epidermis varying
                    from five or six cells in the region of the head to a single layer of cells in
                    the “fins ”; (2) a delicate structureless supporting lamella; (3) a layer of
                    longitudinal muscles. These last have a peculiar arrangement and structure: they
                    are disposed in four bands, two dorsal and two ventral, the action of which is
                    evidently favourable to producing the onward movements of the creature. The
                    muscular fibres, which are transversely striated, are arranged in a series of
                    lamellae whose direction is perpendicular to the longitudinal axis of the body.
                    Projections inward of the supporting lamella bear on either side a single row of
                    muscular fibres; a similar muscular structure occurs in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Nematoidea</hi> and in many <hi rend="italic">Oligoehaeta.</hi> In the anterior
                    region of the body the muscular layer is differentiated into special muscles for
                    the movement of the setae. (4) The body-cavity is lined by a delicate peritoneal
                    epithelium closely applied to the muscular layer of the body-wall and to the
                    gut. The nervous system consists of a cerebral ganglion and a large ventral
                    ganglion—the two united by commissures which pass round the gut; both ganglia
                    are embedded in the epidermis. This primi tive condition of the nervous system
                    is retained in other lowly organized worms (<hi rend="italic">e.g.,
                    Polygordius).</hi> The ventral ganglion is connected with an intra-epidermic
                    nervous plexus which surrounds the whole body. Eyes are present, besides a
                    number of tactile cells upon the outer surface of the body; anteriorly is a
                    ring-shaped structure (<hi rend="italic">r</hi>) which is supposed to be
                    olfactory in function. The generative organs consist of ovaries and testes,
                    which are united in the same individual; the ovaries (<hi rend="italic">e</hi>),
                    placed anterior to the testes, are furnished with oviducts, which appear to
                    terminate in a caecal extremity. The testes (<hi rend="italic">ho)</hi> are
                    placed behind the second septum; they are each furnished with a vas deferens
                    opening on to the exterior and into the body-cavity by a ciliated funnel.</p>
                <p>For embryology, see Balfour, <hi rend="italic">Comparative Embryology,</hi> vol.
                    i. p. 303.</p>
                <p>In spite of the detailed knowledge which we now possess of the structure and
                    development of the <hi rend="italic">Chaetognatha,</hi> the systematic position
                    of the group remains a matter of the greatest uncertainty. That they are an
                    archaic group is shown by their hermaphroditism, by the primitive condition of
                    the nervous system, and by the persistence of the vertical mesentery among other
                    characters; in all these points and in others they agree with such primitive <hi
                    rend="italic">Annelida</hi> as <hi rend="italic">Protodrilus</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Polygordius.</hi> On the other hand, their similarity to the <hi
                    rend="italic">Ncmatoidea</hi> has been dwelt upon; the disposition of the
                    muscles is the same in both groups, and the <hi rend="italic">Gordiacese</hi>
                    have the gut suspended by a dorsal and ventral mesentery in the same fashion as
                    has been described above in <hi rend="italic">Sagitta;</hi> the <hi
                    rend="italic">Chaetognatha</hi> differ, however, from the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Nematoidea</hi> in the important fact of their segmentation. On the whole, it
                    appears that the <hi rend="italic">Chaetognatha</hi> are best regarded as a
                    special phylum equivalent to such groups as <hi rend="italic">Annelida,
                    Platyhelminthcs, Ncmatoidea,</hi> but having no special relation to any one of
                    them.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
