<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0351-0332-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SAVOIE, HAUTE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 21, page 332</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:803903">Aix</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:982026">Jasper</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:990901">Lakes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:979089">Iron</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1002458">Looms</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1179993">Wool</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4736m682">Lakes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zz70">Iron</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43r0pw3g">Looms</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q86t">Chestnut</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43t9dc03">Jasper</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n351/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SAVOIE, HAUTE</label> -, a frontier department of France,
                    formed in 1860 from the old provinces of Genevois, Chablais, and Faucigny, which
                    constituted the northern half of the duchy of Savoy in the kingdom of Sardinia.
                    Situated between 45° 40' and 46° 25' N. lat. and between 5° 50' and 7° 2' E.
                    long., it is bounded N. by the Lake of Geneva, E. by the Valais canton, S.E. by
                    the duchy of Aosta (Italy), S. and S.W. by the department of Savoie, W. by the
                    department of Ain, from which it is separated by the Rhone, and N.W. by the
                    canton of Geneva. Almost everywhere except in the last direction the boundaries
                    are natural. The greater portion of the department is occupied by mountains
                    usually under 8000 feet in height; but it includes Mont Blanc (15,781 feet),
                    while the confluence of the Fier with the Rhone is only 950 feet above the sea.
                    The streams are torrential, and they all join the Rhone either directly or by
                    the Lake of Geneva or the Isère. Most important is the Arve which crosses the
                    department from south-east to north-west from Mont Blanc to Geneva by Chamonix,
                    Sallanches, and Bonneville, receiving from the right the Giffre and from the
                    left the Borne. The Dranse falls into the Lake of Geneva between Evian and
                    Thonon. Direct tributaries of the Rhone are the Usses and the Fier, the outflow
                    of the Lake of Annecy. Passing Mégève, to the south-west of Chamonix, the Arly
                    goes to the Isère. A remarkable variety of climate is produced by the
                    differences of altitude and exposure; it is mildest on the banks of the Lake of
                    Geneva. Annecy has a moderate temperature, lower than that of Paris; bat some
                    parts of the shores of the lake, well sheltered and having a good exposure, form
                    health resorts even in winter. The rainfall on the Lake of Geneva hardly exceeds
                    24 inches; it is three times as heavy in the mountains.</p>
                <p>Of the total area of 1,066,229 acres 345,959 acres are arable, 214,990 woodland,
                    132,206 uncultivated, 95,880 pasturage, 91,432 meadows, 21,252 vineyards. The
                    live stock in 1880 comprised 9774 horses, 93,171 cows or heifers, 11,272 calves,
                    18,769 pigs, 25,331 goats, 33,000 sheep (wool-clip 41 tons), 21,525 hives (104
                    tons of honey, 38 of wax). Cheese is produced to the value of £220,000, and
                    butter to £132,000. The harvest in 1883 included —wheat, 1,472,381 bushels;
                    meslin, 196,510; rye, 190,503. For 1880 the returns were—barley, 136,043
                    bushels; buckwheat, 88,178; maize, 10,928; oats, 793,721; potatoes, 3,730,800;
                    pulse, 42,507; chestnuts, 66,462; besides beetroot, hemp, flax, and colza. In
                    1883 the vintage was 3,221,834 gallons, the average for 1873- 1882 being
                    3,199,570, and cider was produced to the amount of 757,922 gallons (average
                    742,808). Tobacco is successfully grown in a part of the department (Rumilly).
                    Though much of the wood has been cut down, Haute-Savoie still contains fine pine
                    forests below 7200 feet of altitude, and fir, larch, and beech woods below 5000
                    feet, the limit of the elm and ash being 4250, and that of the oak 4000.
                    Splendid walnuts and chestnuts are to be found as high up as 2950 feet and
                    hazels as high as 3600. Argentiferous lead orcs and copper, iron, and manganese
                    ores exist, but are not much worked. About 1000 tons of anthracite and lignite
                    were raised in 1882, and 12,405 tons of asphaltic limestone. Jasper and other
                    beautiful marble, freestone largely used in the buildings of Lyons and Chambéry,
                    limestone, and slates are all quarried. Mineral waters of various kinds abound
                    (Amphion and Evian, chalybeate; St Gervais at the foot of Mont Blanc, hot,
                    sulphurous, and chalybeate; Menthon, sulphurous; La Caille, hot, sulphurous).
                    Cotton manufacture is carried on at Annecy, where one establishment has 20,000
                    spindles, 600 power-looms, and 100 hand-looms, employing<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n352/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0352-0333"/> 500 workers. Some 500,000 or 600,000 yards of
                    silk stuffs are woven throughout the department by some 850 workers; and
                    wool-spinning and wool manufactures are also carried on. In the iron industry
                    1921 tons of cast-iron and 1956 tons of malleable iron were manufactured in
                    1882. Clock-making, taught in two special schools, employs 2000 hands.
                    Tanneries, paper-mills, tile-works, aud flour-mills are numerous. About
                    two-thirds of the cantons have the advantage of belonging to the neutral customs
                    zone—that is, have the right of introducing foreign goods duty free, with the
                    exception of powder and tobacco. Coal, cotton, metals, and provisions are
                    imported; cheese, cattle, timber, leather, asphalt, building stone, and calico
                    are exported. The national roads make a total of 193 miles, other roads 3100
                    miles, and the railways—Annecy to Aix-les-Bains and to Annemasse, on the line
                    from Bellegarde to Evian—96 miles. With its 274,087 inhabitants (1881), who all
                    speak French and are almost exclusively Roman Catholics, Haute-Savoie is only
                    about one-tenth below the average density of France. It forms the diocese of
                    Annecy; the court of appeal and the university academy are at Chambéry, and the
                    department is included in the 14th corps d’armée district (Grenoble). There are
                    4 arrondissements—Annecy (population of town 11,000), Bonneville (2270), St
                    Julien (1500), and Thonon (5440),—28 cantons, and 314 communes.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
