<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0921-0336-0317-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SÁTÁRA, or SATTARAH (9th edition, volume 21, page
                    317)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86q1x">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9qc3b">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pc5x">Soils</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2cg69">Mahrattas</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4804xr51">Mohammedans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v698h77">Mohammedanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1750261">Inch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:883965">Crops</term>
                    <term ref="fast:880858">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1124682">Soils</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:845230">Canals</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n336/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SÁTÁRA, or SATTARAH</label>, a British district in the
                    central division of the Bombay presidency, India, between 16° 50' and 18° 10' N.
                    lat. and 73° 45' and 75° E. long. It has an area of 4988 square miles, and is
                    bounded on the north by the river Nira and the states of Bhor and Phaltan, on
                    the east by Sholapur district, on the south by the Varna river separating it
                    from Kolhapur and Sangli states, and on the west by the Sahyádri mountains,
                    which separate it from the Concan districts of Kolabá and Ratnágiri. The Sátára
                    district contains two main systems of hills, the Sahyádri range and its
                    offshoots, and the Mahádeo range and its offshoots; the former runs through the
                    district from north to south, and the Mahádeo range starts about 10 miles north
                    of Mahabáleshwar and stretches east and south-east across the whole breadth of
                    the district. The Mahádeo Hills are bold and abrupt, presenting in many cases
                    bare scarps of black rock and looking at a distance like so many hill
                    fortresses. Within the limits of Sátára are two river systems—the Bhima system
                    in a small part of the north and north-east, and the Kistna system throughout
                    the rest of the district. (See <hi rend="smallcaps">Kistna.)</hi> The hill
                    forests have a large store of timber and firewood. The whole of Sátára falls
                    within the Deccan trap area; the hills consist of trap intersected by strata of
                    basalt and topped with laterite, while, of the different soils on the plains,
                    the commonest is the black loamy clay containing carbonate of lime. This is a
                    very fertile soil, and when well watered is capable of yielding heavy crops.
                    Sátára district contains some important irrigation works,— including the Kistna
                    Canal, open for 35 miles. In some of the western parts of the district the
                    average annual rainfall exceeds 200 inches; but on the eastern side water is
                    scanty, the rainfall varying from 40 inches in Sátára town to less than 12
                    inches in some places farther east. There is no railway, but the West Deccan
                    Railway, which is in course of construction, will put the district into
                    communication with Poona and Belgaum, and will run through Sátára for about 100
                    miles. The tiger, panther, bear, and sambhar deer are found in the west near the
                    Sahyádris, and the hyaena, wolf, leopard, and smaller game in the east.</p>
                <p>According to the last census returns (1881) the population of Sátára district was
                    1,062,350 (532,525 males and 529,825 females). Hindus numbered 1,008,918,
                    Mohammedans 36,712, and Christians</p>
                <p>886. Four towns had more than 10,000 inhabitants,—Satara (see below), Wai 11,676,
                    Karad 10,778, Tasgaon 10,206. About two-thirds of the Hindus consist of Kunbis
                    and Mahrattas, who during the period of Mahratta ascendency furnished the bulk
                    of the armies; and the Mávlás, who formed Shiváji’s best soldiers, were drawn
                    from the hill tribes of Sátára district. Agriculture supports more than
                    three-fourths of the people; the soil is fertile, and joar forms the staple
                    food; rice is grown in the western valleys, and in the south and east cotton is
                    raised. In 1882-83, of 1,384,255 acres held for tillage, 270,244 were fallow or
                    under grass, while of the remaining 1,114,011 acres 39,757 were twice cropped;
                    cereals, consisting chiefly of joar and bajra, occupied 898,206 acres, pulses
                    159,211 acres, oil-seeds 42,001 acres, and miscellaneous crops the remainder.
                    Besides blankets and coarse cotton cloth the chief exports are grain, tobacco,
                    oil-seeds, chillies, molasses, and a little raw cotton; the imports are
                    piece-goods, hardware, salt, and dates. The gross revenue of the district in
                    1883-84 amounted to £268,779, of which the land contributed £228,749.</p>
                <p>O11 the overthrow of the Jadhav dynasty in 1312 the district passed to the
                    Mohammedan power, which was consolidated in the reign of the Bahmani kings. On
                    the fall of the Bahmanis towards the end of the 15th century each chief set up
                    for himself until the Bijapur kings finally asserted themselves, and under these
                    kings the Mahrattas arose, and laid the foundation of an independent kingdom
                    with Sátára as its capital. Intrigues and dissensions in the palace led to the
                    ascendency of the peshwas, who removed the capital to Poona in 1749, and
                    degraded the raja of Satara into the position of a political prisoner. The war
                    of 1817 closed the career of the peshwas, and the British then restored the
                    titular raja, and assigned to him the principality of Satara. In consequence of
                    political intrigues, he was deposed in 1839, and his brother was placed on the
                    throne. This prince dying without male heirs, the state was resumed by the
                    British Government.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
