<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0921-0798-0773-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SHANS (9th edition, volume 21, page 773)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1086604">Racing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1086436">Race</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1156484">Tribes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1163841">Valleys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:840028">Buddhism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:840320">Buddhists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:970716">Indos</term>
                    <term ref="fast:840025">Buddhas</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207659">Cambodia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210322">Laos</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w08wq8q">Shans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bg2hh25">Mongols</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zf6b">Malays</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p55dr26">Sketching</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86v83">Race</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fr3m">Racing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20h7x">Valleys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n798/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SHANS</label>. This name is applied to a number of for the
                    most part semi-independent communities occupying a region bounded on the W. by
                    Burmah and Assam, N. and N.E. by the Chinese province of Yun-nan, E. by
                    Tongking, and S. by Siam (see Plate IX.). Ethnologically the race has a much
                    wider extension, including the Siamese (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Siam),</hi> and
                    also, according to Garnier and Colquhoun, the hill tribes around the Tong-king
                    delta and various tribes of Kwang-tung and Kwang-se, and extending across the
                    north of Burmah into Assam. It is also widely diffused through south-western
                    Yun-nan. Terrien de Lacouperie considers it allied to the Mon, the Mung, and the
                    Pa, and places its early home in the mountains north of Sze-chuen, whence, not
                    having amalgamated with the growing Chinese empire, it was gradually forced
                    southwards. Although the level of civilization and the purity of their Buddhism
                    vary considerably among the different branches of the race, there is everywhere
                    a remarkable resemblance in appearance, manners, customs, and polity. The
                    traditions current of their origin, too, though localized by each in its own
                    habitat, are closely similar. This great homogeneity seems the more remarkable
                    in that the race is found not only living under many different political
                    systems,— <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> either independent, or subject to Burmah,
                    China, or Siam,—but often in communities isolated by mountain ranges, inhabited
                    by tribes of different race and character. All this seems to point to a
                    political unity in earlier times.</p>
                <p>The Shans probably appeared on the upper Irawadi nearly two thousand years ago,
                    but Burmese and Shan traditions agree that they were established some centuries
                    earlier on the upper waters of the Shweli and on the Salwín and adjacent valleys
                    on the south-west frontiers of Yun-nan. Here, at all events, in the 7th and 8th
                    cen turies, we hear of the growth of that power which, temporarily broken by
                    Burmah in the 11th century, reached its highest development in the 13th. This
                    Shan empire, known by the classical Indian name of Kausambi, —corrupted after
                    the punning Chinese fashion into Koshan-pyi, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> nine
                    Shan states,—was a confederacy of about ten states, known among themselves by
                    the name of the most powerful member, Mau, or Muang Mau. A great leader, Sam
                    Lung Pha, brother of the king of Mau, overran and conquered Upper Assam from the
                    Satiyas in 1229, the dynasty lasting until the British annexation. These Ahorns
                    still inhabit the Assam districts of Sibsagar and south and east Lakhimpur,
                    though pressed on from the south-west by the Bengalis, whom they despise as a
                    black and inferior race, preferring to associate with the Chinese, whom they
                    regard as congeners, and as the greatest race in the world.</p>
                <p>This 13th and the following century also saw Tali to the east and Arakan to the
                    west invaded, Burmah being then weakened by the Mongol invasion; Chieng Mai and
                    other southern Shan states were also annexed, and “Ayuthia” (<hi rend="italic"
                        >i.e</hi>., Siam), Cambodia, and Tavoy are claimed by the Shan historians as
                    among their conquests, the Shan influence being felt even in Java. From the 14th
                    to the 16th century wars with both Burmah and China were frequent, and Shan
                    dynasties ruled at times in Burmah; but in 1556-62 the Burmese conquered
                    Mogaung, the chief province of Mau, when Buddhism is recorded to have been
                    introduced: probably only a reform of religion is meant. In 1604 the districts
                    now known as the Chinese Shan States, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> the heart of
                    the Mau empire, lying chiefly in the Ta-peng basin, east of Bamo,—a town whose
                    population also is mainly Shan,—were finally conquered by China, Mogaung
                    remaining independent on sufferance till absorbed by Burmah in 1796.</p>
                <p>Zimmé or Chieng Mai (including Kiang Hai, Kiang Sen, Lagong, and Lapong), whose
                    capital is now an important and well-built town, and Vien Chang on the east of
                    the Me-kong, were both great Shan centres, warring, with various fortunes, with
                    Burmah and Cambodia and with each other, till subjected by the growing power of
                    Siam late in the last century.</p>
                <p>The Burmese Shan States, especially those more remote from Mandalay, have
                    latterly become practically independent; and, the tyranny which led to extensive
                    southward migration having thus ceased, the stream is partly returning
                    northwards. Descendants, too, of the population deported by Siam from Kiang Sen
                    about a hundred years ago are now by the king’s permission returning to people
                    that fertile territory. The Burmese plan with the Shans was to govern by
                    fostering internal dissensions, and they are bitterly hated, while the Chinese
                    are in an equal degree liked and respected. The great Shan state of Kiang Hung
                    has now accepted the dictation of China, to whom in fact, like some of its
                    lesser neighbours, it has always paid certain taxes, while acknowledging the
                    supremacy of Burmah. Kiang Tung to the south, which has been Burmese for over a
                    century, has lately made overtures to Siam, though not forgetting the injuries
                    inflicted by that power in 1854. The numerous ruins of great cities over the
                    whole region from Chieng Mai to Kiang Tung testify to former wealth and
                    prosperity, though they may not have all existed contemporaneously. In Luang
                    Prabang in the north-east, on the other hand, tribes of a partly Chinese race
                    are pressing southwards. It is remarkable how many of the conquering irruptions
                    of south-east Asia were due mainly to the eviction of such conquerors by some
                    stronger power. Incessant wars and vast deportations have tended to assimilate
                    the various populations of all this region.<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n799/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0921-0799-0774"/> Each Shan state is governed by a <hi
                        rend="italic">tsobwa (chao p'hya),</hi> or supreme chief, aided by a
                    council, and often by a coadjutor. Where the Shans are in immediate contact with
                    one of their great neighbours their habits and customs are necessarily modified;
                    otherwise, speaking generally, civilization increases southwards. Religion is
                    nominallv Buddhist, and the priests, though their lives are usually far from
                    correct, have great influence; temples, caves, and other localities sacred to
                    Buddha are thronged with worshippers liberal with their offerings; but the
                    practical exercise of religion consists chiefly in efforts to propitiate or
                    avert the evil influence of the <hi rend="italic">nats</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                        >p'hees,</hi> demons and spirits everywhere present, to whom all accidents
                    and illnesses are attributed. Along with the Buddha, various images, among which
                    the horse is not uncommon, are adored (though there are temples in which these
                    are not found); and fetiches—natural objects of special form, <hi rend="italic"
                        >e.g.,</hi> of some part of the body—are kept in the house to avert disease.
                    Medical treatment consists largely in magical practices, and individuals
                    denounced by the sick as the cause of their illness frequently have their houses
                    burned and are themselves deported to a distance. Thus, too, ordeals have a
                    prominent place in legal practice. The Shans have no Buddhist prejudices against
                    killing poultry or cattle for food, but like other Indo-Chinese and the Malays
                    do not use milk. Slavery is general; the supply is recruited partly by raids on
                    neighbouring hill tribes; the Indo-Chinese practice of slavery for debt also
                    prevails. The slaves are not ill-treated, and are chiefly employed in field
                    labour by the chaos, who own great numbers. In appearance the North Shans are
                    sallow, but hardly darker than South Europeans, and are characterized by a short
                    broad flat face, more elongated and nearer the Tartar type in the upper classes;
                    they have red cheeks, brown eyes hardly oblique, black hair, nose almost
                    aquiline, and are of medium height. The Chinese Shans are much smaller, with
                    squat figures, prominent cheek-bones, and oblique eyes.</p>
                <p>The practice of tattooing prevails in some districts, down to the upper waters of
                    the Me-nam, and it occurs also among the Laos in the south-east, the tattooed
                    being known as the black-bellied, the non-tattooed as the white-bellied. The
                    Shans are all hardier and more manly than their congeners the Siamese, and they
                    are also more sedate and more self-possessed than the Burmese. Most travellers
                    speak of them as brave, friendly, social, and hospitable, but a good deal of the
                    oppression aud cruelty natural to a semi-barbarous condition prevails. They are
                    cleanly and fond of bathing, the towns and villages being supplied with bamboo
                    aqueducts. Drunkenness, except at festivals, is rare. Gambling is common, whole
                    families being sold into slavery to pay debts thus contracted. Public gaming and
                    the sale of spirits and opium are monopolies. They show much artistic taste in
                    the beautiful colours of their textile fabrics, the needlework and embroidery of
                    the women, and the designing and execution of the silver ornaments which are
                    worn in profusion. They show great aptitude for trade, and are said by Mr Holt
                    Hallett to welcome the prospect of the railway intended to connect their country
                    with Maulmein, crossing thence to Raheng or some neighbouring point on the
                    Me-nam, and on through the fertile valleys and plateaus on its upper tributaries
                    to the Chinese frontier.</p>
                <p>Tea is found, both wild and cultivated, from Zimτne to Kiang Tung. Opium is
                    exported to Mandalay and to China. Indian corn, sugar, and tobacco are grown in
                    the low grounds, and excellent cotton and indigo (which also grows wild in the
                    hills). Teak has long been worked by Anglo-Burmese in the eastern affluents of
                    the Toong-yen and neighbouring valleys, and has become comparatively scarce west
                    of the Me-ping; but it grows freely in the hills and valleys around Kiang Sen
                    and Lagong, and in the hill region of eastern Siam, where, however, it is of
                    inferior quality. Silk is produced, and iron, copper, and silver-lead (galena)
                    ores are worked.</p>
                <p>The Shan languages are classified by Dr Cushing as follows :— Ahom (Assam),
                    extinct; Khamti, on the upper Irawadi and other valleys on the extreme north of
                    Burmah; the Chinese (Mau) Shans, east from Bamo; Shans proper, between the
                    mountains which bound the Burmese plains in the east and the Me-kong, and
                    between ‘23° and 19° N. lat.; Laos to the south of this, from 19° north to the
                    frontiers of Siam; and lastly, Siamese. The last two, as spoken, differ but
                    little, and the three others may be grouped together. All have separate
                    alphabets (related, however, in form), except the Siamese; and, the spelling
                    being phonetic, the orthography is tolerably fixed. But it is a tonal language,
                    and the vowel signs are few, so that some have two or three values assigned
                    them. There are a good many Pali words due to Buddhism, many Burmese words in
                    the districts under Burmese influence, and a large foreign element in the
                    Chinese Shan state of Ho-tha, where the race is perhaps not fundamentally
                    Shan.</p>
                <p>See Ney Elias, <hi rend="italic">Introductory Sketch of the History of the Shans
                        in Upper Burmah an I West Yun-nan,</hi> Calcutta, 1876; Yule, <hi
                        rend="italic">Glossary of Anglo-Indian Words and Phrases</hi> (1886), and
                        <hi rend="italic">Narrative of the Mission to Ava</hi> (1858); Anderson, <hi
                        rend="italic">From Mandalay to Momien</hi>; Colqnhoun, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Among the Shans</hi>; Cushing. <hi rend="italic">Shan Dictionary</hi>
                    (Introduction); Bock. <hi rend="italic">Temples and Elephants·,</hi> Sir A.
                    Phayre, <hi rend="italic">History of Burmah.</hi> (C. τ.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
