<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0921-0137-0120-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">S (9th edition, volume 21, page 120)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1127099">Sounds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126935">Sound</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1032344">Names</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899352">Dues</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1140749">Symbolism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qj77x65">Sound</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49g5gh4j">Names</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cv4br5j">Symbolism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w37kv50">Alphabet</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20d44">Alphabeting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r50f">Phoenicians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n137/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">S</label> represents the hard open (or fricative) sound
                    produced by bringing the blade of the tongue close to the front palate,
                    immediately behind the gums, or rather, this is the normal position for S, as
                    slight varieties can be produced by bringing the tongue farther back. By the
                    “blade” is meant the pointed end of the tongue, not the mere point, which at the
                    same part of the palate produces R. This position differs little from that for
                    TH, into which S passes in a lisping pronunciation; a larger part of the surface
                    of the tongue is brought near to the palate for TH than for S. The symbol which
                    represents the soft open sound corresponding to S is Z, though in practice S
                    often stands for both.</p>
                <p>The history of our symbol S is easy up to a certain point. It is the rounded form
                    of 5, rounded at a very early period for convenience of writing, for the change
                    is apparent in the old Italian alphabet of Caere, and still more on the recently
                    discovered vase of Formello; and even in the scribbling of the Greeks at Abu
                    Simbel—the oldest, or nearly the oldest, bit of Greek epigraphy—perfectly
                    rounded forms stand side by side with the angular ones. The common Greek form Σ
                    was obtained by adding a fourth stroke, and gradually making the top and bottom
                    ones horizontal. When, however, we wish to identify the Greek symbol of three
                    strokes with its Phoenician counterpart, the difficulty begins. The Phoenicians
                    had four symbols for sibilants, known in Hebrew as Zayin, Samekh, Ṣade, and
                    Shin; the last of these at a very early date represented two sounds, the English
                        <hi rend="italic">sh,</hi> and another sound which resembled that of Samekh
                    and ultimately became indistinguishable from it, both being pronounced as the
                    English s. The Greeks did not want all these symbols, consequently in different
                    parts of Greece one or other— not the same—Phoenician symbol fell into disuse.
                    One of these, M or N, called San, though lost in Ionic, appears in old Doric
                    inscriptions, as those of Thera, Melos, and Crete, Argos, Corinth, and Corcyra;
                    but the later Doric form is the usual Sigma; probably San was too like the nasal
                    M. There is no doubt that in form Zeta represents Zayin, and that Xi represents
                    Samekh. Moreover, Zeta and Zayin stand seventh in the Greek and Phoenician
                    alphabets respectively, and Xi and Samekh each fifteenth. Again, the form of San
                    with three strokes corresponds fairly with Ṣade, and Sigma is moderately like
                    Shin; but here the evidence of position comes in again to strengthen a somewhat
                    weak case, for in the old Italian alphabets San has the place of Ṣade, the
                    simpler form occurring in the Caere alphabet, the fuller in that of the Formello
                    vase; in both Sigma (rounded in form) has the place of Shin. These
                    identifications would be certain if the names corresponded as well as the forms;
                    but they clearly do not: Zeta and Ṣade (not Zayin) seem to hold together in
                    sound, and Sigma (as has often been suggested) looks like a “popular etymology”
                    for Samekh. But the objection from difference of names is not fatal. All names
                    which are thought of habitually in rows or sets tend to be modified under the
                    influence of analogy; and analogy has certainly been at work here, for Xi, which
                    is a purely Greek name, is, like Psi, and like Chi and Phi, due to the older Pi.
                    Similarly Eta and Theta have probably made Zeta; but it must be allowed that the
                    metamorphosis of Ṣade is more intelligible (as a matter of sound-change) than
                    that of Zayin. Probably we must have recourse to a different principle to
                    explain at least some part of our difficulty. We may suppose that in some part
                    of Greece the sounds denoted originally by Ṣade and Zayin became
                    indistinguishable; there would then exist for a time one sound but two names. It
                    would be a matter of little moment which name should survive; thus Ṣade (or
                    Zeta) might supersede Zayin, or one name might survive in one district—as San in
                    the Doric, but Sigma in the rest of Greece. This suggestion is made by Dr Taylor
                        <hi rend="italic">(The Alphabet,</hi> ii. 100). The history of the sounds,
                    as well as of the forms, of the Greek sibilants is difficult. Probably Sigma was
                    generally hard—our <hi rend="italic">s</hi> in <hi rend="italic">sign.</hi> But
                    Zeta did not originally denote the corresponding <hi rend="italic">z</hi>:
                    rather it was <hi rend="italic">dz;</hi> some say <hi rend="italic">dj,</hi> as
                    in “John,” but this is not likely. Xi was probably a strong sibilant with a weak
                    guttural, as X was in Latin. If the sound <hi rend="italic">z</hi> existed in
                    Greek, as is probable, it was denoted by Sigma. In Italy, also, we must infer
                    that the soft sibilant was heard too little to need a special symbol, because
                        <hi rend="italic">z</hi>, which exists in the old alphabets of Caere and
                    Formello, was lost early enough to leave a place for the newly-made Italian
                    symbol G. When Z was restored, it was placed at the end of the alphabet and
                    doubtless with the value of Greek Z in the Greek words in which alone it was
                    used. One Latin <hi rend="italic">s—</hi> probably <hi rend="italic">z—</hi>
                    became the trilled <hi rend="italic">r</hi> between two vowels,— <hi
                        rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> in "Papirius” for “Papisius,” “arboris” for
                    “arbosis.”</p>
                <p>In English the symbol <hi rend="italic">s</hi> alone existed till z was
                    introduced from France with words of French origin, as “zeal,” “zone.” An
                    attempt was made to employ it at the end of plural nouns, where the sound is
                    regularly heard except when the last sound of the noun is hard, <hi
                        rend="italic">e.g., “</hi> bedz” (beds), but “hops”; but this was not
                    maintained, nor even consistently done, for the symbol was used even when the
                    sound must have been <hi rend="italic">s.</hi> We regularly write <hi
                        rend="italic">s</hi> for both sounds,— <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> in
                    “lose” and “loose,” “curs” and “curse,” “hers” and “hearse.” When there is a
                    distinction in spelling the <hi rend="italic">s</hi> commonly has the value of
                        <hi rend="italic">z</hi>,— <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> “vies” and “vice,”
                    “pays” and “pace,” “his” and “hiss.” S has the sound of <hi rend="italic"
                        >sh</hi> in “sure,” “sugar,” and some other words; this is due to the
                    palatal sound heard before the <hi rend="italic">u. Sh,</hi> in spite of its
                    spelling, is a single sound, the position of which differs from that for s only
                    in a slight retraction of the point of the tongue; it is commonly found in
                    English words which originally had <hi rend="italic">sk,—e.g.,</hi> “shall,”
                    O.E. <hi rend="italic">seeal</hi>; “shabby,” a doublet of “scabby”; “fish,” O.E.
                        <hi rend="italic">fisk.</hi> The sound is the same as that of French <hi
                        rend="italic">ch</hi> in “chateau,” “chef,” “sécher,” where it is due to
                    assibilation of original <hi rend="italic">k.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
