<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0140-0123-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SABAH, or British North Borneo</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 21, page 123</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:829042">Bays</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1138427">Sultans</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1138426">Sultanate</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:899678">Dutch</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b46q1sk44">Deltas</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4f18sf3s">Charters</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="9" ref="fastgeo:1243192">Borneo</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1216469">Brunei</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n140/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SABAH, or <hi rend="smallcaps">British North
                    Borneo</hi></label>, is all that portion of the island of <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Borneo</hi> (<hi rend="italic">q.v</hi>.) which was formally recognized by the
                    charter of incorporation granted in November 1881 as the territory of the
                    British North Borneo Company. It has a coast-line of over 600 miles, and its
                    area, still to a great extent unexplored,<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>But the officers of the company are very active in
                    exploration. L. B. von Donop, F. Witti (killed 1882), W. B. Pryer, Frank Hatton
                    (killed 1883), and Henry Walker are or have been among the more
                    energetic.</p></note> is estimated at 30,000 square miles. Leaving out of
                    account the deep indentations of the coast-line, it may be said to form a
                    pentagon, of which three sides, the north-west, north-east, and south-east, are
                    washed by the sea, while the remaining two sides are purely conventional lines
                    drawn from Gura Peak (3° 50' N. lat., 116° 10' E. long.), the one almost due
                    east to the Sibuco river, the other north-north-west to the mouth of the
                    Sipitong on Brunei Bay. The latter separates the Company’s territory from the
                    independent sultanate of Brunei; the former is the frontier towards the Dutch
                    possessions.</p>
                <p>The great central feature of Sabah is the magnificent mountain of Kinabalu
                    (compare <hi rend="smallcaps">Borneo)</hi> or Nabalu, built up of porphyritic
                    granite and igneous rocks to a height of 13,698 feet, and dominating the whole
                    northern part of the island, with all its profusion of lesser mountains and
                    hills. Kinabalu, which has the appearance of two mountains, unites towards the
                    east by a low ridge with “Nonohan t’ agaioh (the great Nonohan) and the terminal
                    cone Tumboyonkon (Tamboyukon).” These two summits are respectively 8000 and 7000
                    feet high, and there are others of considerable elevation in the same
                    neighbourhood. At some 15 or 20 miles to the north rises Mount Madalon (5000
                    feet), separated from Kinabalu and the other igneous and metamorphic hills by a
                    wide valley, and consisting of those aqueous rocks, limestones, sandstones, and
                    clays which appear to occupy the whole country to the north. Westward from
                    Kinabalu are hills between 1000 and 2000 feet in height, and about 40 or 50
                    miles south-east is an important group on the north side of the Labuk valley
                    known as the Mentapok Mountains (3000- 8000 feet). The whole surface of the
                    country is channelled by countless streams whose precipitous ravines,
                    boulder-strewn rapids, and enormous beds of rolled pebbles bespeak the denuding
                    energy of tropical rains. The coasts are generally low and flat, and to a great
                    extent lined with casuarina trees, with here and there a stretch of mangrove, a
                    low sandstone or limestone cliff, or a patch of that great forest which in the
                    interior still covers so large a portion of the territory. In the low grounds
                    along the coast and also inland among the hills are vast swamps and watery
                    plains, which in the rainy season, when the rivers rise 20 or 30 feet above
                    their usual level, are transformed into lakes. On the west side of Sabah the
                    principal rivers are the Padas and the Klias, debouching opposite Labuan, but
                    quite unexplored in their upper courses; the Papar (Pappar or Pappal), which
                    passes the village of that name and enters the sea at Papar Point; the
                    Tampassuk, one of the first to be explored (see St John’s <hi rend="italic">Life
                    in the Forests of the Far East)</hi> and remarkable for the waterfall of
                    Pandassan or Tampassuk (1500 feet high, and thus one of the highest in the
                    world), formed by its headwater the Kalupis. The Sekwati, a comparatively small
                    river farther north, is well known for its oil-springs. At the northern
                    extremity of the island the deep inlet of Marudu Bay receives the waters of the
                    Marudu or Maludu river, which rises on the west side of Mount Madalon. On the
                    east coast are the Sugut, which has its headwaters in the hills to the east of
                    Kinabalu, and forms its delta in the neighbourhood of Torongohok or Purpura
                    Island; the Labuk, debouching in Labuk Bay, and having its sources in the
                    highlands about 70 miles inland; the Kinabatangan, with a longer course than any
                    yet mentioned, rising probably between 116° and 117° E. long., and forming at
                    its mouth a very extensive delta to the south of Sandakan Harbour; and finally
                    the Segama, the scene of Frank Hatton’s death (1883). Farther south, and inland
                    from Darvel Bay and Sibuco (or St Lucia) Bay, there are no doubt other rivers of
                    equal, it may be superior, importance; such, to judge by its delta, is the
                    Kalabakong, debouching opposite Sebattik Island. Most of the rivers mentioned
                    are navigable for steam launches of light draught, but their value is frequently
                    impaired by a bar near the mouth. Several of the natural harbours of North
                    Borneo, on the other hand, are at once accessible, safe, and commodious.
                    Sandakan Harbour, on the north-east coast (5° 40' N. lat. and 118° 10' E.
                    long.), runs inland some 17 miles, with a very irregular outline broken by the
                    mouths of numerous creeks and streams. The mouth, only 2½ miles across, is split
                    into two channels by the little island of Balhalla. The depth in the main
                    entrance varies from 10 to 17 fathoms, and vessels drawing 20 feet can advance
                    half-way up the bay. Just within the mouth, on the north side, lies Elopura (see
                    below). At Silam, on Darvel Bay, farther south, there is good anchorage. Kudat
                    (discovered by Commander Johnstone, of H.M.S. “Egeria,” in 1881) is a small but
                    valuable harbour in Marudu Bay running inland for 2 or 3 miles, but rapidly
                    shoaling after the first mile to 1 and 2 fathoms. It affords anchorage for
                    vessels of any draught, but the frontage available for wharves is limited to
                    some 1500 feet. In Gaya Bay, on the west coast, any number of vessels may lie in
                    safety during either monsoon, the depths varying from 6 to 16 and 17
                    fathoms.</p>
                <p>The climate of North Borneo is of course tropical, with a very equable
                    temperature. The lowest minimum of the thermometer recorded in 1883 at Sandakan
                    was 68°·5 in December. The greatest interval without rain was eight days in
                    March. The rainfall was 34½ inches (157 in 1880) at Sandakan, 129 at Papar, and
                    120 at Kudat. In the interior it must often be much above these figures.</p>
                <p>That North Borneo should prove rich in minerals was supposed probable from the
                    character of some other parts of the island; but hitherto investigations have
                    not in this matter proved very successful. Coal or lignite exists, but most
                    frequently in thin seams and insignificant pockets; the petroleum springs cannot
                    come into any true competition with those worked elsewhere; gold has been
                    discovered (1885) in the Segama river and may prove a stimulus to immigration;
                    iron-ores appear both abundant and at times productive; and there are
                    indications of the existence of copper, antimony, tin, and zinc ores. As yet the
                    wealth of the country lies in its timber and jungle products (camphor and
                    gutta-percha in great quantities), and in its edible nuts, guano, sago, sugar,
                    tobacco, coffee, pepper, and gambier. Tobacco is most successfully grown by the
                    natives in the inland districts of Mansalut, Kandassang, Koporin-gan, Gana-Gana,
                    Tomborongo, Karnahan, Penusak, Tiong-Tuhan, &amp;c.; and its cultivation has
                    been taken up by several foreign companies. The birds’-nest caves of Gomanton
                    (Gormanton) near the village of Malape on the Kinabatangan yield the Government
                    a revenue of from $6000 to $7000; and other caves of the same kind are still
                    unworked. As the natives (Dusuns, Tagaas-Bajaus, Idaan, &amp;c.) are scattered,
                    mostly in small villages, throughout the unexplored as well as the explored
                    districts, their number can only be guessed, but it is usually stated at
                    150,000. Since the formation of the company there has been a steady immigration,
                    especially of Chinese from Singapore. At Elopura, the capital of the territory
                    and of its East Coast residency, the inhabitants in 1883 numbered 3770 (1500
                    being Chinese and 1085 Sulus). Hong-Kong and Singapore steamers now call
                    regularly at Sandakan, Gaya, and Kudat. In 1885 the territory was divided into
                    Alcock province (in the north), Keppel province (along the west coast as far
                    north as<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n141/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0141-0124"/> Kimanis Bay), the East Coast residency (to the
                    south-east of Alcock and Keppel provinces), and Dent province (to the south-west
                    of the East Coast residency with the coast from Kimanis Bay to Brunei Bay).</p>
                <p>In 1865 an American company started by Mr Torrey obtained from the sultan of
                    Brunei certain concessions of territory in North Borneo; but this enterprise
                    proved a financial failure and the settlement formed on the Kimanis river broke
                    up. The rights of the American company were bought up by the Austrian Baron von
                    Overbeck and the English merchant Mr Alfred Dent, who further obtained from the
                    sultan of Brunei and the sultan of Sulu a series of charters conferring on them
                    the sovereign authority in North Borneo under the titles of maharajah of Sabah,
                    rajah of Gaya and Sandakan and Data Bandahara. In spite of the opposition of
                    Spain, which claimed that the sultan of Sulu being a Spanish vassal could not
                    dispose of his territory without her consent, the English company organized by
                    Mr Dent succeeded in obtaining a charter of incorporation under Act of
                    Parliament, 1st November 1881, as the “British North Borneo Company,” with right
                    to acquire other interests in, over, or affecting the territories or property
                    comprised in the several grants.</p>
                <p>The text of the charter will be found in the <hi rend="italic">London
                    Gazette,</hi> 8th November 1881 and in the appendix to Mr Joseph Hatton's <hi
                    rend="italic">New Ceylon</hi> (1881); see also Frank Hatton, <hi rend="italic"
                    >North Borneo,</hi> 1885; the <hi rend="italic">Century Magazine,</hi> 1885; the
                    <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh R</hi> eview, 1882; and the <hi rend="italic"
                    >English Illustrated, Magazine,</hi> 1885.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
