<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0717-0692-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SERVIUS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 21, page 692</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1151043">Time</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1086604">Racing</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1086436">Race</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:825070">Back</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4pk07518">Face</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86v83">Race</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fr3m">Racing</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4h41jw08">Servians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n717/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SERVIUS</label>, the commentator on Virgil, is all but
                    unknown to us, so far as personal information goes. From notices in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Saturnalia</hi> of Macrobius, where he appears as an interlocutor,
                    we may infer that in or about 380, though still quite young, he was already
                    distinguished as. a “grammaticus,” that is, as an expert in the criticism,
                    explanation, and teaching of the classical literature of Rome. Servius therefore
                    belongs to the latter half of the 4th and the earlier years of the 5th century,
                    to the age of Symmachus and Claudian, of Jerome and Augustine. The allusions of
                    Macrobius and a short letter from Symmachus to Servius leave no doubt that the
                    grammarian formed one of that band of cultivated men, led by Symmachus, whose
                    eyes were turned towards the pagan past and away from the Christian future, and
                    who breathed into pagan culture its last transient sparks of life and vigour.
                    The race of “grammatici” to which Servius belonged, and which had now run at
                    Rome a course of some 500 years, had done much evil to literature, had helped to
                    corrupt, falsify, encumber, and even in some instances by abbreviations upon
                    abbreviations to kill out the texts on which they worked; but on the whole they
                    had done more good. They had helped to save what could be saved of education,
                    culture, and history, and so had in the main contributed to the preservation of
                    the ancient literature that has come down to us. Of all the “grammatici” none
                    bears on his front more of the virtues and fewer of the vices of the race than
                    Servius. But it must be noted that much which passes under the name of Servius
                    in modern editions, and in modern quotations, most certainly did not proceed
                    from his hand. The comments on Virgil to which his name has been attached come
                    from three different sources. One class of MSS. contains a comparatively short
                    commentary, definitely attributed to Servius. A second class (all going back to
                    the 10th or 11th century) presents a much expanded commentary, in which the
                    first is embedded; but these MSS. differ very much in the amount and character
                    of the additions they make to the original, and none of them bear the name of
                    Servius. The added matter is undoubtedly ancient, dating from a time but little
                    removed from that of Servius, and is founded to a large extent on historical and
                    antiquarian literature which is now lost. The third class of MSS., written for
                    the most part in Italy and of late date, repeats the text of the first class,
                    with numerous interpolated scholia of quite recent origin and little or no
                    value.</p>
                <p>The real Servian commentary (for so we must designate the text that we find in
                    the first class of MSS.) practically gives the only complete extant edition of a
                    classic author written before the destruction of the empire. It is constructed
                    very much on the principle of a modern edition, but with very different ideas
                    both as to the relative and the absolute value of the matters treated. Owing to
                    the delicacy and originality of his veiled style, to the innumerable threads of
                    ancient history, mythology, and antiquities shot through the texture of his
                    poems, owing above all to the firm hold he early gained upon the Latin schools,
                    Virgil had a continuous line of expounders stretching almost from his death to
                    the destruction of the Roman government of the West. Servius built his edition
                    in part on the extensive Virgilian literature of preceding times, much of which
                    is known only from the fragments and facts he has preserved. The notices of
                    Virgil’s text, though seldom or never authoritative in face of the existing
                    MSS., which go back to, or even beyond, the times of Servius, yet supply
                    valuable information concerning the ancient recensions and textual criticism of
                    Virgil. In the grammatical interpretation of his author’s language, Servius does
                    not rise above the stiff and overwrought subtleties of that day; while his
                    etymologies, as is natural, violate every law of sound and sense. As a literary
                    critic the shortcomings of Servius are great, if we judge him by a modern
                    standard, but he shines if compared with his contemporaries. In particular, he
                    deserves credit for setting his face against the prevalent allegorical methods
                    of exposition. But the abiding value of his work lies in his preservation of
                    facts in Roman history, religion, antiquities, and language which but for him
                    might have perished. Not a little of the laborious erudition of Varro and other
                    ancient scholars, to whom time has proved unkind, has survived in Servius’s
                    pages. The older MSS. sometimes add to the name Servius that of Magister (given
                    to other distinguished grammarians at different times); the later Italian MSS.
                    in some cases give his name as Maurus Servius Honoratus. Besides the Virgilian
                    commentary, we have other works of Servius,— a collection of notes on the
                    grammar <hi rend="italic">(Ars)</hi> of Donatus; a treatise on metrical endings;
                    the tract <hi rend="italic">De Centum Meteris</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >Centimeter.</hi></p>
                <p>The most noted editions of the Virgilian commentary are by Fabricius (1551); P.
                    Daniel, who first published the enlarged commentary (1600); and by Thilo and
                    Hagen (Leipsic, 1878-84). The <hi rend="italic">Essai sur Servius</hi> by E.
                    Thomas (Paris, 1880) is an elaborate and valuable examination of all matters
                    connected with Servius; many points are treated also by Ribbeck in his
                    “Prolegomena” to Virgil, and by Thilo and Hagen as above. The smaller works of
                    Servius are printed in Keil’s <hi rend="italic">Grammatici Latini.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
