<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0395-0374-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SCARBOROUGH</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 21, page 374</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49882v82">Resorts</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4r20rz2q">Cistercians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4154ds5t">Friars</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s53t">Normans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20h7x">Valleys</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b47s7hx2m">Piers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41z41t5n">Boroughs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:864222">Cliffs</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:950637">Halls</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1063893">Piers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1163841">Valleys</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1084913">Quakers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1098511">Roads</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n395/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SCARBOROUGH</label>, a parliamentary borough of England,
                    frequently called “the Queen of Watering Places,” situated on the east coast of
                    Yorkshire, in the North Riding, 40 miles from York, and between 54° 15' 0" and
                    54° 17' 15" N. lat. and 0° 22' 25'' and 0° 26' 24'' W. long. Its two parts,
                    north and south, each with a fine stretch of sand and bay, are divided by a
                    rocky promontory 300 feet above the sea, on which stand the remains of the
                    castle. The cliff is much exposed to denudation by the sea, which has been
                    proceeding during the present century at the rate of 1 yard in 17 years. The
                    plateau forming the castle yard in 1190, according to William of Newburgh,
                    comprised 60<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n396/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0396-0375"/> acres, but it is not now more than 17 acres 10
                    perches, or 43 acres, including store yards, dykes, and holms. The first castle
                    was built in the Anglo-Norman period, and is referred to as being in decay in
                    1154—a fact which throws back its origin earlier than 1136, the date assigned
                    for its erection by William Le Gros, earl of Albemarle and Holderness, its first
                    known governor. The list of its governors stretches from that date to 1832. The
                    streets of the older part of the town, immediately south of the castle hill,
                    come down to the sea, but the newer parts of the south as well as the north side
                    are built upon rising ground. A deep valley (Ramsdale) which divides the south
                    side is bridged from St Nicholas Cliff to the South Cliff. The approach by rail
                    is through the upper part of this valley, by the side of which there is a marsh
                    known as the Mere. The town is thus situated in a kind of basin, which opens out
                    to the north towards extensive and lofty moorland ranges. The modern period of
                    its history dates from 1620, when Mrs Farren, a lady resident, first discovered
                    its mineral springs. The town contained 30,504 inhabitants in 1881, but during
                    the season, which lasts from May to October, its population is augmented by from
                    ten to twenty thousand visitors, for whose convenience there is increasingly
                    ample accommodation. The Grand Hotel, fronting the sea on the south bay, stands
                    on St Nicholas Cliff, at the north side of the Ramsdale valley, and is one of
                    the largest in England. An aquarium (1877) stands beneath the Cliff Bridge, and
                    close by is the museum, a Roman-Doric rotunda, built in 1828. The spa saloon,
                    opened in 1800, contains a hall in the Italian-Renaissance style, a theatre, and
                    refreshment rooms. There is a promenade in front protected by a sea wall. The
                    south spring is aperient but contains some iron, while the north or chalybeate
                    spring is more tonic in its properties. The waters, however, are seldom taken
                    now, the town being mainly frequented for the sea-bathing. The grounds of the
                    present spa are tastefully laid out. A foreshore road, made in 1878 by the
                    corporation, and shortly to be extended round the castle cliff to the north
                    side, makes an excellent drive or promenade. The north side has fine sands, a
                    hoist, and a promenade pier, but is not so attractive as the south side, nor are
                    the houses there of so good a character and style. The salubrity of Scarborough
                    is attested by its vital statistics. The mean annual mortality from 1873 to 1882
                    was 18·4 per 1000. The death-rate from consumption in all England is 2·4 per
                    1000; amongst the indigenous population of Scarborough from 1873 to 1882 it was
                    1·7 per 1000. The mean annual temperature is 47·9 Fahr. In December, January,
                    and February it is only 0·6° colder than Brighton, whilst in the summer months
                    Brighton is 3·6 warmer.</p>
                <p>The town is a royal borough, its charter of incorporation dating from 1161. It
                    returned two members to parliament from 1283 to 1885, when one of the seats was
                    taken away. The limits of the municipal and parliamentary boroughs coincide,—the
                    area being 2348 acres, the population 24,259 in 1871 and 30,504 in 1881.</p>
                <p>Shipbuilding, salt-manufacture, and knife-making were formerly common, but the
                    only craft now remaining is jet-manufacture. The fishing trade is, however, very
                    considerable. Disputes about dues for the old pier and the fish-tithe occupy a
                    conspicuous place in the town records; the pier seems to have suffered greatly
                    in the various sieges to which the town, after it was walled, became exposed.
                    The old town-hall in St Nicholas Street, the new town-hall in Castle Road, the
                    market-hall in St Helen’s Square, in the Tuscan style, and the new post office
                    in Huntriss Row are conspicuous amongst the public buildings. There are two
                    theatres. Of the monastic buildings belonging to the Grey Friars, Dominicans,
                    and Carmelites there are no remains, but the parish church of St Mary,
                    conspicuously situated on a mound to the south of Castle Hill, occupies the site
                    of the old Cistercian monastery. The old church was made the site of a battery
                    in the siege of the castle in 1644, and one of its towers fell in 1659. The
                    restoration of the present building took place in 1850. There are other churches
                    and chapels of a much more recent date, including a Roman Catholic church. The
                    racecourse is on the top of a <hi rend="underline">bil</hi> l, commanding fine
                    views of the moors and of the sea.</p>
                <p>The old name of the town was written Skardeburge. It is not mentioned in Domesday
                    Book, but it was probably waste, as Tosti, count of Northumberland, had ravaged
                    and burnt it some time previously. Thorklen mentions it as having been ravaged
                    by Adelbrecht, king of Northumberland, and by Harold Hardrada. Douglas, the
                    Scottish chief, also burnt it in 1318. Henry II. compelled the count of Aumale
                    to surrender the castle in 1155. King John visited the castle in 1206 and 1216,
                    and the “house and castle of Scarborough” are mentioned in 1223. When not used
                    as a temporary royal residence the castle was a royal prison. In 1312 the earl
                    of Pembroke besieged it, and in the Pilgrimage of Grace insurrection (1536) it
                    was unsuccessfully besieged by Sir Robert Aske. A detailed survey of it, made in
                    1538, is still extant, the castle yard and land therein described, with the
                    buildings, corresponding with a survey made in 1839. It was again besieged in
                    1644-45 and in 1648. In 1655 George Fox the Quaker was imprisoned in the castle.
                    In 1645 the town was captured by assault, and in later years its inhabitants
                    were much impoverished by military exactions and expenses. A view of the town
                    and castle in 1485 is still extant. The precise date when the town-walls were
                    dismantled is not known. In 1730 Daniel Defoe, writing from the place, said:
                    “The town is well-built, pleasant, and populous, and we found a great deal of
                    company here, drinking the waters, who have not only come from the north of
                    England but from Scotland.”</p>
                <p>See <hi rend="italic">History of Scarborough Spaw,</hi> 1679; Gent’s <hi
                    rend="italic">History of Scarborough,</hi> 1735; Hinderwell' <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi> s <hi rend="italic">History of Scarborough,</hi>
                    1798; Cole's <hi rend="italic">Scarbrough Worthies,</hi> 1820; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Constitution and Byelaws of the Corporation of Scarbrough,</hi> 1827; <hi
                    rend="italic">Brief History of St Mary's, Scarbrough,</hi> 1845; <hi
                    rend="italic">The Geology of Scarbrough,</hi> by C. Fox Strang-ways, 1880; <hi
                    rend="italic">Flora of Scarbrough,</hi> by G. Masser, 1881; and <hi
                    rend="italic">Scarborough as a Health Resort,</hi> by A. Haviland, 1883.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
