<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0868-0843-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SHREW</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 21, page 843</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="12" ref="fasttopic:1145710">Teeth</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1142046">Tail</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:950358">Hair</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:878236">Cooperativeness</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:878116">Cooperation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4959c77k">Cooperation</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qp14">Insectivora</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="lcsh1910:b4j09wd22">Teething</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="lcsh1910:b4hh6c56c">Teeth</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4794135j">Tail</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4t14tq07">Hair</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n868/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SHREW</label>, a general term applied to the species of the
                    family <hi rend="italic">Soricidae,</hi> order <hi rend="italic"
                    >Insectivora</hi> (see vol. xv. p. 403), but in the British Isles more
                    particularly to the common and to the lesser shrew <hi rend="italic">(Sorex
                    vulgaris,</hi> L., and <hi rend="italic">S. pygmaeus,</hi> Pall.).</p>
                <p>The common shrew is, in England at least, by far the commoner of the two. It is a
                    small animal about the size of the common mouse, which it somewhat resembles in
                    the shape of its body, tail, and feet. But here the resemblance ends, for,
                    unlike the mouse, it possesses a remarkably long and slender muzzle, with
                    prominent nostrils, which project far beyond the lower lip; the eyes are very
                    small and almost concealed by the fur; the ears are wide and short, scarcely
                    rising above the long hairs surrounding them, and are provided internally with a
                    pair of deep folds, capable, when laid forward, of closing the entrance; the
                    tail, which is slightly shorter than the body (without the head), is
                    quadrangular in shape and clothed more or less densely with moderately long
                    hairs, terminating in a short pencil (in old individuals these hairs become worn
                    away, so that in some specimens the tail is almost quite naked); the feet are
                    five-toed, the toes terminating in slender, acutely pointed, non-retractile
                    claws. The dentition is very peculiar and characteristic: there are in all
                    thirty-two teeth, tipped with deep crimson; of these twelve only (the number is
                    characteristic, with one exception only, of the family) belong to the lower jaw;
                    of the remaining twenty ten occupy each side of the upper jaw, and of these the
                    first three, as they are implanted in the premaxillary bone, are termed
                    incisors. The first incisor is a large tooth with a long anterior caninelike
                    cusp and a small posterior one; then follow two small unicuspidate teeth; these
                    are succeeded by three similar progressively smaller teeth, whereof the first
                    has been called a canine and the other two premolars; the next tooth, also a
                    premolar, is a large multicuspidate tooth; and this is followed by three molars,
                    of which the third is small with a triangular crown. In the lower jaw we find on
                    each side anteriorly three teeth corresponding to the seven anterior teeth
                    above, of which the first is almost horizontal in direction, its upper surface
                    being marked by three notches, which<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n869/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0869-0844"/> receive the points of the three upper front teeth
                    with which they come in contact when the jaws are closed; then follow two small
                    teeth and three molars. The body is clothed with closely set uniformly long fur,
                    very soft and dense, varying in colour from light reddish to dark brown above,
                    rarely speckled over or spotted or even banded with white. The under surface of
                    both the body and the tail is greyish; the basal four-fifths of all the hairs
                    above and beneath are dark bluish grey; the hairs of the tail are less densely
                    set and coarser. On each side of the body, at a point about one-third of the
                    distance between the elbow and the knee, may be found, especially in the rutting
                    season, a cutaneous gland covered by two rows of coarse inbent hairs. This gland
                    secretes a peculiar fluid, on which the unpleasant cheesy odour of the animal
                    depends, and which is evidently also protective, rendering it secure against the
                    attacks of many predaceous animals.</p>
                <p>The lesser shrew <hi rend="italic">(S. pygmaeus)</hi> is much less abundant in
                    England and Scotland, but comparatively common in Ireland, where the common
                    shrew has not yet been found. It appears at first sight to be a diminutive
                    variant of that species, which it closely resembles in external form. It was
                    said to differ in having the tail longer than the body (without the head),
                    whereas in the common shrew the body (without the head) is longer than the tail,
                    and in the last unicuspidate upper molar tooth being comparatively larger and
                    more external than in the other species. But the present writer has found these
                    characters so exceedingly liable to variation as to be almost worthless; he has
                    therefore discovered reliable points of distinction as follows:— in <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">S.</hi><hi rend="italic">pygmaeus</hi> the third upper incisor
                    (when the teeth are unworn) is shorter, or at least not longer than the next
                    following tooth, whereas in S. <hi rend="italic">vulgans</hi> it is always
                    longer, and the length of the forearm and hand combined is very constantly 13
                    m.m. in the former species, while in the latter it is 17 m.m.</p>
                <p>The habits of both the common and the lesser shrew correspond. They live
                    generally in the neighbourhood of woods, making their nests under the roots of
                    trees or in any slight depression, occasionally even in the midst of open
                    fields, inhabiting the disused burrows of field-mice. Owing to their very small
                    size, dark colour, rapid movements, and chiefly nocturnal habits they easily
                    escape observation. They seek their food, which consists of insects, insect
                    larvae, small worms, and slugs, under dead leaves, fallen trees, and in grassy
                    places. Like the mole, they are very pugnacious, and if two or more are confined
                    together in a limited space they invariably fight fiercely, the fallen becoming
                    the food of the victorious. They also, like the mole, are exceedingly voracious,
                    and soon die if deprived of food; and it is probably to insufficiency of food in
                    the early dry autumnal season that the well-known immense mortality amongst
                    these animals at that time of the year is due. The breeding season extends from
                    the end of April to the beginning of August, and five to seven, more rarely ten,
                    young may be found in their nests; they are naked, blind, and toothless at
                    birth, but soon run about snapping at everything within reach, the anterior pair
                    of incisors in both jaws quickly piercing the gum, followed by the last pair of
                    upper premolars, which at birth form prominent elevations in the gum.</p>
                <p>The alpine shrew <hi rend="italic">(S. alpinus,</hi> Schinz), restricted to the
                    alpine region of Central Europe, is slightly longer than the common shrew and
                    differs from it conspicuously in its much longer tail, which exceeds the length
                    of the head and body, in the colour of the fur, which is dark on both surfaces,
                    and in the large size of the upper antepenultimate premolar.</p>
                <p>The water-shrew <hi rend="italic">(Crossopus fodiens,</hi> Pall.), the third and
                    last species inhabiting England, differs from the common shrew in being
                    considerably larger with a shorter and much broader muzzle, comparatively
                    smaller eyes, and larger feet adapted for swimming,—the sides of the feet and
                    toes being provided with comb-like fringes of stiff hairs. The tail is longer
                    than the body (without the head) and possesses a well-developed swimming fringe
                    of moderately long regularly ranged hairs, which extend along the middle of its
                    flat under surface from the end of its basal third to its extremity. The fur of
                    the body is long and very dense, varying much in colour in different
                    individuals, and this has given rise to descriptions of many nominal species;
                    the prevailing shades are dark, almost black, brown above, beneath more or less
                    bright ashy tinged with yellowish; occasionally, sometimes in the same brood, we
                    find some individuals with the under surface more or less dark coloured. In the
                    number as well as in the shape of the teeth the water-shrew differs from the
                    common shrew: there is a premolar less on each side above; the bases of the
                    teeth are muck more prolonged posteriorly; and their cusps are much less stained
                    brown, so that in old individuals with worn teeth they often appear altogether
                    white. This species resembles the otter in its aquatic habits, swimming and
                    diving with great agility. It frequents rivers and lakes, making its burrows in
                    the overhanging banks, from which when disturbed it escapes into the water. Its
                    food consists of the different species of water-insects and their larvae, small
                    crustaceans, and probably the fry of small fishes. It is generally distributed
                    throughout England, is less common in Scotland, but as yet it has not been
                    recorded in Ireland.</p>
                <p>The geographical range of the common shrew is exceedingly wide, extending
                    eastwards through Europe and Asia (north of the Himalayas) to North America. The
                    lesser shrew extends concomitantly through Europe and Asia to Saghalin Island;
                    and specimens of the water-shrew have been brought from different parts of
                    Europe and from Asia as far east as the Altai range. In Siberia the common shrew
                    is abundant in the snow-clad wastes about the Olenek river within the arctic
                    circle. Indeed the hardiness of this little animal, as well as of other species
                    of red-toothed shrews, is very remarkable. In Dr C. H. Merriam’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Mammals of the Adirondack Region</hi> we find the following note
                    on the habits of a common North American species <hi rend="italic">(Blarina
                    brevicauda)</hi> of an allied genus:—“The rigors of our northern winters seem to
                    have no effect in diminishing its activity, for it scampers about on the snow
                    during the severest weather, and I have known it to be out when the thermometer
                    indicated a temperature of - 20° Fahr. It makes long journeys over the snow,
                    burrowing down whenever it comes to an elevation that denotes the presence of a
                    log or stump, and I am inclined to believe that at this season it must feed
                    largely upon the chrysalides and larvae of insects that are always to be found
                    in such places.” Other species of red-toothed shrews are restricted chiefly to
                    North America, where they are found in much greater variety than in the Old
                    World, though <hi rend="italic">Crossopus</hi> is not represented. Its place is
                    taken by two species of the genus <hi rend="italic">Sorex (S. palustris,</hi>
                    Richardson, east of the Rocky Mountains, and <hi rend="italic">S.
                    hydrodromus,</hi> Dobson, from Unalaska Island), provided, like the water-shrew,
                    with pedal swimming fringes, but with the unfringed tail and dentition of the
                    common shrew,—the first-named being about as large as the water-shrew, while the
                    Unalaska species scarcely exceeds the size of the lesser shrew. Of the American
                    forms <hi rend="italic">S. bendiri,</hi> Merriam, is by far the largest known
                    species of the genus. In it, as in many others inhabiting North America, the
                    canine shows a tendency to diminish in size, which is more pronounced in <hi
                    rend="italic">S. richardsonii,</hi> Bachm., and in <hi rend="italic">S. vagrans,
                    Cooper</hi>; in <hi rend="italic">S. hoyi,</hi> Baird, it is rudimentary, and in
                    <hi rend="italic">S. crawfordi,</hi> Baird, altogether absent. The diminutive
                    <hi rend="italic">S. personatus,</hi> Geoff., widely distributed throughout
                    temperate North America, resembles <hi rend="italic">S. pygmaeus</hi> in its
                    small size. Other red-toothed shrews belonging to the allied genus <hi
                    rend="italic">Blarvna,</hi> distinguished from <hi rend="italic">Sorex</hi> by
                    their dentition and by the remarkable shortness of the tail, are very common on
                    and characteristic of the North American continent. All the red-toothed shrews
                    (except the aquatic forms) closely resemble one another in habits, and Dr
                    Merriam has made the highly interesting discovery that the common short-tailed
                    North American shrew supplements its insectivorous fare by feeding on
                    beech-nuts, which will account for the generally very worn state of the teeth in
                    this species. In destroying great numbers of slugs, insects, and insect larvae
                    they greatly aid the farmer in the preservation of his crops and merit
                    protection. Although their penetrating odour renders them in a great measure
                    safe from the attacks of rapacious mammals, they are destroyed in large numbers
                    by nocturnal birds of prey. (G. E. D.)<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n870/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0870-0845"/></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
