<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0369-0350-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SAXO GRAMMATICUS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 21, page 350</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b46d5pd23">Heroes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4wp9tb5s">Historians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43j3985w">Danes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4dn3zx91">Anger</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:957686">Historians</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:955558">Heroes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1181638">Writing</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:808763">Anger</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n369/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SAXO GRAMMATICUS</label>, the celebrated Danish historian and
                    poet, belonged to a family of warriors, his father and grandfather having served
                    under king Valdemar I. (d. 1182). He himself was brought up for the clerical
                    profession, entered about 1180 the service of Archbishop Absalon as one of his
                    secretaries, and remained with him in that capacity until the death of Absalon
                    in 1201. At the instigation of the latter he began, about 1185, to write the
                    history of the Danish Christian kings from the time of Sven Estridsön, but later
                    Absalon prevailed on him to write also the history of the earlier, heathen
                    times, and to combine both into a great work, <hi rend="italic">Gesta
                    Danorum.</hi> The archbishop died before the work was finished, and therefore
                    the preface, written about 1208, is dedicated to his successor Archbishop
                    Andreas, and to King Valdemar II. Nothing else is known about Saxo’s life and
                    person; a chronicle of 1265 calls him “mine et urbanae eloquentiai clericus;"
                    and an epitome of his work from about 1340 describes him as “egregius
                    grammaticus, origine Sialandus that he was a native of Zealand is probably
                    correct, inasmuch as, whereas he often criticizes the Jutlanders and the
                    Scanians, he frequently praises the Zealanders. The surname of “Grammaticus” is
                    probably of later origin, scarcely earlier than 1500, apparently owing to a
                    mistake. The title of “provost (dean) of Roskilde,” given him in the 16th
                    century, is also probably incorrect, the historian being confounded with an
                    older contemporary, the provost of the same name. Saxo, from his apprenticeship
                    as the archbishop’s secretary, had acquired a brilliant but somewhat euphuistic
                    Latin style, and wrote fine Latin verses, but otherwise does not seem to have
                    had any very great learning or extensive reading. His models of style were
                    Valerius Maximus, Justin, and Martianus Capella, especially the last.
                    Occasionally he mentions Bede, Dudo, and Paulus Diaconus, but does not seem to
                    have studied them or any other historical works thoroughly, and he neither
                    understands nor is interested in scientific research, in general history, or
                    even in chronology. He wrote because he<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n372/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0372-0351"/> did not like his countrymen to be behind other
                    nations through the want of an historian, and because he washed to perpetuate
                    the record of the exploits of the Danes. His sources are partly Danish
                    traditions and old songs, partly the statements of Archbishop Absalon, partly
                    the accounts of Icelanders, and, lastly, some few earlier, but scanty, sources,
                    being lists of Danish kings and short chronicles, which furnished him with some
                    reliable chronological dates. He considered traditions as history, and therefore
                    made it his chief business to recount and arrange these, by the help of the
                    lists of the kings, into a connected whole. His work, therefore, is a loosely
                    connected series of biographies of Danish kings and heroes; he dwells with
                    predilection on those periods during which Danish kings were said to have made
                    great conquests, and he represents these conquerors as the paragons of their
                    times.</p>
                <p>The first nine books comprise “Antiquity,” that is, traditions of kings and
                    heroes of the half-mythical time up to about 950. Here we have traditions about
                    Fredfrode, about Amleth (Hamlet) and Fenge, about Rolf Krake, Hadding, the giant
                    Starkather, Harald Hildetann, and Ragnar Lodbrok. In this earlier history Saxo
                    has also embodied myths of national gods who in tradition had become Danish
                    kings, for instance, Balder and Hother, and of foreign heroes, likewise
                    incorporated in Danish history, as the Gothic Jarmunrik (A. S. Eormenríc), the
                    Anglian Vermund (A. S. Garmund) and Uffe (A. S. Offa), the German Hedin and
                    Hild, &amp;c. Frequently the narrative is interrupted by translations of poems,
                    which Saxo has used as authentic sources, although they are often only a few
                    generations older than himself. In the later books (x.-xvi.) of his work he
                    follows to a greater extent historical accounts, and the more he approaches his
                    own time the fuller and the more trustworthy his relation becomes; especially
                    brilliant is his treatment of the history of King Valdemar and of Absalon. But
                    his patriotism often makes him partial to his countrymen, and his want of
                    critical sense often blinds him to the historical truth.</p>
                <p>Saxo’s work was widely read during the Middle Ages, and several extracts of it
                    were made for smaller chronicles. It was published for the first time, from a
                    MS. afterwards lost, in Paris, 1514, by the Danish humanist Christiern Pedersen;
                    this edition was reprinted at Basel, 1534, and at Frankfort, 1576. Of later
                    editions may be mentioned that of Stephen Stephanius, Sorö, 1644, that of C. A.
                    Klotz, Leipsic, 1771, and that of P. E. Müller and J. M. Velschow, Copenhagen,
                    1839. No complete MS. any longer exists; yet of late small fragments have been
                    found of three MSS. The most remarkable of these is the fragment found at
                    Angers, in France, written shortly after 1200, perhaps by Saxo himself or under
                    his superintendence; here several corrections are found above the lines, showing
                    how the author varied and polished his Latin style.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
