<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0921-0271-0252-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SAMUEL, Books of (9th edition, volume 21, page
                    252)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795379">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795510">Accounts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1179191">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:918547">Exploitation</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204236">Israel</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n271/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SAMUEL, <hi rend="smallcaps">Books of</hi></label>. The
                    Hebrew Book of Samuel, like the Hebrew Book of Kings, is in modern Bibles
                    divided into two books, after the Septuagint and Vulgate, whose four books of
                    “kingdoms” answer to the Hebrew books of Samuel and Kings. The connexion between
                    the books of Samuel and Kings has been spoken of in the article <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Kings</hi> (<hi rend="italic">q.v</hi>.). These two books,
                    together with Judges, are made up of a series of extracts and abstracts from
                    various sources worked over from time to time by successive editors, and freely
                    handled by copyists down to a comparatively late date, as the variations between
                    the Hebrew text and the Septuagint show. The main redaction of Judges and Kings
                    has plainly been made under the influence of the ideas of the book of
                    Deuteronomy, and it was in connexion with this redaction that the history from
                    the accession of Solomon onwards was marked off as a separate book (see <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Kings).</hi> In Samuel the Deuteronomistic hand is much
                    less prominent, but in 1 Sam. vii. 2-4, and in the speech of Samuel, ch. xii.,
                    its characteristic pragmatism is clearly recognizable; the nature of the old
                    narrative did not invite frequent insertions of this kind throughout the story.
                    So, too, the chronological system which runs through Judges and Kings is not
                    completely carried out in Samuel, though its influence can be traced (1 Sam. iv.
                    18, vii. 2, xiii. 1 <hi rend="italic">sq</hi>., xxvii. 7, 2 Sam. ii 10 <hi
                        rend="italic">sq.,</hi> v. 4 <hi rend="italic">sq.).</hi> In 1 Sam. xiii. 1,
                    in the note “Saul was——years old when he became king and reigned [two] years
                    over Israel” (lacking in LXX.), one of the numbers has been left blank and the
                    other has been falsely filled up by a mere error of the text; the similar note
                    in 2 Sam. ii. 10 seems also to have been filled up at random; it contradicts and
                    disturbs the context. But, though the book of Samuel has been much less
                    systematically edited than Kings, unsystematic additions to and modifications of
                    the oldest narratives were made from time to time on a very considerable scale,
                        and<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n272/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0921-0272-0253"/> in this book, as in Judges, we not seldom
                    find two accounts of the same events which not only differ in detail but plainly
                    are of very different date.</p>
                <p>The book as a whole may be divided into three main sections:—(1) <hi
                        rend="italic">Samuel and Saul,</hi> 1 Sam. i.-xiv.; (2) <hi rend="italic"
                        >The rise and kingdom of David,</hi> 1 Sam. xv.-2 Sam. viii.; (3)</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The personal history of David’s court at Jerusalem</hi> (mainly
                    from a single source, which also includes 1 Kings i., ii.), 2 Sam. ix.-xx.
                    Finally, the appendix, 2 Sam. xxi.-xxiv., must have been added after the book of
                    Kings had been separated from the context to which 1 Kings i., ii. originally
                    belonged. As the greater part of the book of Samuel is occupied with the history
                    of David, which has been discussed at length in his article, and with that of
                    Samuel and Saul, the chief points of which have been critically examined in the
                    article <hi rend="smallcaps">Israel,</hi> a very brief resume of the contents of
                    each of the main sections must here suffice.</p>
                <p>I. The story of Samuel’s birth, consecration to the service of the sanctuary at
                    Shiloh, and prophetic calling (1 Sam. i.-iii.) connects itself through the
                    prophecy of the rejection of the house of Eli (iii. 11 <hi rend="italic"
                        >sq.</hi>) with the history of the disaster of Ebenezer and the capture and
                    restoration of the ark (iv. 1-vii. 1). But the second of these two sections does
                    not seem to have been originally written as the sequel to chaps, i.-iii.; in it
                    we lose sight of Samuel and his prophecy altogether. The song of Hannah (ii.
                    1-10) and the prophecy of the nameless man of God (ii. 27-36) are later
                    insertions (see Wellliausen-Bleek, <hi rend="italic">EM.,</hi> p. 207).</p>
                <p>Chap, vii., with its Deuteronomistic introduction (verses 2-4) and its account of
                    a victory at Ebenezer (the counterpart of the defeat in chap, iv.) which
                    delivered Israel from the Philistines during all the days of Samuel, is
                    inconsistent with the position of the Philistine power at the accession of Saul.
                    The chapter in its present form must be late, though hardly post-exilic, and it
                    is the necessary introduction to the later and less authentic account of the way
                    in which Saul came to the kingdom (chaps, viii., x. 17- 27, xii.). It should be
                    noted, however, that, though Samuel is taken by the late narrator to have a
                    widespread authority, inconsistent with the facts disclosed in the older
                    narrative of the choice of Saul, the sphere assigned to him in vii. 16, 17 is
                    very narrow and agrees with chap. ix.</p>
                <p>Of the beginnings of the kingship of Saul we have a twofold account, the older
                    being that in ix. 1-x. 16, xi. The relative value of the two accounts has been
                    already discussed in <hi rend="smallcaps">Israel,</hi> vol. xiii. p. 403. The
                    older history is continued in chaps, xiii., xiv., but here xiii. <hi
                        rend="italic">7b—</hi> 15—a doublette of the account of the rejection of
                    Saul in chap. xiv.—is certainly foreign to the original context. The summary of
                    Saul’s exploits in xiv. 47 <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi> is written by an admirer,
                    who appears to ascribe to him some of David’s victories. But this does not
                    affect the value of the preceding more detailed narrative, which is plainly
                    based on a full and authentic tradition.</p>
                <p>II. The account of the campaign against Amalek (chap, xv.) does not merely supply
                    details supplementary to xiv. 48 but puts the war with Agag in quite a different
                    light by laying the chief weight on Saul’s disobedience to Samuel and rejection
                    by the prophet. This passage is closely allied to 1 Sam. xxviii. 3-25, which,
                    however, is no part of the original story of Saul’s defeat and. death, as
                    appears by comparing the position of the two armies in xxviii. 4 and xxix. 1.
                    Chap, xv., in like manner, is probably no original part of the narrative of
                    David’s rise, to which it now forms the introduction, and both passages, though
                    relatively ancient additions, represent a type of religious thought and a view
                    of prophecy which can hardly be older than the epoch of Elisha (comp. <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Prophet,</hi> vol. xix. p. 816). The anointing of David
                    (xvi. 1-13) presupposes chap, xv., and is consistent with what follows only if
                    we suppose that the meaning of Samuel’s act was not understood at the time. The
                    older history repeatedly indicates that David’s kingship was predicted by a
                    divine oracle, but would hardly lead us to place the prediction so early (1 Sam.
                    xxv. 30, 2 Sam. iii. 9, v. 2 compared with 1 Sam. xvii. 28, xviii. 23).</p>
                <p>The story of David’s introduction to Saul is told in two forms (xvi. 14-23; xvii.
                    1-xviii. 5). In the former David is already a man of approved courage and parts
                    when he is attracted to the court; in the latter he is an obscure and untried
                    shepherd lad (as in chap, xvi.) when he volunteers to meet Goliath. In the
                    Hebrew text the contradiction between the two accounts is absolute, but the
                    Septuagint omits xvii. 12-31, xvii. 55-xviii. 5, which greatly lessens if it
                    does not entirely remove the difficulty.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p>A further difficulty is caused by 2 Sam. xxi. 19, which
                            makes Elhanan the Bethlehemite slayer of Goliath.</p></note> The rise of
                    Saul’s jealousy against David (xviii. 6-30) and the open breach between them,
                    with David’s flight from the court (xix., xx.), are very confused in the Hebrew
                    text. Some serious difficulties are escaped by following the Septuagint
                    recension, but others remain, and there is a good deal of confusion also in the
                    accounts of David’s life as an outlaw (xxi.-xxvi.) and with Achish (xxvii.). For
                    details see <hi rend="smallcaps">David,</hi> vol. vi. p. 838 <hi rend="italic"
                        >sq.</hi> The narrative is largely made up of detached anecdotes, and
                    sometimes there were two divergent anecdotes based on a single incident. This is
                    clear as regards the two stories of David’s generosity to Saul (xxiv., xxvi.)
                    and still more clear where the LXX. omits one of two parallel anecdotes (see <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">David,</hi><hi rend="italic">ut supra},</hi> while the same
                    account may perhaps be given of the twofold narrative of David’s flight from
                    Saul and of his betaking himself to Achish. At the same time there is sufficient
                    connexion to show that the doublettes and additions are strung on an original
                    thread of continuous history—a history of David, which becomes more free from
                    foreign accretions at the point when the outlaw and refugee acquires, through
                    the death of Saul, a position of commanding importance. Saul’s defeat and death
                    (1 Sam. xxviii. 1, 2, xxx.) are related as part of the history of David, which
                    runs on from this point with little evidence of editorial additions to the close
                    of 2 Sam. v. The summary account of David’s war and government in 2 Sam. viii.
                    appears to be the continuation of the same document; chaps, vi. and vii., on the
                    other hand, seem to have an independent source.</p>
                <p>III. The history of David’s court, a vivid picture of events which must be
                    referred in substance if not in form to a contemporary observer, is in its
                    origin a distinct book from the life of David that closes with 2 Sam. viii. It
                    extends over 2 Sam. ix.- 1 Kings ii. with very little appearance of
                    interpolation except the great appendix, 2 Sam. xxi.-xxiv., and is throughout
                    one of the most admirable remains of ancient history.</p>
                <p>The appendix is made up of various pieces,—chap. xxiv. appearing to attach itself
                    directly to xxi. 1-14, while xxi. 15 <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi> is akin in
                    subject to xxiii. 8 <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi>; the two poems, chap. xxii.
                    (Psalm xviii.) and xxiii. 1-7, have no relation to the context, so that we can
                    only say of them that they were accepted as Davidic at the time—posterior to the
                    Deuteronomistic redaction—when the miscellaneous matter of the appendix was
                    incorporated with our book.</p>
                <p>In this rapid sketch it has not been attempted to notice all the minor marks of
                    editorial retouching found in one or both of the two great recensions of the
                    text, For all details the reader must refer principally to Wellhausen’s repeated
                    studies of the hook, first in his <hi rend="italic">Text der Bucher
                        Samuelis,</hi> 1871, then in the fourth edition of Bleek's <hi rend="italic"
                        >Einleitung,</hi> 1878, and finally in his <hi rend="italic">Prolegomena to
                        the History of Israel</hi> (Eng. tr., 1885). Of earlier works on the subject
                    the relative parts of Ewald's <hi rend="italic">Geschichte</hi> are the most
                    important. The commentaries of Thenius (1st ed. 1842, 2d ed. 18G4) and Keil
                    (1864, Eng. tr. 1866) are not very satisfactory. In English Prof. Kirkpatrick’s
                    short commentary (in the Cambridge Bible for Schools) will be found useful. See
                    also F. H. Woods in <hi rend="italic">Studia Biblica,</hi> Oxford, 1885.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
