<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0921-0178-0161-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ST DENIS (9th edition, volume 21, page 161)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4086371g">Huguenots</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bn9x31n">Tombs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49k45s7h">Basilicas</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1152439">Tombs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:828176">Basilicas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:829042">Bays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1743863">Transepts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1080735">Prussians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:962708">Huguenots</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n178/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ST DENIS</label>, a town of France, in the department of
                    Seine, 4 1/2 miles north of Paris by the Northern Railway, which there divides
                    into two branches leading respectively to Pontoise and Creil, is now a great
                    manufacturing centre for machinery, boats, railway carriages, chemical products,
                    printed goods, candles, beer, leather, and flour. Many of the works are supplied
                    with water from the Crould and the Rouillon, which there fall into the Seine;
                    and a canal extends from the Seine to La Villette, the great inner harbour of
                    Paris. In 1881 the population was 43,127. The name and fame of the town are
                    derived from the abbey founded by Dagobert on the spot where St Denis, the
                    apostle of Paris, was interred (see below). The west front was built between
                    1137 and 1140. The right-hand tower is almost pure Romanesque; that on the left
                    was Gothic, and its spire was carried to a height of 280 feet, but it was struck
                    by lightning in 1837 and its reconstruction effected in so clumsy a manner that
                    it had to be taken down till it was on a level with the roof of the nave. The
                    rose window, now occupied by a clock face, dates from the 13th century. Under
                    one of the three rows of arches above the main entrance runs an inscription
                    recording the erection of the church by Suger with abbatial funds and its
                    consecration in 1140. The porch formed by the first three bays of the church
                    contains some remains of the basilica of Pippin the Short. The nave proper (235
                    feet long and 57 wide) has seven bays, and dates, as well as most of the choir
                    and transepts, from the reign of St Louis. The gallery of the triforium is of
                    open work and is filled in with glass. The secondary apse <hi rend="italic"
                        >(rond-point)</hi> and its semicircular chapels (consecrated on 11th June
                    1144) are considered as the first perfected attempt at Gothic. The transepts
                    have fine 13th-century façades, each with two unfinished towers; if the plan had
                    been fully carried out there would have been six towers besides a central flèche
                    in lead. In the chapels of the nave are the tombs of Louis XII. and Anne of
                    Brittany (1591); of Henry II. and Catherine de’ Medici, a masterpiece by Germain
                    Pilon; of Louis of Orleans and Valentine of Milan, from the old church of the
                    Celestines at Paris; of Francis I. and Claude of France, one of the most
                    splendid tombs of the Renaissance, executed under the direction of Philibert
                    Delorme; and that of Dagobert, which, though considerably dilapidated, ranks as
                    one of the most curious of mediaeval (13th-century) works of art. In the apse
                    some stained glass of the time of Suger still remains. The crypt dates partly
                    from Charlemagne and partly from Suger. In the centre is the vault where the
                    coffin of the dead king used to lie until, to make room for that of his
                    successor, it was removed to its final resting-place. It is at present occupied
                    by the coffin of Louis XVIII., the last sovereign whose body was borne to St
                    Denis and the only one whose ashes have been respected. Besides some fine
                    statues, the crypt contains the Bourbon vault, in which were deposited the
                    remains of Louis XVI. and Marie Antoinette, or at least whatever of them was
                    recoverable from the cemetery of La Madeleine, where the Chapelle</p>
                <p>Expiatoire now stands. The treasury of St Denis has been despoiled of its richest
                    possessions, including the books now in the National Library; but it still
                    contains crosses, altar-pieces, and reliquaries, notably those of St Denis and
                    his two companions, Rusticus and Eleutherius, the three patrons of the basilica.
                    The chapter of St Denis is usually composed of emeritus bishops with the title
                    of canons; but the institution is about to be abolished (1886). St Denis
                    possesses a fine town-house and a poorhouse (300 beds). Its three forts formed
                    part of the Parisian enceinte in 1870-71, and from 23d to 26th January 1871 the
                    place was bombarded by the Prussians, who did considerable damage to the
                    basilica.</p>
                <p>St Denis, the ancient Catulliacum, was a town of no pretensions till the founding
                    of its abbey. The process of rebuilding begun in the 12th century by Abbé Suger
                    was completed under Philip the Bold. In the meantime St Louis caused mausoleums
                    to be erected with figures of the princes already buried in the abbey; and from
                    his time onwards to Henry II. every monarch in succession had his monument.
                    Louis XIV. reduced the abbey to the rank of a priory; and at the Revolution it
                    was suppressed, the tombs being violated and the church sacked (1793). Two years
                    later all the remains and fragments that could be recovered were collected in
                    the museum of the Petits Augustines at Paris; but the bronze tombs had been
                    melted down, the stained-glass windows shattered, and large numbers of
                    interesting objects stolen or lost. Napoleon established in the monastery a
                    school for daughters of the members of the Legion of Honour, which has continued
                    to flourish. Louis XVIII. caused all the articles belonging to St Denis to be
                    brought back from the museums to their original site, and added numerous other
                    monuments from the suppressed abbeys. But it was not till after 1818 that, under
                    the intelligent direction of Viollet le Duc, the damage inflicted by
                    revolutionist and unskillful restorer was repaired and the basilica recovered
                    its original appearance. Charles the Bold instituted the famous fair of Landit,
                    which was transferred from the neighbouring plain to St Denis itself in 1552,
                    and is still held in the town. Sheep and parchment were formerly the staples.
                    The abbey was pillaged by Charles the Bad, king of Navarre, in 1358, by the
                    Burgundians and Flemings in 1111, and by the English in 1130. A sanguinary
                    battle, in which the Catholic leader Constable Anne de Montmorency found victory
                    and death, was fought between Huguenots and Catholics in the neighbourhood on
                    10th November 1567.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
