<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0179-0162-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SAINTE-BEUVE, Charles Augustin</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 21, page 162</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b42b8vc0z">Globes</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93f1p">Jacobins</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4w08wh24">Portraits</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4s756m31">Saints</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62f7n">Reading</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hn48">Mothers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1090626">Reading</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term n="16" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:943553">Globes</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:981035">Jacobins</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n179/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SAINTE-BEUVE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles
                    Augustin</hi></label> (1804-1869), the most notable critic of our time, was born
                    at Boulogne-sur-Mer on 23d December 1804. He was a posthumous child,—his father,
                    a native of Picardy, and controller of town-dues at Boulogne, having married in
                    this same year, at the age of fifty-two, and died before the birth of his son.
                    The father was a man of literary tastes, and used to read, like his son, pencil
                    in hand; his copy of the Elzevir edition of Virgil, covered with his notes, was
                    in his son’s possession, and is mentioned by him in one of his poems.
                    Sainte-Beuve’s mother was half English,—her father, a mariner of Boulogne,
                    having married an Englishwoman. The little Charles Augustin was brought up by
                    his mother, who never remarried, and an aunt, his father’s sister, who lived
                    with her. They were poor, but the boy, having learnt all he could at his first
                    school at Boulogne, persuaded his mother to send him, when he was near the age
                    of fourteen, to finish his education at Paris. He boarded with a M. Landry, and
                    had for a fellow-boarder and intimate friend Charles Neate, afterwards fellow of
                    Oriel College and member of parliament for the city of Oxford. From M. Landry’s
                    boarding-house he attended the classes, first of the Collége Charlemagne, and
                    then of the Collège Bourbon, winning the head prize for history at the first,
                    and for Latin verse at the second. In 1823 he began to study medicine, and
                    continued the study with diligence and interest for nearly four years, attending
                    lectures on anatomy and physiology and walking the hospitals. But meanwhile a
                    Liberal newspaper, the <hi rend="italic">Globe,</hi> was founded in 1827 by M.
                    Dubois, one of Sainte-Beuve’s old teachers at the Collège Charlemagne. M. Dubois
                    called to his aid his former pupil, who, now quitting the study of medicine,
                    contributed historical and literary articles to the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Globe,</hi> among them two, which attracted the notice of Goethe, on Victor
                    Hugo’s <hi rend="italic">Odes and Ballads.</hi> These articles led to a
                    friendship with Victor Hugo and to Sainte-Beuve’s connexion with the romantic
                    school of poets, a school never entirely suited to his nature. In the <hi
                    rend="italic">Globe</hi> appeared also his interesting articles on the French
                    poetry of the l6th century, which in 1828 were collected and published in a
                    volume, and followed by a second volume containing selections from Ronsard. In
                    1829 he made his first venture as a poet with the <hi rend="italic">Pie,
                    Poesies, et Pensées de Joseph Delorme.</hi> His own name did not appear; but
                    Joseph Delorme, that “Werther in the shape of Jacobin and medical student,” as
                    Guizot called him, was the Sainte-Beuve of those days himself. About the same
                    time was founded the <hi rend="italic">Revue de Paris,</hi> and Sainte-Beuve
                    contributed the opening article, with Boileau for its subject. In 1830 came his
                    second volume of poems, the <hi rend="italic">Consolations,</hi> a work on which
                    Sainte-Beuve looked back in later life with a special affection. To himself it
                    marked and expressed, he said, that epoch of his life to which he could with
                    most pleasure return, and at which he could like best that others should see
                    him. But the critic in him grew to prevail more and more and pushed out the
                    poet. In 1831 the <hi rend="italic">Revue des Deux Mondes</hi> was founded in
                    rivalry with the <hi rend="italic">Revue de Paris,</hi> and from the first
                    Sainte-Beuve was one of the most active and important contributors. He brought
                    out his novel of <hi rend="italic">Volupté</hi> in 1834, his third and last
                    volume of poetry, the <hi rend="italic">Pensées d'Août,</hi> in 1837.</p>
                <p>He himself thought that the activity which he had in the meanwhile exercised as a
                    critic, and the offence which in some quarters his criticism had given, were the
                    cause of the less favourable reception which this volume received. He had long
                    meditated a book on Port Royal. At the end of 1837 he quitted France, accepting
                    an invitation from the academy of Lausanne, where in a series of lectures his
                    work on Port Royal came into its first form of being. In the summer of the next
                    year he returned to Paris to revise and give the final shape to his work, which,
                    however, was not completed for twenty years. In 1840 M. Cousin, then minister of
                    public instruction, appointed him one of the keepers of the Mazarin Library, an
                    appointment which gave him rooms at the library, and, with the money earned by
                    his pen, made him for the first time in his life easy in his circumstances, so
                    that, as he afterwards used to say, he had to buy rare books in order to spend
                    his income. A more important consequence of his easier circumstances was that he
                    could study freely and largely. He returned to Greek, of which a French
                    schoolboy brings from his <hi rend="italic">lycée</hi> no great store. With a
                    Greek teacher, M. Pantasides, he read and re-read the poets in the original, and
                    thus acquired, not, perhaps, a philological scholar’s knowledge of them, but a
                    genuine and invaluable acquaintance with them as literature. His activity in the
                    <hi rend="italic">Revue des Deux Mondes</hi> continued, and articles on Homer,
                    Theocritus, Apollonius of Rhodes, and Meleager were fruits of his new Greek
                    studies. He wrote also a very good article in 1844 on the Italian poet Leopardi;
                    but in general his subjects were taken from the great literature which he knew
                    best, that of his own country,—its literature both in the past and in the
                    contemporary present. Seven volumes of “Portraits,” contributed to the <hi
                    rend="italic">Revue de Paris</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Revue des Deux
                    Mondes,</hi> exhibit his work in the years from 1832 to 1848, a work constantly
                    increasing in range and value. In 1844 he was elected to the French Academy as
                    successor to Casimir Delavigne, and was received there at the beginning of 1845
                    by Victor Hugo.</p>
                <p>From this settled and prosperous condition the revolution of February 1848
                    dislodged him. In March of that year was published an account of secret-service
                    money distributed in the late reign, and Sainte-Beuve was put down as having
                    received the sum of one hundred francs. The smallness of the sum would hardly
                    seem to suggest corruption; it appears probable that the money was given to cure
                    a smoky chimney in his room at the Mazarin Library, and was wrongly entered as
                    secret-service money. But Sainte-Beuve, who piqued himself on his independence
                    and on a punctilious delicacy in money matters, was indignant at the entry, and
                    thought the proceedings of the minister of public instruction and his officials,
                    when he demanded to have the matter sifted, tardy and equivocal. He resigned his
                    post at the Mazarin and accepted an offer from the Belgian Government of a chair
                    of French literature in the university of Liège. There he gave the series of
                    lectures on Chateaubriand and his contemporaries which was afterwards (in 1861)
                    published in two volumes. He liked Liège, and the Belgians would have been glad
                    to keep him; but the attraction of Paris carried him back there in the autumn of
                    1849. Louis Napoleon was then president. Disturbance was ceasing; a time of
                    settled government, which lasted twenty years and corresponds with the second
                    stage of Sainte-Beuve’s literary activity, was beginning. Dr Véron, the editor
                    of the <hi rend="italic">Constitutionnel,</hi> proposed to him that he should
                    supply that newspaper with a literary article for every Monday; and thus the <hi
                    rend="italic">Causeries du Lundi</hi> were started. They at once succeeded, and
                    “gave the signal,” as Sainte-Beuve himself says with truth, “for the return of
                    letters.” Sainte-Beuve now lived in the small house in the Rue Mont-Parnasse
                    (No. 11) which he occu<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n180/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0180-0163"/>pied for the remainder of his life, and where in
                    1850 his mother, from whom he seems to have inherited his good sense, tact, and
                    finesse, died at the age of eighty-six. For three years he continued writing
                    every Monday for the <hi rend="italic">Constitutionnel;</hi> then he passed,
                    with a similar engagement, to the <hi rend="italic">Moniteur.</hi> In 1857 his
                    Monday articles began to be published in volumes, and by 1862 formed a
                    collection in fifteen volumes; they afterwards were resumed under the title of
                    <hi rend="italic">Nouveaux Lundis,</hi> which now make a collection of thirteen
                    volumes more. In 1854 M. Fortoul nominated him to the chair of Latin poetry at
                    the College of France. His first lecture there was received with interruptions
                    and marks of disapprobation by many of the students, displeased at his adherence
                    to the empire; at a second lecture the interruption was renewed. Sainte-Beuve
                    had no taste for public speaking and lecturing; his <hi rend="italic">frontis
                    mollities,</hi> he said, unfitted him for it. He was not going to carry on a war
                    with a party of turbulent students; he proposed to resign, and when the minister
                    would not accept his resignation of his professorship he resigned its
                    emoluments. The <hi rend="italic">Étude sur Virgile,</hi> a volume published in
                    1857, contains what he had meant to be his first course of lectures. He was
                    still a titular official of public instruction; and in 1858 his services were
                    called for by M. Rouland, then minister of public instruction, as a lecturer <hi
                    rend="italic">(maître de conférences)</hi> on French literature at the École
                    Normale Supérieure. This work he discharged with assiduity and success for four
                    years. In 1859 he was made commander of the Legion of Honour, having twice
                    previously to 1848 refused the cross. During the years of his official
                    engagement his Monday contributions to the <hi rend="italic">Moniteur</hi> had
                    no longer been continuous; but in 1862 an arrangement was proposed by which he
                    was to return to the <hi rend="italic">Constitutionnel</hi> and again supply an
                    article there every Monday. He consented, at the age of fifty-seven, to try this
                    last pull, as he called it, this “dernier coup de collier”; he resigned his
                    office at the École Normale and began the series of his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Nouveaux Lundis.</hi> They show no falling off in vigour and resource from the
                    <hi rend="italic">Causeries.</hi> But the strain upon him of his weekly labour
                    was great. “I am not a <hi rend="italic">monsieur</hi> nor a gentleman,” he
                    writes in 1864, “but a workman by the piece and by the hour.” “I look upon
                    myself as a player forced to go on acting at an age when he ought to retire, and
                    who can see no term to his engagement.” He had reason to hope for relief. Except
                    himself, the foremost literary men in France had stood aloof from the empire and
                    treated it with a hostility more or less bitter. He had not been hostile to it:
                    he had accepted it with satisfaction, and had bestowed on its official journal,
                    the <hi rend="italic">Moniteur,</hi> the lustre of his literature. The prince
                    Napoleon and the princess Mathilde were his warm friends. A senatorship was
                    mentioned; its income of £1600 a year would give him opulence and freedom. But
                    its coming was delayed, and the strain upon him continued for some time longer.
                    When at last in April 1865 he was made senator, his health "was already
                    seriously compromised. The disease of which he died, but of which the doctors
                    did not ascertain the presence until his body was opened after his death—the
                    stone—began to distress and disable him. He could seldom attend the meetings of
                    the senate; the part he took there, however, on two famous occasions, when the
                    nomination of M. Renan to the College of France came under discussion in 1867
                    and the law on the press in the year following, provoked the indignation of the
                    great majority in that conservative assembly. It delighted, however, all who
                    “belonged,” to use his own phrase, “to the diocese of free thought”; and he gave
                    further pleasure in this diocese by leaving at the beginning of 1869 the <hi
                    rend="italic">Moniteur,</hi> injudiciously managed by the Government and M.
                    Rouher, and contributing to a</p>
                <p>Liberal journal, the <hi rend="italic">Temps.</hi> His literary activity suffered
                    little abatement, but the attacks of his malady, though borne with courage and
                    cheerfulness, became more and more severe. Pain made him at last unable to sit
                    to write; he could only stand or lie. He died in his house in the Rue Mont
                    Parnasse on the 13th of October 1869. He had inherited an income of four
                    thousand francs a year from his mother, and he left it six thousand; to the
                    extent of eighty pounds a year and no further had literature and the senatorship
                    enriched him. By his will he left directions that his funeral was to be without
                    religious rites, quite simple, and with no speeches at the grave except a few
                    words of thanks from one of his secretaries to those present. There was a great
                    concourse; the Paris students, who had formerly interrupted him, came now to do
                    honour to him as a Liberal and a champion of free thought—a senator they could
                    not but admit—undeniably, alas, a senator, but <hi rend="italic">oh, si
                    peu!</hi> Yet his own account of himself is the best and truest,—an account
                    which lays no stress on his Liberalism, no stress on his championship of free
                    thought, but says simply: “Devoted to my profession as critic, I have tried to
                    be more and more a good, and, if possible, an able workman.”</p>
                <p>The work of Sainte-Beuve divides itself into three portions—his poetry, his
                    criticism before 1848, and his criticism after that year. His novel of <hi
                    rend="italic">Volupté</hi> may properly go with his poetry.</p>
                <p>We have seen his tender feeling for his poetry, and he always maintained that,
                    when the “integrating molecule,” the foundation of him as a man of letters, was
                    reached, it would be found to have a poetic character. And yet he declares, too,
                    that it is never without a sort of surprise and confusion that he sees his
                    verses detached from their context and quoted in public and in open day. They do
                    not seem made for it, he says. This admirable critic knew, indeed, what a
                    Frenchman may be pardoned for not willingly perceiving, and what even some
                    Englishmen try to imagine that they do not perceive, the radical inadequacy of
                    French poetry. For us it is extremely interesting to hear Sainte-Beuve on this
                    point, since it is to English poetry that he resorts in order to find his term
                    of comparison, and to award the praise which to French poetry he refuses. “Since
                    you are fond of the poets,” he writes to a friend, “I should like to see you
                    read and look for poets in another language, in English for instance. There you
                    will find the most rich, the most dulcet, and the most new poetical literature.
                    Our French poets are too soon read; they are too slight, too mixed, too
                    corrupted for the most part, too poor in ideas even when they have the talent
                    for strophe and line, to hold and occupy for long a serious mind.” And again:
                    “If you knew English you would have treasures to draw upon. They have a poetical
                    literature far superior to ours, and, above all, sounder, more full. Wordsworth
                    is not translated; these things are not to be translated; you must go to the
                    fountain-head for them. Let me give you this advice: learn English.”</p>
                <p>But, even as French poetry, Sainte-Beuve’s poetry had faults of its own. Critics
                    who found much in it to praise yet pronounced it a poetry “narrow, puny, and
                    stifled,” and its style “slowly dragging and laborious.” Here we touch on a want
                    which must no doubt be recognized in him, which he recognized in himself, and
                    whereby he is separated from the spirits who succeed in uttering their most
                    highly inspired note and in giving their full measure,—some want of flame, of
                    breath, of pinion. Perhaps we may look for the cause in a confession of his own:
                    “I have my weaknesses; they are those which gave to King Solomon his disgust
                    with everything and his satiety with life. I may have regretted sometimes
                    that<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n181/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0181-0164"/> I was thus extinguishing my fire, but I did not
                    ever pervert my heart.” It is enough for us to take his confession that he
                    extinguished or impaired his fire.</p>
                <p>Yet his poetry is characterized by merits which make it readable still and
                    readable by foreigners. So far as it exhibits the endeavour of the romantic
                    school in France to enlarge the vocabulary of poetry and to give greater freedom
                    and variety to the alexandrine, it has interest chiefly for readers of his own
                    nation. But it exhibits more than this. It exhibits already the genuine
                    Sainte-Beuve, the author who, as M. Duvergier de Hauranne said in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Globe</hi> at the time, “sent à sa manière et écrit comme il
                    sent,” the man who, even in the forms of an artificial poetry, remains always
                    “un penseur et un homme d’esprit.” That his Joseph Delorme was not the Werther
                    of romance, but a Werther in the shape of Jacobin and medical student, the only
                    Werther whom Sainte-Beuve by his own practical experience really knew, was a
                    novelty in French poetical literature, but was entirely characteristic of
                    Sainte-Beuve. All his poetry has this stamp of direct dealing with common
                    things, of plain unpretending reality and sincerity; and this stamp at that time
                    made it, as Béranger said, “a kind of poetry absolutely new in France.” It
                    found, therefore, with all its shortcomings, friends in men so diverse as
                    Béranger, Lamartine, Jouffroy, Beyle. Whoever is interested in Sainte-Beuve
                    should turn to it, and will be glad that he has done so.</p>
                <p>It has been the fashion to disparage the criticism of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Critiques et Portraits Littéraires,</hi> the criticism anterior to 1848, and to
                    sacrifice it, in fact, to the criticism posterior to that date. Sainte-Beuve has
                    himself indicated what considerations ought to be present with us in reading the
                    <hi rend="italic">Critiques et Portraits,</hi> with what reserves we should read
                    them. They are to be considered, he says, “rather as a dependency of the elegiac
                    and romanesque part of my work than as express criticisms.” “The <hi
                    rend="italic">Revue des Deux Mondes,”</hi> he adds, which published them, was
                    young in those days, “mixed a good deal of its wishes and its hopes with its
                    criticism, sought to explain and to stimulate rather than to judge. The
                    portraits there of contemporary poets and romance-writers can in general be
                    considered, whether as respects the painter or as respects the models, as
                    youthful portraits only; <hi rend="italic">juvenis juvenem, pinxit."</hi> They
                    have the copiousness and enthusiasm of youth; they have also its exuberance. He
                    judged in later life Chateaubriand, Lamartine, Victor Hugo, more coolly, judged
                    them differently. But the <hi rend="italic">Critiques et Portraits</hi> contain
                    a number of articles on personages, other than contemporary French poets and
                    romance-writers, which have much of the soundness of his later work, and, in
                    addition, an abundance and fervour of their own which are not without their
                    attraction. Many of these are delightful reading. The articles on the Greek
                    poets and on Leopardi have been already mentioned. Those on Boileau, Molière,
                    Daunou, and Fauriel, on Madame de la Fayette and Mademoiselle Aïssé, may be
                    taken as samples of a whole group which will be found to support perfectly the
                    test of reading, even after we have accustomed ourselves to the later work of
                    the master. Nay, his soberness and tact show themselves even in this earlier
                    stage of his criticism, and even in treating the objects of <hi rend="underline"
                    >his</hi> too fervid youthful enthusiasm. A special object of this was Victor
                    Hugo, and in the first article on him in the <hi rend="italic">Portraits
                    Contemporains</hi> we have certainly plenty of enthusiasm, plenty of exuberance.
                    We have the epithets “adorable,” “sublime,” “supreme,” given to Victor Hugo’s
                    poetry; we are told of “the majesty of its high and sombre philosophy.” All this
                    is in the vein of Mr George Gilfillan. But the article next following this, and
                    written only four years later, in 1835, is the article of a critic, and takes
                    the points of objection, seizes the weak side of</p>
                <p>Victor Hugo’s poetry, how much it has of what is “creux,” “sonore,” “artificiel,”
                    “voulu,” “théâtral,” “violent,” as distinctly as the author of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Causeries</hi> could seize it. “The Frank, energetic and subtle,
                    who has mastered to perfection the technical and rhetorical resources of the
                    Latin literature of the decadence,” is a description never to be forgotten of
                    Victor Hugo as a poet, and Sainte-Beuve launches it in this article, written
                    when he was but thirty years old, and still a painter of “portraits de jeunesse”
                    only.</p>
                <p>He had thus been steadily working and growing; nevertheless, 1848 is an epoch
                    which divides two critics in him of very unequal value. When, after that year of
                    revolution and his stage of seclusion and labour at Liége, he came back to Paris
                    in the autumn of 1849 and commenced in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Constitutionnel</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Causeries du Lundi,</hi> he was
                    astonishingly matured. Something of fervour, enthusiasm, poetry, he may have
                    lost, but he had become a perfect critic—a critic of measure, not exuberant; of
                    the centre, not provincial; of keen industry and curiosity, with “Truth” (the
                    word engraved in English on his seal) for his motto; moreover, with gay and
                    amiable temper, his manner as good as his matter,—the “critique souriant,” as,
                    in Charles Monselet’s dedication to him, he is called.</p>
                <p>Merely to say that he was all this is less convincing than to show, if possible,
                    by words of his own, in what fashion he was all this. The root of everything in
                    his criticism is his single-hearted devotion to truth. What he called “fictions”
                    in literature, in politics, in religion, were not allowed to influence him. Some
                    one had talked of his being tenacious of a certain set of literary opinions. “I
                    hold very little,” he answers, “to literary opinions; literary opinions occupy
                    very little place in my life and in my thoughts. What does occupy me seriously
                    is life itself and the object of it.” “I am accustomed incessantly to call my
                    judgments in question anew, and to re-cast my opinions the moment I suspect them
                    to be without validity.” “What I have wished” (in <hi rend="italic">Port
                    Royal)</hi> “is to say not a word more than I thought, to stop even a little
                    short of what I believed in certain cases, in order that my words might acquire
                    more weight as historical testimony.” To all exaggeration and untruth, from
                    whatever side it proceeded, he had an antipathy. “I turn my back upon the
                    Michelets and Quinets, but I cannot hold out my hand to the Veuillots.” When he
                    was writing for the <hi rend="italic">Moniteur</hi> he was asked by the manager
                    of the paper to review a book by an important personage, a contributor; his
                    answer is a lesson for critics and paints him exactly. “I should like to say
                    yes, but I have an insurmountable difficulty as to this author; he appears to me
                    to compromise whatever he touches; he is violent, and has not the tradition of
                    the things he talks about. Thus his article on Condorcet, which the <hi
                    rend="italic">Moniteur</hi> inserted, is odious and false; one may be severe
                    upon Condorcet, but not in that tone or in that note. The man has no <hi
                    rend="italic">insight—</hi> a defect which does not prevent him from having a
                    pen with which at a given moment he can flourish marvellously. But, of himself,
                    he is a gladiator and a desperado. I must tell you, my dear sir, that to have
                    once named him with compliment in some article of mine or other is one of my
                    self-reproaches as a man of letters. Let me say that he has not attacked me in
                    any way; it is a case of natural repulsion.”</p>
                <p>But Sainte-Beuve could not have been the great critic he was had he not had, at
                    the service of this his love of truth and measure, the conscientious industry of
                    a Benedictine. “I never have a holiday. On Monday towards noon I lift up my
                    head, and breathe for about an hour; after that the wicket shuts again and I am
                    in my prison cell for seven days.” The <hi rend="italic">Causeries</hi> were at
                    this price. They came once a week, and to write one of them as he<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n182/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0182-0165"/> wrote it was indeed a week’s work. The
                    “irresponsible indolent reviewer” should read his notes to his friend and
                    provider with books, M. Paul Chéron of the National Library. Here is a note
                    dated the 2d of January 1853: “Good-day and a happy New Year. To-day I set to
                    work on Grimm. A little dry; but after St François de Sales” (his Monday article
                    just finished) “one requires a little relief from roses. I have of Grimm the
                    edition of his <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> by M. Taschereau. I have
                    also the <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi> of Madame d’Épinay, where there are many
                    letters of his. But it is possible that there may be <hi rend="italic"
                    >notices</hi> of him mentioned in the bibliographical book of that German whose
                    name I have forgotten. I should like, too, to have the <hi rend="italic">first
                    editions</hi> of his <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi>; they came out in
                    successive parts.” Thus he prepared himself, not for a grand review article once
                    a quarter, but for a newspaper review once a week.</p>
                <p>His adhesion to the empire caused him to be habitually represented by the
                    Orleanists and the Republicans as without character and patriotism, and to be
                    charged with baseness and corruption. The Orleanists had, in a great degree,
                    possession of the higher press in France and of English opinion,—of Liberal
                    English opinion more especially. And with English Liberals his indifference to
                    parliamentary government was indeed a grievous fault in him; “you Whigs,” as
                    Croker happily says, “are like quack doctors, who have but one specific for all
                    constitutions.” To him either the doctrine of English Liberals, or the doctrine
                    of Republicanism, applied absolutely, was what he called a “fiction,” one of
                    those fictions which “always end by obscuring the truth.” Not even on M. de
                    Tocqueville’s authority would he consent to receive “les hypothèses dites les
                    plus honorables,”—“the suppositions which pass for the most respectable.” All
                    suppositions he demanded to sift, to see them at work, to know the place and
                    time and men to which they were to be applied. For the France before his eyes in
                    1849 he thought that something “solid and stable”— <hi rend="italic">un
                    mur,</hi> “a wall,” as he said—was requisite, and that the government of Louis
                    Napoleon supplied this wall. But no one judged the empire more independently
                    than he did, no one saw and enounced its faults more clearly; he described
                    himself as being, in his own single person, “the <hi rend="italic">gauche</hi>
                    of the empire,” and the description was just.</p>
                <p>To these merits of mental independence, industry, measure, lucidity, his
                    criticism adds the merit of happy temper and disposition. Goethe long ago
                    noticed that, whereas Germans reviewed one another as enemies whom they hated,
                    the critics of the <hi rend="italic">Globe</hi> reviewed one another as
                    gentlemen. This arose from the higher social development of France and from the
                    closer relations of literature with life there. But Sainte-Beuve has more, as a
                    critic, than the external politeness which once at any rate distinguished his
                    countrymen: he has a personal charm of manner due to a sweet and humane temper.
                    He complained of <hi rend="italic">un peu de dureté, "</hi> a certain dose of
                    hardness,” in the new generation of writers. The personality of an author had a
                    peculiar importance for him; the poetical side of his subjects, however latent
                    it might be, always attracted him and he always sought to extricate it. This was
                    because he had in himself the moderate, gracious, amiably <hi rend="italic"
                    >human</hi> instincts of the true poetic nature. “Let me beg of you,” he says in
                    thanking a reviewer who praised him, “to alter one or two expressions at any
                    rate. I cannot bear to have it said that I am the <hi rend="italic">first</hi>
                    in anything whatever, as a writer least of all; it is not a thing which can be
                    admitted, and these ways of classing people give offence.” Literary man and
                    loyal to the French Academy as he was, he can yet write to an old friend after
                    his election: “All these academies, between you and me, are pieces of
                    childishness; at any rate the French Academy is. Our least quarter of an hour of
                    solitary reverie or of serious talk, yours and mine, in our youth, was better
                    employed; but, as one gets old, one falls back into the power of these nothings;
                    only it is well to know that nothings they are.”</p>
                <p>Perhaps the best way to get a sense of the value and extent of the work done in
                    the last twenty years of his life by the critic thus excellently endowed is to
                    take a single volume of the <hi rend="italic">Causeries du Lundi,</hi> to look
                    through its list of subjects, and to remember that with the qualities above
                    mentioned all these subjects are treated. Any volume will serve; let us take the
                    fourth. This volume consists of articles on twenty-four subjects. Twenty of
                    these are the following :—Mirabeau and Sophie, Montaigne, Mirabeau and Comte de
                    la Marck, Mademoiselle de Scudéry, André Chénier as politician, Saint-Évremond
                    and Ninon, Joseph de Maistre, Madame de Lambert, Madame Necker, the Abbé Maury,
                    the Duc de Lauzun of Louis XVI.’s reign, Marie Antoinette, Buffon, Madame de
                    Maintenon, De Bonald, Amyot, Mallet du Pan, Marmontel, Chamfort, Ruhlière.
                    Almost every personage is French, it is true; Sainte-Beuve had a maxim that the
                    critic should prefer subjects which he possesses familiarly. But we should
                    recognize more fully than we do the immense importance and interest of French
                    literature. Certain productions of this literature Mr Saintsbury may misjudge
                    and overpraise; but he is entirely right in insisting on its immense importance.
                    More than any modern literature it has been in the most intimate correspondence
                    with the social life and development of the nation producing it. Now it so
                    happens that the great place of France in the world is very much due to her
                    eminent gift for social life and development; and this gift French literature
                    has accompanied, fashioned, perfected, and continues to reflect. This gives a
                    special interest to French literature, and an interest independent even of the
                    excellence of individual French writers, high as that often is. And nowhere
                    shall we find such interest more completely and charmingly brought out than in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Causeries du Lundi</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Nouveaux
                    Lundis</hi> of the consummate critic of whom we have been speaking. As a guide
                    to bring us to a knowledge of the French genius and literature he is
                    unrivalled,—perfect, so far as a poor mortal critic can be perfect, in knowledge
                    of his subject, in judgment, in tact, and tone. Certain spirits are of an
                    excellence almost ideal in certain lines; the human race might willingly adopt
                    them as its spokesmen, recognizing that on these lines their style and utterance
                    may stand as those, not of bounded individuals, but of the human race. So Homer
                    speaks for the human race, and with an excellence which is ideal, in epic
                    narration; Plato in the treatment at once beautiful and profound of
                    philosophical questions; Shakespeare in the presentation of human character;
                    Voltaire in light verse and ironical discussion. A list of perfect ones, indeed,
                    each in his own line! and we may almost venture to add to their number, in his
                    line of literary criticism, Sainte-Beuve. <hi rend="smallcaps">(m. a.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
