<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0921-0599-0574-04" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SCYTHE and SICKLE (9th edition, volume 21, page
                    574)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210278">Belgium</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:903991">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1132472">Steel</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1027064">Motion</term>
                    <term ref="fast:834091">Blades</term>
                    <term ref="fast:979089">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1134466">Straw</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x05xj9j">Steel</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4js9hb31">Motion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zz70">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vd7z">Graining</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4t14tp2r">Grain</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m03z186">Gallicisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c72h">Gauls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vr13">Stone</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n599/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SCYTHE <hi rend="smallcaps">and</hi> SICKLE</label>. Till the
                    invention of the reaping machine, which came into practical use only about the
                    middle of the 19th century, scythes and sickles were the sole reaping
                    implements. The scythe is worked with two hands with a swinging motion, while
                    the sickle or reaping hook is held in one hand and the reaper bends and cuts the
                    crop with a shearing or hitting motion. Of the two the sickle is the more
                    ancient, and indeed there is some reason to conclude that its use is coeval with
                    the cultivation of grain crops. Among the remains of the later Stone period in
                    Great Britain and on the European continent curved flint knives have
                    occasionally been found the form of which has led to the suggestion that they
                    were used as sickles. Sickles of bronze occur quite commonly among remains of
                    the early inhabitants of Europe. Some of these are deeply curved hooks, flat on
                    the under-side, and with a strengthening ridge or back on the upper surface,
                    while others are small curved knives, in form like the ordinary hedge-bill.
                    Among the ancient Egyptians toothed or serrated sickles of both bronze and iron
                    were used. Ancient Roman drawings show that both the scythe and the sickle were
                    known to that people, and Pliny makes the distinction plain.<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>“Of the sickle there are
                            two varieties, the Italian, which is the shorter and can he handled
                            among brushwood, and the two-handed Gallic sickle, which makes quicker
                            work of it when employed on their [the Gauls’] extensive domains; for
                            there they cut their grass only in the middle, and pass over the shorter
                            blades. The Italian mowers cut with the right hand only” <hi
                                rend="italic">(II. N.,</hi> xviii. 67).</p></note> Although both
                    implements have lost much of their importance since the general introduction of
                    mowing and reaping machinery, they are still used very extensively, especially
                    in those countries where small agricultural holdings prevail. The principal
                    modern forms are the toothed hook, the scythe hook, the Hainault scythe, and the
                    common scythe. The toothed hook, which was in general use till towards the
                    middle of the 19th century, consists of a narrow-bladed curved hook, having on
                    its cutting edge a series of fine close-set serratures cut like file-teeth, with
                    their edges inclined towards the heft or handle. Such sickles were formerly made
                    of iron edged with steel; but in recent times they came to be made of cast steel
                    entirely. Towards the middle of the century the toothed hook was gradually
                    supplanted by the scythe hook or smooth-edged sickle, a somewhat heavier and
                    broader-bladed implement, having an ordinary knife edge. Both these implements
                    were intended for “shearing” handful by handful, the crop being held in the left
                    hand and cut with the tool held in the right. A heavy smooth-edged sickle is
                    used for “bagging” or “clouting,”—an operation in which the hook is struck
                    against the straw, the left hand being used to gather and carry along the cut
                    swath. The Hainault scythe is an implement intermediate between the scythe
                        and<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n600/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0921-0600-0575"/> the sickle, being worked with one hand, and
                    the motion is entirely a swinging or bagging one. The implement consists of a
                    short scythe blade mounted on a vertical handle, and in using it the reaper
                    collects the grain with a crook, which holds the straw together till it receives
                    the cutting stroke of the instrument. The Hainault scythe is extensively used in
                    Belgium. The common hay scythe consists of a slightly curved broad blade varying
                    in length from 28 to 46 inches, mounted on a bent, or sometimes straight, wooden
                    sned or snathe, to which two handles are attached at such distances as enable
                    the workman, with an easy stoop, to swing the scythe blade along the ground, the
                    cutting edge being slightly elevated to keep it clear of the inequalities of the
                    surface. The grain-reaping scythe is similar, but provided with a cradle or
                    short gathering rake attached to the heel and following the direction of the
                    blade for about 12 inches. The object of this attachment is to gather the stalks
                    as they are cut and lay them in regular swaths against the line of
                    still-standing corn. The reaping scythe, instead of a long sned, has frequently
                    two helves, the right hand branching from the left or main helve and the two
                    handles placed about 2 feet apart. The best scythe blades are made from rolled
                    sheets of steel, riveted to a back frame of iron, which gives strength and
                    rigidity to the blade. On the Continent it is still common to mould and hammer
                    the whole blade out of a single piece of steel, but such scythes are difficult
                    to keep keen of edge. There is a great demand for scythes in Russia, chiefly
                    supplied from the German empire and Austria. The principal manufacturing centre
                    of scythes and sickles in the United Kingdom is Sheffield.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
