<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0761-0736-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SHAIRP, John Campbell</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 21, page 736</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:851811">Chairs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1166896">Views</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1075567">Presbyterians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1093898">Religions</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z139">Chairs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4w37kz4v">Teachers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4r20rx5q">Presbyterianism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g8x">Religion</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s53t">Normans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n761/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SHAIRP, <hi rend="smallcaps">John Campbell</hi></label>
                    (1819-1885), principal of the United College, St Andrews, and professor of
                    poetry at Oxford, was born at Houstoun House, Linlithgowshire, on July 30, 1819.
                    He was the third son of Major Norman Shairp of Houstoun and E. Binning, daughter
                    of J. Campbell of Kildaloig, Argyllshire. He was educated at Edinburgh Academy
                    and Glasgow University, where he gained the Snell exhibition, and entered at
                    Balliol College, Oxford, in 1840. while a student at Glasgow and an
                    undergraduate at Oxford it was his privilege to make many warm friends and to be
                    very widely loved. At Glasgow began his lifelong friendship with Dr Norman
                    M'Leod, while among those with whom he was most intimate at Oxford were the
                    names of Bradley, Coleridge, Temple, Clough, Walrond, Riddell, Prichard, and
                    Edwin Palmer. In 1842 he gained the Newdigate prize for a poem on Charles XII.,
                    and in 1844 took his degree with second class honours. During these years the
                    “Oxford movement” was at its height. Shairp’s earnest nature was greatly stirred
                    by Newman’s sermons, while Keble’s poetry spoke home to his heart; but, though
                    full of warm sympathy for many High Church views, he remained faithful to his
                    Presbyterian upbringing. After leaving Oxford he took a mastership at Rugby
                    under Dr Tait; here he sought loyally to develop Dr Arnold’s system by appealing
                    to the better feelings of his pupils and by giving them wide views of culture
                    and education. And in this he was successful, making among his pupils warm and
                    lasting friends. In 1857 he became assistant to the professor of humanity in the
                    university of St Andrews, and in 1861 he was appointed professor of that chair.
                    In 1853 he married Eliza, daughter of Henry Alexander Douglas, Kilhead,
                    Dumfriesshire, and had one surviving son, John Campbell, who became an advocate
                    at the Scottish bar. Shairp was highly respected by the more earnest students,
                    and much loved by some whose spiritual as well as mental nature he helped to
                    quicken. In 1864 he published <hi rend="italic">Kilmahoe, a Highland
                    Pastoral;</hi> in this his devotion to the scenery and the people of the
                    Scottish Highlands, where he always spent his vacations, found vent. In this
                    poem there was a directness, simplicity, and moral earnestness which showed the
                    true poet. In 1868 he republished some articles under the name of <hi
                    rend="italic">Studies in Poetry and Philosophy</hi>; this book showed him to be
                    one of the foremost critics of his day; the chief subjects it discussed were
                    Wordsworth, Coleridge, and Keble. He insisted strongly on the high spiritual
                    teaching and the deep poetical power of the great lake bard.</p>
                <p>While not blind to his many faults of style, his occasional puerility, and his
                    prosiness, he urged his claims as a unique interpreter of Nature and a spiritual
                    philosopher. Coleridge interested him as a poet, but much more as a religious
                    teacher; the <hi rend="italic">Aids to Reflection</hi> was a favourite present
                    to his young friends, and often gave a text for his deeper conversations. The
                    most popular essay was that on Keble, in which he gave a vivid sketch of
                    Newman’s influence in Oxford, while he spoke of the author of <hi rend="italic"
                    >The Christian Year</hi> with enthusiasm as a Christian teacher, and with
                    discerning criticism as a poet. In 1868 he was presented to the principalship of
                    the United College, vacant by the death of J. D. Forbes; he discharged the
                    duties of this office with conscientious zeal and interest, and also continued
                    to lecture from time to time on literary and ethical subjects. A course of the
                    lectures, published in 1870, <hi rend="italic">Culture and Religion,</hi> is one
                    of his most popular works. In 1873 he helped to edit the life of Principal
                    Forbes, and in 1874 he edited Dorothy Wordsworth’s charming <hi rend="italic"
                    >Recollections of a Tour in Scotland in 1803.</hi> In 1877 he was elected
                    professor of poetry at Oxford in succession to Sir F. H. Doyle. Of his lectures
                    from this chair the best were published in 1880 as <hi rend="italic">Aspects of
                    Poetry.</hi> In 1877 he had published <hi rend="italic">The Poetic
                    Interpretation of Nature,</hi> in which he enters fully into the “old quarrel,”
                    as Plato calls it, between science and poetry, and traces with great clear ness
                    and literary acumen the ideas of nature in all the chief Hebrew, classical, and
                    English poets. In 1879 he published a short life of Robert Burns. Such were
                    Shairp’s chief literary works, though many uncollected magazine articles and a
                    few poems show the versatility of his mind; attention may be specially called to
                    his article <hi rend="smallcaps">Keble</hi> in this <hi rend="italic"
                    >Encyclopaedia</hi> as an example of his critical power. In 1882 he was
                    re-elected to the poetry chair and discharged his duties there and at St Andrews
                    till the end of 1884; but his health had been frail for some time, and in March
                    1885 he sought a change of air in the Riviera. He returned in June somewhat
                    benefited, but he caught a chill in the autumn, and, after a short illness, died
                    at Ormsary, Argyllshire, on September 18, 1885.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
