<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0796-0771-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SHANGHAI</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 21, page 771</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="12" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:994503">Lays</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="16" ref="fasttopic:1115220">Shanghaiing</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:981987">Japanning</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:987266">Kiang</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="16" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xh65">Shanghaiing</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4c824k75">Japanning</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4nz80t3c">Lays</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tv2w">Canals</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4q52fm3g">Ports</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fastgeo:1206073">China</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1204082">Japan</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n796/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SHANGHAI</label>, a city of China. The native city of
                    Shanghai is situated in 31° 15' N. lat. and 121° 27Έ. long., and stands on the
                    left or western bank of the Hwang-p’u river, about twelve miles from the point
                    where that river empties itself into the estuary of the Yang-tsze-kiang. The
                    walls which surround it are about 3½ miles in circumference, and are pierced by
                    seven gates. The streets and thoroughfares may be said to illustrate all the
                    worse<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n797/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0797-0772"/> features of Chinese cities—dirt, closeness, and
                    absence of all sanitary arrangements; while the want of any building of
                    architectural or antiquarian interest robs the city of any redeeming traits. On
                    the eastern face of the city, between the walls and the river, stands the
                    principal suburb, off which the native shipping lies anchored. The native town
                    has thus nothing to recommend it except its geographical position. Situated in
                    the extreme eastern portion of the province of</p>
                <p>Kiang-soo, and possessing a good and commodious anchorage, as well as an easy
                    access to the ocean, it forms the principal port of central China.</p>
                <p>From the western wall of the city there stretches away a rich alluvial plain
                    extending over 45,000 square miles, which is intersected by numerous waterways
                    and great chains of lakes. The products of this fertile district, as well as the
                    teas and silks of more distant regions, find their natural outlet at Shanghai.
                    The looms of Soochow and the tea plantations of Gan-hwuy, together with the rice
                    of this “garden of China,” have for many years before treaty days supplied the
                    Shanghai junks with their richest freight. But though thus favourably situated
                    as an emporium of trade Shanghai did not attract the attention of foreign
                    diplomatists until the outbreak of the war of 1841, when the inhabitants
                    purchased protection from the bombarding propensities of Admiral Parker by the
                    payment of a ransom of one million taels. In the Nanking treaty, which was
                    signed in the following year, Shanghai was included among the four new ports
                    which were thrown open to trade by the terms of that document. In 1843 Sir
                    George Balfour, then Captain Balfour, was appointed British consul, and it was
                    on his motion that the site of the present English settlement, which is bounded
                    on the north by the Soochow creek, on the south by the Yang-king canal, and on
                    the east by the river, was chosen. The site, thus defined on its three sides (on
                    the west no boundary was marked out), is three-fifths of a mile in length, and
                    was separated from the native city by a narrow strip of land which was
                    subsequently selected as the site of the French settlement. Later again the
                    Americans established themselves on the other side of the Soochow creek, on a
                    piece of land fronting on the river, which there makes a sharp turn in an
                    easterly direction. At first merchants appeared disinclined to take advantage of
                    the opportunities offered them at Shanghai. “At the end of the first year of its
                    history as an open port Shanghai could count only 23 foreign residents and
                    families, 1 consular flag, 11 merchants’ houses, and 2 Protestant missionaries.
                    Only forty-four foreign vessels had arrived during the same period.”<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">The Treaty
                    Ports of China and Japan,</hi> by W. F. Mayer.</p></note> By degrees, however,
                    the manifold advantages as a port of trade possessed by Shanghai attracted
                    merchants of all nationalities; and from the banks of the Hwang-p’u arose lines
                    of hongs and handsome dwelling-houses, which have converted a reed-covered swamp
                    into one of the finest cities in the East,</p>
                <p>The number of foreigners, other than English, who took up their abode in the
                    English settlement at Shanghai made it soon necessary to adopt some more
                    catholic form of government than that supplied by an English consul who had
                    control only over British subjects, and by common agreement a committee of
                    residents, consisting of a chairman and six members, was elected by the renters
                    of land for the purposes of general municipal administration. It was expected
                    when the council was formed that the three settlements—the British, French, and
                    Americans —would have been incorporated into one municipality, but international
                    jealousy prevented the fulfilment of the scheme, and it was not until 1863 that
                    the Americans threw in their lot with the British. In 1853 the prosperity of the
                    settlements received a severe check in consequence of the capture of the native
                    city by a band of insurgents, who held possession of the walls from September in
                    that year to February 1855. This incident, though in many ways disastrous, was
                    the exciting cause of the establishment of the foreign customs service, which
                    has proved of such inestimable advantage to the Chinese Government. The
                    confusion into which the customs system was thrown by the occupation of the city
                    by the rebels induced the Chinese authorities to request the consuls of Great
                    Britain, France, and the United States to nominate three officers to superintend
                    the collection of the revenue. This arrangement was found to work so well that
                    on the reoccupation of the city the native authorities proposed that it should
                    be made permanent, and Mr H. N. Lay, of H.M.’s consular service, was in
                    consequence appointed inspector of the Shanghai customs. The results of Mr Lay’s
                    administration proved so successful that when arranging the terms of the treaty
                    of 1858 the Chinese willingly assented to the application of the same system to
                    all the treaty ports, and Mr Lay was thereupon appointed inspector-general of
                    maritime customs. On the retirement of Mr Lay in 1862 Sir Robert Hart was
                    appointed to the post, which he still (1886) occupies.</p>
                <p>During the period from 1856 to 1864 the trade of Shanghai increased by leaps and
                    by bounds, and its prosperity culminated between 1860 and 1864, when, in
                    addition to the ordinary commerce, the influx of Chinese into the foreign
                    settlement in consequence of the advance eastward of the T’ai-p’ing rebels added
                    enormously to the value of land and to the profits of the leaseholders. Both in
                    1860 and again in 1861 the rebels advanced to the walls of Shanghai, and on both
                    occasions were driven back in confusion by the British troops and volunteers,
                    aided by the naval forces of England and Frauce. It was in connexion with this
                    resistance to the rebels at Shanghai that General Gordon assumed the command of
                    the Chinese force, which under his direction gave a meaning and reality to the
                    hitherto somewhat boastful title of “ever-victorious army” it had assumed under
                    the generalship of the two American adventurers Ward and Burgevine. To Shanghai
                    the successful operations of Gordon against the rebels brought temporarily
                    disastrous consequences. With the disappearance of the T’ai-p’ings the refugees
                    who had sought safety in the foreign settlements returned to their homes,
                    leaving whole streets and quarters deserted and empty. The loss thus inflicted
                    on the municipality was very considerable, and was intensified by a commercial
                    crisis in the markets of cotton and tea, in both of which articles there had
                    been a great deal of over-spoculation. But, though the abnormal prosperity
                    produced by extraordinary circumstances was thus suddenly brought to an end, the
                    genuine trade of the port has steadily advanced, subject of course to occasional
                    fluctuations. For example, between the years 1878 and 1881 the gross value of
                    the trade increased from 110,956,274 taels to 141,291,357 taels. In 1883,
                    however, this amount fell to 110,433,531 taels, while in 1884 it rose again to
                    113,215,520 taels, although at this time, as will be remembered, hostilities
                    were being carried on between France and China. In the same year 53,562 bales of
                    silk were exported, as against 47,807 bales in 1883, and 27,084,675 lb of green
                    tea, as against 25,336,041 lb in 1883. In black tea there was a falling off, the
                    respective figures being 43,813,058 and 48,251,637 lb. The total burthen of
                    foreign steamers which entered and cleared at Shanghai during 1884 was 3,145,242
                    tons. Of this amount 2,238,433 tons were British, 500,222 were American, 188,484
                    were Japanese, 93,226 were German, 88,983 were French, 24,572 were Russian, and
                    11,322 were Danish.</p>
                <p>According to the latest estimate the native population of the<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n798/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0798-0773"/> city and suburbs of Shanghai amounts to 156,000.
                    When to this number the boat population, amounting to 11,000, and the mixed
                    inhabitants of the foreign settlements, numbering 145,500, are added, a total is
                    reached of 312,500 souls.</p>
                <p>The vastness of English interests in China and the large British population at
                    Shanghai gave rise in 1865 to the establishment of a British supreme court for
                    China and Japan,—Sir Edmund Hornby, who was then the judge of the British court
                    at Constantinople, being the first judge appointed to the new office. The court
                    thus constituted not only exercises jurisdiction over the British subjects at
                    Shanghai but acts as a court of appeal from all British consular courts in China
                    and Japan. All charges against Chinamen within the settlement are tried before a
                    mixed court, which sits daily, presided over by a Chinese official and an
                    officer of the consular service. During the year 1884 2,304 criminal cases were
                    tried before this tribunal, and 99 civil cases,—in 85 of which cases no less a
                    sum than £60,000 was involved.</p>
                <p>A handsome bund runs along the river frontage of the three foreign settlements,
                    and the public buildings, especially in the British settlement, are large and
                    fine. The cathedral, which is built in the Gothic style, is a notable example of
                    Sir Gilbert Scott’s skill as an architect, and the municipal offices,
                    club-house, and hospitals are all admirable in their way. Shanghai is now
                    connected with Peking by a telegraph, which will doubtless before long be
                    supplemented by a railway. Some years ago a short railway was laid down between
                    Shanghai and Woosung by some foreigners who wished to force the pace at which
                    China was progressing. But the time had not come when such a step would be
                    adopted by the Chinese, and after a few weeks’ existence the plant was bought by
                    the native authorities and shipped to Formosa, where it has since been allowed
                    to rust and rot. The climate of Shanghai is essentially unhealthy. It lies low,
                    and, though the early winter is enjoyable, snow and ice being occasionally seen,
                    the summer months are swelteringly hot. Fever, dysentery, and cholera are
                    unfortunately common complaints, and it is only by frequent trips to Japan and
                    Chefoo that the residents are able to preserve health and strength. But,
                    notwithstanding every disadvantage, the position occupied by Shanghai as a
                    centre of trade, situated as it is at the mouth of the Yang-tsze-kiang, in the
                    immediate neighbourhood of the richest silk and tea districts, and in proximity
                    to Japan and the newly-opened ports of Corea, insures for it an increasing
                    volume of commerce and a widening prosperity in the future. (R. K. D.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
