<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0854-0829-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SHÍRAZ</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 21, page 829</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4h708385">Will</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49g84h">Wills</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42r3nw7t">Porter</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zm20">Parsis</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4833n637">Rose</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20h7x">Valleys</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bh84">Gardens</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1175881">Wine</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:937895">Gardens</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:937852">Gardening</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:950204">Hafiz</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1072068">Porters</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:978818">Iranians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1072067">Porter</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n854/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SHÍRAZ</label>, a celebrated city in Persia, capital of Fars,
                    from its site and thoroughly Iranian population may be considered the central
                    point, as it were, of Farsi or Parsi (otherwise Persian) nationality. Owing to
                    the pasture land in its vicinity some derive the name from the native word <hi
                    rend="italic">shir,</hi> "milk;” others again, asserting the number and physical
                    powers of its inhabitants, accept the same word in its sense of “lion,” or take
                    the whole dissyllable as an obsolete word meaning the “lion’s paunch.” To this
                    effect is cited a local saying to the effect that, “like the lion, it devours
                    all they bring into it.” Shíráz is situated in 29° 36' 30" N. lat. and 52° 32'
                    9" E. long., in a high plain or valley more than 20 miles long and less than
                    half as broad, and is approached on the south from the sea—a distance of 170
                    miles<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>As the crow flies,
                    it is only 115 miles N.E. by E. of Bushahr.</p></note> —through lofty mountain
                    passes reaching some 7000 feet above the level of the waters of the Persian
                    Gulf. On the north the approach is also through chains of mountains separating
                    the plains of Shíráz from the valley of the Marv Dasht, intersecting which is
                    the Band Amir river, more poetically than accurately described in <hi
                    rend="italic">Lalla Rookh.</hi> At Kodiyan, a few miles to the northwest of
                    Shiraz, is the source of another river, which, crossing the high road south of
                    the town under the name of the “Kâra Agatch,” falls into the sea about 70 miles
                    below Bushahr (Bushire), after a tortuous course of 300 miles. The city has a
                    handsome bazaar and some good private residences; but its unattractive streets
                    are narrow, and, though not so crowded with beggars as Ispahan, contain many
                    living objects distressing to the eye. The mosques and minarets, albeit of local
                    repute, look more picturesque to the stranger in the distance than under close
                    inspection. One fine view of the town is that on the north, at the pass between
                    the mountains called “Allah Hu Akbar ”— so named, it is conceived, because this
                    would be the traveller’s exclamation of delight when the landscape first opened
                    out upon him. The country in this direction is studded with pleasant gardens.
                    Besides these there are the tombs of the poets Hafiz and Sa'di—both within easy
                    reach of the city. The first—a fine marble monument with a beautifully inscribed
                    ode and other writings upon it—is not a mile from the gate, and is situated in
                    an enclosure bearing the name Háfiziya. The most noted product of Shíráz is its
                    wine, on the merits of which, however, there is much difference of opinion from
                    outside judges. Dr Wills gives an original account of an experiment of his own
                    in making the wine of Shíráz. Its cost in the production was 5 1/2 d. a bottle,
                    and it sold a year after at more than three times that amount. Shíráz is
                    moreover famous for inlaid work (wood and metal) called <hi rend="italic">khátam
                    bandi</hi> (from <hi rend="italic">khatam,</hi> a seal). The population of the
                    city is estimated under 30,000. The ordinary diseases are intermittent fever,
                    diarrhoea, dysentery, typhoid, guinea worm, cholera, diphtheria, small-pox, and
                    ophthalmia.</p>
                <p>Although the praises of Shiráz, its produce, inhabitants, climate, and
                    surroundings of every kind, have been sung by poets for centuries, and are never
                    disputed by Persians who are not Shírazis, yet it is impossible for the sober
                    European traveller to deny that the reality falls far below the picture. We may
                    feel thankful for the wine and the water, the gardens and the monuments, the
                    fruits and the flowers (abundant here as in many other an oasis in the Shah’s
                    dominions); we may sympathize with the national pride in the possession of a
                    Hafiz and a Sa'di; we may believe that the ladies of yore had “eyes brighter
                    than the antelope’s, hair clustering like their own dark grapes, and forms
                    fairer and sweeter than the virgin rose,” and that those of the present day
                    would, if unveiled, strike the spectator with wonder; but one fact remains, —the
                    modern town of Shiráz is not a paradise for those whose personal experience
                    enables them to compare it with the ordinary cities of Europe.</p>
                <p>According to Eastern authorities, Shíráz was founded (or refounded, for some
                    accounts ascribe to it a fabulous antiquity) by a brother of the famous Hajjáj
                    about the beginning of the 8th century, or rather by a cousin of Hajjáj called
                    Mohammed b. Kasim b. Abú '0kail. Six hundred years later it was the capital of
                    the Muzaffar dynasty of princes, when it fell to the arms of Timur. But it
                    attained its greatest reputation in the reign of Karim Khan, who embellished the
                    city greatly and made it the special object of his care. On the downfall of this
                    monarch it was sacked and laid waste by the cruel Agha Mohammed.</p>
                <p>Shíráz has been often described by native geographers and European writers of
                    travel. Among the latter may be mentioned Pietro della Valle, Herbert,
                    Tavernier, Deslandes, and Chardin, in the 17th century, and in the present
                    century Ouseley, Porter, Morier, Scott-Waring, Forster, Binning, and many quite
                    recent travellers. Neither in his serious history nor lighter sketches does Sir
                    John Malcolm give any detailed account of Shíráz as a city, but his notes on its
                    climate may be cited. On one of the hottest days of Juno 1800 the thermometer
                    registered 94° F. in the house and 100° in a tent. In May 1810 it never rose at
                    noon above 88° nor fell below 74°. In the morning, at eight o’clock, it
                    generally stood about 60°. In autumn the heat continued, but in winter it was
                    seen to fall considerably below the freezing point. As late as March there is
                    often a hoar frost on the ground. April, he adds, is a delightful month, the
                    thermometer at sunrise being generally from 50° to 55°, at two <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">p.m.</hi> 80° to 84°, and at nine <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >p.m.</hi> about 64°.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
