<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0664-0639-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SEMIPALATINSK</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 21, page 639</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4h41jp6g">Cossacks</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4mc8rm1n">Plains</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206073">China</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:880643">Cossacks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1028366">Mountains</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1093204">Regionalism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1065075">Plains</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n664/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SEMIPALATINSK</label>, an extensive province <hi
                    rend="italic">(oblast)</hi> of the Russian dominions in Central Asia;
                    administratively it forms a part of the general-governorship of the Steppes,
                    although its northern portions really belong to the Irtish plains of West
                    Siberia. It has an area of 188,300 square miles, and is bounded on the N. by
                    Tobolsk and Tomsk, on the S.E. by China, on the S. by Semiryetchensk, and on the
                    W. by Akmolinsk. As regards configuration, it differs widely in its northern and
                    southern parts. The snowclad ridges (9000 to 10,000 feet) of the great Altai and
                    Narym enter its south-eastern portion, stretching southwards to Lake Zaisan.
                    Another complex of mountains, Kandygatai and Kałbinsk, rising to 5000 and 6000
                    feet above the sea, continues them towards the west; a broad valley intervenes,
                    through which the Irtish finds its way from the Zaisan terrace to the lowlands
                    of Siberia. Many extensions of these mountains and subordinate ridges stretch
                    towards the north. The still lower but wild Jinghiz-tau mountains fill the
                    south-western part of Semipalatinsk, sending out their rocky spurs into the
                    steppe region. In the south, the Tarbagatai (Marmots’) range (9000 to 10,000
                    feet) separates Semipalatinsk from Semiryetchensk and the Chinese province of
                    Jugutchak. Wide steppes fill up the spaces between the mountains: such are the
                    Zaisan steppe (1200 to 1500 feet), between the Tarbagatai and the Altai ranges;
                    the plains of Lake Balkash, some 300 feet lower, to the south of the
                    Jinghiz-tau; and the plains of the Irtish, which hardly rise 600 feet above the
                    sea. All kinds of crystalline rocks—granites, syenites, diorites, and
                    porphyries, as also crystalline slates of all descriptions—are met with in the
                    mountain tracts, which contain also rich gold-bearing sands, silver and lead
                    mines, graphite, coal, and the less valuable precious stones. The geology of the
                    region and even its topography are still but imperfectly known. Numerous
                    boulders widely scattered around the mountains testify to a much wider extension
                    of glaciers in former times. The chief river of the province, the Irtish, which
                    issues from Lake Zaisan, flows north and north-west and waters Semipalatinsk for
                    more than 760 miles. Between Bukhtarma and Ust-Kamenogorsk it crosses the Altai
                    by a wild gorge, with dangerous rapids, through which, however, boats are
                    floated. Lake Zaisan, 80 miles long and from 10 to 20 wide, has depth sufficient
                    for steamboat navigation; steamers traverse also for some 100 miles the lower
                    course of the Black Irtish, which flows from Kuldja to Lake Zaisan. The
                    Kurtchum, the Narym, and the Bukhtarma are the chief right-hand tributaries of
                    the Irtish, while the Bukon, the Kizil-su, and many smaller ones join it from
                    the left; none are navigable, neither are the Kokbekty and Bugaz, which enter
                    Lake Zaisan on the west. Lake Balkash, which borders Semipalatinsk in the
                    south-west, formerly received several tributaries from the Jinghiz-tau. Many
                    smaller lakes (some of them merely temporary) occur on the Irtish plain, and
                    yield salt. The whole of the country is rapidly drying up. The climate is
                    severe. The average yearly temperature reaches 43° in the south and 34° in the
                    north; the winter is very cold, and frosts of - 44° Fahr. are not uncommon,
                    while heats raising the thermometer to 122° in the shade are experienced in the
                    summer. The yearly amount of rain and snow is trifling, although snowstorms are
                    very common; strong winds prevail. Forests are plentiful in the hilly districts
                    and on the Irtish plain, the flora being Siberian in the north and more Central
                    Asiatic towards Lakes Balkash and Zaisan.</p>
                <p>The chief inhabitants are Kirghiz-kazaks, who acknowledged the supremacy of
                    Russia in 1732 and may number now (1886) nearly half a million (479,750 in 1876,
                    of whom 10,950 were settled in towns). The Russian population, which in the same
                    year amounted to nearly 50,000 Cossacks and peasants, has slowly increased
                    since. The aggregate population was in 1882 estimated at 538,400, of whom 34,550
                    lived in towns. The Russians are chiefly agriculturists, and have wealthy
                    settlements on the right bank of the Irtish, as well as a few patches in the
                    south, at the foot of the mountains. The Kirghizes are almost exclusively
                    cattle-breeders and keep large flocks of sheep, horses, and horned cattle, as
                    also camels. Hunting and fishing (in Lake Zaisan) are favourite and profitable
                    occupations with the Cossacks and the Kirghizes. Industries are of course
                    insignificant, except that of mining,—gold being obtained within the province to
                    the amount of from 300 to 400 lb every year; the extraction of silver and lead
                    is very limited. Trade is of some importance, and is increasing,—Russian
                    manufactured articles being exchanged for the raw produce (hides, tallow,
                    cattle) of the region. The province is divided into four districts, the chief
                    towns of which are Semipalatinsk (17,820 inhabitants in 1881), Pavlodar (2260),
                    Kokbekty (3680), and Karkaralinsk (2030). All these towns, lost amidst the sandy
                    steppes, are mere administrative centres. Bukhtarma and Ust-Kamenogorsk (3400),
                    among the mountains, are also worthy of mention.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
