<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0804-0779-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SHARP, James</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 21, page 779</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4sf2md37">Missions</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4r20rx5q">Presbyterianism</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xn1j">Monks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4r785w31">Paper</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1ms2d">Reviews</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1053286">Pardon</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1075567">Presbyterians</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1075562">Presbyterianism</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1025507">Monks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1052348">Paper</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n804/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SHARP, <hi rend="smallcaps">James</hi></label> (1618-1679),
                    archbishop of St Andrews, was the son of William Sharp, sheriff-clerk of
                    Banffshire, and of Isabel Leslie, daughter of Leslie of Kininvie, of the family
                    of Halyburtons of Pitcur in Angus, and was born in Castle Banff on May 4, 1618.
                    He was a clever boy, and his early disposition for the church led to his being
                    called in jest “the young minister.” In 1633 he went to King’s College,
                    Aberdeen, and graduated in 1637. He there studied divinity for one or two years,
                    and probably derived his Episcopal tendencies from the “Aberdeen doctors,”
                    Aberdeen being at that time the home of Episcopal sentiment. On the outbreak of
                    the Covenanting war he went to England (1639) and visited Oxford and perhaps
                    Cambridge, becoming acquainted with the principal English divines. Upon his
                    return he was chosen in 1643 through the influence of Lord Rothes to be one of
                    the “regents” of philosophy in St Leonard’s College, St Andrews. He appears to
                    have continually risen in reputation until in December 1647 he went through his
                    ordinary trials for the ministerial office before the presbytery of St Andrews,
                    and was appointed minister of Crail in Fifeshire, on the presentation of the
                    earl of Crawford, on January 27, 1648. In the great schism of Resolutioners and
                    Protestors, he, with the large majority of educated men, took active part with
                    the former; he was the friend of Baillie, Douglas, Dickson, Wood, Blair, and
                    others, and as early as March 1651 was recognized as one of the lead ing men of
                    the party. His first public employment was in 1656, when he went to London on
                    their behalf to endeavour to counteract with the Protector the influence of
                    Warriston, who was acting for the Protestors. Here he became acquainted with
                    Calamy, Ash, and other leading London Presbyterian ministers, and letters passed
                    between him and Lauderdale, then prisoner in the Tower. He displayed all his
                    undoubted talents for petty diplomacy and considerable subtlety in argument
                    while on this service, and his mission was decidedly successful. He returned to
                    Scotland in 1659, but upon Monk’s march to London was again, in February 1660,
                    sent by the Resolutioners to watch over their interests in London, where he
                    arrived on February 13. He was most favourably received by Monk, to whom it was
                    of great importance to remain on good terms with the dominant party in Scotland.
                    His letters to Douglas and others during this period, if they may be trusted,
                    are useful towards following the intrigues of the time day by day. It must not
                    be forgotten, however, that there is good reason for thinking that Sharp had
                    already made up his mind not to throw away the chances he might have of
                    prominent employment under the Restoration. In the beginning of May he was
                    despatched by Monk to the king at Breda “to deal that he may be sent with a
                    letter to the London Presbyterian ministers, showing his resolution to own the
                    godly sober party.” His letters on this occasion to Douglas show that he
                    regarded himself equally as the emissary of the Scottish kirk. It is to be
                    noticed that he was also the bearer of a secret letter from Lauderdale to the
                    king. He was in fact playing a game admirably suited to his peculiar capacity
                    for dark and crooked ways of dealing. There can be little doubt that while on
                    this mission he was finally corrupted by Charles and Clarendon, not indeed so
                    far as to make up his mind to betray the kirk, but at any rate to decide in no
                    way to imperil his own chances by too firm an integrity. The first thing that
                    aroused the jealousy of his brethren, who, as Baillie says, had trusted him as
                    their own souls, was his writing from Holland in commendation of Clarendon. This
                    jealousy was increased on his return to London (May 26) by his plausible
                    endeavours to stop all coming of Presbyterian commissioners from Scotland and
                    Ireland, though he professed to desire the presence of Douglas and Dickson, by
                    his urgent advice that the Scots should not interfere in the restoration of
                    Episcopacy in England, and by his endeavours to frustrate the proposed union of
                    Resolutioners and Protestors. He informed them that Presbyterianism was a lost
                    cause in England, but as late as August 11 he intimated that, though there had
                    been great danger for the Scottish kirk as well, this danger had been constantly
                    and successfully warded off by his efforts. He returned to Scotland in this
                    month, and busied himself in endeavouring to remove all suspicions of his
                    loyalty to the kirk; but at the same time he successfully stopped all petitions
                    from Scottish ministers to king, parliament, or council. His letters to
                    Drummond, a Presbyterian minister in London, and to Lauderdale, without
                    absolutely committing him, show clearly that he was certain that Episcopacy was
                    about to be set up. How far he was actively a traitor in the matter had always
                    been fairly disputed until the question was at last set at rest by the discovery
                    of his letter, dated May 21, from London, whither he went in April 1661, to
                    Middleton, the High Commissioner, whose chaplain he now was, from which it is
                    proved that he was in confidential communication with Clarendon and the English
                    bishops, that he was earnestly and eagerly co-operating in the restoration of
                    Episcopacy in Scotland, that he had before leaving Scotland held frequent
                    conferences with Middleton on the subject (a fact which he had explicitly and
                    vehemently denied) and was aware that Middleton had<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n805/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0805-0780"/> all along intended it, and that he drew up and
                    was directly responsible for the quibbling proclamation of June 10, the sole
                    purpose of which was “the disposing of minds to acquiesce in the king’s
                    pleasure.” The original of this letter (which is printed in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Lauderdale Papers</hi> and in the <hi rend="italic">Scottish
                    Review)</hi> is preserved in the Museum of the Society of Antiquaries,
                    Edinburgh. It should be noticed that as late as the end of April, on the eve of
                    starting on his mission to court with Rothes and Glencairne, he declared to
                    Baillie that no change in the kirk was intended. The mask was at length dropped
                    in August, when Episcopacy was restored, and Sharp was appointed archbishop of
                    St Andrews. He and Leighton, Fairfoul, and Hamilton “were dubbed, first
                    preaching deacons, then presbyters, and then consecrated bishops in one day, by
                    Dr Sheldon and a few others.” On April 8th the new prelates entered Scotland,
                    and on the forenoon of April 20, 1662, Sharp preached his first sermon at St
                    Andrews.</p>
                <p>Sharp had carefully kept on good terms with Lauderdale, and when the Billeting
                    Plot was concocted in September 1662 against the latter by Middleton, he managed
                    to avoid acting against him; indeed it is probable that, after being appointed
                    under an oath of secrecy to be one of the scrutineers of the billets, he, in
                    violation of the oath, was the cause of Lauderdale receiving timely information
                    of the decision against him; and yet he shortly went up to London to explain the
                    whole affair in Middleton’s interest. When Lauderdale’s supremacy was
                    established he readily co-operated in passing the National Synod Act in 1663,
                    the first step in the intended subjection of the church to the crown. In 1664 he
                    was again in London, returning in April, having secured the grant of a new
                    church commission. His vanity also had been gratified by his being allowed to
                    take precedence of the chancellor at the council. He harassed the ministers who
                    were with his old friend James Wood when he signed his well-known deathbed
                    confession; he cited and fined others, as well as laymen, for withdrawing from
                    the churches; he urged the thorough prosecution of the arbitrary powers granted
                    to the commission, and complained of the slackness of his fellow commissioners.
                    So oppressive was his conduct and that of others of the bishops that it called
                    forth a written protest from Gilbert Burnet. Sharp at once summoned him before
                    the bishops and endeavoured to obtain a sentence of deprivation and
                    excommunication against him, but was overruled by his brethren. On the death of
                    Glencairne, the chancellor’s greatest efforts were made to secure the vacant
                    office for Sharp, and he was not inactive in his own interest; the place was
                    not, however, filled up until 1667, and then by the appointment of Rothes. He
                    was in strict alliance with Rothes, Hamilton, and Dalyell, and the other leaders
                    of oppression, and now placed himself in opposition to the influence of
                    Lauderdale, attacking his friends, and especially the earl of Kincardine. In
                    1665 he was again in London, where, through his own folly and mendacity, he
                    suffered a complete humiliation at the hands of Lauderdale, well described by
                    the historian Burnet. With Rothes he now in great part governed Scotland, and
                    the result of their system of violence and extortion was the rising of the
                    Covenanters, during which, being in temporary charge during Rothes’s absence, he
                    showed, according to Bellenden, the utmost fear, equalled only by his cruelty to
                    the prisoners after the rout of Pentland. When the convention of estates met in
                    January 1667 he received his first rebuff, Hamilton being substituted for him as
                    president. He now tried to curry favour with Lauderdale, to whom he wrote
                    letters of the most whining contrition, and who extended him a careless
                    reconciliation. The expressions of contempt for him which occur at this time, as
                    previously, in the letters of Robert Moray,</p>
                <p>Argyll, and others of Lauderdale’s correspondents, are frequent and very amusing.
                    For a time he made himself actively useful, and was instrumental in restraining
                    his brethren from writing to London to complain of the conciliation policy which
                    for a while Lauderdale carried out, a transaction in which he displayed the
                    utmost effrontery of lying; and, with slight attempts to free himself, he
                    continued faithful in his new service. On July 10, 1668, an attempt was made
                    upon his life by Robert Mitchell, who fired a pistol at him while driving
                    through the streets of Edinburgh. The shot, however, missed Sharp, though his
                    companion the bishop of Orkney was wounded by it, and Mitchell for the time
                    escaped. In August Sharp went up to London, returning in December, and with his
                    assistance, nominally indeed at his suggestion, Tweeddale’s tolerant proposals
                    for filling the vacant parishes with some of the “outed” ministers were carried
                    out. In the debates on the Supremacy Act, by which Lauderdale destroyed the
                    autonomy of the church, he at first showed reluctance to put in motion the
                    desired policy, but gave way upon the first pressure. When, however, Leighton,
                    as archbishop of Glasgow, endeavoured to carry out a comprehension scheme, Sharp
                    actively opposed him, and expressed his joy at the failure of the attempt. From
                    this time he was completely subservient to Lauderdale, who had now finally
                    determined upon a career of oppression, and in 1674 he was again in London to
                    support this policy. In this year also Mitchell, who had shot at him six years
                    before, was arrested, Sharp himself having recognized him, and, upon Sharp’s
                    promise to obtain a pardon, privately made a full confession. When brought into
                    the justiciary court, however, he refused to repeat the confession, whereupon
                    the promise of pardon was recalled; the prisoner was sent to the Bass, and was
                    not brought to trial for four years. In 1678, however, the country being again
                    in great disorder, he was tried on his own confession, which, not having been
                    made before judges, could not legally be brought against him. This plea being
                    overruled, he claimed the promise of pardon. Sharp, however, basely denied that
                    any such promise had been given. His falsehood was proved by the entry of the
                    act in the records of the court. Mitchell was finally condemned, but the
                    condemnation was so evidently unfair and contrary to solemn promise that a
                    reprieve would have been granted had not Sharp himself insisted on his death.
                    This, perhaps the basest action of his base life, was speedily avenged. On May
                    3, 1679, as he was driving with his daughter Isabel to St Andrews, he was set
                    upon by nine men, who were looking for one of the instruments of his cruelty,
                    and, in spite of unmanly beseechings and of the appeals of his daughter, was
                    cruelly murdered. The place of the murder, on Magus Muir, now covered with fir
                    trees, is marked by a monument erected by Dean Stanley, with a Latin inscription
                    recording the deed. It is only right, while recording a career of cold-blooded
                    cruelty and almost unexampled political baseness, to remember that no charge
                    that can be seriously maintained has ever been brought against the morality of
                    Sharp’s private life.</p>
                <p>Unless otherwise mentioned, the proofs of the statements in this article will be
                    found in vols. i. and ii. of the <hi rend="italic">Lauderdale Papers</hi>
                    (Camden Society) and in two articles in the <hi rend="italic">Scottish
                    Review,</hi> July 1884 and January 1885. (O. A.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
