<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0261-0242-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SAMARA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 21, page 242</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g03">Cent</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4t14tp94">Oats</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4736m682">Lakes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20h7x">Valleys</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4pg1hv69">Nonconformists</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4804xr51">Mohammedans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0m53j">Polishing</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4804xp4n">Polishes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:850620">Cent</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:883965">Crops</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1042664">Oats</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:890865">Depositions</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:830297">Bending</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:861575">Circassians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1161461">Unitarians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1025421">Mongols</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:808176">Anabaptists</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n261/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SAMARA</label>, a government of south-eastern Russia, on the
                    left bank of the lower Volga, bounded on the north by Kazan, on the west by
                    Simbirsk and Saratoff, on the east by Ufa and Orenburg, and on the south by
                    Astrakhan, the Kirghiz Steppes, and the territory of the Ural Cossacks. The area
                    is 58,320 square miles, and the population in 1882 was 2,224,093. A line drawn
                    eastwards from the great bend of the Volga—the Samarskaya Luka—would divide the
                    province into two parts, differing in orographical character. In the north flat
                    hills and plateaus, deeply intersected by rivers, cover the surface. Some of
                    these are spurs of the Urals; the others are continuations of the flat swelling
                    which traverses middle Russia from the Carpathians to the Urals and compels the
                    Volga to make its characteristic bend before entering the Aral-Caspian lowlands.
                    The Samara Hills, on the right bank of the river Samara; the Kinel Hills; the
                    Falcon (Sokolii) Hills, to the north of the Buzułuk; the Sok Hills, with the
                    Tsareff Kurgan at the junction of the Sok with the Volga; and the Zheguleff
                    “Mountains” on the Volga opposite Samara are so many names given to separate
                    elevations or parts of plateaus between the deep-cut river valleys. In their
                    highest parts they rise about 1000 feet above the sea, while the level of the
                    Volga at Samara is but 43 feet, and the broad valleys of the Volga affluents
                    sink to a correspondingly low level. South of the Samarskaya Luka the country
                    assumes the characters of a low and flat steppe, recently emerged from the great
                    Post-Pliocene Aral-Caspian basin. Only two ranges of gentle swellings, spurs of
                    the Obshchiy Syrt, enter the south-east corner of the province.</p>
                <p>The geology of Samara is not yet fully known. Carboniferous limestones (Upper?)
                    occupy large tracts in the north-east and east. When approaching the Volga the
                    zechstein appears in wide islands surrounded by the (probably Triassic)
                    variegated marls and sands. Some Jurassic deposits are mentioned about the
                    Samarskaya Luka. Cretaceous deposits, which cover large tracts on the right bank
                    of the Volga, appear on the left bank only in the south-east of Samara, older
                    Tertiary deposits appear also in the very south of Samara; while Pliocene
                    limestones and sandy clays, which cover the obshchiy Syrt and Ust-Urt, protrude
                    north as a narrow strip, reaching the bend of the Volga. The Glacial
                    boulder-clay of middle Russia does not extend as far south-east as Samara, and
                    the Post-Glacial deposits, not yet fully investigated, are represented by loess,
                    black earth, and lacustrine formations. It is now established that during
                    Post-Glacial times the Aral-Caspian sea extended in a wide gulf occupying the
                    broad depression of the Volga as far north as the Samarskaya Luka, Caspian
                    mussels having been traced as far as Samara. The soil is on the whole very
                    fertile. All the northern part of the government is covered with a thick sheet
                    of black earth; this becomes thinner towards the south, clays—mostly
                    fertile—appearing from beneath; salt clays appear in the south-east.</p>
                <p>Samara is inadequately watered, especially in the south. The Volga flows for 550
                    miles along its western border. Its tributaries the Great Tclieremshan (220
                    miles), the Sok (l95 miles), the Samara (340 miles), with its sub-tributaries,
                    and the smaller tributaries the Motcha, Elan-Irghiz or Tchagra, and Little
                    Irghiz are not navigable, partly on account of their shallowness, and partly
                    because of water-mills. When the water is high, boats can enter some of them to
                    a distance of 15 to 30 miles. The Great Irghiz alone, which has an exceedingly
                    winding course of 335 miles, is navigated to Kutchum, and rafts are floated from
                    Nikolaevsk. The banks of both Karamans are densely peopled. The Great and Little
                    Uzeñ water south-eastern Samara and lose themselves in the Kamysh sands before
                    reaching the Caspian. A few lakes and marshes occur in the river-valleys, and
                    salt marshes in the south-east.</p>
                <p>The whole of the region is rapidly drying up. The forests, which are
                    disappearing, are extensive only in the north. Altogether they still cover an
                    area of 3,043,000 acres, or 8 per cent. of the whole surface; prairie and
                    grazing land occupies 11,495,000 acres, and only 4,193,000 acres are
                    uncultivable.</p>
                <p>The climate is one of extremes, especially in the steppes, where the depressing
                    heat and drought of summer are followed in the winter by severe frosts, often
                    accompanied by snow-storms. The average temperature at Samara (53° 11' N. lat.)
                    is only 39°·2 (January, 9°·3; July, 70°·4).</p>
                <p>The population, which was only 1,388,500 in 1853, has almost doubled since then,
                    mostly in consequence of immigration; it reached 2,224,093 in 1882, and must now
                    (1886) be about 2,250,000. Only 139,300 of these live in towns, the remainder
                    being distributed over 4,470 villages, which are often very large, no fewer than
                    150 ranging in population from 2000 to 6000. The Great Russians, who have
                    immigrated in compact masses, now constitute 65 per cent. of the population; the
                    Little Russians, who were settled by the Government about the salt lakes, number
                    about 30,000; and the White Russians, also sent to Samara from West Russia, may
                    number about 15,000. A special feature of Samara is its population of German
                    colonists, from Wúrtemberg, Baden, Switzerland, and partly also from Holland and
                    the Palatinate, whose immigration dates from the invitation of Catherine II. in
                    1762. Protected as they were by free and extensive grants of land, by exemption
                    from military service, and by self-government, they have developed rich colonies
                    of Catholics, Protestants, Unitarians, Anabaptists, Moravians, and Mennonites,
                    most of which have adopted the Russian village-community system, slowly modified
                    by the existence of a special capital reserved for the purchase of land for the
                    increasing population.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>See the interesting work of M. Clauss on “Our Colonies”
                    (Russian).</p></note> They now constitute 40 per cent. of the population of the
                    district of Novo-Uzeñ, and 9 per cent. of that of Nikolaevsk, their aggregate
                    number reaching 150,000. The Moksha and Erzya Mordvinians, now nearly quite
                    Russified, gathered in Samara during the reign of Peter I., when they abandoned
                    in great numbers the left bank of the Volga; they constitute about 10 per cent,
                    of the population. Some 70,000 Tchuvashes and 1500 Votyaks may be added to the
                    above. The Turkish stem is represented by some 100,000 Tartars, 70,000 Bashkirs,
                    and a few Kirghizes. Some baptized Kalmucks were settled in 1730 at Stavropol;
                    and about 600 Adyghe Circassians, settled at Novo-Uzeñ, may still be found
                    there. All these varied elements, living in close juxtaposition, nevertheless
                    continue to maintain their own ethnographical features; the Mordvinians alone
                    have lost their ethnological individuality and rapidly undergo a modification of
                    type as they adopt the life of Russian peasants. As regards religion, the great
                    bulk of the population are Orthodox Greeks; the Nonconformists, who still retain
                    their numerous and widely celebrated communities and monasteries on both the
                    rivers Uzeñ, number several hundred thousands (officially 100,000); next come
                    Mohammedans, 12 per cent.; a variety of Protestant sects, 5 per cent.; Roman
                    Catholics, about 2 per cent.; and, lastly, some 4000 pagans.</p>
                <p>The chief occupation is agriculture,—summer wheat, rye, oats, millet,
                    oil-yielding plants, and tobacco being the principal crops, Owing to its great
                    fertility, Samara usually has a surplus of grain for export, varying from 1½ to
                    4 million quarters (exclusive of oats) annually. In 1883, which was an average
                    year for summer wheat, but under the average for winter rye, the total crops
                    were—wheat, 3,219,600 quarters; rye, 717,800; oats, 1,800,000; barley, 127,300;
                    and other grains, 1,310,000. Notwithstanding this production, varying from
                    5,000,000 to 9,000,000 quarters of grain (exclusive of oats) for a population of
                    only 2¼ millions, Samara is periodically liable to famine to such an extent that
                    men die by thousands of hunger-typhus, are compelled to send (as in 1879) to
                    adjoining provinces to purchase orach as food, or are forced to go by hundreds
                    of thousands in search of employment on the Volga, while millions of quarters of
                    corn are nevertheless exported. The population have no store of corn, or reserve
                    capital for years of scarcity (there were in 1882 only 245,100 quarters of com
                    in the public granaries, and 503,022 roubles of capital for that purpose), and
                    some 210,000 males have in all only 845,000 acres of arable and pasture land.
                    But even this soil, although all taxed as arable, is often of such quality that
                    only 50 to 55 per cent. of it is under crops, while the peasants are compelled
                    to rent from two to two and a half million acres for tillage from large
                    proprietors. At present 8,549,000 acres, or about one-quarter of the total area
                    of<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n262/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0262-0243"/> Samara, purchased from the crown or from the
                    Bashkirs at nominal prices—very often a few copecks per acre—are in the hands of
                    no more than 1704 persons. The aggregate taxes exacted from the peasants
                    amounting to 5,782,870 roubles (1879), that is to say, from 8 to 10 roubles per
                    male, they are, when account is taken of the advances received during scarcity,
                    reduced to absolute destitution whenever the crops are short, so as to be
                    compelled to sell their last horse and cow. In 1880 the arrears reached
                    7,000,000 roubles, to which must be added about 8,000,000 roubles of advances,
                    and in 1882, out of the 1,196,646 roubles proposed to be levied by the zemstvos,
                    376,643 remained in arrears. The general impoverishment may be judged from the
                    death-rate, which for several years has ranged from 46 to 48 per thousand. In
                    1879 61,488 families were compelled to abandon their homes and disperse
                    throughout Russia in search of employment; while 100,000 families were left
                    wholly destitute of cattle in 1880. Notwithstanding an increase of population by
                    nearly one-third during the last twenty years the numbers of sheep and cattle
                    decreased by about one-half from 1863 to 1882.</p>
                <p>The manufactures of Samara are unimportant, the aggregate production (chiefly
                    from tanneries, flour-mills, tallow-melting houses, and distilleries) in 1882
                    reaching only 7,671,000 roubles (£767,100). Petty trades, especially the weaving
                    of woollen cloth, are making progress in the south. The culture of oil-yielding
                    plants is developed in several districts, as is also that of tobacco (10,690
                    acres, yielding 101,980 cwts., in 1884). Trade is very active—corn, tallow,
                    potash, salt, and some woollen cloth being exported; the imports of raw cotton
                    from Central Asia by the Orenburg railway to be forwarded to the interior of
                    Russia are increasing. The aggregate value of merchandise shipped on the Volga
                    and its tributaries within the government reached 27,025,000 roubles in 1882;
                    while 9,100,000 cwts. of merchandise were carried in both directions on the
                    Orenburg railway. The chief loading places are Samara, Stavropol, Bałakova, and
                    Pokrovsk on the Volga, Staro-Mainsk on the Maina, and Ekaterininsk on the
                    Bezentchuk.</p>
                <p>The government is divided into seven districts, the chief towns of which, with
                    population as estimated in 1879, are—Samara (63,400 inhabitants), Bugulma
                    (13,000), Bugurusłan (18,000), Buzułuk (10,500), Nikolaevsk (9,900), Novo-Uzeñ
                    (9700), and Stavropol (4265). Serghievsk (1000) also has municipal institutions;
                    its mineral waters are becoming more and more frequented. Pokrovskaya Słoboda
                    (20,000), Ekaterinenstadt, Głushitza, and Alexandroff Gay, each with more than
                    5000 inhabitants, the loading place of Bałakova (2500), and several others,
                    although still but villages, have more importance than most of the above
                    towns.</p>
                <p>The territory now occupied by Samara was until last century the abode of nomads.
                    The Bulgarians who occupied it until the 13th century were followed by Mongols
                    of the Golden Horde. The Russians penetrated thus far in the 16th century, after
                    the defeat of the principalities of Kazañ and Astrakhan. To secure communication
                    between these two cities, the fort of Samara was erected in 1586, as well as
                    Saratoff, Tsaritsyn, and the first line of Russian forts, which extended from
                    Byełyi Yar to the neighbourhood of Menzelinsk near the Kama. A few settlers
                    began to gather under its protection. In 1670 it was taken by the insurgent
                    leader Stenka Razin, whose name is still remembered in the province. In 1732 the
                    line of forts was removed a little farther east, so as to include Krasnyi Yar
                    and parts of what is now the district of Bugurustan. The Russian colonists also
                    advanced eastwards as the forts were pushed forwards and increased in number.
                    The southern part of the territory, however, remained still exposed to the raids
                    of the nomads. In 1762 Catherine II. invited foreigners, especially Germans, and
                    Nonconformists who had left Russia, to settle within the newly-annexed
                    territory. Emigrants from various parts of Germany responded to the call, as
                    also did the Raskolniks, whose communities on the Irghiz soon became the centre
                    of a formidable insurrection of the peasantry which broke out in 1775 under
                    Pugatcheff and was supported by the Kalmucks and the Bashkirs. After the
                    insurrection, in 1787, a new line of forts from Uzefi to the Volga and the Urals
                    was erected to protect the southern part of the territory. At the end of the
                    18th century Samara became an important centre for trade. As soon as the
                    southern part of the territory became quiet, great numbers of Great and Little
                    Russians began to settle there—the latter by order of Government for the
                    transport of salt obtained in the salt lakes. In the first half of the present
                    century the region was rapidly colonized. In 1847-50 the Government introduced
                    about 120 Polish families; in 1857-59 Mennonites from Dantzic also founded
                    settlements; and in 1859 a few Circassians were brought hither by Government;
                    while an influx of Great Russian peasants continued and still goes on. The
                    territory of Samara remained long under Kazan, or Astrakhan, or Simbirsk and
                    Orenburg. The separate government dates from 1851. (P. A. K.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
