<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0711-0980-0145-11" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HARDOUIN, John (7th edition, volume 11, page
                    145)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4t43j79n">Librarians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4086358z">Medals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49g5gh4j">Names</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term ref="fast:997301">Librarians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1013537">Medals</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193640980?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HARDOUIN, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi></label>, a Jesuit,
                    one of the most learned, and at the same time most singular men whose names are
                    to be found in the history of letters, was born at Quimper, in 1646. He was the
                    son of a bookseller; and this circumstance, in furnishing him with the means of
                    instruction, no doubt contributed to develope that desire for knowledge which at
                    first formed the principal trait of his <hi rend="superscript"> i</hi>
                    character. When his studies were terminated, he made application to the Jesuits,
                    into whose body he wished to be received; but he only obtained his admission
                    after two years of trial and examination; from which it may reasonably be
                    conjectured that, at the age of twenty, he gave no proofs of those brilliant
                    qualities for which he was afterwards distinguished. For some time he professed
                    rhetoric, and then proceeded to Paris in order to complete his course of
                    theology. He was associated with Father Garnier in classifying the books
                    belonging to the college of Louis the Great, and in 1683 he succeeded to the
                    office of librarian. The learned were then preparing editions of the classical
                    authors for the use of the Dauphin; but none of them had ventured to undertake
                    the <hi rend="italic">Natural History</hi> of Pliny, a work the text of which
                    has suffered more than that of almost any other ancient author, and which, to be
                    thoroughly understood and appreciated, requires extensive knowledge of various
                    kinds. Father Hardouin undertook<pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193640993?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0711-0993-0146"/> this task, to
                    which he applied himself with incredible zeal. In trying to determine the
                    positions of the towns mentioned by Pliny, he became sensible that a knowledge
                    of medals would assist him in clearing up different points of ancient geography;
                    and with this view he immediately applied to the study of numismatics, in which
                    he soon rendered himself profound. His edition of Pliny was completed in five
                    years, and, when it appeared, made the learned and indefatigable editor known to
                    all Europe. This work, which, according to Huet, would have occupied any five
                    ordinary scholars fifty years, met with so flattering a reception, that Father
                    Hardouin could not enjoy his success with moderation. The commendations which
                    poured in upon him from all quarters intoxicated him with pride; and he no
                    longer spoke of other antiquaries, except with the utmost contempt. The latter,
                    again, set themselves to humble him in his turn, by depreciating his merits, and
                    exaggerating his faults. Hardouin replied with bitterness, and in his reasonings
                    displayed more subtlety than good faith; for rather than confess his errors, he
                    attempted to palliate them by paradoxes, and, proceeding from one thing to
                    another, he at length came to advance some so utterly extravagant, that, if they
                    have not ruined his reputation, as some pretend, they have at least weakened the
                    impression which would otherwise have been produced by his really prodigious
                    knowledge. In one of his works, <hi rend="italic">La Chronologie
                    expliquée</hi><hi rend="italic">par</hi><hi rend="italic">les Médailles,</hi> he
                    ventured to maintain that ancient history had been entirely recomposed in the
                    thirteenth century, with the help of the works of Cicero and Pliny, the Georgies
                    of Virgil, and the satires and epistles of Horace, the only monuments which, in
                    his opinion, had any claim to antiquity. This strange assertion, which tended to
                    raise doubts as to the authenticity of the sacred Scriptures themselves, caused
                    his production to be suppressed, drew down upon him the censure of his
                    superiors, and obliged him, in 1708, to make a retractation, but without in any
                    degree changing his opinions, which he reproduced in several of his works.
                    Besides his office of librarian, Hardouin filled a chair of theology; and,
                    notwithstanding the continual distractions to which he was exposed, he passed
                    few years without publishing some new writing, as remarkable for erudition as
                    for novelty of the ideas. He rose, summer and winter, at four in the morning,
                    and continued his readings until night was well advanced. Endowed with an
                    astonishing memory, and a sagacity which made itself be remarked even in his
                    greatest aberrations, he would have more certainly obtained the glory he coveted
                    if be had pursued it less eagerly. He thought himself original when he was only
                    singular; and he frequently advanced vain subtleties or extravagant paradoxes,
                    that he might avoid repeating what others had said before him. He prepared
                    himself for death with Christian resignation, and terminated his long career,
                    which it would have been easy for him to render more honourable, as well as more
                    useful, in the house of his order at Paris, on the 3d of September 1729, in the
                    eighty-third year of his age. His epitaph, written by Jacob Vernet of Geneva,
                    gives a very just idea of the celebrated personage, and of the strange mixture
                    of pride and naivete, of scepticism and solid piety, which made up his
                    character.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Naked,
                    unvarnished truth is a rare ingredient in epitaphs. The following, however,
                    which is that alluded to in the text, presents, in this respect, a remarkable
                    exception</p><p>In expectatione judicii Hic jacet hominum paradoxotatos Natione
                    Gallus, religione jesuita, Orbis litterati portentum</p><p>Veneranđae
                    antiquitatis cultor et depraeđator Docte febricitans</p><p>Somnia et inaudita
                    commenta vigilans edidit. Scepticum pie egit</p><p>Credulitate puer Audacia
                    juvenis Deliriis senex,</p><p>Verbo dicam, hic jacet Harduinus.</p></note> His
                    principal works are: 1. Nummi antiqui Populorum et Urbium illustrati, de re
                    monetaria veterum Romanorum ex Plinii Secundi sententia, Paris, 1684, in 4to; 2.
                    Antirrheticus de Num· mis antiquis Coloniarum et Municiporum ad Jo.
                    Foy-Vaillant, ibid. 1689, in 4to; 3. C. Plinii Secundi Historiae Naturalis libri
                    xxxvii. Paris, 1689, in five vols. 4to; 4. S. Joannis Chrysostomi Epistola ad
                    Caesarium monachum, notis illustrata, Paris, 1686, in 4to; 5. Chronologiae ex
                    Nummis antiquis restitutae specimen primum, Paris, 1696, in 4to; 6. Opera
                    Selecta, Amsterdam, 1709, 1719, in folio; 7. Conciliorum Collectio Regia Maxima,
                    Paris, 1715 and the following years; 8. Apologie d’Homère, où l’on explique le
                    véritable dessein de l’Iliade, et la Théo-mythologie, Paris, 1716, in 12mo; 9.
                    Opera Varia Posthuma, Amsterdam, 1733, in folio; 10. Commentarius in Novum
                    Testamentum, Amsterdam, 1742, in folio; 11. Prolegomena ad censuram Scriptorum
                    veterum, London, 1766, in 8vo; and, 12. a very great number of Dissertations,
                    chiefly on Medals, in the <hi rend="italic">Mémoires de Trévoux,</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">(λ.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
