<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0711-2176-0237-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HENRYSON, Robert (7th edition, volume 11, page
                    237)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1142246">Tales</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vb0p">Caesars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27px1w">Lamentations</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fx7409k">Laments</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193642176?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HENRYSON, <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert</hi></label>, one of
                    the most celebrated of the early Scotish poets, is described as chief
                    schoolmaster of Dunfermline, and this is almost the only particular of his life
                    that is sufficiently ascertained. According to one writer, he was a notary
                    public, as well as a schoolmaster; and another is inclined to identify him with
                    Henryson of Fordell, the father of James Henryson, who was king’s advocate and
                    justice clerk, and who perished in the fatal battle of Floddon. This very
                    dubious account seems to have originated with Sir Robert Douglas; who avers that
                    Robert Henryson appears to have been a person of distinction in the reign of
                    James the Third, and that he was the father of the king’s advocate. Douglas
                    refers to a certain charter, granted by the abbot of Dunfermline in 1478, where
                    Robert Henryson subscribes as a witness;<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Douglas’s Baronage of Scotland, p. 518.</p></note> but in
                    this charter he certainly appears without any particular distinction, as he
                    merely attests it in the character of a notary public. A later writer is still
                    more inaccurate when he pretends that the same witness is described as Robert
                    Henryson of Fordell:<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Sibbald’s Chronicle of Scottish Poetry, vol. i. p. 88.</p></note> in this
                    and other two charters which occur in the chartulary of Dunfermline, he is
                    described as a notary public, without any other addition.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Chartulary of Dunfermline, f. 64. a—Robert
                    Henryson is a witness to other two charters which occur in the same record, f.
                    63. a. b. His only mark of distinction is that of being designated <hi
                    rend="italic">Magister,</hi> while the names of several other witnesses appear
                    without this title. He had perhaps taken the degree of master of
                    arts.</p></note> That the notary public, the schoolmaster of Dunfermline, and
                    the proprietor of Fordell, were one and the same individual, is by no means to
                    be admitted upon such slender and defective evidence. Henryson, or, according to
                    its more modern and less correct form, Henderson, was not at that period an
                    uncommon surname. It is not however improbable that the schoolmaster may have
                    exercised the profession of a notary. While the canon law prevailed in Scotland,
                    this profession was generally exercised by ecclesiastics, and some vestiges of
                    the ancient practice are still to be traced: every notary designates himself a
                    <hi rend="italic">clerk</hi> of a particular diocese; and by the act of 1584,
                    which under the penalty of deprivation prohibited the clergy from following the
                    profession of the law, they still retained the power of making testaments; so
                    that we continue to admit the rule of the canon law, which sustains a will
                    attested by the parish priest and two or three witnesses.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Decretales Gregorii IX. lib. iii. tit. xxvi.
                    cap. χ.</p></note> If therefore Henryson was a notary, it is highly probable
                    that he was also an ecclesiastic, and if he was an ecclesiastic, he could not
                    well leave any legitimate offspring. The poet, in one of his works, describes
                    himself as “ane man of age ;” and from Sir Francis Kinaston we learn that “being
                    very old he dyed of a diarrhea or fluxe.” With respect to the period of his
                    decease, it is at least certain that he died before Dunbar, <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193642189?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0711-2189-0238"/> who in his
                    Lament, printed in the year 1508, commemorates him among other departed
                    poets.</p>
                <p>In Dunfermling he hes tane Broun, With gude Mr. Robert Henryfoun.</p>
                <p>The compositions of Henryson evince a poetical fancy, and, for the period when he
                    lived, an elegant simplicity of taste. He has carefully avoided that cumbrous
                    and vitiated diction which had begun to prevail among the Scotish as well as the
                    English poets. With his power of poetical conception he unites no inconsiderable
                    skill in versification: his lines, if divested of their uncouth orthography,
                    might often be mistaken for those of a much more modern poet. His principal work
                    is the collection of Fables, thirteen in number, which have been printed in
                    various forms. They are written in a pleasing manner, and are frequently
                    distinguished by their arch simplicity; but in compositions of this nature,
                    brevity is a quality which may be considered as almost indispensable, nor can it
                    be denied that those of Henryson sometimes extend to too great a length. The
                    collection is introduced by a prologue, and another is prefixed to the fable of
                    the lion and the mouse. The latter prologue exhibits a curious specimen of the
                    literature of that age. In a delightful morning of June, the poet wanders into a
                    wood, and reclines himself, in the midst of flowers, under the shade of a
                    hawthorn; where, having made the sign of the cross, he falls asleep, and fancies
                    himself to be accosted by a person of a goodly appearance. This venerable
                    stranger proves to be AEsop; who is here represented as a Roman and a poet, and
                    in whom it is not easy to recognise the reputed author of the fables written in
                    Greek prose. Mr Tyrwhitt, who was equally familiar with classical and with
                    Gothic literature, has remarked that in many passages quoted from AEsop by
                    writers of the middle ages, it is difficult to ascertain what author they
                    mean.</p>
                <p>Henryson’s Tale of the vponlands Mouse and the bur-gesse Mouse may be regarded as
                    one of his happiest efforts in this department. The same tale, which is borrowed
                    from AEsop, has been told tíy many other poets, ancient as well as modern.
                    Babrius has dispatched the story of the two mice in a few verses,<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Babrii Fabularum
                    choliambicarum libri tres, collegit Fr. Xav. Berger, p. 9. Monachii, 18IG,
                    8vo.</p></note> but Henryson has extended it over a surface of several pages. To
                    this fable of the Scotish poet, it does not, in the opinion of Dr Nott, seem
                    improbable that Sir Thomas Wyatt might have been indebted, if not for the idea
                    of his first satire, at least for the manner of telling the story.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Nott’s Essay on Wyatt’s
                    Poems, p. cxliii—In the'Appendix, No∙vi. Dr Nott has printed Henryson’s fable
                    from the Harleian MS.</p></note> Henryson’s Tale of Sire Chauntecleire and the
                    Foxe is evidently borrowed from Chaucer’s Nonnes Preestes Tale. From these
                    apologues some curious fragments of information may be gleaned. That of the
                    Sheepe and the Dog contains all the particulars of an action before the
                    consistory court, and probably as complete an exposure of such transactions as
                    the author could prudently hazard. The proceedings of the ecclesiastical courts
                    seem about this period to have been felt as a common grievance; and they are
                    still more decidedly reprehended in the Satyre of Sir David Lindsay, whose works
                    furnish many valuable contributions to the history of manners and customs.</p>
                <p>Another conspicuous production of Henryson is the Testament of Cresseid,<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The Testament of Cresseid,
                    compylit be Μ. Robert Henrysone, Sculemaister in Dunfermeling, Imprentit at
                    Edinburgh be Henrie Charteris, 1593, 4to—“Ffor the author of this supplement,”
                    says Sir Francis Kinaston, “called the Testament of Creseid, which may passe for
                    the sixt and last booke of this story, I have very sufficiently bin informed by
                    Sr. Tho. Ereskin, late earleof Kelly, and divers aged schollers of the Scottish
                    nation, that it was made and written by one Mr. Robert Henderson, sometime
                    cheife schoole-master in Dumfermling, much about the time that Chaucer was first
                    printed and dedicated to King Henry the 8th by Mr. Thinne, which was neere the
                    end of his raigne. This Mr. Henderson wittily observing that Chaucer in his 5th
                    booke had related the death of Troilus, but made no mention what became of
                    Creseid, he learnedly takes upon him, in a fine poeticall way, to exprès the
                    punishment and end due to a false unconstant whore, which commonly terminates in
                    extreme misery.” See the Loves of Troilus and Creseid, written by Chaucer; with
                    a Commentary by Sir Francis Kinastou, p. xxix. Lond. 179θ, 8vo. Kinaston had
                    translated into Latin rhyme two books of Chaucer’s poem, and had published them
                    under the title of <hi rend="italic">Amorum Troili et</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Creseidce</hi><hi rend="italic">libri duo priores</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Angtì-</hi><hi rend="italic">co-Latini.</hi> Oxoniae, 163δ, 4to. He completed
                    his version of the poem, together with a commentary; and his manuscript at
                    length came into the possession of Mr Waldron, who announced his intention of
                    committing it to the press, but did not find encouragement to proceed beyond a
                    short specimen.</p></note> which is a sequel to Chaucer’s Troy-lus and Creseyde,
                    and is commonly printed among the works of that poet.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>This poem is quoted as Chaucer’s, by Mr
                    Strutt in his View of the Dress and Habits of the People of England, vol. ii. p.
                    279, and by Mr Douce in his Illustrations of Shakspeare, vol. i. p. 15.
                    487∙</p></note> It evidently rises above the ordinary standard of that period,
                    and on some occasions evinces no mean felicity of conception. The silent
                    interview between Troilus and Cresseid is skilfully delineated; and the entire
                    passage has been described as beautiful by a very competent judge of old
                    poetry.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Scott’s Notes to
                    Sir Tristrem, p. 362.</p></note> It is unnecessary to remark that for “the tale
                    of Troy divine,” neither Chaucer nor Henryson had recourse to the classical
                    sources:<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See Warton’s
                    Hist, of English Poetry, vol. ii. p. 220, and Douce’s Illustrations of
                    Shakspeare, vol. ii. p. 65.</p></note> this, like some other subjects of ancient
                    history, had been invested with all the characteristics of modern romance; nor
                    could the Scotish poet be expected to deviate from the models which delighted
                    his contemporaries. Sir Troilus is commended for his knightly piety; a temple is
                    converted into a <hi rend="italic">hirh</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> Mercury is
                    elected speaker of the parliament; and Cresseid, on being afflicted with a
                    leprosy, is consigned to a spittal-house, in order to beg with cup and clapper.
                    The personages are ancient, but the institutions and manners are all modern.</p>
                <p>Henryson’s tale of Orpheus is not free from similar incongruities, and possesses
                    fewer attractions; it is indeed somewhat languid and feeble, and may have been a
                    lucubration of the author’s old age. Sir Orpheus is represented as a king of
                    Thrace, and is first dispatched to heaven in search of the lost Eurydice.</p>
                <p>Quhen endit was the ſangis lamentable, He tuke his harp, and on his breſt can
                    hyng, Syne paſsit to the hevin, as fais the fable, To ſeke his wyf, bot that
                    auailit no thing: By Wadlyng ftrete<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Watling Street is a name given to one of the great Roman
                    ways in Britain. (Horsley’s Roman Antiquities of Britain, p. 387∙ Lond. 1732,
                    fol.) This passage, which to some persons may appear so unintelligible, will be
                    best explained by a quotation from Chaucer’s House of Fame, b. ii.</p><p>Lo,
                    quod he, caſte vp thyne eye, Se yonder, lo, the Galaxye, The whiche men clepe
                    the Milky Way, For it is whyte; and ſome perfay Callen it Watlynge
                    ftrete.</p></note> he went but tarying, Syne come doun throu the fρere of Saturn
                    aid, Quhilk fader is of all thir fternis cald.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Heire begynnis the Traitie of Orpheus Kyng,
                    and how he yeid to Hewyn and to Hel to ſeik his Queue: and ane othir Ballad in
                    the lattir end. Edinburgh, <hi rend="italic">Chepman and Myllar</hi><hi
                    rend="italic subscript"> i</hi> 1508, 4to.</p></note></p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193642202?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0711-2202-0239"/>
                <p>Having searched the sun and planets without success, he directs his course
                    towards the earth, and in his passage is regaled with the music of the spheres.
                    His subsequent adventures are circumstantially, but not very poetically
                    detailed. In enumerating the various characters whom he finds in the domains of
                    Pluto, the poet is guilty of a glaring anachronism: here Orpheus finds Julius
                    Caesar, Nero, and even popes and cardinals; and it is likewise to be remarked
                    that the heathen and the Christian notions of hell are blended together. But
                    such anachronisms are very frequently to be found in the writers of the middle
                    ages. Mr Warton remarks that Chaucer has been guilty of a very diverting, and
                    what may be termed a double anachronism, by representing Creseyde and two of her
                    female companions as reading the Thebaid of Statius. Like the fables of
                    Henryson, his tale of Orpheus is followed by a long moral; and here he professes
                    to have derived his materials from Boethius and one of his commentators.</p>
                <p>The Bludy Serk is an allegorical poem of considerable ingenuity. The poet
                    represents the fair daughter of an ancient and worthy king as having been
                    carried away by a hideous giant, and cast into a dungeon, where she was doomed
                    to linger until some valiant knight should achieve her deliverance. A worthy
                    prince at length appeared as her champion, vanquished the giant, and thrust him
                    into his own loathsome dungeon. Having restored the damsel to her father, he
                    felt that he had received a mortal wound. He requested her to retain his bloody
                    shirt, and to contemplate it whenever a new lover should present himself. It is
                    unnecessary to add that the interpretation of this allegory involves the high
                    mysteries of the Christian faith. The poem bears an obvious resemblance to two
                    distinct tales which occur in the <hi rend="italic">Gesta Romanorum.</hi> In the
                    first of these, a noble lady having been cruelly oppressed by a tyrant, is
                    relieved by a valiant pilgrim, who falls in the moment of victory. According to
                    his injunctions, she places his staff and scrip in her chamber; but on being
                    addressed by three kings, in whom we are instructed to recognize the devil, the
                    world, and the flesh, she afterwards removes these memorials, and forgets her
                    obligations. The other tale represents the daughter of a king as having suffered
                    dishonour from a tyrannical duke. When reduced to poverty and wretchedness, she
                    is accosted at the wayside by a certain valiant knight, who, on condition of
                    obtaining her hand, undertakes to fight the oppressor, and to recover her
                    inheritance. A fierce combat ensues. Before he slays his antagonist, he receives
                    a mortal wound, which, after an interval of three days, terminates his life. She
                    hangs up his bloody armour in a chamber, and on being addressed by any new
                    suitor, she surveys this memorial of her deliverer, and declares her resolution
                    to form no new attachment.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Gesta Rhomanorum, cum applicationibus moralizatis ac mysticis, f. xiii.
                    xxvii. edit. Hagenaw, 1508, 4to.</p></note></p>
                <p>The Abbay Walk is of a solemn character, and is not altogether incapable of
                    impressing the imagination. Its object is to inculcate submission to the various
                    dispensations of Providence, and this theme is managed with some degree of
                    skill. Of his poem entitled the Garment of Gude Ladyis, Lord Hailes has remarked
                    that “the comparison between female ornaments and female virtues, is extended
                    throughout so many lines, and with so much of a tire-woman’s detail, that it
                    becomes somewhat ridiculous.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Bailes’s Ancient Scottish Poems, p. 279. Edinb. 1770,
                    12mo.</p></note> But the most beautiful of Henryson’s productions is Robene and
                    Makyne, the earliest specimen of pastoral poetry in the Scotish language. We
                    consider it as superior in many respects to the similar attempts of Spenser and
                    Browne: it is free from the glaring improprieties which sometimes appear in the
                    pastorals of those more recent writers, and it exhibits many genuine strokes of
                    poetical delineation. The shepherd’s indifference is indeed too suddenly
                    converted into love; but this is almost the only instance in which the
                    operations of nature are not faithfully represented. The story is skilfully
                    conducted, the sentiments and manners are truly pastoral, and the diction
                    possesses wonderful terseness and suavity.</p>
                <p>The Fables of Henryson have lately been reprinted<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Ľdinb. 1832, 4to. This edition was printed
                    for the Maitland Club.</p></note> from the edition of Andrew Hart; of which the
                    only copy known to exist was lately added to that great repository of Scotish
                    literature, the Advocates Library. It is a small octavo volume, which, although
                    in a very frail condition, cost no small price. This edition, printed in 1621,
                    is not however the first; and indeed the title-page indicates the work to be
                    “newlie reuised and corrected.” In the library of Sir Andrew Balfour, which was
                    sold by auction in 1695, there appears to have been a copy of an edition printed
                    at Edinburgh in 1570. And after a short interval the work was exhibited in an
                    English dress: “The fabulous Tales of Esope and Phrygian, compiled moste
                    eloquently in Scottishe metre, by Mr. Robert Henrison, and now lately
                    Englished.” London, printed by Richard Smith, 1577, 8vo. Of this edition there
                    is a copy in the library of Sion College. Among the Harleian manuscripts in the
                    British Museum are preserved “The morall Fai-billis of Esope, compylit be
                    Maister Robert Henrisoun, Scolmaister of Dunfermling, 1571.” This is apparently
                    the date of the transcript, which is conjectured to have been taken from tïie
                    edition of the preceding year. The manuscript, as Mr Pinkerton has stated, “is
                    well writen and preserved, and has some curious illuminations, tho poorly
                    done.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Pinkerton’s List
                    of the Scotish Poets, p. c.</p></note> Ten of the fables, together with several
                    other poems of the same author, are to be found in Bannatyne’s manuscript. The
                    various works of Henryson afford so excellent a specimen of the Scotish language
                    and versification, that a complete collection, printed with due accuracy and
                    accompanied with proper illustrations, could not fail to be highly acceptable to
                    the lovers of our early literature. (x.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
