<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0711-1682-0199-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HEBERDEN, William (7th edition, volume 11, page
                    199)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1062841">Physicians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:866956">Cold</term>
                    <term ref="fast:923528">Fever</term>
                    <term ref="fast:954023">Heating</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1063025">Physics</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795379">Accounting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f41h">Physicians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41834445">Cold</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gc8s">Fever</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q52ff6p">Heat</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4g44hr3b">Heating</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4f47gx2h">Physics</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193641682?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HEBERDEN, <hi rend="smallcaps">William</hi></label>, a
                    practical physician of great celebrity, was born in London in the year 1710. He
                    was sent at a very early age, near the end of 1724, to St John’s College,
                    Cambridge. He took his first degree in 1728, and obtained a fellowship about
                    1730; he became master of arts in 1732, and took his degree in physic in 1739.
                    He remained at Cambridge about ten years longer as a practitioner of physic, and
                    gave an annual course of lectures on the Materia Medica. In 1746 he became a
                    fellow of the Royal College of Physicians in London, and two years afterwards he
                    left Cambridge, having presented to St John’s College the specimens which had
                    been subservient to his lectures. He also added to this donation, a few years
                    afterwards, a collection of astronomical instruments of some value. Having
                    determined to establish himself in London, he was elected a fellow of the Royal
                    Society in 1769; and he was employed in a very extensive medical practice for
                    more than thirty years. When he became sensible that his age required some
                    indulgence, he resolved to pass his summers at a house which he had taken at
                    Windsor; but he continued his practice in the winter for some years longer. In
                    January 1760 he married Mary, daughter of W. Wollaston, Esq. by whom he had five
                    sons and three daughters; but he survived them all, except Dr W. Heberden, and
                    Mary, married to the Rev. G. Jenyns. In 1778 he was made an honorary member of
                    the Royal Society of Medicine at Paris.</p>
                <p>Dr Heberden’s first publication seems to have been a short essay on the
                    incongruous composition of the mithridate and theriac, entitled Antitheriaca,
                    8vo, 1745. 2. He sent to the Royal Society an Account of a very large Human
                    Calculus, weighing more than 2į pounds avoirdupois <hi rend="italic">(Phil.
                    Trans,</hi> xlvi. 1750, p. 596; <hi rend="italic">Al&gt;r.</hi> xi. p. 1005). 3.
                    Account of the Effect of Lightning at South Weald in Essex <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Phil. Trans,</hi> liv. 1764, p. 198). Both these essays are erroneously
                    attributed, in Dr Maty’s index, to his brother, Dr Thomas Heberden of Madeira,
                    who sent several other papers to the society. Dr Heberden was one of the
                    principal contributors to the first three volumes of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Medical Transactions,</hi> published in a great measure at his suggestion, by
                    the College of Physicians, in which we find about sixteen of his original
                    communications. 4. Remarks on the Pump Water of London, 1768. 5. Observations on
                    Ascarides. 6. On Night Blindness, or Nyctalopia. 7. On the Chicken-Pox. 8. On
                    the Epidemical Cold of 1767. 9. Queries, relating to bark, camphor, cold, the
                    gout, and apoplexy. 10. On Hectic Fever. 11. On the Pulse. 12. On a Disorder of
                    the Breast, the <hi rend="italic">angina pectoris.</hi> 13. On Diseases of the
                    Liver. 14. On the Nettle Rash. 15. On Noxious Fungi. 16. Queries; on sizy blood,
                    on hernia, on damp clothes, on venesection in hemorrhages. 17. On an Angina
                    Pectoris. 18. On the Ginseng. 19. On the Measles. 20. Table of the Mean Heat of
                    the different Months in London <hi rend="italic">(Phil. Trans,</hi> lxxviii.
                    1778, p. 86.) 21. Commentarii de Morborum Historia et Curatione, London, 1802,
                    in 8vo; also in English. He had long been in the habit of making notes in a
                    pocket-book, at the bed-sides of his patients; and every month he used to select
                    and copy out, under the proper titles of the diseases, whatever he thought
                    particularly worthy to be recorded. In the year 1782 he employed himself in
                    digesting this register into the form of a volume of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Commentaries</hi> on the history and cure of diseases, religiously observing
                    never to depend on his memory for any material circumstance that he did not find
                    expressly written down in his notes. These commentaries were intrusted to the
                    care of his son, Dr W. Heberden, to be published after his death. We find in
                    them a greater mass of valuable matter, accurately observed and candidly
                    related, than in almost any other volume which has ever appeared upon a medical
                    subject; yet they are but too likely to chill the ingenuous ardour of many a
                    youthful mind, and even to lead to a total apathy with respect to the diligent
                    study of a profession in which so respectable a veteran was so often disposed to
                    exclaim, that “all is vanity.” There are indeed many instances in which he does
                    not seem to have been perfectly master of all the instruments of his art: thus,
                    he appears to have been but partially acquainted with the virtues and various
                    uses of antimony and ipecacuan, and to have reasoned very inaccurately on the
                    operation for a strangulated hernia. But it has been remarked, that the more
                    experience a physician acquires in his profession, the more he is in general
                    inclined to approach the opinions of Dr Heberden, and to esteem his
                    writings.</p>
                <p>Notwithstanding that he has been accused of having occasionally been liable to
                    personal and professional prejudices, it may safely be asserted, that he
                    possessed a singular combination of modesty and dignity of character. He was not
                    only a well-informed and accomplished scholar, but a man of the purest integrity
                    of conduct, of mild and courteous manners, distinguished by genuine piety, and
                    by unaffected benevolence of heart. It is related by one of his biographers,
                    that he bought a sceptical work, left in manuscript by Dr Conyers Middleton, of
                    his widow, for L.50, in order to burn it. He was at the expense of publishing
                    another work of the same author, on the servile condition of physicians amongst
                    the ancients, as well as an edition of some of the plays of Euripides, by
                    Markland. He had an opportunity of rendering an essential service to Dr
                    Letheriand, a man of the deepest and most extensive learning and science that
                    adorned the last century, but of retired habits, and very little known even in
                    his own profession, though he contributed by his literary information to the
                    popularity of more than one of his colleagues. Dr Heberden’s extensive practice
                    made it inconvenient for him to accept the appointment of physician to the
                    queen; and the king, who had always shown him the greatest esteem and regard,
                    readily adopted his disinterested recommendation of Dr LetherIand as his
                    substitute in the situation. He died on the 17th of May 1801, at the age of
                    above ninety years, having exhibited at the close of his life the same serenity
                    of mind which· he had enjoyed throughout its course. <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Life</hi> prefixed to his <hi rend="italic">Commentaries</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >;</hi> Chalmers’ <hi rend="italic">Biographical Dictionary,</hi> xvii.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
