<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0716-7905-0080-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">NEHEMIAH, or Nehemias</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 16, page 80</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b47s7ht9n">Walls</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r13x">Cupping</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4m32nc36">Fires</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b40k26c70">Fire</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1170190">Walls</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:885243">Cupping</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:925697">Fires</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:925173">Fire</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194557905" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">NEHEMIAH, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Nehemias</hi></label>, son
                    ofHachaliah, was born at Babylon during the captivity (Nehem. i. 1, 2, <hi
                    rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">seq.').</hi> He was, according to some,
                    of the race of the priests; but according to others, he was of the tribe of
                    Judah and the royal family. Those who maintain the former opinion support it by
                    a passage in Ezra (x. 10), where he is called a priest; but those who believe
                    that he was of the race of the kings of Judah say that as Nehemiah for a
                    considerable time governed the republic of the Jews, it is probable he was of
                    that tribe to which the kings always belonged. Nehemiah mentions his brethren
                    Hanani, and some other Jews, who, having come to Babylon during the captivity,
                    acquainted him with the sad condition of their country; and the office of
                    cup-bearer to the king of Persia, to which Nehemiah was promoted, is considered
                    as a further proof that he was of an illustrious family. Lastly, he excuses
                    himself from entering into the inner part of the temple, probably because he was
                    only a layman (Nehem. vi. 11). “Should such a man as I flee? And who is there
                    that, being as I am, would go into the temple to save his life ?” The Scripture
                    (Ezra, ii. 63; Nehem. vii. 65) calls him <hi rend="italic">tirshatha,</hi> or
                    cup-bearer; no doubt because he held this employment at the court of Artaxerxes
                    Longimanus. He had an exceeding great tenderness for the country of his fathers,
                    although he had never seen it; and one day, when some Jews newly arrived from
                    Jerusalem acquainted him with the miserable state of that city, that its walls
                    were beaten down, its gates burned, and the Jews become a reproach amongst all
                    nations, he became so sensibly affected with this relation, that he fasted,
                    prayed, and humbled himself before the Lord, imploring him to be favourable to
                    the design which he had then conceived of asking the king’s permission to
                    rebuild Jerusalem. In the course of his attendance at court, he presented the
                    cup to the king according to custom, but with a countenance sad and dejected,
                    which the king observing, entertained some suspicion that he had conceived some
                    evil design; but Nehemiah disclosing the occasion of his disquiet, explained the
                    cause of his grief, upon which Artaxerxes gave him permission to go to
                    Jerusalem, and repair its walls and gates, upon this condition, however, that he
                    should return to court at a time appointed. Letters were accordingly made out,
                    directed to the governors beyond the Euphrates, with orders to furnish Nehemiah
                    with the timbers necessary for covering the towers and gates of the city, and
                    the house designed for Nehemiah himself, who was now appointed governor of
                    Judaea, in the year of the world 3350.</p>
                <p>Nehemiah having arrived at Jerusalem with the king’s commission, went round the
                    city, and having viewed the condition of the walls, assembled the chief of the
                    people, produced his commission, and exhorted them to undertake the reparation
                    of the gates and the walls of the city. Finding every person ready to obey him,
                    he immediately began the work. The enemies of the Jews observing these works in
                    such forwardness, employed all the means in their power to deter Nehemiah from
                    this undertaking, and made several attempts to surprise him; but finding that
                    their designs had been discovered, and that the Jews were upon their guard, they
                    had recourse to stratagem, endeavouring to draw him into an ambuscade in the
                    fields, where they pretended they would finish the dispute at an amicable
                    conference. But Nehemiah gave them to understand that the work he had begun
                    required his personal attendance, and that therefore he could not meet them. He
                    returned the same answer to four several messages that they sent, one after
                    another, on the same subject.</p>
                <p>Sanballat, the chief of the enemies of the Jews, together with hisassociates,≡ent
                    information of a report that the Jews were building the walls of Jerusalem
                    solely with the design of rendering it a place of strength, to support them in
                    an intended revolt; and that Nehemiah had also suborned <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:194557918" xml:id="kp-eb0716-7918-0081"/>false prophets to favour his
                    designs, and to encourage the people to choose him king; wherefore, in order to
                    put a stop to these rumours, he advised Nehemiah to come to him, that they might
                    confer together, and adopt such resolutions as should be found convenient.
                    Nehemiah, however, gave himself no trouble on this account, but returned for
                    answer, that all these accusations were false, and had been made at random.
                    About the same time he discovered that a false prophet called Shemaiah had been
                    corrupted by his enemies, and that some of the chief men of the city were
                    secretly in confederacy with them. Yet all this did not discourage him; he went
                    on with his work, and happily completed it in fifty-two days after it had been
                    commenced.</p>
                <p>We read in the books of the Maccabees that Nehemiah sent to search for the holy
                    fire, which before the captivity of Babylon the priests had hidden in a dry and
                    deep pit; but not finding any fire there, and only a thick muddy water, he
                    sprinkled this upon the altar; whereupon the wood which had been moistened with
                    this water took fire as soon as the sun began to appear. When this miracle came
                    to the knowledge of the king of Persia, he caused the place to be encompassed
                    with walls where the fire had been hidden, and granted great favours and
                    privileges to the priests. It is recorded in the same books, that Nehemiah
                    erected a library, in which he placed whatever he could find, either of the
                    books of the prophets, of King David, or of such princes as had made presents to
                    the temple. Lastly, he returned to Babylon, according to the promise which he
                    had made to king Artaxerxes, about the thirty-second year of that prince’s
                    reign, and in the year of the world 3563; but he subsequently revisited
                    Jerusalem, where he died in peace, about the year 3580, having governed the
                    people of Judah for about thirty years.</p>
                <p>The book which, in the English Bible, as well as in the Hebrew, bears the name of
                    <hi rend="italic">Nehemiah.,</hi> is in the Latin Bible called the book of <hi
                    rend="italic">Esdras</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and it must be confessed, that
                    though this author speaks in the first person, and though at the first reading
                    one would think that he had written it day by day as the transactions occurred,
                    yet there are some things in the book which could not have been written by
                    Nehemiah himself. For example, memorials are quoted, in which were registered
                    the names of the priests in the time of Jonathan the son of Eliashib, and even
                    down to the times of the high priest Jaddus, who went out to meet Alexander the
                    Great, which must have been afterwards added.</p>
                <p>It may well be questioned whether this Nehemiah be the same that is mentioned in
                    Ezra, ii. 2, and Nehem. vii. 7, as one who returned from the Babylonian
                    captivity under Zerubbabel; since from the first year of Cyrus to the twentieth
                    of Artaxerxes Longimanus, no less than ninety-two years intervene; so that
                    Nehemiah must at this time have been a very old man, at the lowest computation
                    an hundred, and consequently incapable of being the king’s cup-bearer, of taking
                    a journey from Shushan to Jerusalem, and of behaving there with all the courage
                    and activity which have been ascribed to him. We may therefore conclude that
                    this was a different person, though of the same name, and that Tirshatha, the
                    other name by which he is called (Ezra, ii. 63; and Nehem. vii. 65), denotes the
                    title of his office, and, both in the Persian and Chaldaic tongues, was the
                    general name given to the king’s deputies and governors.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
