<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0716-7801-0072-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">NECROMANCY</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 16, page 72</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:888385">Dead</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:903991">Egyptians</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1033832">Nationalism</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1076268">Priests</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1061214">Phoenicians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r50f">Phoenicians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b49s1kn07">Priests</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zd0b">Ghosts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="11" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204236">Israel</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194557801" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">NECROMANCY</label>, the art of revealing or foretelling
                    future events by a pretended communication with the dead.</p>
                <p>This most superstitious and impious imposture appears to have had its origin at
                    an early period in Egypt, and to have been thence propagated in every nation
                    with the manners of which history has made us acquainted. The conquests of
                    Sesostris might introduce it into India; the Israelites would naturally borrow
                    it from the people amongst whom they sojourned four hundred years; and it would
                    easily find its way into Phoenicia, from the vicinity of that country to the
                    land of its nativity. From the Egyptians and Phoenicians it was adopted, with
                    the other rites of paganism, by the Greeks; and with Grecian literature and
                    Grecian manners it was imported into Rome. It was not, however, confined to the
                    pagan nations of antiquity. It spread itself throughout all the modern nations
                    of Europe, and took such deep root as to be long retained even after those
                    nations had been converted to the Christian faith.</p>
                <p>Of its early antiquity we have complete evidence in the writings of Moses, where
                    it is severely condemned as an abomination to the Lord; and although it appears
                    to have even then spread into Phoenicia, we might yet conclude that its
                    birthplace had been Egypt, because, at their exod, the Israelites were corrupted
                    only by Egyptian superstitions, and because necromancy seems to have been one of
                    those whoredoms which the prophet Ezekiel represents his countrymen as having
                    brought with them from Egypt, and continued to practise until they were carried
                    as captives into Babylon.</p>
                <p>If from sacred we proceed to consult profane authors, we shall find them not only
                    affirming that Egypt had been the birthplace of necromancy, but in some degree
                    accounting for the origin of so impious a delusion. From Diodorus we learn that
                    the Grecian fable of Charon the ferryman of hell, of Styx, Cocytus, the Elysian
                    Fields, Tartarus, the judgment of Minos and Rhadamanthus, &amp;c. with the whole
                    scenery of the infernal regions, were imported from Egypt into Greece. The
                    ancient Egyptians, and indeed all the people of the East, made use of caves as
                    burying-places; which were well suited to the solemn sadness of surviving
                    friends, and proper receptacles for those who were never more to behold the
                    light. In Egypt, many of these subterranean cavities being dug out of the
                    natural rock, still remain, and command the admiration of travellers; and near
                    to the pyramids in particular there are some apartments of a wonderful fabric,
                    which, though they extend in length upwards of four thousand feet, and are about
                    thirty feet in depth, appear to have been, if not entirely dug, at least reduced
                    to form, by the chisel or the pick-axe of the artist.</p>
                <p>From the practice of burying in such caverns sprung the opinion that the infernal
                    mansions were situated somewhere near the centre of the earth, which by the
                    Egyptians was believed to be not very distant from its surface. In these dreary
                    abodes, it was easy for such adepts as the priests of Egypt to fabricate Erebus,
                    and Tartarus, and the Elysian Fields, and all those scenes which were displayed
                    before the initiated (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Mysteries),</hi> and by them
                    described to the millions of the people. As it was in those dark abodes that
                    necromancy was practised, it would be no difficult matter for such magicians as
                    withstood Moses, to impose so far upon the credulous vulgar as to make them
                    believe, that in consequence of their invocations they actually saw the ghosts
                    of their friends ascend out of the earth. It appears from the book of Exodus,
                    that the Israelitish women were, even in the wilderness, well acquainted with
                    the use of the mirror, which was therefore undoubtedly known to the Egyptians.
                    But a mirror of a particular form, and properly illuminated at the instant
                    required, might be easily made to reflect, in a cavern from which all other
                    light was carefully excluded, the image of the deceased, when called upon by the
                    necromancer; and we can also readily conceive, that with respect to the question
                    to be proposed, a person might be concealed, prepared to give such ambiguous
                    answers as would satisfy the inquirer, and at the same time to save the credit
                    of the oracle. The terrified imaginations of the spectators would aid the
                    delusion, and make a very slight resemblance pass for the ghost or s∕δωλoy of
                    their departed friend; or the necromancer might assign plausible reasons why a
                    spectre, after having dwelt for some time in the infernal regions, should lose
                    something of its resemblance to the body which it animated. Such juggling
                    tricks, though performed by artists less accomplished than Jannes and Jambres,
                    have gained credit amongst people much more enlightened than the Egyptians can
                    possibly have been when the science of necromancy was invented by their
                    priests.</p>
                <p>That the Israelites, notwithstanding the prohibition of their legislator,
                    continued to practise the rites of necromancy, is apparent from Saul’s
                    transaction with the witch of Endor. From the same transaction, it is likewise
                    apparent that the witches of Israel, and therefore in all probability the
                    necromancers of Egypt, pretended to evoke the ghosts of the dead by a demon or
                    familiar spirit, which they had at their command to employ upon every emergency.
                    This demon was called <hi rend="smallcaps">ob</hi>; and therefore Saul desires
                    his servants to find him a woman who was mistress of an <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >ob.</hi><note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The original
                    or radical signification of this word occurs in Job (xxxii. ver. 19), where
                    Elihu compares his belly to new bottles, which he calls <hi rend="italic"
                    >οboth,</hi> the plural of <hi rend="italic">οb.</hi> But as bottles were then
                    made of leather, new bottles filled with wine and ready to burst, as Elihu
                    describes them, would of course be of a form nearly globular. Hence it may be
                    inferred that the original import of <hi rend="italic">οb</hi> was <hi
                    rend="italic">round</hi> or <hi rend="italic">globular</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >;</hi> but <hi rend="italic">b</hi> and <hi rend="italic">p</hi> being labials,
                    are often changed into each other; and, therefore, from the Hebrew <hi
                    rend="italic">ob</hi> is derived the Greek ’«ψ, <hi rend="italic"
                    >oculus,</hi><hi rend="italic">iπ&lt;roμaι, video,</hi> and the Latin <hi
                    rend="italic">ops,</hi> a name under which the earth was worshipped. <hi
                    rend="italic">Uþis</hi> was a name of Diana or the moon: the father of one of
                    the Dianas was likewise <hi rend="italic">Upis</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> but
                    this <hi rend="italic">Upis</hi> was undoubtedly the sun. Now the difference
                    between <hi rend="italic">upis</hi> and <hi rend="italic">opis</hi> is nothing;
                    and hence we are led to believe, that as they are all derived from <hi
                    rend="italic">ob,</hi> this word was employed by the early idolaters of Egypt to
                    denote the first and greatest of Pagan gods, the Sun. If so, those wretches who
                    pretended to be mistresses of <hi rend="italic">obs</hi> were exactly the same
                    kind of impostors with the Pythonesses of the Greeks.</p></note> It is probable
                    that those wretched impostors had in their pay some persons who occasionally
                    acted the part of the demon, and, when the execution of the plot required their
                    agency, emitted, by means of a cavity dug for that purpose, a low hollow voice
                    from below the ground. Hence we find Isaiah, in his denunciations against Ariel,
                    saying, “Thou shalt be brought down, and shalt speak out of the ground; and thy
                    speech shall be low out of the dust, and thy voice shall be as one that hath a
                    familiar spirit <pb break="no" facs="nls:194557814" xml:id="kp-eb0716-7814-0073"
                    />(an <hi rend="smallcaps">ob),</hi> out of the ground, and thy speech shall
                    whisper out of the dust.”</p>
                <p>But although the Egyptian priests were undoubtedly the inventors of the whole
                    mystery of necromancy, and although it was from them imported into Greece by the
                    Selli or priests of Dodona, it does not appear that the Grecian necromancers
                    pretended to be masters of <hi rend="smallcaps">obs</hi> or familiar spirits.
                    Mopsus, Orpheus, Linus, Eumolpus, and others, who either travelled into Egypt in
                    quest of knowledge, or were actually natives of that country, instructed the
                    early Greeks in this occult science; but whatever might be the practice of these
                    apostles themselves, their disciples professed to do all the feats of magic by
                    performing certain rites, by offering certain sacrifices, by muttering a certain
                    form of words, and by charms, spells, and exorcisms. By these they pretended to
                    evoke the dead as certainly as the Egyptians and Jews did by their familiar
                    spirits. By a small display of critical learning this might easily be proved
                    from the popular story of Orpheus and Eurydice, which certainly was founded on
                    one of these necromantic deceptions exhibited in a cave near Dodona, where the
                    priests had a <hi rend="italic">hades</hi> or infernal mansion, in humble
                    imitation of those with which the first of them were well acquainted in Egypt.
                    It is indeed evident, without the aid of criticism; no man of any letters can be
                    ignorant, that whatever superstitions of this kind prevailed amongst the Romans
                    were borrowed from the Greeks. But we all know that Virgil makes one of his
                    shepherds, by means of certain herbs, poisons, and senseless charms, raise up
                    ghosts from the bottoms of their graves; and Lucian has fabricated a story of
                    this kind, which may be considered as an exact parallel to that of the witch of
                    Endor. Just before the battle of Pharsalia he makes young Pompey travel by night
                    to a Thessalian sorceress, and anxiously inquire of her the issue of the war.
                    This female necromancer, by a tedious process of charms and incantations,
                    conjures up the ghost of a soldier who had been recently slain. The phantom,
                    after a long preamble, denounces a prediction much of the same kind with that
                    which the king of Israel received from Samuel at Endor; and though we have
                    elsewhere shown, that nothing but the spirit of God could have foreseen the
                    inevitable destruction of Saul, his sons, and his army, it was very easy for any
                    man of tolerable sagacity to foresee the defeat of Pompey’s raw and
                    undisciplined troops by the hardy veterans of the victorious Caesar.</p>
                <p>It would be endless to enumerate all the fallacious evocations of ghosts, and the
                    ambiguous responses returned by those pretended spirits, of which we have
                    received accounts from the poets and historians of the celebrated nations of
                    antiquity. We shall therefore proceed to mention a few which occur in the
                    fabulous history of more modern nations, and then leave the subject to the
                    meditation of our readers. In Mallet’s Northern Antiquities we have the
                    following account of a necromantic exploit, between which and the descent of the
                    ancient heroes into hell it is impossible not to remark a striking
                    similitude.</p>
                <p>Odin, the sovereign of man, arises. He saddles his horse Sleipner; he mounts, and
                    is conveyed to the subterranean abode of <hi rend="italic">Ilela.</hi> The dog
                    which guards the gates of death meets him. His breast and his jaws are stained
                    with blood. He opens his voracious mouth to bite, and barks a long time at the
                    father of magic. Odin pursues his way; and the infernal cavern resounds and
                    trembles under his horse’s hoofs. At length he reaches the deep abode of death,
                    and stdps near the eastern gate, where stands the tomb of the prophetess. He
                    sings with a voice adapted to call up the dead; he looks towards the world; he
                    engraves Runic characters upon her tomb; he utters mysterious words; and he
                    demands an answer, until the prophetess is constrained to arise and utter the
                    words of the dead. “Who is this unknown that dares to disturb my repose, and
                    drag me from the grave, in which I have been dead so long, all covered with
                    snow, and moistened with the rain ?”</p>
                <p>The Gaelic druids pretended to be masters of the same secret. This is evident
                    from the name of a species of divination called <hi rend="italic">taghairm,</hi>
                    notuncommon amongst the Scotch Highlanders so recently as in the beginning of
                    the eighteenth century. This word seems to be compounded of <hi rend="italic"
                    >ta,</hi> which in some parts of the Highlands is still used to denote a spirit
                    or ghost, and <hi rend="italic">ghairm,</hi> which signifies calling upon or
                    invoking. <hi rend="italic">Taghairm,</hi> therefore, in its original import, is
                    necromancy in the most proper sense of that word.</p>
                <p>There were different kinds of <hi rend="italic">taghairm,</hi> of which one was
                    practised in Skye. The diviner covered himself with a cow’s hide, and repaired
                    at night to some deep-sounding cave, whither the person who consulted him
                    followed soon afterwards without any attendants. At the mouth of the cave he
                    proposed aloud the questions of which he wanted solutions; and the man within
                    pronounced the responses in a tone of voice similar to that with which the <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">obs,</hi> or pretended demons of antiquity, gave from beneath
                    the ground their oracular answers. That in the latter days of <hi rend="italic"
                    >taghairm,</hi> the Gaelic diviners pretend to evoke ghosts, and from them to
                    extort solutions of difficulties proposed, we have no positive evidence; but
                    that such was the original pretence there can be little doubt, when we reflect
                    either upon the place where this species of divination was practised, or upon
                    the import of the word by which it was denominated.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
