<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0716-9504-0203-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">NICHOLS, Frank</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 16, page 203</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4f47gx2h">Physics</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gc8s">Fever</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r39q">Franks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4gx44x4f">Doctors</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f41h">Physicians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1063025">Physics</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:923528">Fever</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:933759">Franks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1062841">Physicians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1198508">Mead</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:950637">Halls</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194559504" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">NICHOLS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Frank</hi></label>, doctor of
                    physic, was born in London in the year 1699. His father was a barrister at law,
                    and both his parents were of good families in Cornwall. After receiving the
                    first rudiments of his education at a private school in the country, where his
                    docility and sweetness of temper endeared him equally to his master and his
                    schoolfellows, Frank was in a few years removed to Westminster, and from thence
                    to Oxford, where he was admitted a commoner of Exeter College, under the tuition
                    of Mr John Haviland, on the 4th of March 1714. There he applied himself
                    diligently to all the usual academical studies, but particularly to natural
                    philosophy and polite literaturς, of which the fruits were most conspicuous in
                    his subsequent lectures on physiology. After reading a few books on anatomy, in
                    order to perfect himself in the nomenclature of the animal parts then adopted,
                    he engaged in dissections, and then devoted himself to the study of nature,
                    perfectly free and unbiassed by the opinions of others.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:194559517" xml:id="kp-eb0716-9517-0204"/>
                <p>When he was chosen reader of anatomy in that university, he employed his utmost
                    attention to elevate and illustrate a science which had there been long
                    depressed and neglected; and by quitting the beaten track of former lecturers,
                    and minutely investigating the texture of every viscus, as well as the nature
                    and order of every vessel, he gained a high and just reputation. He did not then
                    reside at Oxford; but when he had finished his lectures, he used to repair to
                    London, the place of his abode, where he had determined to settle. He had once
                    an intention of establishing himself in Cornwall, and for a short time practised
                    there with great reputation; but being soon tired of the fatigues attendant on
                    that profession in the country, he returned to London, bringing back with him a
                    great insight, acquired by diligent observation, into the nature of the miliary
                    fever, and which was attended with the most salutary effects in his subsequent
                    practice in the metropolis.</p>
                <p>About this time he resolved to visit the Continent, partly with the view of
                    acquiring a knowledge of men, manners, and languages, but chiefly to make
                    himself acquainted with the opinions of foreign naturalists on his favourite
                    study. At Paris, by conversing freely with the learned, he soon recommended
                    himself to their notice and esteem. Winslow’s was the only good system of
                    physiology at that time known in France, and Morgagni’s and Santorini’s in
                    Italy. On his return to England, he repeated his physiological lectures in
                    London, which were much frequented, not only by students from both the
                    universities, but also by many surgeons, apothecaries, and others. Soon
                    afterwards, his new and successful treatment of the miliary fever, then very
                    prevalent in the southern parts of England, added much to his reputation. In
                    1725, at a meeting of the Royal Society, he gave his opinion on the nature of
                    aneurisms, in which he dissented from that expressed by Dr Freind in his History
                    of Physic.</p>
                <p>In the beginning of the year 1728, he was chosen a fellow of the Royal Society,
                    to which he afterwards communicated the description of an uncommon disorder,
                    namely, a polypus, resembling a branch ôf the pulmonary vein, for which Tulpius
                    has strangely mistaken it, coughed up by an asthmatic person. He also made
                    observations on a treatise, by M. Helvetius of Paris, concerning the lungs.
                    Towards the end of the year 1729, he took the degree of doctor of physic at
                    Oxford. On his return to London, he underwent an examination by the president
                    and censors of the College of Physicians, previously to his being admitted a
                    candidate, which every practitioner must be a year before he can apply to be
                    chosen a fellow. Dr Nichols was admitted into the college on the 26th of June
                    1732; and two years afterwards, being chosen Gulstonian reader of Pathology, he
                    made the structure of the heart and the circulation of the blood the subject of
                    his lectures. In 1736, at the request of the president, he again read the
                    Gulstonian lecture, taking for his subject those parts of the human body which
                    serve for the secretion and discharge of the urine, with the causes, symptoms,
                    and cure of the diseases occasioned by the stone. In 1739, he delivered the
                    anniversary Harveian oration. In 1743, he married Elizabeth, youngest daughter
                    of the celebrated Dr Mead, by whom he had five children, two of whom died young.
                    In 1748, Dr Nichols undertook the office of surgical lecturer, beginning with a
                    learned and elegant dissertation on the <hi rend="italic">Anima</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Medica.</hi> About this time, on the death of Dr John Cuningham,
                    one of the elects of the college, Dr Abraham Hall was, without any apparent
                    reason, chosen to succeed him in preference to Dr Nichols, who was his senior.
                    With a just resentment, he immediately resigned the office of surgical lecturer,
                    and never after attended the meetings of the fellows, excepting when business of
                    the utmost importance was in agitation. In 1751» he took some revenge in an
                    anonymous pamphlet, entitled The Petition of the Unborn Babes to the Censors of
                    the Royal College of Physicians of London, in which Dr Nesbit <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Focus'),</hi> Dr Maule <hi rend="italic">(Maulus),</hi> Dr Barrowby <hi
                    rend="italic">(Barebone)</hi> principally, and Sir William Browne, Sir Edward
                    Hulse, and the Scotch incidentally, are the objects of his satire.</p>
                <p>In 1753, on the death of Sir Hans Sloane in his ninety-fourth year, Dr Nichols
                    was appointed to succeed him as one of the king’s physicians, and held that
                    office till the death of his royal master in 1760, when this skilful physician
                    was superseded with something like the offer of a pension, which he rejected
                    with disdain. The causes of the uncommon disorder of which George II. died, viz.
                    a rupture of the right ventricle of the heart, he explained in a letter to the
                    Earl of Macclesfield, president of the Royal Society, which was published in the
                    Philosophical Transactions.</p>
                <p>In 1772, Dr Nichols published a second edition of his treatise <hi rend="italic"
                    >De Anima</hi><hi rend="italic">Medica,</hi> to which he added a dissertation
                    <hi rend="italic">De motu Cordis</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Sanguinis in liomine nato</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">non
                    nato,</hi> inscribed to his learned friend and coadjutor Dr Lawrence.</p>
                <p>Being at length tired of London, and also desirous of superintending the
                    education of his son, he removed to Oxford, where he had most agreeably spent
                    some years in his youth. But when the study of the law recalled Mr Nichols to
                    London, he took a house at Epsom, where he passed the remainder of his life in
                    literary retirement, not inattentive to natural philosophy, especially the
                    cultivation of grain and the improvement of barren soils, and contemplating also
                    with admiration the internal nature of plants, as taught by Linnaeus.</p>
                <p>His constitution never was robust. In his youth, at Oxford, he was with
                    difficulty recovered from a dangerous fever by the skill of Drs Frampton and
                    Frewen; and afterwards at London he had frequently been afflicted with a
                    catarrh, and an inveterate asthmatic cough, which, returning with great violence
                    at the beginning of the year 1778, deprived the world of this valuable man, on
                    the 7th of January, in the eightieth year of his age.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
