<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0716-8191-0102-06" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">NERO, Claudius Caesak</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 16, page 102</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:937144">Galba</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1006241">Majorities</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:908898">Emperors</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:888134">Daughters</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4m32nc36">Fires</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b40k26c70">Fire</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kj57">Caesarism</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c72h">Gauls</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4nv99d9z">Extracts</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:194558191" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">NERO, <hi rend="smallcaps">Claudius Caesak</hi></label>, the
                    sixth of the Caesars, was the fourth Roman emperor in succession from Augustus,
                    and descended from a family which had taken an active part in all the important
                    political transactions of their country. This family, however, had partaken of
                    the degeneracy of the times, and the more immediate predecessors of Nero had
                    been more distinguished for their follies and extravagancies than for the stern
                    virtues of the earlier ages. His grandfather, Cneius Domitius, was chiefly known
                    for the cruelties he had allowed to be perpetrated in the gladiatorial
                    exhibitions, which it was at last found necessary to put down by a public edict,
                    the private remonstrances of Augustus*having been disregarded. Cneius Domitius
                    was married to Antonia Major, the elder daughter of Marc Antony by Octavia,
                    sister to Augustus, and had by her L. Domitius, the father of Nero. L. Domitius
                    attended C. Caesar to the East, where he was dismissed with ignominy, because he
                    had put to death his freedman for refusing to drink as much wine as he ordered.
                    Towards the end of the reign of Tiberius, he was accused of a variety of
                    enormities, and only escaped by the death of the emperor. He was married to
                    Agrippina, the daughter of Germanicus, and the sister of Caligula the
                    emperor.</p><p>Nero was born at Antium, in Latium, on the15th of December, <hi rend="smallcaps">λ.</hi> D. 37, nine months after the murder of Tiberius, and in the first year
                    of Caligula’s reign. On receiving the congratulations of his friends, his father
                    said that it was no subject of joy, as he was certain that nothing good could
                    spring from such parents as himself and Agrippina. Nero lost his father in his
                    third year, and was at the same time deprived by Caligula of his patrimonial
                    estate. The young Nero took refuge in the house of his aunt, Aemilia Lepida,
                    till the accession of Claudius, <hi rend="smallcaps">a. d.</hi> 41, when the
                    property of his father was restored, and he also became the heir of his
                    step-father, Crispus Passienus, an old rich senator, whom his mother had in the
                    meanwhile married. In his eleventh year he was adopted by the Emperor Claudius,
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">a. d.</hi> 48, who had been induced, by the wiles of his
                    mother, to raise her to the imperial throne. He was now placed under the tuition
                    of the philosopher Annaeus Seneca; but the pernicious doctrines and example of a
                    corrupt court were far more likely to make an impression upon the youthful mind
                    of Nero than the stern doctrines of the philosopher. We must not therefore place
                    the follies of the prince to the account of Seneca, nor conclude that he did not
                    perform his duty towards him. In his seventeenth year, <hi rend="smallcaps">a.
                    d.</hi> 54, he married Octavia, the daughter of Claudius; and the same year he
                    ascended the throne (13th of October), on the death of the emperor, who was
                    supposed to have been poisoned by Agrippina.</p><p>Nero began his reign with the usual professions of respect for the senate, and of
                    an intention to take its opinion in all matters of importance. The
                    administration of affairs was chiefly in the hands of Agrippina, of Burrus the
                    prefect of the praetorian guard, and of Seneca the instructor of the emperor.
                    The two latter tried to moderate the furious proceedings of Agrippina, and to
                    prevent her from taking any part in public affairs. Her quarrels with Nero soon
                    enabled them to succeed in this object, as her imperious disposition could
                    endure no rival. Her friend Pallas, who had assisted her to get rid of Claudius,
                    was ordered to retire from court; and Britannicus, the son of Claudius, whose
                    cause Agrippina threatened to espouse, was removed by poison. In the meanwhile,
                    Nero amused himself by night in traversing the streets of Rome in search of
                    adventures: he used to attack people returning from supper, and even to break
                    into shops and rob them, sometimes at the risk of his life. The most innocent of
                    his amusements was music, of which he is said to have been passionately
                    fond..</p><pb break="no" facs="nls:194558204" xml:id="kp-eb0716-8204-0103"/><p>His whole time was devoted to the cultivation of this taste, and, after he had
                    delighted the ears of private parties with his vocal powers, he at last made his
                    appearance upon the public stage, at Naples, <hi rend="smallcaps">a. d.</hi> 64,
                    and was of course much applauded. It is said, that whilst he was performing, the
                    theatre was shaken violently by an earthquake, but that he was so absorbed with
                    the music that he did not perceive it. Agrippina made many attempts to regain
                    her influence over her son, and some of these were of the most flagitious kind;
                    but Nero having become entirely devoted to Poppaea Sabina, was encouraged by her
                    to get rid of Agrippina. After making several abortive attempts, he at last
                    succeeded, <hi rend="smallcaps">a. d.</hi> 59; and, that he might be legally
                    united to Poppaea, he ordered his wife Octavia to be put to death, <hi rend="smallcaps">a.</hi> D. 62. By Poppaea he had one daughter, who died in
                    infancy; and he is said to have soon got rid of this woman by striking her with
                    his heel on the stomach when she annoyed him by complaining of his being
                    frequently absent from her. The dreadful conflagration which happened at Rome,
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">a.</hi> D. 64, was generally believed at the time to have
                    been caused by his orders; and it was even said, that at the moment when it was
                    raging most furiously, he appeared on the top of the palace of Maecenas, on the
                    Esquiline Hill, and sung part of a tragedy entitled the Burning of Troy. It
                    continued to rage during six days, and was only at last stopped by throwing down
                    some of the houses, and thereby preventing the communication of the fire. The
                    use which Nero afterwards made of the space thus cleared by the fire was a
                    strong corroboration of the truth of the report. ’ He appropriated the ground to
                    himself, and erected a palace, called <hi rend="italic">Aurea Domus</hi> from
                    its magnificence, but which was still more remarkable for the beauty of the
                    gardens and ground attached to it. They were laid out under the direction of
                    Severus and Celer, two engineers, who proposed to him to cut a canal along the
                    coast, from Lake Avernus to Ostia, a distance of 160 miles. what advantage he
                    supposed likely to arise from such a project it is difficult to discover; but he
                    actually commenced it in the vicinity of Cumae, and it is supposed that the <hi rend="italic">Lago di Licola</hi> is the remains of this foolish enterprise.
                    Another work which he attempted had been projected by Caligula. This was to cut
                    through the Isthmus of Corinth; and so much interest did he take in the work,
                    that he commenced itwith his own hand, in order to encourage the workmen to
                    proceed in it with zeal. The people were so firmly convinced that the
                    conflagration had been the work of incendiaries, that Nero found it necessary to
                    turn the public indignation in some other direction than himself. The Christians
                    were at this time attracting attention, and, like most new sects, were charged
                    by their enemies with the most atrocious crimes. Nero accused them of having set
                    fire to the city, and many were in consequence put to the most cruel deaths. His
                    conduct had now excited very general indignation against him; and as no one felt
                    secure of his life, a conspiracy was entered into by all the principal men in
                    Rome, including Seneca, and Lucan the poet. It does not appear that Seneca had
                    any thing farther to do with the conspiracy than that he was cognizant of it.
                    The conspiracy, however, was discovered, <hi rend="smallcaps">a.</hi> D. 65, and
                    most of the conspirators were put to death. On the murder of Poppaea, Nero
                    proposed to marry Antonia, daughter of Claudius; but she preferred death to an
                    union with such an inhuman monster. He married Steti-lia Messalina, by whom he
                    had no children. The first circumstance which excited his alarm was the revolt
                    of Vindex, governor of Gaul, who published a manifesto against him, in which he
                    gave the greatest annoyance to Nero by calling him a miserable and despicable
                    musician. Nothing could have given Nero greater pain than such an assertion. A
                    few days afterwards he received intelligence from Spain of the desertion of
                    Galba, who was destined to be emperor; and he at once gave himself up for lost.
                    He sent some of his most faithful freedmen to prepare some ships at Ostia for
                    flight, and in the meanwhile solicited some tribunes and centurions of the
                    praetorian guard to accompany him; but on various pretexts they refused. He soon
                    found himself completely abandoned by all except a few of his freedmen, one of
                    whom, Phaon, offered to conceal him in his villa, about four miles from Rome,
                    between the Via Salaria and Nomentana. But on his way thither he was recognised
                    by a soldier, and though he reached his place of concealment, he was soon
                    discovered, and had only time to give himself a mortal wound when his enemies
                    appeared. He died on the 9th of Junè; <hi rend="smallcaps">a. d.</hi> 68, in the
                    thirty-second year of his age, and the anniversary day on which he had put his
                    wife Octavia to death. He was sucéeeded by Galba, the last of the family of
                    Augustus who ruled the Roman empire. (Suetonius’ Life of Nero; Dion. Cassius, in
                    the Extracts of Zephilinus; Tacitus’ Annals, books xiii.-xvi.)</p></div></body></text></TEI>