<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0716-0505-0280-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">NOTTINGHAM</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 16, page 280</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:961111">Hospitalers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:887617">Danes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:827285">Baptists</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1058777">Personals</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1058667">Personality</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1058664">Personalism</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1058861">Persons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43j3985w">Danes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48911q68">Baptists</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45t3g226">Unitarianism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zg6gf8v">Quakers</term>
                    <term n="18" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194560505" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">NOTTINGHAM</label>, a large market-town of England, the
                    capital of the county of the same name, in the centre of England. It is a place
                    of great antiquity, deriving its name from the Saxon word <hi rend="italic"
                    >Snottingaham,</hi> which is descriptive of its position as a retreat in rocks,
                    since there were formerly many, and are still a few, caverns, cut on the soft
                    rock on which its castle was built. It is by some antiquaries asserted that it
                    was once a Roman station; but that is a subject of controversy. The earliest
                    records notice some incursions of the Danes about 866; but they appear to have
                    received a check from the town, and a defeat near it from King Alfred, who
                    afterwards made it the winter-quarters of his army. William the Conqueror
                    erected a castle, and constructed fortifications so strong as to render the
                    place impregnable against any of the methods of attack which were then known.
                    King Richard Coeur de Lion assembled a parliament in this place previously to
                    his departure for the Holy Land, and another soon after his return from
                    Palestine. It was from Nottingham that Richard III. marched forth to his fatal
                    battle of Bosworth Field. There Charles I. erected his royal standard at the
                    commencement of the civil war, at the spot which is now covered by St James’
                    Church. The Castle of Nottingham, defended by the royalists, was besieged by the
                    parliamentary forces under the command of Colonel Hutchinson, to whom, after a
                    brave defence, it at length surrendered, the particulars of which are related in
                    a most interesting manner by the wife of that officer. When Cromwell had
                    attained supreme power, he ordered the fortifications to be destroyed and the
                    castle to be dismantled. At the beginning of the present century, this town and
                    neighbourhood were distinguished by the riotous disposition manifested amongst
                    the lower orders, who acquired the denomination of Luddites, and were excited to
                    destroy much of that machinery by the aid of which the town subsequently
                    attained to its present high degree of affluence. These disturbances were
                    quelled by the pow er of the law, and some wholesome severities; but it caused
                    the removal of many of the capitalists, and a large portion of the trade, to
                    distant and more tranquil districts. During the excitement respecting
                    parliamentary reform in 1832, a very violent spirit was manifested, which led to
                    the destruction of a silk-mill in the neighbourhood, the burning of the ancient
                    castle belonging to the Duke of Newcastle, and outrages upon private houses.
                    These disturbances led to a few exemplary punishments, and some heavy burdens on
                    the town, to indemnify those whose property had suffered by the riots.</p>
                <p>Nottingham is finely situated upon the side of a hill overlooking the valley of
                    the Trent, and near to the south-, western extremity of what was formerly the
                    forest of Sherwood, once famous as the resort of the celebrated Robin Hood, but
                    now a well-cultivated district. The environs of the town are picturesque and
                    beautiful; and there is a delightful walk on the bank of the river Leen, having
                    a fine view of the south front of the castle, and of the gardens, which were
                    formerly the fish-ponds belonging to that edifice. The windings of the river
                    Trent have also a great effect on the whole scenery.</p>
                <p>Some of the old streets are narrow, but in the great extension of the place of
                    late years some new and spacious avenues have been built, and much improvement
                    has been judiciously effected. The market-place is one of the finest in England.
                    It is spacious, occupying an area of 27,515 square yards, or rather more than
                    five acres and a half. It is well paved, and admirably adapted for the purpose
                    of the three weekly markets held in it on Wednesday, Friday, and Saturday, the
                    last of which is the principal one. At the east of the market-place stands the
                    Exchange Hall, which is a noble-looking building. The pediment is crowned with a
                    well-proportioned pedestal, on which stands the figure of Justice. On the
                    pediment are the town arms, with an oak branch on one side, and an olive branch
                    on the other; and underneath it, with a clock intervening, is a handsome
                    Venetian window, ornamented with two elegant Ionic columns, which lights the
                    spacious room within it. That apartment, when the temporary doors which divide
                    it are thrown open, is 123 feet long, thirty wide, and thirty high, with an
                    arched ceiling. It is used for public dinners, at which more than 400 persons
                    can be commodiously seated, and also for public meetings. This room was nearly
                    destroyed by an accidental fire in 1836, but has been restored and further
                    beautified. One part of the building is appropriated to magisterial business,
                    and another is occupied by the Artisan’s Library; an institution possessing some
                    thousand volumes, which are lent out to members, who pay seven shillings and
                    sixpence on admission, and one shilling and sixpence quarterly. Underneath the
                    Exchange there are a few shops in front, but the principal part of the
                    ground-floor is appropriated to shambles. In another part of the market-place is
                    the Subscription Library, containing a large collection of valuable books; and a
                    news-room; a cabinet of mineralogy, with sculpture, maps, and portraits of
                    eminent individuals connected with the town, amongst whom are Colonel
                    Hutchinson, Lord Byron, Sir Richard Arkwright, and others.</p>
                <p>The other civic buildings are the county jail and hall, a commodious but not
                    elegant structure; the house of correction, which stands on the site of a
                    convent of the hospitallers of St John of Jerusalem; the town hall and town
                    jail, where the borough assizes and sessions, and the mayor’s and sheriff’s
                    courts, are held; the assembly-room, a very elegant building, just erected and
                    fitted up with much taste; and the free grammar school, in which about a hundred
                    boys are gratuitously instructed in Greek and Latin.</p>
                <p>The edifices for religious worship are in about the same proportion to the number
                    of the inhabitants as is seen in other places which have increased with similar
                    rapidity. St Mary’s is usually denominated the mother church of the town, from
                    its priority of erection. It resembles a cathedral more than a parish church in
                    its extent, its architecture, and its decorations, and is the most striking
                    object in the place, when viewed from what is called the high pavement. It
                    stands on an elevated spot, and is said to be nearly seventy feet above the
                    level of the meadows near the town. The date of the erection is unknown, but is
                    said to have been in the fifteenth century. It is in the form of a cross, and
                    has a handsome square tower, in which there <pb break="no" facs="nls:194560518"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0716-0518-0281"/>is a musical peal of ten bells. The length of the
                    structure in the inside is 216 feet, the breadth in the centre ninety-seven, at
                    the west end or principal entrance sixty-seven, and in the chancel twenty-nine
                    feet. The height of the tower is 126 feet, and that of the side aisles sixty
                    feet. The porch on the south side is a very ancient piece of workmanship, on the
                    fluting of the pediment of which were sculptured red and white roses, some
                    traces of which may even yet be discovered. In the west gallery there is an
                    excellent organ of great power, supported by two Tuscan columns, over which is a
                    picture of David playing on his harp. There are in this church many monumental
                    inscriptions on tombs of the family of the Earls of Clare, and one of an Earl of
                    Meath, and the mausoleum of the family of the Wrights.</p>
                <p>Besides the mother church, there are provided for the adherents of the
                    established worship the following edifices, all of them capacious, and
                    appropriately finished, viz. St James’, St Nicholas’, St Paul’s, and St Peter’s.
                    The chapels of various sects are numerous, amounting to twenty, but some of them
                    are very small. They are classed thus: Independents; Baptists, two subdivisions;
                    Wesleyan Methodists, three subdivisions; and one each for Unitarians, Roman
                    Catholics, Quakers, Huntingtonians, and Ingham-ites or Sabellians.</p>
                <p>The charitable institutions depending on endowed foundations or on voluntary
                    contributions are numerous. The General Hospital, built in 1781, contains about
                    two acres of land, given partly by the Duke of Newcastle, and partly by the
                    corporation. It is supported chiefly by subscriptions, and usually contains
                    about 120 patients; whilst between five and six hundred are out-patients,
                    receiving medical advice and assistance. The General Lunatic Asylum is a modern
                    and spacious brick building, erected in 1810, at an expense of nearly L.20,000.
                    There are extensive courts, gardens, and places for recreation, and the whole
                    economy of the place is constructed in such a manner as may best contribute to
                    the recovery or the welfare of the miserable inhabitants. Labray’s and Lambley’s
                    Hospitals are small asylums for aged widows; and Collins’ Hospital is a splendid
                    charity, founded by one of the Smith family of the town, of which Lord
                    Carrington is the present head. It consists of twenty-four small but convenient
                    dwellings for ìsmany poor widows, each of whom receives four shillings weekly,
                    and two tons and a half of coal every year. From the same endowment Carrington
                    Street Hospital has lately occn built, where twenty poor persons are comfortably
                    accommodated. Plumtree Hospital, founded by a family of that name, since
                    transplanted into Kent, in the year 1392, out twice repaired since, viz. in 1650
                    and 1751, has been <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> ebuilt under an act of
                    parliament passed in 1823. Thirteen aged widows are provided with comfortable
                    dwellings vithin the house, and allowed six shillings weekly, whilst hirty
                    others, called out-pensioners, receive ten pounds a •ear. Willoughby’s Hospital
                    contains nineteen tenements, he inhabitants of which receive a small pension.
                    Woo-ey’s Alms are dwellings for six poor persons; and Bilby’s Llmshouses for
                    eight persons, who have each a loaf weekly, nd two tons of coal at Christmas.
                    Warser’s Gate Hos-ital gives apartments to six, and Hanley’s to twelve poor ⅛
                    ersons.</p>
                <p>The other public edifices that deserve notice are the !arracks, built in 1792, a
                    handsome building, with well-con-rived apartments for officers and for the
                    privates, and suit-ble stabling for three troops of horse; the Riding School;
                    small theatre, never long opened nor much attended; ιe water-works, in two parts
                    of the town; the gas-works; id the bridge over the river Trent after that stream
                    has -en augmented by the waters of the Dove and the Derent.</p>
                <p>The population of this town in 1801 amounted to 28,861, in 1811 to 34,253, in
                    1821 to 40,415, and in 1831 to 50,680. This great increase, arising from the
                    progressive extension of its manufacturing industry, is not, however, confined
                    within the limits of the town, but is exhibited in the villages either
                    contiguous to it and forming its suburbs, or at a few miles distance. Thus
                    Snenton, which conjoins the town, contained in 1801 but 558, and in 1831 it had
                    3605 inhabitants; Radford, a parish within a mile of Nottingham, had in 1801 but
                    2269, and in 1831, 9806 persons; Lenton, another parish, in 1801 had 893
                    inhabitants, and in 1831, 3077. There are other parishes near to it, in which a
                    similar progress has been making, so that Nottingham, with its dependencies,
                    maybe estimated, supposing that the increase since 1831 has been at the same
                    rate as in the previous periods, to have more than 70,000 individuals. According
                    to the account of Mr Rickman, the males above twenty years of age employed in
                    the stocking and lace trade are, in Nottingham 4740, in Radford 1300, in Lenton
                    300, at Snenton 430, and at Beeston 300.</p>
                <p>The Trent, which is navigable up to the town, and the various canals which branch
                    from that river, afford the means of easy communication with every part of the
                    kingdom.</p>
                <p>The chief accumulation of capital in the town and its vicinity has been from its
                    manufactures. The most ancient, and still the most extensive, is that of
                    stockings. The earliest introduction of that neat piece of machinery, the
                    stocking-frame, at nearly the same period into Leicester and Nottingham, gave to
                    those towns a superiority in fabrication, which has subsequently been
                    maintained, and which has nearly superseded the domestic manufacture of knitting
                    stockings. The stockings of the two towns, made either from wool, thread,
                    cotton, or silk, are to be seen in every part of the world, and far excel in
                    beauty and cheapness any that are made elsewhere in imitation of them.</p>
                <p>The prosperity of Nottingham has, however, been advanced in a prodigious degree
                    by a new manufacture executed by machinery, analogous to that of the
                    stockingframe, but contrived with a greater portion of mechanical ingenuity.
                    This article of commerce is known by the name of bobbin net. It generally
                    resembles lace, and has in a great degree supplanted that pillow lace for which
                    Flanders, France, and some counties of England were once highly celebrated.</p>
                <p>Although this trade originated at Nottingham, yet the riotous disposition of the
                    workmen called Luddites (which has been already noticed), who opposed all those
                    improvements in machinery to which the extension of this trade has been
                    indebted, caused many of the capitalists to remove their establishments to other
                    and some very distant counties. Yet, notwithstanding such removals, and the
                    rivals thereby created, the trade here has gone on increasing, and is still most
                    extensive in and around Nottingham. Our limits do not admit of tracing the
                    various steps of improvement with great minuteness. At first, only plain nets
                    were made, then quillings were introduced, and afterwards figured or fancy
                    patterns were produced. The two last are the highest priced, and the chief
                    object of the manufacturers here. The number and description of the machines in
                    January 1836 were thus dispersed :—In Nottinghamshire, 372 for plain nets, 1006
                    for quillings, and 784 for fancies; in Leicestershire 207 for plain,
                    thirty-seven for quillings, ninety-nine for fancies; in Derbyshire 192 for
                    plain, forty-nine for quilling, fourteen for fancies; in Devonshire,
                    Somersetshire, and the Isle of Wight, 654 for plain, thirty for quilling, 103
                    for fancies. Total for plain 1425, for quillings 1122, for fancies 1000. The
                    improvement made by the introduction of the quilling and fancy nets has caused
                    additional capital to be invested in machinery, and the employment of from 1500
                    to 2000 additional <pb break="no" facs="nls:194560531"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0716-0531-0282"/>workmen; and the above statement shows that this
                    benefit has principally fallen to the share of Nottingham.</p>
                <p>The following calculation, made by Mr W. Felkin, will show, in a national point
                    of view, the great value of this apparently minute branch of industry. That
                    gentleman estimates that, in the year 1835, there were used in this trade
                    1.850,000 lbs. of sea-island cotton wool, valued at L. 185,000, and 25,000 lbs.
                    of silk, valued at L.40,000. T he produce of these raw materials, and their
                    disposal, are stated by the same person thus: Home consumption for nets,
                    L.320,000; for quillings, L.2l0,000; for fancies, L.580,000; total, L.1,110,000.
                    Foreign trade, for nets, L.340,000; for quillings, 282,000; for fancies,
                    L.480,000; total, L. 1,102,000.</p>
                <p>1he plain nets made in the other parts of the kingdom are mostly sent to
                    Nottingham in the rough state, where they receive the finishing operations of
                    gassing, bleaching, and dressing. The amount of these was, in the year 1835,
                    L.328,000; so that this town, besides the profit upon the goods manufactured in
                    and near it, gains a considerable share of the profit upon the goods made by
                    their rivals.</p>
                <p>The net wages earned by men vary from twelve to thirty-five shillings a week,
                    according to the kind, the width, and the speed of the machines at which they
                    are employed. Sixteen shillings is about the average. Wages to women vary from
                    three to twelve shillings, as they may be occupied, but average about six
                    shillings a week. Children are paid from one to four shillings, and can be
                    useful as embroiderers, or in mending and winding. Mr Felkin says it is
                    difficult to estimate how many persons altogether are employed in the various
                    departments of this flourishing trade.</p>
                <p>Besides the staple trades, there are, in and around the town, several large
                    factories for spinning and weaving cotton goods.</p>
                <p>Nottingham has been celebrated for its ale, the qualities of which have been the
                    theme of song. It is still good, and very potent. Its excellence has been
                    attributed by some to the good quality of the barley grown in the neighbourhood,
                    by others to the purity of the water, and by many to the excellent cellars
                    scooped out of the rock with which most of the good houses are furnished.</p>
                <p>This town returns two members to the House of Commons. The freemen, who were
                    formerly the sole electors, are still numerous, but are exceeded in number by
                    the ten-pound voters.</p>
                <p>By the municipal corporation reform law passed in 1835, this town is to continue
                    a corporation, is divided into seven wards, and has a mayor, fourteen aldermen,
                    and forty-two councillors, with twelve justices of the peace appointed by the
                    crown.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
