<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0112-0099-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">PUFENDORF, Samuel</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 20, page 99</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1033832">Nationalism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1004072">Lutherans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4dn3zx91">Anger</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43j3985w">Danes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1204537">Sweden</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1242804">Scandinavia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204558">Denmark</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n112/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PUFENDORF, <hi rend="smallcaps">Samuel</hi></label>
                    (1632-1694), was born at Chemnitz, Saxony, on the 8th of January 1632, the same
                    year which also saw the birth of three other illustrious political and
                    philosophical writers—Locke, Cumberland, and Spinoza. He belonged to an
                    ecclesiastical family; his father was a Lutheran pastor, and he himself was
                    destined for the ministry. Having completed his preliminary studies at the
                    celebrated school of Grimma, he was sent to study theology at the university of
                    Leipsic, at that time the citadel of Lutheran orthodoxy. Its narrow and dogmatic
                    teaching was profoundly repugnant to the liberal nature of the young student,
                    who was not long in bidding adieu to the professors of theology and throwing
                    himself passionately into the study of public law. He soon went so far as to
                    quit Leipsic altogether, and betook himself to Jena, where he formed an intimate
                    friendship with Erhard Weigel the mathematician, a man of great distinction.
                    Weigel was imbued with the Cartesian philosophy; and it was to his teaching and
                    to the impetus he gave to the application of the mathematical method that
                    Pufendorf owes the exact and ordered mind, and the precision, frequently
                    approaching almost to dryness, which characterize his writings. It was also
                    under Weigel’s influence that he developed that independence of character which
                    never bent before other writers, however high their position, and which showed
                    itself in his profound disdain for “ipsedixitism,” to use the piquant phrase of
                    Bentham.</p>
                <p>Pufendorf was twenty-five years old when he quitted Jena. He hoped to find a
                    career in some of the administrative offices which were so frequently the refuge
                    of the learned in the small states of ancient Germany; but in this he was
                    unsuccessful. In 1658, thanks to his eldest brother Isaiah, who had given up
                    university teaching to enter the Swedish service, he went, in the capacity of
                    tutor, into the family of Petrus Julius Coyet, one of the resident ministers of
                    Charles Gustavus, king of Sweden, at Copenhagen. At this time Charles Gustavus
                    was endeavouring to impose upon Denmark a burdensome alliance, and in the middle
                    of the negotiations he brutally opened hostilities. The anger of the Danes was
                    turned against the envoys of the Swedish sovereign; Coyet, it is true, succeeded
                    in escaping, but the second minister, Steno Bjelke, and the whole suite were
                    arrested and thrown into prison. Pufendorf shared this misfortune, and the
                    future successor of Grotius was subjected to a strict captivity of eight months’
                    duration. Like Grotius, he too had his Loevestein. The young tutor, deprived of
                    books, occupied himself during his captivity in meditating upon what he had read
                    in the works of Grotius and Hobbes. He mentally constructed a system of
                    universal law; and, when, at the end of his captivity, he accompanied his
                    pupils, the sons of Coyet, to the university of Leyden, he was enabled to
                    publish the fruits of his reflexions under the title of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Elementa jurisprudentiae</hi><hi rend="italic">universalis,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">libri</hi><hi rend="italic">duo.</hi> The work was dedicated to
                    Charles Louis, elector palatine, an enlightened prince and patron of science,
                    who offered Pufendorf a chair of Roman law at Heidelberg, and when this was
                    declined he created a new chair, that of the law of nature and nations, the
                    first of the kind in the world. Pufendorf accepted it, and was thus in 1661, at
                    the age of twenty-nine, placed in the most enviable of positions. He showed
                    himself equal to his task, and by his science and eloquence proved himself to be
                    an honour and an ornament to the university.</p>
                <p>The keenly sarcastic tract <hi rend="italic">De statu imperii germanici, liber
                    unus,</hi> dates from this period of his life. Small in bulk, it is great in
                    significance, and is one of Pufendorf’s most important works. Written with the
                    assent of the elector palatine, but published under the cover of a pseudonym at
                    Geneva in 1667, it was supposed to be addressed by a gentleman of Verona,
                    Severinus de Monzambano, to his brother Laelius. The pamphlet made a great
                    sensation. Its author arraigned directly the organi <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n113/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0113-0100"/> zation of the holy empire and exposed its
                    feebleness, denounced in no measured terms the faults of the house of Austria,
                    and attacked with remarkable vigour the politics of the ecclesiastical princes.
                    But he did not thus describe the evil without at the same time suggesting the
                    remedy. Thinking that Germany could not attain to a true monarchy without a
                    great revolution, he proposed to call together a confederation, with a perpetual
                    council representing all the members and occupying itself with external affairs.
                    Before Pufendorf, Philipp Bogislaw von Chemnitz, publicist and soldier, had
                    written, under the pseudonym of “Hippolytus a Lapide,” <hi rend="italic"
                    >De</hi><hi rend="italic">ratione</hi><hi rend="italic">status in</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">imperio</hi><hi rend="italic">nostro Romano-Germanico.</hi>
                    Inimical, like Pufendorf, to the house of Austria, Chemnitz had gone so far as
                    to make an appeal to France and Sweden. Pufendorf, on the contrary, rejected all
                    idea of foreign intervention. But in his plan, in which national initiative was
                    all in all, were propounded the ideas of an army supported at the general
                    expense, the secularization of the ecclesiastical principalities, the abolition
                    of convents, and the expulsion of the Jesuits. His little book is perhaps the
                    most important that was produced in relation to the public law and politics of
                    Germany, and it is noteworthy that he reveals himself as a consummate statesman,
                    having a broad comprehension of the present and a clear insight into the future.
                    Subsequent events proved the justice of his conclusions.</p>
                <p>In 1670 Pufendorf was called to the university of Lund. The influence of his
                    brother Isaiah, as also some disagreements which he had had with his colleagues
                    at Heidelberg, influenced his decision to accept the call; but by this
                    acceptance he did not break with German culture, for in Scandinavia that culture
                    was predominant. The sojourn at Lund was fruitful. In 1672 appeared the <hi
                    rend="italic">De jure</hi><hi rend="italic">natur</hi><hi rend="italic">ae
                    et</hi><hi rend="italic">gentium,</hi><hi rend="italic">libri</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">octo,</hi> and in 1675 a résumé of it under the title of <hi
                    rend="italic">De officio</hi><hi rend="italic">hominis et civis.</hi> The
                    treatise <hi rend="italic">De jure natures</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">gentium</hi> is the first systematic work on the subject. Grotius,
                    whom Pufendorf has been accused of having too servilely followed, had more
                    especially treated of international relations; and on the other hand Oldendorp,
                    Hemming, and Winkler treated of the rudimentary part of the subject. Pufendorf
                    took up in great measure the theories of Grotius and sought to complete them by
                    means of the doctrines of Hobbes and of his own ideas. Judging of the work of
                    Pufendorf as a whole, Mr Lorimer has felt justified in saying that “his
                    conception was a magnificent one, and in the effort which he made to realize it
                    he has left behind him a work which, notwithstanding the unpardonable amount of
                    commonplace which it contains and its consequent dulness, is entitled to the
                    respect of all future jurists. It was nothing less than an attempt to evolve
                    from the study of human nature a system of jurisprudence which should be of
                    universal and permanent applicability.” The author derived law from reason, from
                    the civil law, and from divine revelation, and established thus three
                    “disciplines ”—natural law, civil law, and moral theology. Natural law is all
                    that is commanded to us by pure reason, and hence resulted the first important
                    peint in Pufendorf’s theory, viz., that natural law does not extend beyond the
                    limits of this life and that it confines itself to regulating external acts.
                    Pufendorf combats Hobbes’s conception of the state of nature, and concludes that
                    the state of nature is not one of war but of peace. But this peace is feeble and
                    insecure, and if something <hi rend="superscript"> ι</hi> else does not come to
                    its aid it can do very little for the preservation of mankind. As regards public
                    law Pufendorf, while recognizing in the state <hi rend="italic">(civitas)</hi> a
                    moral person <hi rend="italic">(persona</hi><hi rend="italic">moralis),</hi>
                    teaches that the will of the state is but the sum of the individual wills that
                    constitute it, and that this association explains the state. In this <hi
                    rend="italic">a priori</hi> conception, in which he scarcely gives proof of
                    historical insight, he shows himself as one of the precursors of J. J. Rousseau
                    and of the <hi rend="italic">Contrat</hi><hi rend="italic">social.</hi> On the
                    subject of international law, with which he occupies himself incidentally, it is
                    to be noted that Pufendorf belongs to the philosophical school, and also that he
                    powerfully defends the idea that international law is not restricted to
                    Christendom, but constitutes a common bond between all nations because all
                    nations form part of humanity. As was to be expected, the work made a sensation:
                    it provoked enthusiastic admiration as well as anger and indignation; the author
                    was praised to the skies on the one hand, and accused of irréligion and atheism
                    on the other. The universities of Lund and Leipsic, above all, furnished
                    adversaries and critics. Being passionately attacked, he defended himself with
                    passion, and he may be held to have come victorious out of these conflicts in
                    which his combative and sarcastic soul delighted, for Pufendorf dearly loved a
                    fray.</p>
                <p>In 1677 he was called to Stockholm in the capacity of historiographer-royal. To
                    this new period belong among others the work <hi rend="italic">On the Spiritual
                    Monarchy of the Pope,</hi> which was afterwards inserted in his <hi
                    rend="italic">Introduction to the History of the principal States in Europe at
                    the present Day,</hi> also the great <hi rend="italic">Commentariorum</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">de rebus Suecicis,</hi><hi rend="italic">libri</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">XXVI.,</hi><hi rend="italic">ab expeditione Gustavi Adolphi regis
                    in Germaniam ad abdicationem usque</hi><hi rend="italic">Christines</hi> and a
                    <hi rend="italic">History of</hi><hi rend="italic">Charles</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Gustavus.</hi> In his historical works Pufendorf is hopelessly dry; but he
                    professes a great respect for truth and generally draws from archives. The
                    treatise <hi rend="italic">On the Spiritual Monarchy of the Pope</hi> alone
                    recalls Severinus de Monzambano. There we find the same vigour and the same
                    passion, and all through its pages we feel the indignation of the Protestant who
                    sees the noble cause of religious liberty menaced by the papacy and by its two
                    allies Louis XIV. and James II. Of the same nature is another work of this
                    period, <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">habitu religionis</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">christianae</hi><hi rend="italic">ad</hi><hi rend="italic">vitam
                    civilem,</hi> in which he undertakes to trace the limits between ecclesiastical
                    and civil power, and where he expounds for the first time completely the theory
                    known under the name of “Kollegial System” or “Kollegialismus,” which was
                    actually applied later in Prussia. This work is dated 1687. In 1688 Pufendorf
                    was called to the service of Frederick William, elector of Brandenburg. He
                    accepted the call; but he had no sooner arrived than the elector died. His son
                    Frederick III. fulfilled the promises of his father, and Pufendorf,
                    historiographer and privy councillor, was instructed to write <hi rend="italic"
                    >The History of the Elector William the Great.</hi> The king of Sweden did not
                    on this account cease to testify his goodwill towards Pufendorf, and in 1694 he
                    created him a baron. In the same year, on the 26th of October, Pufendorf died at
                    Berlin and was buried in the church of St Nicholas, where an inscription to his
                    memory is still to be seen.</p>
                <p>The value of the man whose life has been thus briefly sketched was great; he was
                    at once philosopher, lawyer, economist, historian, we may even add statesman.
                    His influence also was considerable, and he has left a profound impression on
                    thought, and not on that of Germany alone. Posterity nas, however, done him
                    scant justice, and has not acknowledged what it really owes to him. Much of the
                    responsibility for this injustice rests with Leibnitz, who would never recognize
                    the incontestable greatness of one who was constantly his adversary. Everybody
                    knows the bitter criticism which he made on Pufendorf, “vir parum jurisconsultus
                    et minime philosophus.” This is only the condensed expression of a multitude of
                    judgments passed by him on the author of the <hi rend="italic">De jure</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">naturae et</hi><hi rend="italic">gentium.</hi> It was on the
                    subject of the pamphlet of Severinus de Monzambano that the quarrel began. The
                    conservative and timid Leibnitz was beaten on the battlefield of politics and
                    public law, and the aggressive spirit of Pufendorf aggravated yet more the
                    dispute, and so widened the division. From that time the two writers could never
                    meet on a common subject without attacking each other. The combat was almost
                    always decided in favour of Pufendorf, but the irony of fate has ratified the
                    words of his adversary, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n114/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0114-0101"/> and the future has accepted an estimate dictated
                    by anger and spite.</p>
                <p>See H. von Treitschke, “Samuel von Pufendorf,” <hi rend="italic">Preussische
                    Jahrbücher,</hi> 1875, vol. XXXV. p. 614, and vol. xxxvi. p. 61; Bluntschli, <hi
                    rend="italic">Deutsches</hi><hi rend="italic">Staats-Wörterbuch,</hi> vol. viii.
                    p. 424, and <hi rend="italic">Geschichte des allgemeinen</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Statsrechts</hi><hi rend="italic">und der Politik,</hi> p. 108; Lorimer, <hi
                    rend="italic">The Institutes of the Law of Nations,</hi> vol. i. p. 74; Droysen,
                    “Zur Kritik Pufendorf’s,” in his <hi rend="italic">Abhandlungen zur neueren
                    Geschichte;</hi> Roscher, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der National-Oekonomik in
                    Deutschland,</hi> p. 304; Franklin, <hi rend="italic">Das deutsche Reich
                    nach</hi><hi rend="italic">Severinus</hi><hi rend="italic">von Monzambano.</hi>
                    (E. N.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
