<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0034-0021-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">PRUSSIC ACID</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 20, page 21</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4m03z42n">Nickel</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xj73">Ferries</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4mg7fx61">Cobalt</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41j97c0n">Hydrogen</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ht2gj64">Nitrogen</term>
                    <term n="38" ref="lcsh1910:b47p8tc8d">Potassium</term>
                    <term n="26" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term n="21" ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f47d">Potash</term>
                    <term n="20" ref="lcsh1910:b4cf9j625">Ammonia</term>
                    <term n="20" ref="lcsh1910:b4gx44v51">Silver</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:939255">Gays</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:923054">Ferries</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1038046">Nitrogen</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1037441">Nickel</term>
                    <term n="38" ref="fasttopic:1073293">Potassium</term>
                    <term n="26" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term n="21" ref="fasttopic:1073274">Potash</term>
                    <term n="20" ref="fasttopic:1118999">Silvering</term>
                    <term n="20" ref="fasttopic:807737">Ammonia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n34/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PRUSSIC ACID</label>, the familiar name for a dangerously
                    poisonous, though chemically feeble, acid, known scientifically as “hydrocyanic
                    acid,” or “cyanide of hydrogen,” is here taken as a convenient heading under
                    which to treat of cyanides generally. This generic term (from <hi rend="italic"
                    >κυανός,</hi> blue) is not meant to hint at any generic property; it is due
                    simply to the fact that all cyanides, in an historical sense, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n35/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0035-0022"/> are derivatives of a blue pigment which was
                    discovered accidentally by Diesbach, a Berlin colourmaker, about the beginning
                    of the 18th century.</p>
                <p>The foundations of our present knowledge of cyanides were laid by Scheele (1783),
                    whose discoveries were subsequently (from 1811) confirmed and supplemented,
                    chiefly in the sense of quantitative determinations, by Gay-Lussac. Although we
                    have no space for further historical notes, we must not omit to state that
                    Gay-Lussac, as one result of his work, conceived and introduced into chemistry
                    the notion of the “compound radical,” having shown that prussic acid and its
                    salts are related to the group NC in precisely the same way as chlorides are to
                    chlorine, or sulphides to sulphur. This idea, in his own eyes and in those of
                    his contemporaries, was greatly fortified by his success in even isolating his
                    “cyanogène” as a substance.</p>
                <p>In preparing cyanogen or cyanides in the laboratory the operator now always
                    starts from prussiate of potash, with which, accordingly, we begin.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Prussiate of Potash,</hi> (NC) <hi rend="subscript"> β</hi>
                    Fe.K <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> + 3H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O (syn.
                    ferrocyanide of potassium; Germ. <hi rend="italic">Blutlaτιgensalz).—</hi> This
                    salt is being produced industrially from animal refuse (hide and horn clippings,
                    old shoes, blood solids, &amp;c. ), carbonate of potash, and iron filings or
                    borings as raw materials. The carbonate of potash is fused at a red heat in an
                    iron pear-shaped vessel suspended within a furnace, or on the cupel-shaped sole
                    of a reverberatory furnace, and the animal matter, which should be as dry as
                    possible, is then introduced in instalments along with the iron. The fusion is
                    continued as long as inflammable gases are going off; then the still fluid mass
                    is ladled out and allowed to cool, when it hardens into a black stone-like body
                    known to the manufacturer as “metal.” When the broken-up metal is digested with
                    water in an iron vessel prussiate of potash passes into solution, while a black
                    residue of charcoal, metallic iron, sulphide of iron, &amp;c., remains. The
                    clarified solution, after sufficient concentration in the heat, deposits on
                    cooling part of its prussiate in lemon-yellow quadratic crystals (generally
                    truncated octahedra), which are purified by recrystallization. The last
                    mother-liquors furnish an impure green salt, which is added to a fresh fuse and
                    so utilized.</p>
                <p>In former times it was believed that the prussiate was produced during the fusion
                    process, and in the subsequent process of lixiviation simply passed into
                    solution, until Liebig showed that this view was untenable. The fuse cannot
                    contain ready-formed prussiate, because this salt at a red heat breaks up with
                    formation of a residue of carbide of iron and cyanide of potassium. The metal in
                    fact when treated with dilute alcohol gives up to it plain cyanide of potassium,
                    and the fully exhausted residue yields no prussiate on treatment with water. The
                    prussiate accordingly must be produced during the process of lixiviation by the
                    action of the cyanide of potassium on some ferrous compound in the metal. Liebig
                    thought that it was partly the metallic iron, partly the sulphide of iron
                    present in the metal, which effected the conversion. According to more recent
                    researches a double sulphide, K <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> S + Fe <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> S <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>, which is always
                    produced during the fusion (from the reagents proper and the sulphur of the
                    organic matter and that of the sulphate of potash present in the carbonate as an
                    impurity), plays this important part. The double sulphide by the action of water
                    breaks up into alkaline sulphide, sulphide of iron (FeS), and sulphur. This
                    sulphide of iron is of a peculiar kind; it does what <hi rend="italic"
                    >ordinary</hi> FeS does not effect, readily at least: it converts the cyanide
                    into prussiate, thus, 6NC. K + FeS = K <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> S + (NC) <hi
                    rend="subscript"> β</hi> Fe.K <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>, while the eliminated
                    sulphur of the original Fe <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> S <hi rend="subscript">
                    3</hi> unites with another part of the cyanide of potassium into sulphocyanate,
                    S + NCK = SNC.K, which latter salt is thus unavoidably produced as a (rather
                    inconvenient) byeproduct. Pure prussiate of potash has the specific gravity
                    1*83; it is permanent in the air. It loses its water, part at 60° C., the rest
                    at 100° C., but very slowly. The anhydrous salt is a white powder. The crystals
                    dissolve in four parts of cold and in two parts of boiling water. It is
                    insoluble in, and not dehydrated by, alcohol.</p>
                <p>Prussiate of potash has the composition of a double salt, Fe(NC) <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> +4KNO, but the idea that it contains these two binary
                    cyanides is entirely at variance with its reactions. Cyanide of potassium is
                    readily decomposed by even the feeblest acids, and to some extent even by water,
                    with elimination of hydrocyanic acid, and on this account perhaps is intensely
                    poisonous. A solution of the prussiate remains absolutely unchanged on
                    evaporation, and the action on it even of strong acids in the cold results in
                    the formation of the hydrogen salt, (NC) <hi rend="subscript"> β</hi> FeH <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 4</hi>, which is decomposed, it is true, but only when the
                    mixture is heated, with evolution of hydrocyanic acid. It is not poisonous. Its
                    solution when mixed with nitrate of silver does not give a precipitate of
                    cyanide of silver, NC. Ag, and a solution of the two nitrates, but yields a
                    unitary precipitate of the composition (NC) <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi> Fe.Ag
                    <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>, which contains all the iron; only nitrate of
                    potassium passes into solution. Other heavy metallic salts behave similarly. On
                    the strength of these considerations chemists, following the lead of Liebig,
                    view prussiate as a binary compound of potassium, K <hi rend="subscript">
                    4</hi>, with a complex radical, N <hi rend="subscript"> β</hi> C <hi
                    rend="subscript"> β</hi> Fe, ‘ ‘ ferrocyanogen.”</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Hydrocyanic Acid,</hi> NC.H.—This acid is prepared most
                    conveniently from prussiate of potash. Wöhler recommends the following method.
                    Ten parts of powdered prussiate are placed in a retort, the neck of which is
                    turned upwards, and a (cooled down) mixture of seven parts of oil of vitriol and
                    fourteen parts of water is then added. If the aqueous acid is wanted, the
                    exit-end of the retort is joined on direct to a Liebig’s condenser, which must
                    be kept very cool by a current of cold water. If the anhydrous acid is desired,
                    two wide-necked bottles (or two large U-tubes) charged with fused chloride of
                    calcium and kept at 30“ C. by immersion in a water bath of this temperature,
                    must be inserted between the retort and condenser. In this case more
                    particularly it is indispensable to provide for a most efficient condensation of
                    the vapours; the exitend of the condenser should be provided with an adapter
                    going down to near the bottom of the receiver, which must be surrounded by a
                    freezing mixture. The temperature of the latter, of course, must not be allowed
                    to fall to the freezing-point of the distillate. The retort is heated by means
                    of a sand bath and a brisk distillation maintained until the residue begins to
                    dry up. The result of the reaction is in accordance with the assumption that the
                    dilute vitriol, in the first instance, converts the prussiate, one-half into
                    (NC) <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi> Fe.H <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>, the other
                    into (NC) <hi rend="subscript"> β</hi> Fe.K <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> H <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, and that through the effect of the heat these two
                    bodies decompose each other into {(NC) <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi> Fe} K <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> Fe, which remains in the residue as a precipitate, and
                    (NC) <hi rend="subscript"> β</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi> =6NCH, which
                    distils over. Real NCH is a colourless liquid of 0 ’ 6967 specific gravity at
                    18° C., which freezes at -15° C. (Gay-Lussac) into a white fibrous solid.
                    According to Schulz the acid, if really pure, remains liquid at - 37° C. It
                    boils at 26° '5 C.; at 4° ’ 5 its vapour-tension already amounts to half an
                    atmosphere. The vapour is inflammable and burns into carbonic acid, water, and
                    nitrogen. The acid mixes with water in all proportions, with contraction and yet
                    absorption of heat. The solution behaves on distillation like a mere mechanical
                    mixture of its two components. Prussic acid has a very peculiar powerful smell;
                    more characteristic still is a kind of choking action which even the highly
                    attenuated vapour exerts on the larynx. Prussic acid is fearfully poisonous; a
                    few drops of even the ordinary pharmaceutical preparation (of 2 per cent.) are
                    sufficient to kill a large dog. It acts with characteristic promptitude,
                    especially when inhaled as a vapour. Even a relatively large dose, if it has
                    once found its way into the stomach without producing a fatal effect, is said to
                    do relatively little harm there.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>The <hi rend="italic">British Pharmacopoeia</hi> prescribes
                    for the medicinal acid a strength of 2 per cent, of real NCH. The two medicinal
                    preparations known as <hi rend="italic">aqua</hi><hi rend="italic">amygdalarum
                    amararum</hi> and as <hi rend="italic">aqua laurocerasi</hi> respectively
                    contain prussic acid in combination with hydride of benzoyl, C <hi
                    rend="subscript"> β</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> s</hi>.COH. In neither case
                    does the prussic acid pre-exist in the vegetable materials, but is produced
                    during the mashing process which precedes the distillation, by a fermentative
                    decomposition of the amygdalin which they contain. (See <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Fermentation,</hi> vol. ix. p. 96.)</p></note></p>
                <p>Prussic acid is characteristically prone to suffer “spontaneous decomposition.”
                    Whether the <hi rend="italic">pure</hi> anhydrous acid really is, in the
                    strictest sense of the word, still requires to be found out; the ordinary
                    preparation, when kept in a close bottle, soon turns brown and turbid from ‘ ‘
                    azulmic " acid, a substance of complex constitution. Other things are formed at
                    the same time. <hi rend="italic">The pure</hi> aqueous acid is liable to similar
                    changes; in its case formiate of ammonia always forms the predominant product.
                    This change is easily understood—</p>
                <p>NC. H + 2H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O = NH <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> + H.
                    COOH. Ammonia. Formic acid.</p>
                <p>A strong aqueous prussic acid, when mixed with fuming hydrochloric acid, is soon
                    converted into a magma of crystals of salammoniac, with formation of formic
                    acid, which remains dissolved. And yet, most singularly, the addition to the
                    preparation of a small proportion of hydrochloric or sulphuric acid is the best
                    means for preventing, or at least greatly retarding, its spontaneous change in
                    the very same direction. Aqueous prussic acid acts only very feebly (if at all)
                    on blue litmus; it combines with aqueous caustic alkalis but does not decompose
                    their carbonates; nor does it act upon the generality of insoluble basic
                    metallic oxides or hydrates; mercuric oxide and oxide of silver form noteworthy
                    exceptions to this rule.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Cyanogen,</hi> (NC) <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> ∙—When dry
                    mercuric cyanide is heated it breaks up, below redness, into mercury and
                    cyanogen gas; part of the latter, however, always suffers polymerization into a
                    solid called “.paracyanogen,” and presumed to consist of molecules (NC) <hi
                    rend="subscript"> S</hi>. Cyanogen gas is colourless; it has the specific
                    gravity demanded by its formula. It possesses a peculiar odour and has a
                    characteristic <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n36/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0036-0023"/> irritating effect on the eyes and mucous
                    membranes of the nose. It is poisonous. By strong pressure it is condensible
                    into a liquid which freezes at — 34 <hi rend="superscript"> o-</hi> 4 C., and
                    has the following vapour-tensions <hi rend="italic">P</hi> at the temperatures
                    <hi rend="italic">t</hi> stated—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">t =</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>-20° 7</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>-10°</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0°</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>+ 10°</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>+ 20° C.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">P=</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1∙85</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2∙7</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3-8</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5 atmos.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>At ordinary temperatures water dissolves about 4 <hi rend="italic">'5</hi> times,
                    alcohol about 23 times its volume of the gas. The solutions are liable to (very
                    complex) spontaneous decomposition. The list of products includes oxalate of
                    ammonia and urea. Cyanogen burns with a characteristically beautiful
                    peach-blossom coloured flame into carbonic acid and nitrogen. This gas cyanogen,
                    as already stated, is to cyanides what chlorine gas Cl <hi rend="subscript">
                    2</hi> is to chlorides, but it is well to remember that the analogy, though
                    perfect in regard to the corresponding formulae, does <hi rend="italic"
                    >not,</hi> as a rule, extend to the conditions of formation of the bodies
                    represented. Thus cyanogen does not unite with hydrogen into prιtssic acid, nor
                    does it combine with ordinary metals in the chlorine fashion. When passed over
                    heated potassium, it is true, it combines with it into cyanide; and caustic
                    potash-ley absorbs it λvith formation of cyanide and cyanate (NCO.K), just as
                    chlorine yields chloride and hypochlorite KC10; but this is about the sum-total
                    of the analogies in action. Yet metallic cyanides of all kinds can be produced
                    indirectly.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Cyanide of Potassium,</hi> NC.K.—An aqueous mixture of the
                    quantities NCH and KHO no doubt contains this salt, but it smells of the acid,
                    and on evaporation behaves more like a mixture of the two congeners than in any
                    other way. An exhaustive union can be brought about by passing NCH vapour into
                    an alcoholic solution of KHO; the salt NC.K then comes down as a crystalline
                    precipitate, which must be washed with alcohol and dried, cold, over vitriol. A
                    more convenient method is to dehydrate yellow prussiate and then decompose it by
                    heating it to redness in an iron crucible. The Fe(NC) <hi rend="subscript">
                    2</hi> part of the salt breaks up into cyanogen and nitrogen, which go off, and
                    a carboniferous finely-divided iron, which remains, with cyanide of potassium,
                    which at that temperature is a thin fluid. Yet the iron sometimes refuses to
                    settle with sufficient promptitude to enable one to decant off the bulk even of
                    the fused cyanide. According to private information received by the writer a
                    French manufacturer uses a certain kind of very porous fireclay as an efficient
                    filtering medium.</p>
                <p>The ordinary “cyanide of potassium” of trade is not strictly that at all, but at
                    best a mixture of the real salt with cyanate. It is produced by fusing a mixture
                    of eight parts of anhydrous prussiate and three parts of anhydrous carbonate of
                    potash, allowing the reaction</p>
                <p>(NC) <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi> Fe. K <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> + K <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> CO <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> = CO <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> + Fe + 5NCK + K. NCO</p>
                <p>Cyanate to complete itself and the iron to settle, and decanting off the clear
                    fuse. The product goes by the name of “Liebig’s cyanide,” but the process was
                    really invented by Rodgers.</p>
                <p>Fused cyanide of potassium assumes on cooling the form of a milky white
                    stone-like solid. It fuses readily at a red heat, and at a white heat
                    volatilizes without decomposition, provided that it is under the influence of
                    heat alone; in the presence of air it gradually passes into cyanate; when heated
                    in steam it is converted into carbonate of potash with evolution of ammonia,
                    carbonic oxide, and hydrogen. When heated to redness with any of the more easily
                    reducible metallic oxides it reduces them to the metallic state, while it passes
                    itself into cyanate. It also reduces the corresponding sulphides with formation
                    of sulphocyanate; for example, Pb(S or 0)+ NCK = Pb +NC(O or S)K. Hence its
                    frequent application in blowpipe analysis. When heated with chlorates or
                    nitrates it reduces them with violent explosion. The aqueous solution of the
                    salt has a strongly alkaline reaction; it smells of hydrocyanic acid and is
                    readily decomposed by even such feeble acids as acetic or carbonic. It readily
                    dissolves precipitated chloride, bromide, and iodide of silver; this is the
                    basis of its application in photography. Large quantities of the salt are used
                    in electroplating.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Other Binary Cyanides.—</hi> Of these only a few can be noticed
                    here. (1) <hi rend="italic">Cyanide of sodium</hi> is very similar to the
                    potassium salt. The same remark, in a more limited sense, holds for the cyanides
                    of barium, strontium, and calcium. (2) <hi rend="italic">Cyanide of
                    ammonium</hi> (NC.NH <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>) forms crystals volatile at
                    36° C. and smelling of ammonia and hydrocyanic acid. The solution in water
                    decomposes spontaneously, pretty much like that of the free acid. But the
                    anhydrous vapour by itself stands a high temperature, as is proved by the fact
                    that it is produced largely when ammonia is passed over red-hot charcoal, C +
                    2NH <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> = H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> + NCH. NH <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 3</hi>. (3) <hi rend="italic">Mercuric cyanide,</hi> Hg(NC)
                    <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, forms very readily when mercuric oxide is
                    dissolved in aqueous prussic acid. The solution on evaporation and cooling
                    deposits crystals soluble in eight parts of cold water. This salt is not at all
                    decomposed, even when heated, by water, nor appreciably by dilute sulphuric or
                    nitric acid; boiling hydrochloric acid eliminates the NC as hydrocyanic acid;
                    sulphuretted hydrogen acts similarly in the cold. It gives no precipitate with
                    nitrate of silver, nor is it changed visibly by caustic alkalis. It readily
                    unites not only with other cyanides but also with a multitude of other salts
                    into crystallizable double salts. Mercurous cyanide, Hg <hi rend="subscript">
                    2</hi> (NC) <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, seems to have no existence. When it is
                    attempted to produce it by double decompositions, the mixture Hg + (NC) <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> Hg comes forth instead of the compound Hg <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> (NC) <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> ∙ (4) Heavy metallic
                    cyanides are mostly insoluble in water, and the general method for their
                    preparation is to decompose a solution of the respective sulphate, chloride,
                    &amp;c., with one of cyanide of potassium. The most important general property
                    of these bodies is that they readily dissolve in solution of cyanide of
                    potassium with formation of double cyanides, which in their capacity as double
                    salts all exhibit, in a higher or lower degree, those anomalies which were fully
                    explained above (see “prussiate of potash ”). These “metallo-cyanides,” as we
                    will call them, being all, unlike plain cyanide of potassium, very stable in
                    opposition to water and aqueous alkalis, are readily produced from almost any
                    compound of the respective metallic radical—some from the metal itself— by
                    treatment with solution of cyanide of potassium. In all we have said “potassium”
                    may be taken as including sodium and in a limited sense ammonium, but the
                    potassium compounds are best known, and we accordingly in the following section
                    confine ourselves to these.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Metallo-cyanides.</hi> —(1) <hi rend="italic">Silver.—</hi>
                    Cyanide of silver, Ag.NC, is produced as a precipitate by addition of
                    hydrocyanic acid or cyanide of potassium to solution of nitrate of silver. The
                    precipitate is similar in appearance to chloride of silver and, like it,
                    insoluble in cold dilute mineral acids, but soluble in ammonia. At a red heat it
                    is decomposed with formation of a residue of carboniferous metallic silver.
                    Precipitated cyanide of silver, though insoluble in hydrocyanic acid, dissolves
                    readily in cyanide of potassium with formation of argentocyanide, AgK. (NC) <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, which is easily obtained in crystals, permanent in the
                    air and soluble in eight parts of cold water. Chloride of silver dissolves in
                    cyanide of potassium solution as readily as the cyanide does and with formation
                    of the same double salt— AgCl + 2 KN C = KC1 + AgK( NC) <hi rend="subscript">
                    2</hi>. This salt is used very largely in electro-plating. (2) <hi rend="italic"
                    >Lead.—</hi> From a solution of the acetate cyanide of lead is precipitated by
                    addition of hydrocyanic acid or cyanide of potassium. The precipitate, Pb(NC)
                    <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, has the exceptional property of being insoluble in
                    cyanide of potassium. (3) <hi rend="italic">Zinc.—</hi> Cyanide of zinc, Zn(NC)
                    <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, is obtained by addition of hydrocyanic acid to a
                    solution of the acetate, as a white precipitate readily soluble in cyanide of
                    potassium with formation of a double salt, ZnK <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> (NC)
                    <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>, which forms well-defined crystals. (4) <hi
                    rend="italic">Nickel.—</hi> The cyanide, Ni(NC) <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, is
                    an apple-green precipitate, which is obtained by methods similar to those given
                    under ‘ ‘ zinc.” It readily dissolves in cyanide of potassium with formation of
                    a crystallizable salt, NiK <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> (NC) <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 4</hi> + H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O, the solution of
                    which is stable in air and not convertible into one of a nickelic (Ni"')
                    compound by chlorine (compare “cobalt” <hi rend="italic">infra).</hi> The
                    potassio-cyanides of silver, zinc, and nickel as solutions are not changed
                    visibly by caustic alkalis, but their heavy metals can be precipitated by
                    sulphuretted hydrogen or sulphide of ammonium, as from solutions of, for
                    instance, the chlorides. Aqueous mineral acids (in the heat at least) decompose
                    them exhaustively with elimination of all the NC as NCH. (5) <hi rend="italic"
                    >Copper.—</hi> When cyanide of potassium solution is added to one of sulphate of
                    copper, a yellow precipitate of cupι <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> ic cyanide,
                    Cu(NC) <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, comes down; but on boiling this precipitate
                    loses cyanogen and is converted into a white precipitate of the cuprous salt
                    Cu(NC). This white precipitate dissolves in cyanide of potassium with formation
                    chiefly of two crystalline double salts, viz., CuNC + 6NCK, easily soluble in
                    water, and CuNC + NCK. The latter is decomposed by water with elimination of
                    Cu.NC. The solution of the 6NC.K salt is <hi rend="italic">not</hi> precipitated
                    by sulphuretted hydrogen. Solutions of potassio-cyanides of cuprosum are used in
                    electro-plating. (6) <hi rend="italic">Gold.</hi> —Metallic gold dissolves in
                    cyanide of potassium solution in the presence of air, thus—</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Au + 2KNC + ⅞O=⅜K</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps">
                    2</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">O+AuK.(NC)</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps">
                    2</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">.</hi></p>
                <p>This auro-cyanide of potassium is used largely for electro-gilding, for which
                    purpose it is conveniently prepared as follows. Six parts of gold are dissolved
                    in aqua regia and the solution is precipitated by ammonia. The precipitate (an
                    explosive compound known as “fulminating gold ”) is dissolved in a solution of
                    six parts of cyanide of potassium, when the double salt is formed with evolution
                    of ammonia. The salt crystallizes in rhombic octahedra, soluble in seven parts
                    of cold water.</p>
                <p>In the following potassio - cyanides the heavy metals cannot be detected by means
                    of their ordinary precipitants; these salts all behave like the potassium salts
                    of complex radicals composed of the heavy metal and all the cyanogen. (7) <hi
                    rend="italic">Cobalt.—</hi> Cyanide of potassium when added to a solution of a
                    cobaltous salt (CoCl <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, &amp;c. ) gives a precipitate
                    soluble in excess of reagent. The solution presumably contains a
                    cobalto-cyanide, Co(NC) <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>.≈KNC, but on exposure to
                    air eagerly absorbs oxygen with formation of cobalti-cyanide, thus—</p>
                <p>Co(NC), f-4KNC + ⅜O = ⅜K <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O + Co"'(NC) <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 3</hi>.3KNC.</p>
                <p>Chlorine (Cl instead of ⅜0) acts more promptly with a similar effect If the
                    alkaline solution is acidified and boiled, the same cobalti cyanide is produced
                    with evolution of hydrogen—</p>
                <p>Co(NC) <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> + 4KNC + HC1 = KC1 + ⅜H <hi rend="subscript">
                    2</hi> + Co"'(NC) <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>.3KNC.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n37/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0037-0024"/>
                <p>Cobalti-cyanide of potassium, (NC) <hi rend="subscript"> β</hi> Co'". K <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 3</hi>, forms yellow crystals isomorphous with those of red
                    prussiate (see <hi rend="italic">infra).</hi> It is a remarkably stable salt. In
                    its behaviour to reagents it exhibits none of the characters of a cobalt salt or
                    of a simple cyanide. Aqueous mineral acids convert it into the hydrogen salt
                    (NC) <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi> Co"Η <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>, which
                    remains undecomposed on boiling. Heavy metallic salts produce precipitates of
                    cobalti-cyanides; for example, (NC) <hi rend="subscript"> β</hi> Co"'. Ag <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 3</hi>. (8) <hi rend="italic">Ferrosum.—</hi> See “prussiate
                    of potash” above. (9) <hi rend="italic">Fcrrieum.—</hi> Ferric hydrate and
                    ferric compounds generally do not act upon cyanide of potassium in a manner
                    analogous to that of ferrous compounds; but a ferri-cyanide analogous to the
                    cobalti-salt referred to in (7) is readily produced by passing chlorine into a
                    cold solution of ordinary prussiate, (NG) <hi rend="subscript"> β</hi> Fe".K <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 4</hi> + Cl∙=KCl + (NC) <hi rend="subscript"> β</hi> fe"'.K
                    <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Here we use the symbol “fe” as designating 56 parts of
                    ferric iron,—“Fβ” meaning the same quantity of ferrosum.</p></note> In preparing
                    the salt an excess of chlorine and elevation of temperature must be avoided, or
                    else part of the salt is decomposed with formation of a green precipitate. The
                    solution on evaporation and cooling yields splendid dark red crystals, soluble
                    in 2’54 parts of water of 15 <hi rend="superscript"> o-</hi> 6 C. (Wallace),
                    forming a most intensely yellow solution. (Ordinary prussiate solution is only
                    pale yellow even when saturated in the cold. ) This salt (discovered by L.
                    Gmelin in 1822) is now being manufactured industrially and is known in commerce
                    as “red prussiate.” In its reactions it is analogous to ordinary yellow
                    prussiate. The same group, (NC) <hi rend="subscript"> β</hi> Fe, which in the
                    latter acts as a four-valent, in the red salt plays the part of a tri-valent
                    radical, (NC) <hi rend="subscript"> β</hi> fe. But the radical thus modified has
                    a great tendency to assume the four-valent form; hence an <hi rend="italic"
                    >alkaline</hi> solution of red prussiate is a powerful oxidizing agent, (NC) <hi
                    rend="subscript"> β</hi> fe.K <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> + KHO = (NC) <hi
                    rend="subscript"> β</hi> Fe. K <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> + HO. The HO goes to
                    the reducing agent Like the yellow salt, red prussiate is not poisonous, at
                    least when pure.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ferro-and Ferri-cyanides of Iron.—</hi> The two prussiates are
                    constantly being used in the laboratory as very delicate reagents for the
                    detection of iron salt, and for the discrimination of ferrous and ferric
                    compounds in solutions,—(1) ferro-cyanide and ferrous salt, white precipitate;
                    (2) ferri-cyanide and ferric salt, intensely brown coloration; (3) ferro-cyanide
                    and ferric salt, blue precipitate; (4) ferri-cyanide and ferrous salt, blue
                    precipitate. These blue precipitates are being produced industrially and used as
                    pigments, under the names of “prussian blue” and “Turnbull’s blue” for (3) and
                    (4) respectively. The latter has been thus known for now half a century; yet the
                    constitution of the precipitates and the true rationale of their formation have
                    been fully cleared up only during the last few years. The main results of the
                    researches referred to are included in the following paragraphs.</p>
                <p>(1) <hi rend="italic">Ferro-cyanide of Hydrogen,</hi> (NC) <hi rend="subscript">
                    β</hi> Fe. H <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>, is obtained as a white crystalline
                    precipitate when air-free concentrated solution of yellow precipitate is mixed
                    with hydrochloric acid and ether. It is easily soluble in water and in alcohol.
                    An aqueous solution of it is prepared for technical purposes by mixing a strong
                    solution of yellow prussiate with enough tartaric acid to bring down the
                    potassium as cream of tartar. When the solution of this ferro-hydrocyanic acid
                    is boiled half the cyanogen goes off as N CH, while the other remains as part of
                    a white, rather unstable, precipitate, (NC) <hi rend="subscript"> β</hi> Fe .∩
                    <hi rend="superscript"> θ</hi>. When the solution is exposed to the air,
                    especially at higher temperatures, part of the cyanogen goes off as NCH, another
                    part suffers oxidation into H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O + NC, and this
                    latter combines with the Fe(NC) <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> of the original
                    compound into blue bodies similar in their general properties to prussian blue.
                    This latter change is utilized in calico-printing for producing patterns of, or
                    dyeing with, prussian blue. The white precipitate (NC) <hi rend="subscript">
                    β</hi> Fe.^ <hi rend="superscript"> e</hi> may be looked upon as an acid of
                    which <hi rend="subscript"> p</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi></p>
                <p>(2) <hi rend="italic">Everett’s Salt,</hi> (NC) <hi rend="subscript"> β</hi> Fe.
                    is the potash salt. This salt is produced in the ordinary process lor making
                    prussic acid (see above). It is probably identical with the white precipitate
                    produced when ferrous salt is decomposed by prussiate of potash. Everett’s salt
                    when exposed to the air quickly absorbs oxygen and becomes blue; the reaction,
                    as Williamson showed, assumes a simple form when the precipitate is boiled with
                    nitric acid. One-half of the potassium is then oxidized away, and a blue double
                    ferri-cyanide of potassium and ferrosum takes the place of the original
                    precipitate :—</p>
                <p>(NC) <hi rend="subscript"> β</hi> Fe. K <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> Fe = ⅛(K <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O as nitrate) + {(NC) <hi rend="subscript"> β</hi> fe}
                    "'Fe"K'. Williamson’s blue.</p>
                <p>This blue when boiled with ferro-cyanide of potassium is reconverted into the
                    original EveYett’s salt with formation of a solution of red prussiate—</p>
                <p>(NC) <hi rend="subscript"> β</hi> fe. KFe* + K <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> *K
                    <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>. Fe(NC) <hi rend="subscript"> β</hi> =(NC) <hi
                    rend="subscript"> β</hi> fe. K <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> + Fe(NC) <hi
                    rend="subscript"> β</hi>. FeK <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, Red prussiate.
                    Everett’s salt.</p>
                <p>the asterisked radicals changing places.</p>
                <p>(3) <hi rend="italic">Soluble Prussian Blue</hi> is <hi rend="italic"
                    >isomeric</hi> with Williamson’s blue. It is produced by mixing a solution of
                    feme salt with <hi rend="italic">excess</hi> of yellow prussiate, which,
                    however, is an old process; what has been ascer tained lately is that the very
                    same precipitate is produced by addition to a ferrous salt of an excess ς&gt;f
                    red prussiate.</p>
                <p>I. (NC) <hi rend="subscript"> β</hi> fe.K <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> + FeCl <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> = 2KCl + (NC) <hi rend="subscript"> β</hi> fe. KFe =
                    B'.</p>
                <p>II. (NC) <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi> Fe. K <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> + feCl
                    <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> = 3KC1 + (NC) <hi rend="subscript"> β</hi> Fe. Kfe
                    = B".</p>
                <p>B' and B" in the formulae look different, but the difference is only apparent; in
                    either case the group (NC) <hi rend="subscript"> β</hi> is combined with IFe and
                    lie and IK; the bodies are identical (Skraup; Reindel). The precipitate B,
                    though insoluble in salt solutions, is soluble in pure water, forming an
                    intensely blue solution; hence the name.</p>
                <p>Now the potassium in soluble prussian blue can be displaced by iron in two ways,
                    namely, by digestion with solutions of ferrous or ferric salts. In the former
                    case (NC) <hi rend="subscript"> β</hi> feFeK becomes (NC) <hi rend="subscript">
                    β</hi> feFe∣, or empirically (NC) <hi rend="subscript"> 12</hi> Fe <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 5</hi>; this is Gmelin’s (“Turnbull’s”) blue. In the
                    lattercase (NC) <hi rend="subscript"> β</hi> FefeKbec0mes(NC) <hi
                    rend="subscript"> β</hi> Fefe4, or empirically (NC) <hi rend="subscript">
                    18</hi> Fe <hi rend="subscript"> 7</hi>; this is prussian blue as discovered by
                    Diesbach. Contrasting this latter formula with that of Gmelin’s blue (NC) <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 18</hi> Fe <hi rend="subscript"> 7</hi> ∣, we see that the
                    latter needs only lose ⅜Fe to become prussian blue; this surplus iron in fact
                    can be withdrawn by means of nitric acid.</p>
                <p>In the manufacture of prussian blue the general process is to first precipitate
                    ferrous sulphate with yellow prussiate and then to fully oxidize the precipitate
                    by means of nitric acid or chlorine as far as the oxygen of the air does not do
                    it. The following receipt is recommended amongst others. Six parts each of green
                    vitriol and yellow prussiate are dissolved separately, each in fifteen parts of
                    water, and the solutions mixed. One part of concentrated sulphuric acid and
                    twenty-four parts of fuming muriatic acid are then added, and after standing
                    some hours also a solution of bleaching powder in instalments until the blue
                    colour is fully developed. “Turnbull’s” blue is made by precipitating red
                    prussiate of potash with excess of ferrous salt; but it is easily seen from what
                    was said above that the use of this relatively expensive double cyanide might be
                    dispensed with. The properties of the two pigments are {&gt;retty much the same.
                    They are sold in the form of solid cakes or umps, which, in addition to their
                    blue colour, present a coppery lustre on fracture. They are stable against
                    acids, but sensibly affected (bleached) on prolonged exposure to sunlight; and,
                    although they stand neutral soap fairly well, they are decomposed promptly by
                    solutions of even the carbonates of the alkalis with formation of hydrated
                    oxides of iron. The cheaper commercial varieties are more or less largely
                    diluted with clay, sulphate of baryta, &amp;c. Pure prussian blue dissolves
                    readily in a dilute solution of oxalic acid; the intensely blue solution used to
                    serve as a blue ink, but has come to be superseded by the several more brilliant
                    blues of the coal-tar series. These tar-blues have displaced prussian blue also
                    in other applications, and as a commercial pigment it has besides to struggle
                    against ultramarine. In short, it has gone very much out of use, and as a
                    consequence the manufacture of yellow prussiate is no longer so remunerative as
                    it used to be.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Analysis of Cyanides.—</hi> As hydrocyanic acid and cyanide of
                    potassium are dangerously poisonous, and the latter at least is easily procured
                    in commerce, the detection of cyanogen in this state of combination is one of
                    the problems of forensic chemistry. To detect such cyanogen in, say, the
                    contents of a stomach the first step is to distil the mass after acidification
                    with tartaric acid, which decomposes cyanide of potassium but does not liberate
                    prussic acid from prussian blue (or even prussiate of potash ?). If the
                    distillate gives <hi rend="italic">no</hi> precipitate with nitrate of silver
                    hydrocyanic acid is absent, if it does the precipitate may have been produced by
                    hydrochloric acid, which may then be eliminated by redistillation with borax or
                    sulphate of soda, neither of which affects NCH. But even in the presence of
                    chlorides the following two tests give perfect certainty. (1) A solution of
                    hydrocyanic acid, when alkalinized with caustic potash and then mixed with,
                    first ferroso-ferric salt and then excess of hydrochloric acid, gives a
                    precipitate, or at least a green suspension, of prussian blue. (2) A solution of
                    NCH, when mixed with ammonia and yellow sulphide of ammonium, is changed into
                    one of sulphocyanate of ammonium, which, after removal of the excess of reagents
                    by evaporation at a gentle heat, strikes an intense and very characteristic red
                    colour with feιτic salts, which colour does <hi rend="italic">not</hi> vanish
                    (as that of ferric acetate does) on even strong acidification with mineral acid
                    (Liebig’s test). The <hi rend="italic">quantitative</hi> determination of
                    cyanogen given as an aqueous solution of hydrocyanic acid or cyanide of
                    potassium can (if haloids are absent) be effected by adding excess of nitrate of
                    silver, then acidifying, if necessary, with nitric acid, filtering off, washing,
                    drying, and weighing the cyanide of silver produced. AgNC=134 corresponds to NCH
                    = 27 parts. Amoreex-peditious method has been invented by Liebig. A known
                    quantity of the given prussic acid is alkalinized strongly with caustic potash
                    and then diluted freely with water. The caustic alkali usually contains plenty
                    of chloride as an impurity, else a little alkaline chloride must be added. A
                    standard solution of nitrate of silver (conveniently adjusted so as to contain
                    6’30 grammes of fused nitrate per 1000 cubic centimètres, equivalent to 2
                    grammes of NCH) is now dropped in from a burette until the cloud of chloride of
                    silver which appears locally from the first just fails to disappear on stirring,
                    <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> until the reaction 2KNC + AgNO <hi rend="subscript"
                    > 3</hi> = KAg.(NC) <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> + KNO <hi rend="subscript">
                    3</hi><pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n38/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0038-0025"/> has just been completed. One cub. cent, of silver
                    solution used indicates 2 milligrammes of NCH. Liebig’s method lends itself
                    particularly well for the assaying of the medicinal acid and of cyanide of
                    potassium. The two tests for hydrocyanic acid given above apply as they stand to
                    solutions of the cyanides of alkali and alkaline-earth metals, but <hi
                    rend="italic">not</hi> to mercuric cyanide. In regard to all other cyanides we
                    have only space to say that from a certain set (which includes the
                    cobalti-cyanides and the platinum cyanides) cyanogen cannot be extracted at all
                    as NCH (or AgNC) by any known methods. Such bodies must be identified by their
                    own specific reactions or by elementary analysis. All cyanides are decomposed by
                    <hi rend="italic">hot</hi> concentrated sulphuric acid; the carbon goes off as
                    CO, the nitrogen remains as sulphate of ammonia and the metals as sulphates,
                    which brings them within the range of the routine methods of analysis.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Cyanates.—</hi> These were discovered by Wöhler. The potassium
                    salt NCO.K is produced by the oxidation of fused cyanide, for preparative
                    purposes most conveniently by Wöhler’s method. An intimate mixture of two parts
                    of absolutely anhydrous prussiate of potash and one part of equally dry binoxide
                    of manganese is heated on an iron tray until the mass has become brownish black
                    and just begun to fuse. It is now allowed to cool and exhausted by boiling 80
                    per cent, alcohol. The filtrate on cooling deposits crystals of the salt NCO.K.
                    If only an aqueous solution of this salt is wanted for immediate use, the fuse
                    may be extracted by <hi rend="italic">cold</hi> water. From this solution the
                    cyanate of silver, NCO.Ag, or lead, (NCO) <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> Pb, can
                    be prepared by precipitation with solutions of the respective nitrates or
                    acetates. <hi rend="italic">Hot</hi> water decomposes cyanate of potash promptly
                    with formation of carbonates of potash and ammonia, KNCO + 2H <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O = NH <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> + KHO + CO <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> ∙ On addition of mineral acid to even the cold solution
                    only a very little of the cyanic acid is liberated as such; the bulk breaks up
                    at once with effervescence, thus, NCO. H + 2H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O =
                    NH <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> + CO <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> + H <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O. Very interesting is the action of the solution of
                    cyanate of potash on sulphate of ammonia; its direct effect is the formation of
                    cyanate of ammonia, NCO.NH <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>, but this salt almost
                    immediately passes spontaneously into its isomer urea, which is not a cyanate at
                    all but the amide of carbonic acid, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> CO(OH) <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi>-2(OH) + 2NH <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> =CθiJS <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>. This reaction was discovered by Wöhler, who thus for
                    the first time produced an organic substance from inorganic materials, or
                    virtually from its elements. Singularly, it is this pseudo-cyanate urea which
                    serves as a material for making cyanic acid. When hydrochlorate of urea, HC1.CON
                    <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>, is heated to 145°
                    C. the latter behaves as if it were cyanate of ammonia: the ammonia unites with
                    the hydrochloric acid into sal-ammoniac and the cyanic acid is set free, but
                    immediately suffers polymerization into cyanuric acid, a solid tri - basic acid
                    of the composition N <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> C <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>
                    O <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>, which, being
                    difficultly soluble, can be freed from the sal-ammoniac by being washed with
                    cold water. If perfectly anhydrous cyanuric acid be subjected to dry
                    distillation it furnishes a distillate of (liquid) cyanic acid NCO. H, which
                    must be condensed in a vessel surrounded by a freezing mixture.</p>
                <p>Cyanic acid has a very appreciable vapour-tension even at ordinary temperatures,
                    and the least trace of its vapour makes itself felt by a characteristically
                    violent and dangerous action on the respiratory organs. With dry ammonia gas it
                    unites into true cyanate of ammonia. We do not know much of its own properties,
                    because as soon as it comes out of the freezing mixture it begins to suffer
                    polymerization into “cyamelid” with great evolution of heat. This cyamelid is a
                    porcelain-like mass, insoluble in all ordinary solvents and devoid of acid
                    properties. Dry distillation reconverts it into cyanic acid.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Thiocyanates.—</hi> This term means bodies like cyanates, but
                    containing sulphur instead of the oxygen of the latter. Thiocyanates are better
                    known, however, as sulphocyanates or sulphocyanides. (1) The potassium salt
                    NCS.K is formed when cyanide of potassium is fused with sulphur or certain
                    metallic sulphides, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> PbS. The usual method of
                    preparation is to fuse together forty-six parts of dehydrated yellow prussiate
                    of potash, seventeen of dry carbonate of potash, and thirty-two of sulphur. The
                    fuse is exhausted with boiling alcohol and the filtered solution allowed to
                    cool, when crystals of the salt separate out. The salt is very soluble in water
                    with characteristically large absorption of heat. (2) The ammonium salt NCS. NH
                    <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> can be prepared by allowing a mixture of alcohol,
                    strong aqueous ammonia, and bisulphide of carbon to stand for a time and then
                    warming it. Thiocarbonate of ammonium, CS <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>.(NH <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 4</hi>) <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> S, is produced first, but
                    subsequently it gives up 2H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> S to the ammonia and
                    becomes NCS. NH <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>, which is easily obtained in
                    crystals. The tar water obtained in the manufacture of coal-gas sometimes
                    contains sufficient quantities of this salt to make it worth while to recover
                    it. Both the potassium and the ammonium salt are much used as reagents, and more
                    especially as precipitants for copper and silver. Solutions of cupric salt when
                    mixed with sulphocyanate assume the dark-brown colour of the cupric salt Cu(NCS)
                    <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, but on addition of sulphurous acid the colour
                    disappears and a white precipitate of cuprous sulphocyanide,</p>
                <p>NCS.Cu, comes down, which, if enough of reagent was used, contains all the
                    copper. If sulphocyanate is added to nitrate of silver, all the silver is
                    precipitated as Ag. NCS, similar in appearance to the chloride and, like it,
                    insoluble in water and in nitric acid. Upon this and the fact that
                    sulphocyanates strike a deep red colour with ferric salts Volhard has based an
                    excellent titrim etric method for the determination of silver. (See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Silver.)</hi><hi rend="italic">Syntheses of Cyanogen Compounds.
                    —</hi> Synthetical organic chemistry dates from Wöhler’s discovery of the
                    artificial formation of urea, and in the further development of this branch of
                    the science cyanogen has played a prominent part. (For illustrations we may
                    refer to certain passages in the present article and in those on <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Methyl</hi> and on <hi rend="smallcaps">Nitrogen.)</hi> Hence
                    it is worth while to enumerate briefly the synthetical method for the making of
                    cyanogen itself. (1) Hydrocyanic acid is produced when a current of electric
                    sparks is made to cross a mixture of acetylene, C <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> H
                    <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, and nitrogen. (2) Cyanide of ammonium is formed
                    when ammonia is passed over red-hot charcoal (see <hi rend="italic">supra).</hi>
                    (3) Metallic cyanides are produced when dry nitrogen gas is passed over a dry
                    mixture of carbonate of potash or baryta and charcoal at a white heat. A similar
                    reaction goes on spontaneously in the iron-smelting furnaces and gives rise to
                    the formation of vapour of cyanide of potassium. (4) Sulphocyanide of ammonium
                    is produced from bisulphide of carbon and ammonia, as explained above. (W.
                    D.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
