<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0048-0035-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">PSKOFF</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 20, page 35</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:890865">Depositions</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:932562">Foresters</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1010775">Marshes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1093204">Regionalism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1106456">Scandinavianism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1106459">Scandinavians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1102429">Russians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206891">Poland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210278">Belgium</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7f10g">Esthonians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b47941291">Scandinavians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4pg1hv69">Nonconformists</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42z12q4d">Marshes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sx86">Personality</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20h7x">Valleys</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4sj19z78">Potatoes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ft8dp2t">Sand</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n48/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PSKOFF</label>, a government of the lake-region of northwest
                    Russia, which extends from Lake Peipus to the source of the Dwina, having St
                    Petersburg on the N., Novgorod, Tver, and Smolensk on the E., Vitebsk on the S.,
                    and Livonia on the W. It has an area of 16,678 square miles. In the south-east
                    it extends partly over the Alaun heights —a broad ridge 800 to 1000 feet above
                    the sea, deeply indented with numerous valleys and ravines, thickly covered with
                    forests, and dotted with small lakes and ponds. In the district of Toropets
                    these heights take the name of Vorobiovy Hills; extending westwards into
                    Vitebsk, they send to the north a series of irregular ranges, separated by broad
                    valleys, which occupy the north-western parts of Pskoff and give rise to the
                    rivers flowing into Lakes Peipus and Ilmen. A depression 120 miles long and 35
                    miles broad, watered by the Lovat and Polist, occupies the interval between the
                    two hilly tracts; it is covered throughout with forests and thickly studded with
                    marshes overgrown with rank vegetation, the only tracts suitable for human
                    occupation being narrow isolated strips of land on the banks of rivers, or
                    between the marshes, and no communication is possible except along the
                    watercourses. These marshy tracts, which extend westwards into Vitebsk and
                    north-eastwards towards St Petersburg, were even more impassable ten centuries
                    ago, and, encircling the old Russian city of Pskoff, formed its best protection
                    against the repeated attacks of its neighbours.</p>
                <p>With the exception of the south-eastern corner, where Carboniferous rocks make
                    their appearance, nearly the whole of the government consists of Devonian
                    deposits of great thickness,—the Old Red Sandstone, with subordinate layers of
                    various sandstones, and clays containing brown iron ore; and the White
                    Limestone, which contains layers of dolomite, marls, clays with deposits of
                    gypsum, and white sandstone, which is extensively quarried for building
                    purposes. As regards the fauna the Devonian deposits of Pskoff are intermediate
                    between those of Belgium, the Eifel, and Poland and those of middle Russia. The
                    whole is covered with very thick sheets of boulder clay and bears unmistakable
                    traces of glacial action; the bottom moraine of the Scandinavian and Finnish
                    ice-sheet formerly extended over the whole of this region, which often takes the
                    shape of ridges <hi rend="italic">(kames</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >eskers'),</hi> the upper parts consisting of Glacial sands and post-Glacial
                    clays, sands, and peat-bogs. The soil is thus not only infertile on the whole,
                    but also badly drained, on account of the impermeable nature of the boulder clay
                    and the frequent occurrence of depressions having no distinct outlets to the
                    rivers. Only those parts of the territory which are covered with thicker strata
                    of post-Glacial deposits are suitable for agriculture.</p>
                <p>The rivers are numerous and belong to three separate basins—to Lakes Peipus and
                    Pskoff the rivers in the northwest, to Lake Ilmen those in the middle, and to
                    that of the Dwina the rivers in the south-east. A great number of small streams
                    pour into Lake Pskoff, the chief being the Velikaya, which flows from south to
                    north and receives numerous tributaries, which are used for floating rafts, a
                    wide region being thus brought into communication with Lake Peipus and thence
                    with the Narova. The Velikaya, which is now navigable for only 25 'miles from
                    Lake Pskoff, was formerly deeper. The Lovat and Shelon, belonging to the basin
                    of Lake Ilmen, are both navigable, and a lively traffic is carried on on both;
                    while the Dwina flows for 100 miles on the borders of the government or within
                    it, and is used only for floating timber. There are no less than 850 lakes in
                    Pskoff, with a total area of 391 square miles. The largest is Lake Pskoff, which
                    is 50 miles long and 13 broad, and covers 312 square miles, having a depth of
                    from 3 to 18 feet: it is connected bv a channel, 40 miles <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n49/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0049-0036"/> long and 3 to 10 wide, with Lake Peipus. Its
                    islands, numbering nearly fifty, have an aggregate population of 2000 persons.
                    The marshes on the banks of the Polist are nearly 1250 square miles in extent;
                    one in the neighbourhood of Lake Dviniye is 27 miles long and 17 broad, and
                    another on the Toropa extends for 17 miles, while many elongated marshes, 15,
                    20, and 30 miles long and from 2 to 3 broad, run parallel to one another in the
                    broad depression of the Lovat. Forests occupy nearly one-half (about 45 per
                    cent.) of the entire area, and in some districts (Cholm, Toropets, Porkhoff) as
                    much as two-thirds of the surface. Large pine forests are met with in the north;
                    in other parts the birch and aspen prevail; but almost one-quarter of the forest
                    area is covered with low brushwood.</p>
                <p>The climate is very moist and changeable. The average temperature is 41° Fahr,
                    (17 <hi rend="superscript"> o,</hi> l in January and 64 <hi rend="superscript">
                    o,</hi> 8 in July).</p>
                <p>The population of the government, which was 895,710 in 1881 (718,910 in 1863),
                    consists almost exclusively of Great Russians, there being only 8000 Esthonians
                    (in the district of Pskoff), about 500 Letts, and less than 1500 Jews. Many
                    German traders live at Pskoff. The Russians and the greater part of the
                    Esthonians belong to the Greek Church, or are Nonconformists (upwards of 12,000
                    in 1866, according to official figures). Of the total number of inhabitants only
                    58,900 live in towns, the remainder being distributed over no fewer than 15,000
                    small villages.</p>
                <p>Notwithstanding the infertility of the soil the chief occupation is
                    agriculture—rye, oats, barley, and potatoes being grown everywhere; but though
                    corn is exported by the larger landowners to the average annual amount of nearly
                    1,600,000 bushels the amount imported is much greater (9,600,000 bushels). The
                    annual export of flax is estimated at 530,000 cwts., Pskoff, Ostroff, Opotchka,
                    Porkhoff, and Soltsy being important centres for the trade. The average annual
                    crops during 1870-77 were 28,972,800 bushels of corn and 5,984,000 bushels of
                    potatoes. The limited area of pasture lands is unfavourable for cattle-breeding,
                    and in 1881 there were only 171,000 horses, 304,000 head of cattle, and 166,000
                    sheep; murrains are very frequent. Fishing is a considerable source of wealth on
                    the shores of the larger lakes, small salted or frozen fish <hi rend="italic"
                    >{snyetki)</hi> being annually exported to the value of £25,000 or £35,000. The
                    timber trade is steadily increasing, the exports being estimated at present at
                    nearly £50,000; wood for fuel is, however, at the same time imported from the
                    government of St Petersburg. The population engage also in the preparation of
                    lime, in stone-quarrying, in the transport of merchandise, and in some domestic
                    trades. The manufactures are insignificant; their aggregate production in 1879
                    reached £518,800, and gave occupation to only 2350 persons. The total amount of
                    merchandise loaded and discharged on the rivers within the government in 1880
                    was 1,761,000 cwts.</p>
                <p>Pskoff is divided into eight districts, the chief towns of which are—Pskoff
                    (21,170 inhabitants), Cholm (5550), Novorjeff (1915), Opotchka (4075), Ostroff
                    (4200), Porkhoff (3925), Toropets (5760), Velikiya Luki (6600). Alexandrovskii
                    Posad (2920) and Soltsy (5825, an important shipping place on the Shelofi river)
                    have also municipal institutions.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
