<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0044-0033-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ROXBURGH</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 21, page 33</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:985798">Kale</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1134794">Streets</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1159786">Tweed</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:883965">Crops</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:884187">Crosses</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1109125">Scots</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b45d8np3k">Kale</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b43j3989t">Sparring</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pp2k">Cross</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zv9m">Streets</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4b56db1m">Minstrels</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4sf2mc29">Ballads</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4nz80t3c">Lays</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n44/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ROXBURGH</label> a border county of Scotland, occupying the
                    greater part of the border line with England, is bounded E. and S.E. by
                    Northumberland, S.E. by Cumberland, S.W. by Dumfriesshire, W. by Selkirkshire,
                    N.W. by Midlothian, and N.E. by Berwickshire. It lies between 55° 6' 30" and 55°
                    42' 30" N. lat., and between 2° 10' and 3° 7' W. long. Its greatest length from
                    north to south is 43 miles, and its greatest breadth about 30 miles. The area is
                    428,464 acres, or about 670 square miles.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Surface and Geology.—</hi> The greater part of Roxburgh is
                    included in Teviotdale. The whole course of the Teviot, 40 miles in length, is
                    included within the county. It rises in the ranges of greywacke hills which
                    separate the county from Dumfriesshire and Selkirk, and runs north-eastwards,
                    following the deposition of the greywacke rocks to the Tweed at Kelso, and
                    dividing the county into two unequal parts. On the north a high range of land
                    runs parallel with its banks and slopes to its margin. South-west between
                    Dumfries and Cumberland the greywacke formation constitutes an almost continuous
                    succession of eminences, through which the Liddel finds its way southwards. The
                    highest summits of the greywacke ranges exceed 1800 feet. Although occasionally
                    rocky and rugged, the hills are for the most part rounded in outline and clothed
                    with grass to their summits. This Silurian formation occupies nearly the whole
                    of the western half of the county, but along with the greywacke rocks is
                    associated clay slate of a bluish colour, glimmering with minute scales of mica
                    and frequently traversed by veins of calcareous spar. The formation is succeeded
                    to the eastward by an extensive deposit of Old Red Sandstone, forming an
                    irregular quadrangular area towards the centre of the county, emitting two
                    irregular projections from its southern extremity, and interrupted towards the
                    north by an intrusion of trap rocks. Owing to the sandstone formation the
                    transverse valleys formed by various affluents of the Teviot present features of
                    great interest. The action of the water has scooped deep channels in the rock,
                    and thus formed picturesque narrow defiles, of which the high sandstone scaurs
                    are a pro<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n45/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0045-0034"/>minent characteristic, their dark red colour
                    blending finely with the bright green woods and sparkling streams. The best
                    example of this species of scenery is on the Jed near Jedburgh. From the left
                    the Teviot receives the Borthwick and the Ale, both rising in Selkirkshire, and
                    from the right the Allan, the Slitrig, the Rule, the Jed, the Oxnam, and the
                    Kale, which rise in the high grounds towards the English border. As the Teviot
                    approaches Hawick the county becomes more cultivated, although frequent
                    irruptions of igneous rocks in the shape of isolated hills lend to it
                    picturesqueness and variety. Towards the Tweed, where the lower division of the
                    coal formation prevails, it expands into a fine champaign country, richly
                    cultivated and finely wooded. The Tweed, which enters the county about two miles
                    north of Selkirk, crosses its northern corner, eastwards by Abbotsford, Melrose,
                    and Kelso to Coldstream. Its tributaries within the county are, besides the
                    Teviot, the Gala, the Leader, and the Eden. One of the principal features of the
                    Tweed district is the beautiful group of the Eildon Hills near Melrose,
                    consisting of felspathic porphyry, the highest of the three peaks reaching 1385
                    feet. The extensive range of the Cheviots running along the Northumberland
                    border is of similar formation. Within Roxburghshire they reach a height of over
                    2400 feet. The lochs are comparatively few, the principal being Yetholm or
                    Primside Loch, and Hoselaw in Linton parish.</p>
                <p>The principal minerals are calcareous spar and quartz. The spar is frequently of
                    a red or rose character indicating the presence of hematite. In the greywacke
                    strata fossils are very rare, but in the Old Red Sandstone fossil fishes of the
                    genus <hi rend="italic">Pterixhthys</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Holoptychius</hi>
                    are very numerous, and a great variety of plant impressions have been found,
                    especially fucoids, but also vegetables of a higher origin, including distinct
                    petrifactions of <hi rend="italic">Galamites.</hi><hi rend="italic">Climate and
                    AgrieUlture.—</hi> The mean annual temperature approximates to that of Scotland
                    generally, but it is much warmer in the low and arable portions, where also the
                    rainfall is much less than in the hilly regions. The soil varies much in
                    different districts, being chiefly loam in the Iowand level tracts along the
                    banks of the river, where it is also very fertile. In other parts a mixture of
                    clay and gravel prevails, but there is also a considerable extent of mossy land.
                    The hilly district is everywhere covered by a thick green pasturage admirably
                    suited for sheep. Both in the pastoral and in the arable districts agriculture
                    is in a very advanced condition. The chief attention is devoted to cattle and
                    sheep rearing.</p>
                <p>Of the total area of 428,464 acres, 184,196 were in crops in 1885, 48,506 being
                    under corn crops, 28,385 green crops, 59,937 clover, 47,058 permanent pasture,
                    and 310 fallow. Of the area under corn crops, 32,624 acres, or fully two-thirds,
                    were occupied by oats, and 13,355 acres by barley. Tuniips and swedes were the
                    principal green crons, occupying 25,143 acres, while potatoes occupied only
                    2118. Tue total number of horses was 4420, of which 3697 were used solely for
                    purposes of agriculture; of cattle 17,831, of which 5154 were cows and heifers
                    in milk or in calf; of sheep 502,721; and of pigs 4783. The valued rental in
                    1674 was £314,633 Scots, or £26,219 sterling, while that in 1883-84 was £420,403
                    including railways. According to the parliamentary return of lands and
                    heritages, the total number of owners was 2455, of whom 1880 possessed less that
                    one acre. The duke of Buccleuch possessed 104,461 acres, or nearly a fourth of
                    the whole; the duke of Rox-burgho, 50,459; the countess of Home, 25,380; marquis
                    of Lothian, 19,740; and Sir William F. Elliot of Stobs, 16,475.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Manufactures.—</hi> Though essentially an agricultural county,
                    Roxburghshire possesses woollen manufactures of some importance, including
                    tweeds, blankets, shawls, and hosiery, the principal seats being Hawick,
                    Jedburgh, and Kelso.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Railways.—</hi> The county is intersected by one of the lines
                    of railway from Edinburgh to London (the “Waverley” route), which passes Melrose
                    and Hawick. At Riccarton a branch passes south-eastwards to Newcastle. The
                    northern district is crossed by the border railway from St Boswells to Kelso,
                    Coldstream, and Berwick, a branch passing south from near Kelso to Jedburgh.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Population.</hi> —⅛etween 1831 and 1881 the population
                    increased from 43,663 to 53,442 (25,436 males, 28,006 females), but from 1861 to
                    1871 there was a decrease from 54,119 to 49,407. The town population numbered
                    24,273 in 1881, the village 6627, and the rural 22,542. Jedburgh (population
                    2432) is a royal burgh; it is also a police and parliamentary burgh, as is
                    likewise Hawick (16,184); Kelso (46S7) is a police burgh. The most important
                    villages are Melrose (1550), Newcastlcton (924), and Yetholm (746).</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">History and Antiqtiities.—</hi> Among the more important relics
                    of the early inhabitants of the county are the so-called Druidical remains at
                    Tinnishill between the j&gt;arishes of Castleton and Canonbie, at
                    Ninestaneriggnear HermitageCastle, and at Plenderleath between the Oxnam and the
                    Kale. Of old forts there are two of great size on the summits of Caerby and
                    Tinnishill in Liddesdale, and a number of smaller ones in different parts of the
                    county. On the northwest of the Eildon Hills are two fossae or ramparts forming
                    a circuit of more than a mile. On Caldshiels Hill there was another British
                    fort, and between them a ditch with rampart of earth defending the country from
                    the east. The famous Catrail, “partition of the fence,” the most important of
                    the British remains in the kingdom, extended a distance of 45 miles from near
                    Galashiels in Selkirkshire through Roxburgh to Peel Fell on the border. The
                    Roman AVatling Street touched on Roxburgh at Broomhartlaw, whence passing along
                    the mountains now forming the boundary of the county for a mile and a half,
                    until it entered Scotland at Blackball, it turned northward by Bonjedward, Mount
                    Teviot, Newton, Eildon, and Newstead to Channelkirk in the Lammermuirs. On its
                    line there were important stations at Chewgreen in the Cheviots <hi
                    rend="italic">O. Ad Fines),</hi> Bonjedward <hi rend="italic">(Gaxlanica),</hi>
                    and Eildon Hill (? <hi rend="italic">Trimontiitm).</hi> Another Roman road,
                    called the Maidenway from Maiden Castle in AVestmoreland entered Roxburgh at
                    Deadwater, and under the name of the AVheelcauseway traversed the north-east
                    corner of Liddesdale into Teviotdale. From AVatling Street a branch called the
                    Devil’s Causeway passed to the Tweed. After forming part of the kingdom of
                    Northumberland for several centuries, Roxburgh was relinquished along with
                    Lothian to the Scottish king about 1020 (see Lothian, vol. xv. p. 10). It is
                    supposed to have been formed into a shire in the reign of David I., its ancient
                    Countytown of Roxburgh forming, along with Edinburgh, Berwick, and Stirling, the
                    court of the four burghs of Scotland, whose laws were collected by that king.
                    Roxburgh Castle, between the Tweed and Teviot near Kelso, was a royal residence
                    of the Saxon kings of Northumbria and afterwards of the Scottish monarchs. It
                    was frequently taken by the English, and James II. was killed there by the
                    bursting of a cannon. After this it remained in ruins till it was repaired by
                    Protector Somerset, shortly after which it was demolished. Hermitage, in
                    Liddesdale, the scene of Leyden’s ballad of <hi rend="italic">Lord Sοιιlis,</hi>
                    was probably built by Nicholas de Sules in the beginning of the 13th century. On
                    the forfeiture of the Soulis family in 1320, it was granted by Robert the Bruce
                    to Sir John Graham of Aber-corn, and passed by the marriage of his heiress Mary
                    to her husband AVilliam Douglas, knight of Liddesdale, who starved Sir Alexander
                    Ramsay of Dalhousie to death in it in 1342 in revenge for Ramsay’s appointment
                    as sheriff of Roxburgh by David II. In 1492 Archibald Douglas, fifth earl of
                    Angus, exchanged the Hermitage for Bothwell Castle, on the Clyde, with Patrick
                    Hepburn, first earl of Bothwcll; and it was there that his descendant, the
                    fourth earl, was visited in 1566 by Mary queen of Scots. The principal of the
                    other old castles are Branxholm on the Teviot, long the residence of the
                    Buccleuchs and the scene of Sir AValter Scott’s <hi rend="italic">Lay of the
                    Last Minstrel</hi>; Cessford, on a ridge inclining towards the Kale, formerly of
                    great strength, besieged in 1520 by Surrey, to whom itsurrendered; and
                    Ferniehirst, the mansion of the Kers, on the Jed, occupying the site of a
                    baronial fortress erected in 1410, and the scene of many a fray. The district
                    was for a long time the scene of continual border conflicts, the leaders in
                    which were the Armstrongs and other chiefs occupying the fortresses or peels,
                    chiefly in Liddesdale, as at Gilknockie, Castleton, AVhitehaugh, Copshaw, Syde,
                    Mangerton, Goranberry, Hartsgarth, and Newcastleton. Among many fine modern
                    mansions mention may be made of Floors Castle, the seat of the duke of
                    Roxburghe; Minto House, the seat of the earl of Minto; and Abbotsford, built by
                    Sir Walter Scott. Few counties can boast of such important ecclesiastical
                    remains as those of the abbeys of Melrose, Jedburgh, and Kelso. There are
                    several ancient crosses in the county, the principal being those at Ancrum,
                    Bowden, Maxton, and Melrose. Among numerous eminent men connected with Roxburgh
                    mention may be made of Samuel Rutherfurd the theologian, JamesThomson, author of
                    <hi rend="italic">The Seasons,</hi> John Leyden the poet, and Sir Gilbert Elliot
                    of Minto.</p>
                <p>See Jeffrey, <hi rend="italic">Ηiιtοry of Roxburghshire,</hi> 4 vols., 1857-C4;
                    Armstrong's <hi rend="italic">History of LidJesdale,</hi> 1884. (T. F. U.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
