<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0921-0058-0047-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">RUBY (9th edition, volume 21, page 47)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205049">Victoria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205406">Afghanistan</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207555">Montana</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1211700">Mexico</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210251">Colorado</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204820">Arizona</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204543">Australia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204537">Sweden</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vr13">Stone</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4np1wt1r">Syrians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kh0c">Afghans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k35mg6d">Corundum</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49882p5c">Chromium</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h41jt0c">Tinting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1133812">Stone</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1133955">Stoning</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1141359">Syrians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:880422">Corundum</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859964">Chromium</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n58/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">RUBY</label>. This name is applied by lapidaries and
                    jewellers to two distinct minerals, which may be distinguished as the true or
                    Oriental ruby and the spinel ruby. The former is a red variety of corundum or
                    native alumina, of <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n59/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0921-0059-0048"/>great rarity and value, while the latter is an
                    aluminate of magnesium, inferior to the true ruby in hardness and much less
                    esteemed as a gem stone. With ancient writers the confusion was even greater,
                    for they appear to have classed together under a common name, such as the <hi
                        rend="italic">car-bunxulus</hi> of Pliny or the <hi rend="italic"
                        >άνθραξ</hi> of Greek writers, not only our two kinds of ruby but also
                    garnets and other inferior stones of a brilliant fiery colour. By modern
                    mineralogists it has come to be understood that when the word ruby is used
                    without any qualifying prefix the true or Oriental stone is invariably
                    indicated.</p>
                <p>The Oriental ruby, like all other varieties of corundum, crystallizes in the
                    rhombohedral system; but, as it usually occurs as small pebbles or rounded
                    fragments, the crystalline form can rarely be traced. Its colour varies from
                    deep cochineal to pale rose red, in some cases inclining to purple, the most
                    valued tint being that known to experts as pigeon’s blood colour. On exposure to
                    a high temperature the ruby becomes green, but regains its original colour on
                    cooling—a behaviour which is consistent with the supposition that the stone owes
                    its colour to the presence of oxide of chromium, and indeed in artificial rubies
                    the required tint is always obtained by the use of some compound of chromium.
                    When a ruby of the most esteemed colour is properly viewed through a
                    dichroiscope, the colour is resolved into a carmine and an aurora red, or red
                    inclining to orange. By this test the true ruby may be distinguished from spinel
                    and garnet, since these minerals crystallize in the cubic system and therefore
                    are not di-chroic. Another mode of distinction is suggested by the high density
                    of corundum: the specific gravity of the true ruby reaches or even rises
                    slightly above 4, and thus greatly exceeds that of either spinel or garnet. But
                    perhaps the simplest test is afforded by its great hardness (H = 9): the sharp
                    edge of a corundum crystal will readily scratch either a spinel or a garnet, but
                    has no effect on a ruby. The true ruby has a very high index of refraction (∕z,=
                    l <hi rend="superscript">-</hi> 78), and to this character is due the remarkable
                    lustre of the polished stone. Mr Crookes has shown that the ruby is brilliantly
                    phosphorescent when subjected to radiant discharge in a properly exhausted
                    vessel, and curiously enough the red light emitted is equally vivid whatever be
                    the colour of the corundum under experiment. The microscopic structure of the
                    ruby has been studied by Mr Sorby, who finds that the stone contains fluid
                    cavities and numerous crystallized enclosures of other minerals <hi
                        rend="italic">(P roc. Roy. Soc.,</hi> χvii.. 1869, p. 291).</p>
                <p>The Oriental ruby is a mineral of very limited distribution, its principal
                    localities being confined to the kingdom of Burmah. The most ιmporUnt ruby mines
                    are situated at Kyat Pyen, about 70 miles to the north-east of Mandalay; there
                    are also mines at ' Mookop, a little farther north, and others in the Sagyin
                    Hills, within 16 miles of Mandalay. In all these localities the rubies occur in
                    association with sapphires and other precious stones, forming a gem-bearing
                    gravel which is dug up and washed in very primitive fashion. By far the larger
                    number of the rubies are of small size, and the larger stones are generally
                    flawed. All rubies exceeding a certain weight were the property of the king of
                    Burmah. The mines were jealously watched, and it was difficult for Europeans to
                    obtain access to them; but some of the Ava workings were visited and described
                    many years ago by Père Giuseppe d <hi rend="superscript">i</hi> Amato, and more
                    recently those near Mandalay have been described by Mr Bredmeyer, who was
                    officially connected with them (Ball). It is βUted in the older works on
                    mineralogy that rubies occur in the Capelan Mountains near Syrian, in Pegu. In
                    peninsular India there are but few localities that yield rubies, but they have
                    been reported from the corundum mines of the Salem district in Madras and from
                    Mysore. In Ceylon they occur with sapphires, but are rarer than those gems, and
                    the Ceylon rubies are not usually of good colour. Rubies have been brought from
                    Gandamak, in Afghanistan, but most of the stones reputed to be Afghan rubies are
                    merely spinels.</p>
                <p>In 1871 some remarkable deposits of corundum were discovered by Col. C. W. Jenks
                    in Macon co., North Carolina. Rubies, sapphires, and large pebbles of coarse
                    corundum were found in thθ bed of a river near a large mass of serpentine which
                    afterwards became known as Corundum Hill, and these pebbles were eventually
                    traced to certain veins in the serpentine. The corundum occurred crystallized
                        <hi rend="italic">in situ,</hi> but was rarely of such a colour as would
                    entitle it to be called ruby. Mr G. F. Kunz, who has lately written an article
                    on American precious stones, states that rubies and sapphires have also been
                    found at Vernon, New Jersey; near Helena, Montana; at Santa Fe, New Mexico; in
                    southern Colorado; and in Arizona.</p>
                <p>Australia has occasionally yielded true rubies, but mostly of small size and
                    inferior quality. In Victoria they have been found in the drifts of the
                    Beechworth gold fields and at the Berwick tin mine, Wallace’s Creek; while in
                    New South Wales they occur at Mudgee, in the Cudgegong and some of its
                    tributaries, and at Tumberumba, co. Wynyard. A magenta-coloured turbid ruby from
                    Victoria is known under the name of “barklyite.”</p>
                <p>The “star ruby” is a rather cloudy variety from Ceylon, exhibiting when cut <hi
                        rend="italic">en cabochon</hi> a luminous star of six rays, reflected from
                    the convex surface of the stone.</p>
                <p>The largest ruby known in Europe is said to be one of the size of a small hen’s
                    egg, which was presented by Gustavus III. of Sweden to the empress of Russia on
                    the occasion of his visit to St Petersburg. Rubies of larger size have been
                    described by Tavernier and other Oriental travellers, but it is probable that in
                    many cases spinels have been mistaken for true rubies. There seems no doubt that
                    the great historic ruby set in the Maltese cross in front of the imperial state
                    crown of England is a spinel. This stone was given to Edward the Black Prince by
                    Pedro the Cruel, king of Castile, on the victory of Najera' in 1367, and it was
                    afterwards worn by Henry V. at the battle of Agincourt, when it narrowly escaped
                    destruction.</p>
                <p>The spinel ruby has been described in the article Mineralogy (vol. xvi. p. 386,
                    sp. 93). The spinels used for jewellery are mostly obtained in Burmah, where
                    they occur as octahedral crystals or as water-worn pebbles in association with
                    the true ruby, for which they are often mistaken. They are also found in the
                    gem-bearing gravels of Ceylon, Victoria, and New South Wales. The delicate
                    rose-pink variety known as balas ruby was worked for centuries in Badakhshan,
                    but the operations appear to have been suspended of late years. The mines are
                    situated on the river Shighnan, a tributary of the Oxus. It is commonly said
                    that the name “balas” or “balash” is a corruption of Badakhshan, while others
                    derive it from Balkh.</p>
                <p>The Oriental ruby has always been esteemed of far higher value than any other
                    precious stone. A ruby of perfect colour, weighing five carats, is worth at the
                    present day ten times as much as a diamond of equal weight (Streeter). As the
                    weight of the stone increases, its value rapidly rises, so that rubies of
                    exceptional size command enormous prices. There is consequently much temptation
                    to replace the true stone by spinel or garnet or even paste. By means of oxide
                    of chromium an excellent imitation of the colour of the ruby is obtained; and,
                    though the ordinary “strass,” or fine lead-glass, is very soft, and therefore
                    soon loses its lustre, it is yet possible to produce a paste consisting of
                    silicate of alumina which is almost as hard as rock crystal.</p>
                <p>It is an interesting fact that the chemist has frequently succeeded in causing
                    alumina to assume artificially many of the physical Characteristicsof the native
                    ruby. As far back as 1837 M. Gaudin reproduced the ruby on a small scale by
                    exposing ammonia-alum to the heat of the oxyhydrogen blowpipe, whereby he
                    obtained fused alumina which was readily coloured by the addition of oxide of
                    chromium. A different method was followed by Ebelmen. He dissolved alumina in
                    boric acid at a high temperature, and on the cooling of the mass obtained the
                    alumina in a crystallized form; while if chromate of ammonium was present the
                    crystals became veritable ruby. MM. Sainte-Claire Deville and Caron heated a
                    mixture of fluoride of aluminium, fluoride of chromium, and boric acid, and thus
                    obtained a fluoride of boron, which, being volatile, readily escaped, and left a
                    solid residue of alumina coloured by the chrome. These, however, were only
                    laboratory experiments, and it was reserved for MM. Frémy and Feil, in 1878, to
                    reproduce the ruby and sapphire on a scale suggestive of some commercial
                    importance. By heating a mixture of artificial alumina and red lead in a
                    fireclay crucible, they obtained a vitreous silicate of lead (the silica being
                    derived from the crucible) and crystallized alumina, while the addition of
                    bichromate of potassium caused this alumina to assume the coveted tint of the
                    ruby.</p>
                <p>For a general description of the ruby see E. Jannettaz, <hi rend="italic">Diamant
                        et Pierres Précieuses</hi> (1881); Kluge, <hi rend="italic">Handbuch der
                        Edelsteinkunde</hi> (1860); Sclirauf, <hi rend="italic">Edelsteinkunde</hi>
                    (1869); Church, <hi rend="italic">Precious Stones</hi> (1883); Streeter, <hi
                        rend="italic">Precious Slones and Gems</hi> (4th ed., 1884). For Indian
                    localities see Ball's <hi rend="italic">Econcrmic Geology,</hi> being vol. iii.
                    of the <hi rend="italic">Manual of the Geology of India</hi> (1881); for
                    Australian localities, Livcrsidgc's <hi rend="italic">Minerals of New South
                        Wales</hi> (2d ed., 1882); for United States rubies, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Quart. Jour. Geol. Soc. Lond.,</hi> vol. xxx. 1874, p. 303, and <hi
                        rend="italic">American Jour. Science,</hi> ser. iii. vol. iv. 1872, pp.
                    109,175, and Kunz’s article in <hi rend="italic">Mineral Resources of the United
                        States,</hi> by A. Williams, jun. (1883). For the history of the stone
                    consult King's <hi rend="italic">Natural Hist, of Precious Stones</hi> (1865),
                    and for artificial rubies, <hi rend="italic">Comptes Rendus,</hi> vol. lxxxv.
                    1877, p. 1029. (F. W. R.)</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n60/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0060-0049"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
