<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0921-0065-0054-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">RUFF (9th edition, volume 21, page 54)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vt1gs03">Reefs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4t727j3q">Darwinism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43f4kq7b">Descents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47659j0m">Descent</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m9h">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w922">Writers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1092354">Reefs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:832970">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130432">Sports</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795379">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795510">Accounts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:833880">Blacks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210572">Iceland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n65/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">RUFF</label> a bird so called from the very beautiful and
                    remarkable frill of elongated feathers that, just before the breeding-season,
                    grow thickly round the neck of the male, who is considerably larger than the
                    female, known as the Reeve. In many respects this species, the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Tmnga pugnαx</hi> of Linnaeus and the <hi rend="italic">Machetes
                        pugnax</hi> of the majority of modern ornithologists, is one of the most
                    singular in existence, and yet its singularities have been very ill appreciated
                    by zoological writers in general. <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p>Mr Darwin, though frequently citing ( <hi rend="italic"
                                >Descent of Man and Sexual Selection,</hi> i. pp. 270, 306; ii. pp.
                            41, 42, 48, 81, 84, 100, 111) the Ruff as a witness in various
                            capacities, most unfortunately seems never to have had its peculiarities
                            presented to him in such a form that he could fully perceive their
                            bearings. However, the significance of the lesson that the Ruff may
                            teach was hardly conceivable before he began to write; but the fact is
                            not the less to be regretted that he never elucidated its importance,
                            not only in regard to “Sexual Selection,” but more especially with
                            respect to “Polymorphism.” He appears not to have consulted Montagu’s
                            original account of this bird, and seems to have known it only by the
                            excerpt given by Macgillivray, in which were not included the important
                            passages on the extreme diversity of plumage exhibited by the males—that
                            author passing over this wonderful peculiarity in a paragraph of less
                            than a score of lines. </p></note> These singularities would require
                    almost a volume to describe properly. The best account of them is unquestionably
                    that given in 1813 by Montagu <hi rend="italic">(Suppl. On. Dictionary),</hi>
                    who seems to have been particularly struck by the extraordinary peculiarities of
                    the species, and, to investigate them, expressly visited the fens of
                    Lincolnshire, possibly excited thereto by the example of Pennant, whose
                    information, personally collected there in 1769, was of a kind to provoke
                    further inquiry, while Daniel <hi rend="italic">(Rural Sports,</hi> iii. p. 234)
                    had added some other particulars, and subsequently Graves in 1816 repeated in
                    the same district the experience of his predecessors. Since that time the great
                    changes produced by the drainage of the fen-country have banished this species
                    from nearly the whole of it, so that Lubbock <hi rend="italic">(Obs. Fauna of
                        Norfolk,</hi> pp. 68-73) and Mr Stevenson <hi rend="italic">(Birds of
                        Norfolk,</hi> ii. pp. 261—271) can alone be cited as modern witnesses of its
                    habits in England, while the trade of netting or snaring Ruffs, and fattening
                    them for the table has for many years practically ceased.</p>
                <p>The cock-bird, when out of his nuptial attire, or, to use the fenman’s
                    expression, when he has not “his show on,” and the hen at all seasons, offer no
                    very remarkable deviation from ordinary Sandpipers, and outwardly <hi
                        rend="superscript">2</hi> there is nothing, except the unequal size of the
                    two sexes, to rouse suspicion of any abnormal peculiarity. But when spring comes
                    all is changed. In a surprisingly short time the feathers clothing the face of
                    the male are shed, and their place is taken by <hi rend="italic">papillae</hi>
                    or small caruncles of bright yellow or pale pink. From each side of his head
                    sprouts a tuft of stiff curled feathers, giving the appearance of long ears,
                    while the feathers of the throat change colour, and beneath and around it
                    sprouts the frill or ruff already mentioned as giving the bird his name. The
                    feathers which form this remarkable adornment, quite unique among birds, are,
                    like those of the “ear-tufts,” stiff and incurved at the end, but much
                    longer—measuring more than two inches. They are closely arrayed, capable of
                    depression or elevation, and form a shield to the front of the breast
                    impenetrable by the bill of a rival. <hi rend="superscript">3</hi> More
                    extraordinary than this, from one point of view, is the great variety of
                    coloration that obtains in these temporary outgrowths. It has often been said
                    that no one ever saw two Ruffs alike. That is perhaps an over-statement; but,
                    considering the really few colours that the birds exhibit, the variation is
                    something marvellous, so that fifty examples or more may be compared without
                    finding a very close resemblance between any two of them, while the individual
                    variation is increased by the “ear-tufts,” which generally differ in colour from
                    the frill, and thus produce a combination of diversity. The colours range from
                    deep black to pure white, passing through chestnut or bay, and many tints of
                    brown or ashy-grey, while often the feathers are more or less closely barred
                    with some darker shade, and the black is very frequently glossed with violet,
                    blue, or green—or, in addition, spangled with white, grey, or gold-colour. The
                    white, on the other hand, is not rarely freckled, streaked, or barred with grey,
                    rufous-brown, or black. In some examples the barring is most regularly
                    concentric, in others more or less broken-up or undulating, and the latter may
                    be said of the streaks. It was ascertained by Montagu, and has since been
                    confirmed by the still wider experience and if possible more carefully conducted
                    observation of Mr Bartlett, that every Ruff in each successive year assumes
                    tufts and frill exactly the same in colour and markings as those he wore in the
                    preceding season; and thus, polymorphic as is the male as a species, as an
                    individual he is unchangeable in his wedding-garment —a lesson that might
                    possibly be applied to many other birds. The white frill is said to be the
                    rarest.</p>
                <p>That all this wonderful “show” is the consequence of the polygamous habit of the
                    Ruff can scarcely be doubted. No other species of Limicoline bird has, so far as
                    is known, any tendency to it. Indeed, in many species of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Limicolss,</hi> as the Dotterel, the <hi rend="smallcaps">Godwits</hi>
                    (vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">x.</hi> p. 720), Phalaropes, and perhaps some others,
                    the female is larger and more brightly coloured than the male, who in such cases
                    seems to take upon himself some at least of the domestic duties. Both Montagu
                    and Graves, to say nothing of other writers, state that the Ruffs, in England,
                    were far more numerous than the Reeves; and their testi mony can hardly be
                    doubted; though in Germany Naumann ( <hi rend="italic">V'og. Deutschlands,</hi>
                    vii. p.</p>
                <p><hi rend="superscript">2</hi> Internally there is a great difference in the form
                    of the posterior margin of the sternum, as long ago remarked by Nitzsch.</p>
                <p><hi rend="superscript">3</hi> This “ruff” has been compared to that of
                    Elizabethan or Jacobean costume, but it is essentially different, since that was
                    open in front and widest and most projecting behind, whereas the bird’s
                    decorative apparel is most developed in front and at the sides and scarcely
                    exists behind.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n66/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0066-0055"/>
                <p>544) considers that this is only the case in the earlier ’ part of the season,
                    and that later the females greatly outnumber the males. It remains to say that
                    the moral characteristics of the Ruff exceed even anything that might be
                    inferred from what has been already stated. By no one have they been more
                    happily described than by Wolley, in a communication to Hewitson <hi
                        rend="italic">{Eggs of Brit. Birds,</hi> 3d ed., p. 346), as follows: —</p>
                <p>“The Ruff, like other fine gentlemen, takes much more trouble with his courtship
                    than with his duties as a husband. Whilst the Reeves are sitting on their eggs,
                    scattered about the swamps, he is to be seen far away flitting about in flocks,
                    and on the ground dancing and sparring with his companions. Before they are
                    confined to their nests, it is wonderful with what devotion the females are
                    attended by their gay followers, who seem to be each trying to be more attentive
                    than the rest. Nothing can be more expressive of humility and ardent love than
                    some of the actions of the Ruff. He throws himself prostrate on the ground, with
                    every feather on his body standing up and quivering; but he seems as if he were
                    afraid of coming too near his mistress. If she flies off, he starts up in an
                    instant to arrive before her at the next place of alighting, and all his actions
                    are full of life and spirit. But none of his spirit is expended in care for his
                    family. He never comes to see after an enemy. In the [Lapland] marshes, a Reeve
                    now and then flies near with a scarcely audible <hi rend="italic"
                    >ka-ka-kuk</hi>; but she seems a dull bird, and makes no noisy attack on an
                    invader.”</p>
                <p>Want of space forbids a fuller account of this extremely interesting species. Its
                    breeding-grounds extend from Great Britain <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p>In England of late years it has been known to breed only
                            in one locality, the name or situation of which it is not desirable to
                            publish. </p></note> across northern Europe and Asia; but the birds
                    become less numerous towards the east. They winter in India, reaching even
                    Ceylon, and Africa as far as the Cape of Good Hope. The Ruff also occasionally
                    visits Iceland, and there are several well-authenticated records of its
                    occurrence on the eastern coast of the United States, while an example is stated
                        <hi rend="italic">{Ibis,</hi> 1875, p. 332) to have been received from the
                    northern part of South America. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a. n.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
