<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0902-0035-0026-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ANGEL (9th edition, volume 2, page 26)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:944037">God</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term ref="fast:808746">Angels</term>
                    <term ref="fast:882407">Creationism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:882382">Creation</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204236">Israel</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bz61d88">Judaism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wd3q15g">Angels</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46t0gw81">Belief</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sn01649">Creation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n35/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ANGEL</label> is a transcription of the Greek άγγελος, <hi
                    rend="italic">a messenger,</hi> but in signification corresponds to the special
                    theological sense which the latter word assumed among the Hellenistic Jews (and
                    hence in the New Testament and in Christian writings), by being adopted as the
                    translation of the Hebrew <hi rend="italic">MaVakh.</hi> Thus both name and
                    notion of angel · go back to the Old Testament.</p>
                <p>The Old Testament belief in angels has two sides, being, on the one hand, a
                    particular development of the belief in special manifestations of God to man;
                    and on the other hand, a belief in the existence of superhuman beings standing
                    in a peculiar relation of nearness to God. These two sides of the doctrine are
                    historically associated and cooperate in the later developments of Biblical
                    angelology, but are not in all parts of the Old Testament fused into perfect
                    unity of thought.</p>
                <p>The first side of the belief in angels is expressed in the word <hi rend="italic"
                    >Mal’akh,</hi> a messenger or ambassador,—more fully, <hi rend="italic"
                    >messenger of Jehovah [E. V.,</hi> angel of the <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Lord],</hi><hi rend="italic">messenger of God.</hi> The whole Old Testament
                    revelation moves in the paradox that God is invisible and inaccessible to man,
                    and yet approaches man in unmistakable self-manifestation. This manifestation
                    takes place in various ways,—in the priestly oracle, in prophecy, in the glory
                    of God within the sanctuary [shekhina]. But in particular the early history
                    represents God as manifesting himself by his <hi rend="italic">messenger.</hi>
                    In special crises “the messenger of Jehovah” calls from heaven to Hagar or to
                    Abraham (Gen. xxi., xxii.) Or if God seeks to commune more fully with a man, his
                    messenger appears and speaks to him. The narratives of such angelophanies vary
                    in detail. Generally there is but one angel, but Abraham is visited by three
                    (Gen. xviii.) Sometimes the dignity of the heavenly visitor is detected while he
                    is present, at other times he is mistaken for a prophet, and recognised only by
                    something supernatural in his disappearance (Judges vi. 21, <hi rend="italic"
                    >f.,</hi> xiii. 20). Jacob wrestles all night with a “man,” who at length with a
                    touch dislocates his thigh (Gen. xxxii. 24, <hi rend="italic">ff.)</hi> At other
                    times no human form is seen. It is the angel of Jehovah who speaks to Moses in
                    the burning bush, and leads the Israelites in the pillar of cloud and smoke
                    (Exod. iii. 2, xiv. 19).</p>
                <p>In all this there is perfect indifference to the personality of the angel, who
                    displays no individuality of character, refuses to give a name (Gen. xxxii.;
                    Judges xiii.), acts simply as the mouthpiece of God. This is carried so far that
                    in his mouth the pronoun <hi rend="italic">I</hi> indicates Jehovah himself;
                    while the narrative passes, without change of sense, from the statement, “the
                    angel of Jehovah appeared, spoke,” &amp;c., to “Jehovah appeared, spoke.” <hi
                    rend="italic">(Cf.,</hi> for example, Exod. iii. ver. 2 with ver. 4; xiii. 21,
                    with xiv. 19.) Those who see the angel say they have seen God (Judges xiii. 22;
                    Gen. xxxii. 30). The angelophany is a theophany as direct as is possible to man.
                    The idea of a full representation of God to man, in all his revealed character,
                    by means of an angel, comes out most clearly for the angel that leads Israel in
                    the very old passage, Exod. xxiii. 20, ff. This angel is sent before the people
                    to keep them in the way and bring them to Canaan. He speaks with divine
                    authority<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n36/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0902-0036-0027"/>, and enforces his commands by divine sanctions,
                    “for my name <hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> the compass of
                    my revealed qualities] is in him.” The question naturally arises, how the angel
                    who possesses these high predicates stands related to angels who elsewhere
                    appear not representing the whole selfmanifestation of God to his people, but
                    discharging isolated commissions. The Biblical data for the solution of this
                    question are very scanty. An essential distinction between the “angel of the
                    Lord,” who speaks in all things with full divine authority, and subordinate
                    angels, is sought mainly in Gen. xviii. and in Exod. xxxii. 30, ff., xxxiii.
                    compared with Isaiah lxiii. 9. In the former case, though two of the three
                    angels leave Abraham, Jehovah goes his way only on the departure of the third.
                    Yet the two angels when they come to Lot are apparently as direct a
                    manifestation of God to him as the third was to Abraham (xix. 18, ff.) And in
                    the other passage it has not been clearly made out that there is really a
                    distinction drawn between an angel who represents God’s presence and an angel of
                    a lower kind who does not do so. The notion (long current in dogmatic theology,
                    and which goes back to the earliest controversies between Jews and Christians)
                    that “the angel of the Lord,” as contradistinguished from created angels, is the
                    Logos—the second person of the Trinity—has found defenders down to the present
                    day (Hengstenberg, Keil, &amp;c.), but certainly does not express the sense of
                    the Old Testament writers. And it seems equally unprofitable to base on such
                    passages as we have cited, a controversy whether “the angel of Jehovah” is one
                    special angel charged throughout history with special functions towards the
                    covenant people, or is any angel who from time to time has a special commission,
                    or is to be viewed, at least in some cases, not as a hypostatic being, but
                    simply as a momentary sinking of the invisible God into the sphere of
                    visibility. The <hi rend="italic">function</hi> of the angel so entirely
                    overshadows his <hi rend="italic">personality,</hi> that the Old Testament does
                    not ask who or what this angel is, but what he does. And the answer to this last
                    question is, that he represents God to man so directly and fully, that when he
                    speaks or acts God himself is felt to speak or act. The strongest passage
                    perhaps is Gen. xlviii. 15, <hi rend="italic">f</hi></p>
                <p>The disposition to look away from the personality of the angels and concentrate
                    attention on their ministry, runs more or less through the whole Old Testament
                    angel-ology. It is indeed certain,—to pass to the second side of the
                    doctrine,—that the angelic figures of the Bible narrative are not mere
                    allegories of divine providence, but were regarded as possessing a certain
                    superhuman reality. But this reality is matter of assumption rather than of
                    direct teaching. Nowhere do we find a clear statement as to the creation of the
                    angels [Gen. ii. 1 is ambiguous, and it is scarcely legitimate in Psalm cxlviii.
                    to connect ver. 2 with ver. 5]. That they are endowed with special goodness and
                    insight, analogous to human qualities, appears as a popular assumption, not as a
                    doctrine of revelation (1 Sam. xxix. 9; 2 Sam. xiv. 17, xix. 27). Most
                    characteristic for the nature of the angels is the poetical title “sons of God”
                    <hi rend="italic">{Bné</hi><hi rend="italic">Elohim,</hi> or, with a slight
                    modification, <hi rend="italic">Bnê,</hi><hi rend="italic">Elim,</hi> in English
                    version incorrectly “mighty,” “sons of the mighty,” Ps. xxix. 1, lxxxix. 6),
                    which, in accordance with the idiomatic force of the word <hi rend="italic"
                    >sons,</hi> may be paraphrased, “Beings who in a subordinate way share something
                    of divine majesty.” Perhaps in Psalm lxxxii. the name Elohim itself varies with
                    the more usual “sons of Elohim.”</p>
                <p>Taken collectively, the angels form the hosts of Jehovah (Ps. ciii. 21, &amp;c.),
                    or the host of heaven (1 Kings xxii. 19), names correlative to the new title of
                    God which springs up at the close of the period of the Judges, “Jehovah ΓGod of]
                    hosts.” The notion of angels as divine armies is not like that of the individual
                    “messenger” closely connected with the theophânic history (yet compare Gen.
                    xxxιi. 1, <hi rend="italic">2;</hi> Joshua V. 13, <hi rend="italic">sqq.),</hi>
                    but belongs rather to the delineation of the majesty of God in poetry and
                    prophecy. As the whole conception of the heavenly palace and throne is obviously
                    symbolical, we must allow for conscious poetic art when the angels are
                    represented surrounding God’s throne in the form of an <hi rend="italic"
                    >assembly</hi> or <hi rend="italic">privy council</hi> of holy ones (consecrated
                    servants), praising his name, or receiving his commands, and reporting their
                    execution (Ps. xxix., lxxxix. 6-8; 1 Kings xxii. 19, ff.; Jobi.) Similarly much
                    must be allowed for the free play of fancy when in the last judgment against the
                    enemies of his people, Jehovah descends to battle with his <hi rend="italic"
                    >heroes</hi> (Joel iv. 11), his <hi rend="italic">holy ones</hi> (Zech. xiv. 5),
                    or when he triumphantly enters Zion amidst myriads of heavenly war chariots (Ps.
                    lxviii. 17). Compare Isa. lxvi. 15, Hab. iii., which show how closely such
                    imagery is connected with the physical phenomena of the thunderstorm.</p>
                <p>With the development of the idea of countless hosts of divine ministers is
                    naturally associated, in place of the old angelic theophany, the conception of
                    an invisible agency of angels, who are henceforth seen only in vision or to eyes
                    specially opened (Num. xxii. 31; 2 Kings vi. 17). To the guidance of Israel by
                    the angel of Jehovah succeeds the belief in angelic guidance of individuals (Ps.
                    xxxiv. 7), more or less poetically worked out (Ps. xci. 11). Conversely,
                    pestilence and other judgments are angelic visitations (2 Sam. xxiv.; 2 Kings
                    xix. 35; Ps. lxxviii. 49, where the “evil angels” of the English version are not
                    wicked angels, but angels of evil). At length this is carried so far that all
                    natural forces that serve God are viewed as his messengers, Ps. civ. 4: “He
                    makes winds his messengers, flaming fire his ministers.” This passage clearly
                    shows the elasticity of the whole conception. Similar is the way in which the
                    stars, which share with the angels the name “host of heaven,” appear associated
                    with the latter (Job xxxviii. 7). Hence the later elemental angels.</p>
                <p>Angelic interpretation between God and man reappears in Job xxxiii. 23 (c∕. iv.
                    13, <hi rend="subscript"> t</hi> ∕.), and converse with angels forms a large
                    part of the visionary setting of the later prophetical books (Ezekiel,
                    Zechariah). But these visions, to which the prophets do not ascribe objective
                    reality, illustrate rather the religious imagination than the theology of the
                    period.</p>
                <p>The idea of ranks and classes of angels, though naturally suggested by the
                    conception of a host (c∕. Joshua v. 13, <hi rend="italic">sqq.),</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript"> was u</hi> P t° this time undeveloped; for neither the
                    purely symbolical cherubim, nor the unique and obscure seraphim of Isaiah vi.,
                    have in the Old Testament the meaning later conferred on them of distinct
                    classes of angels. But the angels of Zechariah present something of a systematic
                    scheme, though it seems unsafe, with Ewald and others, to see in the seven eyes
                    of Jehovah (iii. 9, iv. 10) a developed doctrine of seven chief angels (as in
                    Tobit xii. 15; Rev. viii. 2), parallel to and influenced by the <hi
                    rend="italic">Amesha-çpentas</hi> of the Eranian mythology. The book of Daniel
                    shows a much fuller development in a similar line. Israel, Persia, &amp;c., have
                    special angels (princes), whose contests represent those of human history
                    (chaps, x., xii, <hi rend="italic">cf.</hi> Isa. xxiv. 21,∕.) “The great prince
                    who presides over” Israel is named Michael (who is like God <hi rend="italic"
                    >T),</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">angelus interpres</hi> is called Gabriel
                    (man of God). The analogy of these notions to those of Zarathustrism is less
                    decided than has often been supposed; but the freedom which Old Testament
                    writers allow themselves in matters of imaginative representation, to which
                    these conceptions mainly belong, is such as to render foreign influence quite
                    credible.</p>
                <p>The ranks, classes, and names of angels are a favourite topic of post-canonical,
                    and especially of Apocalyptic literature. In the book of Enoch, cherubim,
                    seraphim, and even the wheels of Ezekiel’s vision, become distinct classes <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n37/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0902-0037-0028"/> of angels; and Rafael (c∕. Tobit xii. 5),
                    Phanuel, Uriel, &lt;fcc., are added to the names of individual archangels.
                    Specially celebrated is the interpretation which this book gives of Gen. vi. 2,
                    where the sons of God are understood as angels. This interpretation seems to
                    have influenced Jude, ver. 6 (c∕. 2 Pet. ii. 4), was current in the early church
                    as well as in Judaism, and (though the narrative so understood is quite unique
                    in the circle of Biblical ideas) is defended on philological grounds by the best
                    recent scholars, the occurrence being viewed as history or as myth according as
                    the interpreter is theosophically or critically inclined. Of other passages in
                    later Jewish literature it may suffice to refer to the full account of the
                    creation of angels of various functions, presiding over various powers of
                    nature, in the <hi rend="italic">Boole of Jubilees {cf.</hi> Roensch, <hi
                    rend="italic">Das</hi><hi rend="italic">Buch der Jubiläen,</hi> p. 259).</p>
                <p>The angelology of the New Testament attaches closely to the notions already
                    developed. The ministry of angels is, as in the Old Testament, specially
                    connected with the work of salvation (Heb. i. 14), and with the person of Christ
                    (John i. 51), to whom after the temptation (and at Gethsemane ?) angels
                    minister, and who can at will command their aid (Mat. xxvi. 53). As in the later
                    Old Testament books, revelations by angels are given in vision or dream, but
                    even waking eyes see the angel or angels who minister at the resurrection. So an
                    angel delivers Peter {Acts xii.), &amp;c. As in the Old Testament, the figure of
                    angels is human, their raiment white, and their aspect luminous. A multitude of
                    angels appear singing praises at the nativity (Luke ii. 13), and in general they
                    sympathise with the repentance of sinners and the progress of the divine kingdom
                    (Luke xv. 10; 1 Pet. i. 12). . Gabriel reappears in Luke i. The belief in
                    special guardian angels of individuals appears as current (Acts xii. 15), but
                    the words of Jesus (Mat. xviii. 10) hardly go farther than the statements of the
                    Psalms. The angelic hosts of the prophetic eschatology are naturally transferred
                    to the second coming (Parusia) of our Lord. The saints after the resurrection
                    are like the angels (Mat. xxii. 30; Luke xx. 36). In the Apocalypse angels play
                    a great part. Notable features, in addition to the seven highest angels ( viii.
                    2), are the angels of the seven churches (who, however, are by many taken as
                    human figures, church officers), and the association of special angels with'
                    cosmical forces, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> angels of fire and water (xvi. 5,
                    xiv. 18). The same idea appears even more sharply expressed in the writings of
                    Paul, if, as Ritschl has rendered plausible, the elements (elemental powers) of
                    the world (Col. ii.; Gal. iv. 3) are the angels, and specially the angels of the
                    law. This view is connected with the characteristic position of Paul and the
                    Epistle to the Hebrews, that the inferiority of the old covenant is stamped by
                    the fact that the law was given and enforced by angels (Gal. iii, iv.; Heb. ii.;
                    <hi rend="italic">cf.</hi> Acts vii. 53), an idea partly based on Exod. xxiii.
                    20, <hi rend="italic">f.,</hi> and partly on a transference to Sinai of the
                    usual poetico-prophetic imagery of a theophany—a transference suggested by Ps.
                    lxviii. 17, Deut, xxxiii. 2, and actually carried out in the LXX. translation of
                    the latter text, and in the current Jewish theology of the period. Angel worship
                    is condemned in Col. ii. (probably with reference to Essene doctrine); <hi
                    rend="italic">cf.</hi> Rev. xix. 10. In Heb. ii., and 1 Cor. vi. 3, Christians
                    are superior to angels.</p>
                <p>Theological reflection on the doctrine of angels already begins among the
                    Alexandrian Jews; and Philo, who calls them “a chorus of unembodied souls”
                    occupying the air, places them in close parallelism to his speculations on the
                    divine <hi rend="italic">ideas</hi> or <hi rend="italic">powers.</hi> From this
                    association the transition is easy to Gnostic speculations, where the ranks of
                    angels appear as produced by successive emanation, and thus sene to fill up the
                    interval which Gnosticism puts between God and the world. In this connection we
                    find also a doctrine of creation by angels (Basilides), and dualistic views of
                    good and evil angels. Against these heresies the early church emphasises the
                    creation of angels and the fall of the evil angels, but Origen tells us that up
                    to his time the ecclesiastical doctrine did not define “quando isti creati sint
                    vel quales aut quomodo sint.” On these topics, however, many subtle questions
                    arose, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> whether angels have bodies of an ethereal
                    kind, whether they were created before the world or along with the light,
                    &amp;c. Gradually angel-worship sprung up, and in spite of the opposition of the
                    best fathers (Theodoret, Augustin, &lt;fcc.), became firmly established, and is
                    still acknowledged in the Roman catechism. An elaborate theory of the angelic
                    hierarchy, based on Neoplatonic doctrines, is laid down in the work of
                    Pseudo-Dionysius, <hi rend="italic">De Hierarchia Celesti</hi> (5th century),
                    and exercised much influence on mediaeval theology, which accepted the work as a
                    genuine product of the apostolic age. The schoolmen treat of angels under the
                    doctrine of creation, dividing rational creatures into angels, who are pure
                    spirits, and men <hi rend="italic">{Sent. Lib.</hi> ii., dist. i,, <hi
                    rend="italic">sqq.),</hi> and the nature and powers of angels form the most
                    notorious problems of the misdirected subtlety of the schools <hi rend="italic"
                    >{cf. e.g.,</hi> Duns on the <hi rend="italic">Second Boole of Sentences').</hi>
                    Protestant theologians have always felt less interest in the subject, and
                    generally reduce the doctrine of angels to a mere appendix to the doctrine of
                    creation or of God’s works. Recent writers often go much farther. Thus,
                    Schleiermacher sums up the whole doctrine of angels by saying, that the possible
                    existence of angels should not influence conduct, and that revelations of their
                    being are no more to be looked for. A reaction, partly rooted on the later
                    philosophy of Schelling, has led several German theologians (Hofmann, &amp;c.)
                    to lay more weight on the doctrine.</p>
                <p>The Biblical doctrine of angels must be studied with the aid of the best books on
                    Biblical theology (Schulz, Oehler, Ewald, Weiss, &amp;c.), and of the
                    commentaries on special passages. The book of Enoch is accessible in Dillmann’s
                    translation, and other Jewish notions may be found in Eisenmenger. The
                    literature of the subject, theological and theosophic, is immense. (w. R.
                    s.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
