<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0902-0346-0327-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ARCH (9th edition, volume 2, page 327)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j96091f">Arches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qn6g">Crowns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vr13">Stone</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4f18sj2n">Equilibrium</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n29p65z">Architects</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:813061">Arches</term>
                    <term ref="fast:884318">Crowns</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1133812">Stone</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1133955">Stoning</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:813114">Architects</term>
                    <term ref="fast:984032">Journalism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n346/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ARCH</label>, in building, a portion of mason-work disposed
                    in the form of an arc or bow, and designed to carry the building over an open
                    space. The simplest and oldest expedient for supporting a structure over a
                    door-way is to use a single stone or lintel of sufficient length. On account of
                    the difficulty of procuring stones of great size, this expedient can only be
                    used for moderate apertures <hi rend="italic">; nor</hi> can it be applied when
                    there is to be a heavy superstructure, because the weight resting on the lintel
                    would cause a compression of the upper, and a distension of the under side. Now,
                    no kind of stone can bear any considerable distending strain, and thus
                    stone-lintels are liable to fracture. The ancient Greek temples afford instances
                    of the use of horizontal lintels of considerable size, but these architraves
                    carry only the cornice of the building. The employment of a colonnade with flat
                    architraves to support an upper story is contrary to sound principles, and, even
                    in the case of ordinary house 3, we see that the builder has been fain to
                    relieve the pressure on the lintel by means of a concealed arch. In stone-work
                    we must depend on compression alone.</p>
                <p>When a lintel had been accidentally broken in two, we may suppose that the masons
                    had set the ends of the halves upon the door-posts, and brought the broken ends
                    together. In this way there would be formed a support for the upper building
                    much stronger than was the stone when entire; only there is a tendency to thrust
                    the doorposts asunder, and means must be taken to resist this out-thrust. The
                    transition from this arrangement to that of three or more wedge-shaped stones
                    fitted together was easy, and thus the gradual development of the arch
                    resulted.</p>
                <p>So long as such structures are of small dimensions no great nicety is required in
                    the adaptation of the parts, because the friction of the surfaces and the
                    cohesion of the mortar are sufficient to compensate for any impropriety of
                    arrangement.. But when we proceed to construct arches of large span we are
                    forced to consider carefully the nature and intensity of the various strains in
                    order that provision may be made for resisting them.</p>
                <p>Until the laws of the equilibrium of pressures were discovered, it was not
                    possible to investigate these strains, and thus our knowledge of the principles
                    of bridge-building is of very recent date; nor even yet can it be said to be
                    perfected. The investigation is one of great difficulty, and mathematicians have
                    sought to render it easier by introducing certain pre-supposed conditions; thus,
                    in treatises on the theory of the arch, the structure is regarded as consisting
                    of a course of arch-stones resting on abutments, and carrying a load which is
                    supposed to press only downwards upon the arch-stones. Also cohesion and
                    friction are put out of view, in other words, the investigation is conducted as
                    if the stones could slide freely upon each other. Now, if the line of pressure
                    of one stone against another cross their mutual surface perpendicularly, there
                    is no tendency to slide; and if this condition be adhered to throughout the
                    whole structure, there must result complete stability, since the whole of the
                    friction and the whole consistency of the cement contribute thereto. But if, in
                    any case, the line of pressure should cross the mutual surface obliquely, the
                    tendency to slide thereby occasioned must be resisted by the cohesion, and so
                    the firmness of the structure would be impaired. Hence an investigation,
                    conducted on the supposition of the non-existence of cohesion, must necessarily
                    lead us to the best possible construction. But we can hardly say as much in
                    favour of the hypothesis that the load presses only downwards upon the
                    arch-stones. In order to place such a supposition in accordance with the facts
                    of the case, we should have to dress the inner ends of the arch-stones with
                    horizontal facets for the purpose of receiving and transmitting the downward
                    pressure. But if, as is usually the case, the inner surfaces be oblique, they
                    cannot transmit a vertical pressure unless in virtue of cohesion, and then this
                    hypothesis of only downward pressure on the arch-stones is not in accordance
                    with the fundamental principle of stability. In a thorough &gt; investigation
                    this hypothesis must be set aside, and the oblique pressure on the inner ends of
                    the arch-stones must be taken into account. Since the depth of the arch-stones
                    is small in comparison with the whole dimensions of the structure, and since the
                    line of the pressure transmitted from one to another of them must alw ays be
                    within that depth, it is admissible to suppose, for the purpose of analysing the
                    strains, that the arch-stones form an exceedingly thin course, and that their
                    joints are everywhere normal to the curve of the arch. Eventually, however, the
                    depth of the arch-stones must be carefully considered.</p>
                <p>We may best obtain a clear view of the whole subject by first assuming that the
                    load presses only downwards on the arch-stones, or that the inner ends of these
                    are cut with horizontal facets.</p>
                <p>Let Q'P'APQ (fig. 4) represent a portion of such an arch placed equally on the
                    two sides of the crown A, then the whole weight of the structure included
                    between the two vertical lines ΡΉ' and PH must be supported at P <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi> and P, so that the downward pressure at the point P
                    must be tho weight of the building imposed over AP. This pressure downwards is
                    accompanied by a tendency to separate tho <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n347/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0902-0347-0328"/> supporting points P' and P. Now, as this tendency
                    is horizontal its intensity cannot be changed, by the load acting only
                    downwards, and must remain the same throughout the structure, wherefore the
                    actual pressure at P must be found by combining this fixed horizontal thrust
                    with the downward pressure equal to the weight of the bridge from A to P. If,
                    then, we draw <hi rend="italic">ah</hi> horizontally to represent this constant
                    thrust, and <hi rend="italic">ap</hi> upwards to represent the weight of this
                    portion of the arch, the line <hi rend="italic">ph</hi> muât, according to the
                    law of the composition of pressures, indicate both in direction and in intensity
                    the actual strain at the point P. This pressure must be perpendicular to the
                    joint of the stones, and must therefore be parallel to the straight line drawn
                    to touch the curve at P.</p>
                <p>Hence, if the form of the inside of the arch, or the <hi rend="italic"
                    >intrados</hi> as it is called, be prescribed, we can easily discover the law of
                    the pressures at its various parts; thus, to find the strain at the point Q, we
                    have only there to apply a tangent to the curve and to draw <hi rend="italic"
                    >hq</hi> parallel thereto; <hi rend="italic">hq</hi> represents the oblique
                    strain at Q; <hi rend="italic">aq</hi> represents the whole weight from the
                    crown A to Q, and therefore <hi rend="italic">pq</hi> is proportional to the
                    weight imposed upon the position PQ of the arc.</p>
                <p>Using the language of trigonometry, the horizontal thrust is to the oblique
                    strain at any part of the curve as radius is to the secant of the angle of
                    inclination to the horizon; also the same horizontal thrust is to the Weight of
                    the superstructure as radius is to the tangent of the same inclination. And
                    thus, if the intrados be a known curve, such as a circle, an ellipse, or a
                    parabola, we are able without much trouble to compute, on this hypothesis, the
                    load to be placed over each part.</p>
                <p>If we use the method of rectangular co-ordinates placing <hi rend="italic">x</hi>
                    along OH and <hi rend="italic">z</hi> vertically downwards, so that Pπ may be
                    the increment of <hi rend="italic">x,</hi> πQ that of <hi rend="italic">z,</hi>
                    the tangent of the inclination at P is -√-∖ and therefore if <hi rend="italic"
                    >h</hi> stand for the horizon-ÔX</p>
                <p>tai strain, and <hi rend="italic">τo</hi> for the weight of the arch, we
                    have—</p>
                <p><hi rend="superscript"> κ</hi> =⅛-</p>
                <p>while the oblique strain is Λ <hi rend="subscript"> i</hi> γ∕(~g-Γ^)- Also the
                    change of weight from P to a proximate point Q is <hi rend="superscript"> δ</hi>
                    *=* <hi rend="superscript"> s</hi> (⅛)∙</p>
                <p>Let RST be the outline which the mason-work would have if placed compactly over
                    the arch-stones, in which case RST is called the <hi rend="italic"
                    >extrados,</hi> then the weight supported at P is proportional to the surface
                    ARSP, and the increment of the weight is proportional to PSTQ, hence if the
                    weights and strains be measured in square units of the vertical section of the
                    structure, and if <hi rend="italic">y</hi> be put for PS, the thickness of the
                    mason-work, we have—</p>
                <p>δw = yδz, whence <hi rend="italic">y</hi><hi rend="italic">= h .</hi></p>
                <p>When the curve APQ is given, the relations of 2 and of its differentials to <hi
                    rend="italic">x</hi> are known, and thus the configuration of the extrados can
                    be traced, and we are able to arrange the load so as to keep all the strains in
                    equilibrium.</p>
                <p>But when the form of the extrados is prescribed and that of the intrados is to be
                    discovered, we encounter very great difficulties. Seeing that our hypothesis is
                    not admissible in practice, it is hardly worth while to engage in this inquiry;
                    it may suffice to take a single, and that the most interesting case.</p>
                <p>If the whole space between the arclnstones and the roadway be filled up, the
                    extrados becomes a straight line, and when this is horizontal we have <hi
                    rend="italic">y = z,</hi> so that the form of the arch must be such as to
                    satisfy the condition—</p>
                <p><hi rend="subscript"> 7</hi> δ⅛ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> =⅛ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi> that is to say, <hi rend="italic">z</hi> must be a
                    function of <hi rend="italic">x</hi> such as to be proportional to its own
                    second derivative or <hi rend="italic">differential coefficient.</hi> Now this
                    character is distinctive of the catenarian functions, and therefore ultimately
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">a</hi> i ∙v ’ * <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> √ ’ * )</p>
                <p><hi rend="subscript"> e</hi> = A∣e <hi rend="italic">+e</hi> j, where A is AO,
                    the thickness at the crown of the arch, and <hi rend="italic">e</hi> the basis
                    of the Napierian system of logarithms. In this case, since <hi rend="italic">δw
                    = zδx,—</hi> w = A <hi rend="subscript"> 5</hi> ∕Λ^e <hi rend="superscript">
                    λ</hi>- <hi rend="italic">e *</hi><hi rend="italic">∣</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >,</hi> so that the form of the arch and also its weight may readily be computed
                    by help of a table of catenarian functions.</p>
                <p>Let us now consider the case when the ends of the archstones are dressed
                    continuously, while the imposed load is formed of stones having vertical faces.
                    The weight of the column PSTQ resting on the oblique face PQ is prevented from
                    sliding by a resistance on the vertical surface QT, which resistance goes to
                    partly oppose the horizontal strain transmitted by the preceding arch-stone; and
                    thus the out-thrust of the arch, instead of being entirely resisted by the
                    ultimate abutment, is spread over the whole depth of the structure. In this case
                    the horizontal thrust against QT is to the weight of the · column as <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Qt,</hi> the increment of 2, is to Pτr, the increment of <hi
                    rend="italic">x&gt;</hi> wherefore, putting H for the horizontal thrust at the
                    crown of the arch, and <hi rend="italic">h</hi> for that part of it which comes
                    down to P, the decrement of <hi rend="italic">h</hi> from P to Q is proportional
                    to the rectangle under PS and Q7r, that is to say, <hi rend="italic">δh =
                    yδz.</hi></p>
                <p>Now, the whole decrement from the crown downwards is the sum or integral of all
                    such partial decrements, and therefore the horizontal thrust transmitted to P is
                    expressed by the symbol—·</p>
                <p>⅜ = H-∕^, while the whole weight supported at P is the analogous integral <hi
                    rend="italic">w =Jyox.</hi></p>
                <p>But the resultant of these two pressures must be perpendicular to the joint of
                    the arch-stones, or parallel to the line of the curve; wherefore ultimately we
                    obtain, as the condition of equilibrium in such a structure, the equation—</p>
                <p>δ2(H-∕^) = δ≠δx.</p>
                <p>Since the vertical pressure at P is <hi rend="italic">w,</hi> while the
                    horizontal strain is <hi rend="italic">h,</hi> the intensity of the oblique
                    strain at P must be <hi rend="italic subscript"> f</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >J{w</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic">+ h</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> r</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >.</hi> Now, in passing to the proximate point Q, <hi rend="italic">io</hi>
                    becomes <hi rend="italic">w + δw,</hi> while <hi rend="italic">h</hi> is reduced
                    to <hi rend="italic">h-δw^,</hi> so that the oblique strain at Q must be—</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">oz</hi></p>
                <p>√{(∞ + δ <hi rend="subscript"> κ</hi>.)≡+(Λ-δw∣) <hi rend="superscript"> s</hi>},
                    or, neglecting the second power of the infinitesimally small increment <hi
                    rend="italic">δw</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> f λ</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >∕</hi><hi rend="italic">∣</hi><hi rend="italic">w-+ p</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">+ 2wδw</hi><hi rend="italic">- 2hδw^</hi>
                    &gt;, but <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n348/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0902-0348-0329"/><hi rend="italic">w =</hi> wherefore the strain at
                    Q is <hi rend="subscript                     smallcaps"> a</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">∕(w</hi><hi rend="superscript                     smallcaps">
                    2</hi> + A <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>), <hi rend="italic">or</hi> exactly
                    the same as that at P. This result might have been obtained from the
                    consideration that the thrust upon the surface PQ is perpendicular to the
                    oblique strain, and can tend neither to augment nor to diminish it. Hence, as a
                    characteristic of this arrangement, we have the law that the tension across the
                    joints of the arch-stones is the same all along, and therefore is equal to H,
                    the horizontal tension at the crown of the arch.</p>
                <p>From this it at once follows that if <hi rend="italic">r</hi> be the radius of
                    curvature at the point P, <hi rend="italic">y</hi> being the vertical thickness
                    of the mason-work there, H = <hi rend="italic">ry,</hi> so that if R be the
                    radius of curvature at the crown of the arch, and A the thickness there, the
                    horizontal thrust there, or the strain transmitted along the arch-stones, is H =
                    RAH, being measured in square units of surface; hence also A: <hi rend="italic"
                    >y</hi><hi rend="italic">:: r</hi>: R, or the thickness at any place, is
                    inversely proportional to the radius of curvature there.</p>
                <p>When the form of the intrados is given, its curvature at any point is known, and
                    from that the thickness of the stone-work and the shape of the extrados can be
                    found. The most useful case of the converse problem is, again, that in which the
                    extrados is a horizontal straight line.</p>
                <p>Let OH, figure 6, be the horizontal extrados, and A the crown of the arch; make
                    also AB such that its square may represent the horizontal thrust there; then,
                    having joined OB and drawn BC perpendicular to it, and meeting the continuation
                    of OA in C, C is the centre of curvature for the crown of the arch. Or, if the
                    radius of curvature and the thickness of the arch at the crown be prescribed, we
                    may obtain the horizontal thrust by describing on CO. a semicircle, cutting a
                    horizontal line through A in the point B, then the horizontal thrust is equal to
                    the weight of the quantity of the stone-work which would fill up the square on
                    AB. The conditions of the problem require that the curve APQ be so shaped as
                    that the radius of curvature at any point P shall be inversely proportional to
                    the ordinate HP.</p>
                <p>Resuming the general equation of condition—</p>
                <p>δz(H <hi rend="italic">-fy8z) = 8xfy8x,</hi> and observing that in this case <hi
                    rend="italic">y = z,</hi> we have—· δ.^(H <hi rend="italic">-fi8z) = 8xfz8x
                    .</hi></p>
                <p>Now the integral <hi rend="italic">fz8z</hi> is ∣z <hi rend="superscript">
                    2</hi>, but as it must be reckoned only from A where <hi rend="italic">z</hi> =
                    A, the equation becomes</p>
                <p>δz(H + ∣A <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> — ∣z <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>) =
                    <hi rend="italic">8xfz8x.</hi></p>
                <p>The coefficient of δz becomes less when <hi rend="italic">z</hi> increases, and
                    when ⅛z <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> = H <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + ⅛A
                    <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, this coefficient becomes zero, at which time <hi
                    rend="italic">8x</hi> also becomes zero in proportion to <hi rend="italic"
                    >8z;</hi> that is to say, the direction of the curve becomes vertical.
                    Wherefore, if we make OD = D such that D <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> = A <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + 2H <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, we shall obtain
                    that depth at which the curve is upright, or at which the horizontal ordinate DQ
                    is the greatest, and then the equation takes the form—</p>
                <p>δz(D <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>-z <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>) = 2δ≠δr, by
                    help of which we should be able to find <hi rend="italic">x</hi> in terms of z.
                    The computation, however, is attended with considerable difficulty, and
                    therefore it may be convenient to attempt a graphical solution. Since, for any
                    vertical ordinate HP( = z), the horizontal thrust is j(D <hi rend="superscript">
                    2</hi>- z <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>), while the oblique strain is ⅛(D <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> — A <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>), the obliquity of
                    the curve at P has for ^P)2 ∕^2</p>
                <p>its cosine the value 7-—— , wherefore the angle at which the curve crosses the
                    horizontal line <hi rend="italic">pP</hi> is known. Let then a multitude of such
                    lines be drawn in the space between BA and DQ, and let the narrow spaces thus
                    marked be crossed in succession from A downwards by lines at the proper
                    inclination, and we shall obtain a representation of the curve, which will be
                    nearer to the truth as the intervals are more numerous. The beginning of the
                    curve at A may be made a short arc of a circle described from the centre C <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi>.</p>
                <p>Since the minute differentials thus obtained are proportional to the sides of a
                    triangle whose hypotenuse is D <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>- A <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, and one of whose sides is D <hi rend="superscript">
                    2</hi> — z <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, we must have—</p>
                <p>D <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> -g <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> √{(D <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>-A <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>) <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>-(D <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>-z <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>) <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>} <hi
                    rend="superscript"> α</hi> ' ’ and the integration of this would give the value
                    of <hi rend="italic">x.</hi> If we put φ for the inclination of the curve at any
                    point P, D <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>-z <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> = (D
                    <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>-A <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>) cos ≠,</p>
                <p>.∙. z = {D <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>-(D <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>-A <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>) cos ≠} <hi rend="superscript"> i</hi>, and taking
                    the differential, <hi rend="italic">8z≈</hi> ⅛(D <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    = A <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>) sin ≠{D <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>-(D
                    <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>-A <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>) cos ≠}* <hi
                    rend="italic">8φ,</hi><hi rend="subscript"> si</hi> H. cos <hi rend="italic"
                    >φ</hi>. δ&lt;p <hi rend="superscript"> 0X</hi> ~ √{D <hi rend="superscript">
                    2</hi>-2Hcos&lt;p} ’</p>
                <p>where 2Ξ is put for its equivalent D <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>- A <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>. The integral of this expression may be obtained by
                    developing the radical in terms arranged according to the powers of cos <hi
                    rend="italic">φ,</hi> and then integrating each term separately. The result is a
                    series of terms proceeding by the powers of cos <hi rend="italic">φ,</hi> the
                    coefficient of each power being itself an interminate series; and the rate of
                    convergence is so slow as to make the labour of the calculations very great.
                    Such expressions belong to the class of <hi rend="italic">elliptic
                    functions,</hi> for which peculiar methods have been devised. Fortunately the
                    actual calculation is not required in the practice of bridgebuilding, and
                    therefore we shall only refer the reader to the above-named subject.</p>
                <p>If the horizontal thrust and the thickness at the crown of the arch be
                    prescribed, the radius of curvature there must be the same whichever of the two
                    hypotheses be adopted; now, if we sweep an arch from the centre C with the
                    radius CA, the catenarian curve lies outside of it, while the curve which we
                    have just been considering lies inside. Each of these is compatible with sound
                    principles: the one if the inner ends of the arch-stones be dressed with
                    horizontal facets, the other if the ends be dressed to a continuous curve;
                    wherefore, between these two limits we may have a vast variety of forms, each of
                    which may be made consistent with the laws of equilibrium by merely dressing the
                    inner ends of the arch-stones at the appropriate angles. Hence an entirely new
                    field of inquiry, in which we may find the complete solution of the general
                    problem :—</p>
                <p>“The intrados and extrados of an arch being both prescribed, to arrange the parts
                    consistently with the laws of equilibrium.”</p>
                <p>Let PQ represent the inner end of one of the arch-stones, the part Q7 being
                    vertical, and P&lt;∕ being sloped at some angle which is to be found; put <hi
                    rend="italic">t</hi> for the tangent of the inclination of the joint P to the
                    vertical, <hi rend="italic">θ</hi> for that of f⅛ to the horizontal line, then
                    the horizontal <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n349/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0902-0349-0330"/> strain at 1’ is —, while the corresponding strain
                    at Q is *</p>
                <p>, and if P&lt;? were horizontal these would be alike; <hi rend="italic">t</hi> +
                    θi but the obliquity of Pg ’ causes the load <hi rend="italic">δw</hi> which is
                    placed on it to generate a horizontal pressure <hi rend="italic">θδw,</hi>
                    wherefore—</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">w</hi> w+δw ,</p>
                <p>-——- = 0δw, whence <hi rend="italic">t t+ ot</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">
                    λ</hi><hi rend="italic">W</hi><hi rend="italic">'M</hi> 1 <hi rend="subscript">
                    fl</hi> w Ji <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> 0=- <hi rend="subscript"> 5</hi>-ς or
                    <hi rend="italic">θt</hi> = r- —-1.</p>
                <p>i <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> δw <hi rend="italic">t lw t</hi></p>
                <p>Now, when the forms of the intrados and extrados are both given, the values of
                    <hi rend="italic">w, t, δw, δt,</hi> are thence deducible, so that the value of
                    <hi rend="italic">θ</hi> may always be computed by help of differentiations
                    only; excepting, indeed, that integrations may be needed for determining the
                    value of <hi rend="italic">w,</hi> which is the area included between the two
                    curves.</p>
                <p>In this very simple investigation we have the complete solution of the principal
                    problem in bridge-building. The data needed for determining the shape of the
                    inner end of the arch-stone are already in the hands of the architect, who must
                    know, from his plans, the weight of each part and the inclination of each joint
                    <hi rend="italic">; so</hi> that, with a very small addition to the labour of
                    his calculations, he is enabled to put the structure completely in equilibrium,
                    even on the supposition of there being no cohesion and no friction; that is to
                    say, he is enabled to obtain the greatest stability of which a structure having
                    the prescribed-outlines is susceptible. Even although he may not care to have
                    the stones actually cut to the computed shape, and may regard their usual
                    roughness and the cement as enough, he may judge, by help of the above formula,
                    of the practicability of his design <hi rend="italic">; for</hi> if at any place
                    the value of <hi rend="italic">θδt</hi> come out with the wrong sign, that is,
                    if <hi rend="italic">u&gt;.δt</hi> be less than <hi rend="italic">t.δw,</hi> the
                    building is unstable, whereas if <hi rend="italic">w.δt</hi> be greater than <hi
                    rend="italic">t.δw</hi> everywhere, the design, as far as these details go, is a
                    safe one.</p>
                <p>In every possible arrangement of the details, the horizontal thrust at the crown
                    of the arch is transmitted to and resisted by the ultimate abutments. The only
                    effect, in this respect, of varieties in the form of construction is to vary the
                    manner of the distribution of that strain among the horizontal courses. Hence
                    one great and essential element of security,—the first thing, indeed, to be seen
                    to,—is that the ground at the ends of the proposed bridge be able to resist this
                    out-thrust. Another, and not less important one is, that the arch-stones be able
                    to withstand the strains upon them. In this respect much depends on the
                    workmanship; it is all important that the stones touch throughout their whole
                    surfaces: if these surfaces be uneven the stones must necessarily be subjected
                    to transverse strains, and so be liable to fracture. The practice, too common
                    among house-masons, of cheaply obtaining an external appearance of exactitude,
                    by confining their attention to a chisel-breadth around the outside, is not
                    permissible here, nor should any reliance be placed on the layer of mortar for
                    making up the inequalities.</p>
                <p>The limit, to the span of an arch depends primarily on the quality of the
                    material of the arch-stones. At the crown of the arch the horizontal thrust is
                    the weight of as much of the masonry as fills a rectangle whose length is equal
                    to R, the radius of curvature, and whose breadth is A, the effective thickness
                    there; now this strain has to be borne by the arch-stones, whose depth we shall
                    denote by <hi rend="italic">d,</hi> and therefore these stones must be
                    subjected, as it were, to the RA direct pressure of a vertical column whose
                    height is</p>
                <p>This column must be much shorter than that which the stone is actually able to
                    bear.</p>
                <p>The ability of a substance to resist a crushing pressure is generally measured by
                    the length of the column which it is able to support, without reference to the
                    horizontal section; but it may be questioned whether this mode of estimation be
                    a sound one, for it does seem natural to suppose that a block three inches
                    square should bear a greater load than nine separate blocks each one inch
                    square, seeing that the centre block in the entire stone is protected on all
                    sides; and thus it is possible that we under-estimate the greatest practicable
                    span of a stone arch. This difficult subject belongs to the doctrine of
                    “Strength of Materials.”</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Arch, Skewed.</hi> —In the earlier days of bridge-building
                    the road was led so as to cross the river or ravine perpendicularly, but in
                    modern engineering we cannot always afford to make the detour necessary for this
                    purpose, and must have recourse to the <hi rend="italic">skeιυed</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">oblique</hi> arch, having its plan rhomboidal, not
                    rectangular.</p>
                <p>If AB, CD, figure 8, represent the roadway, and EF,</p>
                <p>GH, the boundaries of the abutment walls placed obliquely, we easily perceive
                    that the thrust cannot be perpendicular to the abutments, for then it would go
                    out on the side walls which have no means of resistance; the thrust can only be
                    resisted in the direction of the road. Hence if the structure be divided into a
                    multitude of slices by vertical planes parallel to the parapet, the strains
                    belonging to each slice must be resisted within that slice, and each should form
                    an arch capable of standing by itself. The abutment, therefore, cannot have a
                    continuous surface as in the common or right arch, but must be cut in steps to
                    resist the oblique pressure; wherefore also the ultimate foundation stones must
                    present surfaces perpendicular to the road.</p>
                <p>Attending for the momeut to one only of these divisions, say to a thin slice
                    contiguous to the side wall EG, let us study the manner in which the arch-stones
                    in it must be shaped. At the crown I the pressure is horizontal in the plane
                    EIG, and therefore the joint of the stones there must be perpendicular to AB,
                    and so also must be its projection on the horizontal plane.</p>
                <p>Proceeding along the line of the curve to the point R, we observe that the
                    pressure there must be in the direction of a tangent to the curve, wherefore the
                    surface of a joint at R must be perpendicular to that tangent, and the <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n350/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0902-0350-0331"/> exposed face of the stone must be right-angled.
                    Now, the projection upon a horizontal surface of a right angle placed obliquely
                    is not necessarily right; in this case it cannot be right, and therefore the
                    course of a line of joints represented in plan must bend away from being
                    perpendicular to the side wall towards being parallel to the line of the
                    abutment. Thus a continuous course of joints beginning at I must be shown in
                    plan by some curved line such as IP∕&gt;.</p>
                <p>In many of the skewed bridges actually built, the outline of the arch is divided
                    into equal parts, as seen on the ends of the vault; the curved joint-lines
                    IPjt&gt; thus become portions of screws drawn on an oblique cylinder, and,
                    although the arch-stone at the crown be rectangular, those on the slope cease to
                    be so. The bearing surface is thus inclined to the direction of the pressure,
                    and the tendency is to thrust out the arch-stones at the acute corners F and G.
                    The fault is exactly the same as if, in ordinary building, the mason were to bed
                    the stones off the level. The consequence is that skewed stone-bridges have not
                    given satisfaction, the fault being attributed to the principle of the skew,
                    whereas it should have been assigned to the unskilfulness of the design.</p>
                <p>Let figure 9 be an elevation projected on a vertical plane parallel to AB, EIG,
                    FSH, being the outlines of the ends of the arch, and the sections taken at equal
                    intervals along the crown line being also shown; then, since the projection of a
                    right angle upon a plane parallel to one of its sides is always right, the joint
                    at R, as seen on this elevation, must be perpendicular to the curve at R, and
                    thus the curve IP∕&gt;, representing one of the joint-courses, must cross each
                    of the vertical sections perpendicularly. In this way each of the four-sided
                    curvilinear spaces into which this elevation is divided must be right-angled at
                    its four corners. This law is general, and enables us to determine the details
                    of any proposed oblique arch.</p>
                <p>If we draw, as in figure 9, the end elevation of the vault as intersected by
                    numerous parallel planes, and lead a curved line crossing all these
                    intersections perpendicularly, we obtain the end elevation of one of the
                    jointlines, and are able from it to prepare any other of its projections. The
                    form and character of this end elevation IP∕&gt; depends entirely on the nature
                    of the curve EIG, but is the same whatever may be the angle of the skew. In
                    order to examine its general character, let us take in the crown line two
                    closely contiguous points I, K, and from these lead the joint-lines IP, KQ, of
                    equal length, then the straight line PQ is equal and parallel to IK, on any of
                    the projections.</p>
                <p>If in the end elevation, figure 9, we continue the joint IP to meet the vertical
                    section OQ in p, we may regard PQp as a small rectilineal triangle, right angled
                    at <hi rend="italic">p,</hi> while PQp is the inclination to the horizon. Now,
                    PQ: Qp:: R: cos PQp, while PQ is equal to KI, the breadth of the arch-stone at
                    the crown, wherefore the breadth of the course at the crown is to the breadth of
                    the same course at any other place as radius is to the cosine of the inclination
                    there. Hence it follows, as is shown in the end elevation, figure 10, that the
                    arch-stones gradually diminish in breadth from the crown downwards, being halved
                    in breadth at an inclination of 60°. At a greater inclination they become still
                    narrower, and an infinity of them would be needed to reach the abutment of a
                    semicircular or semi-elliptic arch, because the cosine of the inclination there
                    is zero. In no properly-built skewed bridge can the arch-stones show equal
                    divisions; and it is impossible to continue the arch to the complete half circle
                    or half ellipse.</p>
                <p>Passing from the end elevation, figure 9, to the plan, figure 8, we observe that
                    Qp on the plan is less than <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> the actual Qp of the
                    elevation in the ratio of the cosine of the inclination to radius, and,
                    therefore, on the plan, the breadth at the crown is to the apparent breadth of
                    the course at any other place as the square of the radius is to the square of
                    the cosine of the inclination there; so that, at the inclination of 60° the
                    apparent breadth will be quarter of that at the crown.</p>
                <p>Again, in figure 11, which is the side elevation of the vault, or its projection
                    on a vertical plane perpendicular to the road, the apparent distance Qp is to
                    the actual distance Qp of figure 9 as the sine of the inclination is to radius,
                    wherefore, the apparent breadth Qp on this projection is proportional to the
                    product of the sine by the cosine of the inclination, that is, to half the sine
                    of twice the inclination. The width on this projection is therefore greatest at
                    an inclination of 45°, being there just one-half of the actual breadth at the
                    crown of the arch.</p>
                <p>This reasoning is founded on the supposition that the distance IK is excessively
                    small, and the resulting conclusions are strictly true only of an infinitely
                    narrow course of arch-stones; they are, indeed, <hi rend="italic">differential
                    equations</hi> which must be <hi rend="italic">integrated</hi> in order to be
                    applied to actual practice. Thus we have seen that the curved line IP, figure 9,
                    crosses the section NP perpendicularly at P, but then it does not continue in
                    this direction for any perceptible distance. The draughtsman may attempt to
                    trace it by making the sections very numerous, and by drawing perpendiculars
                    across the successive intervals; but however numerous he may make these
                    sections, he can thus only effect an approximation to the true curve. We must
                    <hi rend="italic">integrate,</hi> that is, we must obtain the aggregate of an
                    infinite number of infinitely small portions in order to reach an absolutely
                    true result.</p>
                <p>These conclusions hold good whatever may be the outline of the arch. The most
                    common, and therefore the most interesting case, is when the longitudinal
                    section is circular, the cross section taken perpendicularly to the abutment
                    being then an ellipse with its shorter diameter placed horizontally, the vault
                    being an oblique cylinder. Figure 9 is actually drawn for the circular arch. If
                    then O be the centre of the circular arc NP, the curve IP must <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n351/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0902-0351-0332"/> at P tend towards 0, so that the draughtsman,
                    while making the step across one of the intervals, has only to keep his straight
                    edge up to the corresponding place of the centre. If we place the paper
                    horizontally, fix a small heavy round body at P to the end of a thread OP, and
                    then draw the end 0 of that string along the straight line HEF, P would always
                    move towards the then position of the point 0, and would trace out the curve of
                    which we are in search. The projection, then, of the joint of an oblique
                    circular arch upon a vertical plane parallel to the road, is always the curve
                    known by the name of the <hi rend="italic">Tractory.</hi> All tractories have
                    the same shape, the size merely is regulated by the length of the thread OP,
                    that is, by the radius of curvature of the circular arch. Hence, if the
                    delineation of it have been accurately made in one case, the curve for another
                    case may be obtained by mere enlargement or reduction; or, still better, in all
                    cases it may be traced by help of a table of co-ordinates, such as that
                    subjoined, which shows the dimensions of the tractory as represented in figure
                    12, in decimal parts of the radius of curvature of the arch. The computations
                    have been made tor equal motions of the point 0, corresponding, therefore, to
                    equal distances measured along the crown-line of the arch. The headings of the
                    columns sufficiently explain their contents. By help of these the form of the
                    tractory may easily be obtained, and with a piece of veneer or of thin metal cut
                    to this ßhape, the architect may obtain all the details of the intended
                    structure, first working out the said elevation, figure 9, and transferring the
                    several points therefrom to the other projections.</p>
                <p>If we put s for the angle of the skew, <hi rend="italic">v</hi> for the distance
                    IN measured along the crown of the vault, and <hi rend="italic">i</hi> for the
                    inclination at the point P, <hi rend="italic">r</hi> being the radius of the
                    arch, the distance IN or tθ of figure 10 is clearly <hi rend="italic">υ</hi> sin
                    <hi rend="italic">s,</hi> and as the result of the integration, we obtain—</p>
                <p><hi rend="superscript"> v s</hi> ^ <hi rend="superscript"> n</hi>-'- = Nap. log
                    tan (45° + Jι), by help of which equation we can readily determine <hi
                    rend="italic">i</hi> when <hi rend="italic">V</hi> is known, or <hi
                    rend="italic">v</hi> when <hi rend="italic">i</hi> is given. The table of
                    Napierian logarithmic tangents being very scarce, it is convenient to convert
                    these into denary or common logarithms. Putting, as is usual, M for the modulus
                    of denary logarithms, that is, for <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 43429 44819,
                    the above equation becomes—</p>
                <p>y . <hi rend="italic">V.</hi> sin s = log tan (45° + <hi rend="italic">⅛i),</hi>
                    from which it is quite easy to tabulate the values of <hi rend="italic">i</hi>
                    corresponding to equidifferent values of <hi rend="italic">v,</hi> because the
                    constant factor—</p>
                <p>M. sin s</p>
                <p>τ ’ has to be only once computed; <hi rend="italic">i,</hi> that is, the number
                    of degrees in the arc NP being thus computed for each of the successive sections
                    of the vault, we have only to divide a tape-line so as to show degrees and
                    minutes of the actual circle in order to be able at once to mark the course of
                    the joints upon the centering of the arch; or better still, instead of the
                    degrees, we may write upon the tape the successive values of NP, and then the
                    commonest workman will be able to lay off the lines.</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p><hi rend="italic">l</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell><p>»</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>sin t</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>COS t</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Z-βin <hi rend="italic">i</hi> 1</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>•0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0 00</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>∙ooooo</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>ι∙ooooo</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>∙ooooo</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>•1</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>5 43</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•09967</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•99502</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•00033</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>•2</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>11 23</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•19738</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•98033</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•00262</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>•3</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>16 56</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•29131</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•95663</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•00869</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>•4</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>22 20</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•37995</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•92501</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•02005</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>•5</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>27 31</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•46212</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•88682</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•03788</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>•6</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>32 29</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•53705</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•84355</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•06295</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>•7</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>37 11</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•60437</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•79670</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•09563</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>•8</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>41 37</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•66404</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•74770</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•13596</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>•9</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>45 45</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•71630</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•69779</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•18370</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>10</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>49 36</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•76159</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•64805</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•23841</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>11</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>53 11</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•80050</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•59933</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•29950</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1∙2</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>56 29</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•83365</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•55229</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•36635</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1∙3</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>59 31</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>86172</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•50738</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•43828</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1∙4</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>62 18</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•88535</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•46492</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•51465</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1∙5</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>64 51</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•90515</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•42510</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•59485</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1∙6</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>67 10</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•92167</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•38798</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•57833</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1∙7</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>69 18</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•93541</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•35357</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•76459</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1∙8</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>71 14</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•94681</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•32180</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>85319</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1∙9</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>72 59</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•95624</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•29259</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•94376</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>2 0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>74 35</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•96403</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•26580</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>l∙03597</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>21</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>76 02</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•97045</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•24129</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1Ί2955</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>2∙2</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>77 21</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•97574</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•21892</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1∙22426</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>2∙3</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>78 33</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•98010</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•19852</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1'31990</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>2∙4</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>79 38</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•98367</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•17995</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1'41633</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>2∙5</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>80 37</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•98661</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•16307</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1∙51339</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>2∙6</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>81 30</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•98903</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•14773</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>l∙61097</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>2∙7</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>82 19</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•99101</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•13381</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>170899</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>2∙8</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>83 02</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•99263</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•12117</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1'80737</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>2∙9</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>83 42</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•99396</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•10971</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>l∙90604</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>3∙0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>84 18</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•99505</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•09933</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2∙00495</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>IO</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>TPO</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>OT</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>TP</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>»T</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The only other kind of skewed arch likely to possess any interest is the
                    elliptic. In right arches the semi-ellipse is sometimes used on account of the
                    grace of its form, but this reason for its adoption disappears in the case of
                    the skew, because then we can only use a portion of the semi-ellipse. The end
                    elevation of a joint in an elliptic skewed arch is a modified form of the
                    tractory, and the general features of the arrangement are analogous to those of
                    the circular arch.</p>
                <p>The arch-stone of a common bridge is wedge-shaped, having two flat faces AαcC,
                    BδdD, inclined to suit tho breadth of the course, but in the skewed bridge the
                    corresponding faces are twisted, Cc not being parallel to Aα, and thus the
                    dressing of them requires both skill and care. The dimensions of the stone and
                    the inclinations of its four edges may easily be computed when its intended
                    position is known, and thus the degree of twist on each of its faces may be
                    ascertained, and the lines may then be marked off on the ends of the stone.</p>
                <p>The theory of the skewed arch was given for the first time in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Transactions of the Royal Scottish Society of Artsioτ</hi> 1833;
                    from which it was copied into the <hi rend="italic">Civil Engineer and
                    Architect’s Journal</hi> for July 1840, which see. (For the history and various
                    forms of the arch see <hi rend="smallcaps">Architecture.) (e. s.)</hi><pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n352/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0902-0352-0333"/></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
