<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0902-0136-0123-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ANTHROPOMORPHISM (9th edition, volume 2, page
                    123)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944037">God</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150276">Thoughtfulness</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198492">Faith</term>
                    <term ref="fast:918891">Expressionism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z892f8z">Faith</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rn1g">Light</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r31v">Lighting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bw6x">Spirits</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n136/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ANTHROPOMORPHISM</label> is a term used in theological
                    writings to denote the figure by which words expressing human organs and
                    activities are applied to the divine Being; in short, it is the conception and
                    representation of God as possessed of corporeal and human properties. Originally
                    and literally the word implied only the ascribing to God a physical form
                    resembling the human body, and consequently included under it all forms of
                    expression which attribute to Him the exercise of physical organs and senses.
                    But its meaning was soon extended so as to comprehend all representations of God
                    which require Him either to be in himself corporeally extended, or to possess a
                    corporeal body as the necessary condition of His activity. In this wider sense
                    all theories were designated anthropomorphic, which identified God with light or
                    the physical universe, or which placed alongside of Him a primeval, uncreated
                    matter.</p>
                <p>Primitive ideas of God are necessarily framed by man from the analogy of his own
                    nature. He is, however, able to represent God to himself under the analogy of
                    his mental or spiritual, as well as under that of his material nature. This more
                    refined form was called anthropo-pathism, and is that mode of contemplating the
                    divine attributes founded on the analogy of God to the human spirit All forms of
                    expression which ascribe to God passions, intelligence, or volition, rest
                    ultimately upon this supposed analogy. In modern theology and philosophy, it is
                    this mode of thought that usually receives the name of anthropomorphism.</p>
                <p>Anthropomorphism is inseparable from early religion. The first dim intuition of
                    God as the ruler of the universe, on whom we depend, cannot at an early time be
                    seized in all its purity by reason. Sense and imagination are developed before
                    reason, and in semi-barbarous intelligences completely overbalance it. The
                    object of their faith is not God himself, but God as manifested in nature and
                    history. It is only through ideas derived from sensible objects and elevated by
                    the imagination that man can clothe his primitive thought of God with attributes
                    that enable him to realise it, to bring it home to himself. He must represent
                    God as in all respects like himself, superior only in power. The very words by
                    which alone he can give expression to the first workings of his consciousness of
                    God carry with them a sensible meaning, and hence react powerfully on the
                    development of his belief. They imperceptibly fix attention upon the physical
                    facts involved in them, and their merely symbolic use is forgotten. Hence arise
                    myths. Even among peoples in whom the growth of the religious consciousness was
                    extraordinarily favoured, strong traces of anthropomorphism are to be found. In
                    the Hebrew literature there is a prevailing anthropomorphic idea of God. He is
                    represented as seeing, hearing, smelling; as having a visible, corporeal
                    presence; as hating, loving, and repenting. Although the pure idea of God as a
                    spirit, as the very essence of being, is distinctly recognised and insisted upon
                    by the prophets and lawgivers, the people demanded a visible symbol, a sensible
                    emblem of their faith. Great part of the ceremonial law is taken up with the
                    attempt to reconcile this desire for visible symbol with the purer requirements
                    of their faith. Christian thought freed itself completely from the yoke of this
                    crude anthropomorphism by its fundamental axiom that God is a spirit. Theology
                    since then has had to steer its course with care between two opposite
                    tendencies: one striving to attain to a living personal community with God
                    through Christ, and thereby running the risk of introducing foreign elements
                    into the idea of God; the other, from undue fear of anthropomorphism, tending to
                    reduce the idea of God to a blank negation, a substance without qualities. In
                    the history of the church these tendencies appeared at a very early period. In
                    the Clementine homüies, but particularly in Tertullian (see <hi rend="italic"
                    >Adv. Praxean,</hi> c. vii.; <hi rend="italic">De Came Christi,</hi> c. xi.)
                    there is distinct anthropomorphism. Tertullian declares that nothing can have
                    real being that is not extended, corporeal; God, therefore, he seems to identify
                    with an ethereal being of light. An example of the finer form in which human
                    affections are ascribed to God may be found in Lactantius <hi rend="italic">(De
                    Ira Dei,</hi> c. ii.) The Alexandrian theologians, from their philosophical
                    training, were specially opposed to anthropomorphism, but in their hands the
                    danger of the opposite tendency is seen. According to some of them, we know God
                    only by negation,—we know what He is not, not what He is. Others <hi
                    rend="italic">(e.g.,</hi> Irenaeus, Novatian) declare that all the predicates of
                    God are only in image; and that, from the finitude of our minds, we must use
                    terms expressing not God’s nature, but our own ignorance. Phrases in Scripture
                    which seemed to be anthropomorphic were explained by the Fathers as revelations
                    of God in such a way as to be intelligible to us. This revelation was called
                    (see Chrysostom, <hi rend="italic">Hom.</hi> iii. c. 3) condescension or divine
                    economy.</p>
                <p>The church itself was not free from anthropomorphism of the crudest type. In the
                    2d century Melito, bishop of Sardis, wrote a book concerning the corporeity of
                    God, and in the 4th century Audaeus, in Mesopotamia, held <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n137/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0902-0137-0124"/> similar views, and had many followers. In the
                    Middle Ages the question gradually merged into the more philosophical one of the
                    relation between reason and faith. In modern theology the problem again appears,
                    but its aspect is completely philosophical. Philosophy, indeed, has never ceased
                    to concern itself with this very question. Xenophanes mocked the
                    anthropomorphism of his countrymen; Aristotle denied to the gods ethical virtue
                    and the possession of emotions or passions; he allowed to them only a life of
                    intellectual speculation. The Epicureans thought the gods lived in complete
                    quiescence, and concerned themselves not at all with the affairs of men (see
                    Lucretius, ii. 646). Philo exhibits very strongly the tendency to reduce the
                    Deity to a lifeless abstraction, whose attributes are only negatively known. In
                    modern philosophy, Descartes attempted to settle the problem, by affirming that
                    any attributes in us which involve limitation or imperfection cannot be ascribed
                    to God, but that attributes which do not imply imperfection can be predicated of
                    Him. Spinoza is one of the strongest opponents of any form of anthropomorphism,
                    and from him the modern aspect of the question may be said to proceed. He
                    brought clearly to light the fundamental difficulty, the reconciliation of the
                    infinite and absolute nature of God with any attribute whatsoever; for
                    attribute, as such, implies negation, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> limitation.
                    Spinoza dismisses as anthropomorphic the idea of God as an intelligence, as free
                    to act, and as ruling the world, and thus destroys the ideas of design in nature
                    and of providence. The consequences of this theory on questions relating to the
                    personality of God, miracles, prayer, &amp;c., have been worked out very fully
                    in the most recent times.</p>
                <p>Thus the real problem at the root of the question as to the legitimacy of
                    anthropomorphic modes of thought, is the philosophical one of the limits of
                    human intelligence, of the relation between the divine thought in itself and in
                    nature and human intelligence. A long line of philosophic thinkers affirm the
                    impossibility of human intelligence penetrating the nature of the divine, and
                    point out our inability to solve the many contradictions which arise in the
                    attempt to do so. According to them, we can only think of God by analogy; our
                    ideas of Him must be anthropomorphic, but they are at the same time known to be
                    entirely symbolical. The best known representatives of this mode of thought are
                    Bishop Browne and the late Dean ManseL</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
