<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0902-0609-0548-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ARMENIAN CHURCH, The (9th edition, volume 2, page
                    548)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hx15t8m">Eucharist</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r724">Presents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c552">Nestorians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s33k">Creeds</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:814767">Armenians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1036176">Nestorians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="fast:896108">Documentation</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1151043">Time</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n609/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ARMENIAN CHURCH, <hi rend="smallcaps">The</hi></label>, is
                    one of the oldest Eastern Christian churches not in communion with the orthodox
                    Greek Church or with the Church of Rome.</p>
                <p>1. <hi rend="italic">History.—</hi> This is divided into three periods, from 34
                    to 302 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.,</hi> from 302 to 491, and from 491 to the
                    present time. (1.) The first period is mainly legendary. The Church of Armenia
                    claims an older than apostolic foundation. Our Lord, they say, corresponded by
                    letter with Akbar, prince of Ur or Orfa; and the apostle Thaddeus, accompanied
                    by Bartholomew and Judas, preached the gospel, and founded a Christian church in
                    Armenia as early as the year 34 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> But whatever the
                    value of these primitive traditions, Armenia could hardly be said to have a
                    church at all during this first period, although there are evident traces of
                    Christian worship in the country at a very early time. (2.) The historical
                    founder of the Armenian Church was S. Gregory, called the “Illuminator.” He was
                    a prince of the reigning family of the Arsacidae, who, having been converted to
                    Christianity, was eager for the conversion of his countrymen. In his missionary
                    work he endured many persecutions, but at last managed to win over the king of
                    Armenia and a considerable portion of his subjects. At the king’s desire Gregory
                    went to Caesarea, or Sis, and was there consecrated bishop of Armenia (302 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">a.d.)</hi> His successors afterwards assumed the title of .
                    Patriarch, subsequently Catholicos, and under their rule the infant church grew
                    and prospered. It had to struggle against the opposition of heathen
                    fellow-countrymen and Persian conquerors, but it succeeded in establishing
                    itself in the hearts of the people. The Bible was translated in 410 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi>; the Liturgy, said to be very old, was improved; and
                    the Armenian bishops took part in several of the synods of the church, notably
                    in the third oecumenical council (Ephesus, 431 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.)</hi>
                    About 450 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> the Armenian Church suffered a severe
                    persecution, which prevented any of the bishops being present at the fourth
                    oecumenical council (Chalcedon, 451 <hi rend="smallcaps">a,d.),</hi> at which
                    Eutyches and hià followers, the extreme opponents of Nestorius, were condemned.
                    The Armenian Church never accepted the decisions of the Council of Chalcedon,
                    and, in 491 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.,</hi> the patriarch, in full synod,
                    solemnly annulled them. This act led to the separation of the Armenian from the
                    orthodox Greek Church. (3.) The period of schismatic existence divides into
                    three—(a), from 491 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> to the middle of the 15th
                    century; (δ), from the middle of the 15th to the middle of the 18th centuries;
                    (c), from 1746 down to the present time. It is difficult to account for the
                    schism of the Armenian Church; according to common report, the Armenians were
                    Eutychians, and were virtually cut off from the church when the Council of
                    Chalcedon condemned that heresy, but their own account of the matter in their
                    authoritative documents is very different. They allege that they were misled by
                    false reports when they annulled the fourth council; that it was reported to
                    them that the council had decided in favour of the Nestorian heresy, and that
                    this mistake was confirmed by a letter to the patriarch upon the subject from
                    the bishop of Rome, in which certain words were used which might easily be
                    interpreted in the Nestorian sense. The Patriarch Narses, in his letter to the
                    Emperor Manuel Com-nenus, in 1166, distinctly repudiates the Eutychian heresy,
                    but it is to be noted that, in defending the doctrinal views <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n610/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0902-0610-0549"/> of his church, he employs the somewhat vague
                    terms in use before the Council of Chalcedon, not those stricter definitions
                    which were in use afterwards; he employs <hi rend="italic">(rvppi^v;,</hi> for
                    instance, in its pre-Chalcedonian meaning, not ίνωσις. However occasioned, the
                    separation was gradual; Armenian bishops attended the 5th, 6th, and 7th
                    oecumenical councils (2d of Constantinople, 553; 3d of Constantinople, 680; 2d
                    of Nicaea, 788), and the church acknowledges the decrees of those councils as
                    binding. Cut off from the Eastern Church, the Armenian bishops became all the
                    more closely identified with their native country, and kept alive patriotic
                    feeling in times of great national distress. In spite of many national
                    calamities, foreign domination, internal dissensions, and even banishment, the
                    Armenian Church preserved its character, doctrine, and discipline until the
                    middle of the 15th century, when great dissensions arose which -resulted in a
                    schism. These quarrels were occasioned by Jesuit missionaries, who endeavoured
                    to make the Armenians adopt the doctrine, liturgy, and ceremonies of the Roman
                    Church. They succeeded in prevailing upon a great number of the adherents of the
                    Armenian Church to separate from the community and join the communion of Rome.
                    The Catholic Armenians, as they are called, first became a separate community
                    towards the end of the 16th century; their existence has proved a source of
                    great weakness to the orthodox church, and through their exertions the old
                    persecutions were revived. This state of matters went on until the middle of the
                    18th century, when the patriarch sought and obtained the intervention of Peter
                    the Great of Russia. Since then the Armenian Church has found shelter under the
                    protection of Russia. There is a reformation now going on in the Armenian
                    Church, and a Reformed Church has arisen, which seeks to ally itself with the
                    Calvinist Churches of Europe and America.</p>
                <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Doctrines.—</hi> These are almost identical with those of
                    the orthodox Greek Church. The Armenians accept the first three, and the fifth,
                    sixth, and seventh oecumenical councils, denying that of Chalcedon only, but, as
                    has been explained, they, in their authoritative documents, reject the Eutychian
                    heresy, which that council was called to condemn. The chief source of
                    information as to the doctrine is contained in the letter of Narses above
                    referred to. They reject the Western addition of <hi rend="italic">filioque</hi>
                    to the Nicene Creed, and deny the distinctive doctrines of the Roman Church.</p>
                <p>3. The <hi rend="italic">Liturgy</hi> is said to date from the 1st century, and
                    to have been founded on that of the Church of Jerusalem. St Gregory remodelled
                    it, and introduced the Nicene Creed, using that edition which contains the
                    damnatory clause, and adding a conclusion of his own. Prayers of John Chrysostom
                    and of Basil the Great were introduced in 430 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi>
                    Prayers are said for the dead, and entreaty is made for the pardon of their
                    sins, but the church does not believe in purgatory, nor admit of indulgences.
                    The holy days are Sundays, the chief feasts observed in the Eastern Church, and
                    ten national saints’ days. Christmas is celebrated on the 6th of January, on the
                    day of the Epiphany, and not on the 25th of December.</p>
                <p>4. <hi rend="italic">Sacraments.—</hi> The Church of Armenia has the seven
                    sacraments: baptism, confirmation, the eucharist, penance, ordination, marriage,
                    and extreme unction, <hi rend="italic">Baptism</hi> is by immersion; the child
                    is immersed three times; it is then anointed with holy oil, is confirmed, and
                    partakes of the eucharist in both elements. <hi rend="italic">Confirmation</hi>
                    is administered to children immediately after baptism. The <hi rend="italic"
                    >eucharist</hi> is administered in both elements to all members of the church;
                    the bread is always unleavened, and the wine is not mixed with water. Confession
                    must precede the partaking of the eucharist, save in the case of children under
                    seven years of age. <hi rend="italic">Penance</hi> consists of confession and
                    fasting. <hi rend="italic">Ordination</hi> is by anointing with the holy oil.
                    The τnαrnαye <hi rend="italic">service</hi> is almost the same as in the Greek
                    Church. In <hi rend="italic">extreme unction</hi> only priests are anointed with
                    oil. Laity have the prayers said over them, but are not anointed.</p>
                <p>5. <hi rend="italic">The Clergy.—</hi> There is the threefold order— bishops,
                    priests, and deacons; and there are three degrees of episcopal rank—the
                    archbishops (chief among whom is the patriarch or catholicos), the bishop, and
                    the vartabed, or doctor of theology, who has frequently charge of a diocese,
                    with episcopal functions. The clergy are further divided into the black and the
                    white. The black clergy are monks, and are alone eligible for the higher
                    clerical offices; the white clergy include the parish priests and lower clergy.
                    The clergy may marry before ordination, but not after; and a priest’s widow is
                    not allowed to remarry. The priesthood is hereditary. During his father’s or
                    grandfather’s lifetime the heir may follow a secular calling; but he must leave
                    this and enter the priest’s office on the death of the priest he is heir to.
                    There are four patriarchs, who have their seats at Constantinople, Jerusalem,
                    Sis, and Etchmiadzin. The clergy of all ranks are supported entirely by the
                    free-will offerings of the people.</p>
                <p>Authorities :— <hi rend="italic">The Life and Times of S. Gregory the
                    Illuminator,</hi> translated, by S. C. Malan, 1868. (This is a translation of
                    authoritative papers, and includes a short summary of the state of the Armenian
                    Church. It is founded on authoritative documents.) <hi rend="italic">The Divine
                    Liturgy of the Armenian Church,</hi> transi, by S. C. Malan, Lond. 1870 (very
                    carefully done). <hi rend="italic">Histoire, Dogmes,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Traditions</hi><hi rend="italic">et Liturgie de l'Eglise Arménienne,</hi>
                    Paris, 1855 (fuller, but not so accurate). <hi rend="italic">Codex</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Mysterii</hi><hi rend="italic">Missal Armenorum</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">seu</hi><hi rend="italic">Liturgia Armena,</hi> Pome, 1677 (Lat
                    and Armen. Later editions of the Liturgy published at Rome belong to the
                    Catholic Armenian Church, and are worthless). (T. Μ. L.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
