<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0902-0152-0139-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ANTONINUS, Wall of (9th edition, volume 2, page
                    139)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1170190">Walls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839101">Britons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1114160">Sex</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1030128">Museums</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47s7ht9n">Walls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z892m1t">Celtic</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0329f">Britons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t08d">Dykes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46m33654">Dikes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n152/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ANTONINUS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Wall of</hi></label>, called
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Graham’s Dyke</hi> by the natives of the district through
                    which it passed, is the name given by historians to that series of defensive
                    posts, connected by a rampart and a wall, which at one time extended across the
                    island from the Frith of Clyde on the west to the Frith of Forth on the east.
                    The former of these appellations it has received from the Roman emperor in whose
                    reign it was erected; the origin of the latter is more doubtful, a probable
                    opinion being that which regards it as a corruption of the Celtic <hi
                    rend="italic">greim,</hi> a place of strength, and <hi rend="italic">diog,</hi>
                    a trench or rampart.</p>
                <p>We are informed by Tacitus that Agricola, during his fourth summer in Britain (81
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.),</hi> occupied himself in consolidating his previous
                    conquests, and that for this purpose he caused a series of detached forts to be
                    built on the isthmus that joins the two friths as a barrier against the still
                    unconquered Caledonians of the north. It was along, or almost along, the same
                    line, that one of his successors in the command of the Roman troops in Britain
                    raised the more permanent military work known as Antonine’s wall.</p>
                <p>The writer of the life of the emperor Antoninus Pius in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Historice Augustee Scriptores</hi><hi rend="italic">Sex,</hi> usually supposed
                    to have been Julius Capitolinus, expressly states that Lollius Urbicus, a legate
                    of that emperor, erected, after several victories over the Britons, “another
                    rampart of turf” to check their inroads. No locality is specified, but a
                    fragment of a stone, now in the museum of the university of Glasgow, has an
                    inscription in which the name of this Lollius seems to occur. This fragment, and
                    the numerous monumental records bearing the name of Antonine that have been
                    discovered along its course, identify beyond all reasonable doubt the wall
                    between the Forth and Clyde as that spoken of by the annalist, and furnish
                    satisfactory proof of the correctness of its best-known name. And if a small
                    pillar figured by Gordon, and at one time in the library of the university of
                    Edinburgh, was found, as is probable, near the wall, it fixes the year 140 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> as the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n153/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0902-0153-0140"/> exact date at which the portion of the work
                    connected with the pillar was executed.</p>
                <p>In addition to the annalist just mentioned, several other ancient historians are
                    supposed to allude to Antonine’s wall; but their brief statements are so vague
                    that further reference to what they say is unnecessary. Of mediaeval writers
                    Bede is almost the only one who notices it, but he erroneously ascribes its
                    erection to the natives of the south acting according to advice given them by
                    the Romans. Timothy Pont, who early in the 16th century personally surveyed a
                    large portion of Scotland while gathering materials for his projected <hi
                    rend="italic">Scottish Atlas,</hi> drew the attention of antiquaries to this
                    memorial of Roman times, though to him, as well as to his successors in
                    antiquarian research for nearly a century, it was known as “Agricola’s vallum,
                    or Graham’s Dike.” It is to Gordon that the merit must be awarded of having been
                    the first to give to the world a satisfactory account of the “wall of Antoninus
                    Pius.” A chapter of the <hi rend="italic">Itinerarium, Septentrionale</hi> is
                    devoted to it, and plans are given of the principal forts, as well as engravings
                    of the legionary tablets and other objects of interest that had, up to the
                    author’s day, been dug out of its ruins. Gordon was followed by Horsley and Roy,
                    the latter of whom made in 1755 a new survey of it, which enabled him to correct
                    Gordon in some particulars. Lastly, in the <hi rend="italic">Caledonia</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Romana</hi> of Stuart, we have a complete and, on the whole,
                    accurate description of the wall, with figures of all the sculptured stones
                    found near its course up to the date at which he wrote.</p>
                <p>The nature and appearance of the wall when perfect have been described by all
                    these writers in very similar terms, though they differ somewhat as to the.
                    measurement of its several parts. “It consisted,” says Stuart, “in the first
                    place, of an immense fosse or ditch—averaging about 40 feet in width, by some 20
                    in depth — which extended over hill and plain in one unbroken line from sea to
                    sea. Behind this ditch on its southern side, and within a few feet of its edge,
                    was raised a rampart of intermingled stone and earth, strengthened by sods of
                    turf, which measured, it is supposed, about 20 feet in height, and 24 in
                    thickness at the base. This rampart was surmounted by a parapet, behind which
                    ran a level platform for the accommodation of its defenders. To the southward of
                    the whole was situated the military way—a regular causewayed road about 20 feet
                    wide—which kept by the course of the wall at irregular distances, approaching in
                    some places to within a few yards, and in others receding to a considerable
                    extent.” Along the entire line there were at least eighteen principal stations
                    or forts, with smaller watchtowers in the intervening spaces. The rampart seems
                    to have consisted for the most part of earth or turf, as stated by the annalist;
                    but stone was, no doubt, employed in the building of the forts and watchtowers
                    as well as in certain portions of the rampart itself.</p>
                <p>Although in many parts of its course all traces of Antonine’s wall have long been
                    obliterated, the line along which it stretched has been mapped out by Gordon and
                    others with sufficient accuracy. Commencing in the west on a height called
                    Chapel Hill, near the village of Old Kilpatrick in Dumbartonshire, and now
                    distant from the River Clyde about 150 yards, it ran eastwards, passing in
                    succession Kirkintilloch, Croy, Castlecary, and Falkirk, and terminated at
                    Bridgeness, a rocky promontory that projects into the Frith of Forth south of
                    Borrowstounness in Linlithgowshire. Its eastern termination was long supposed to
                    have been near the kirk of Carriden. In 1869, however, a sculptured legionary
                    tablet, since deposited in the museum of the Society of Antiquaries of Scotland,
                    was found at Bridgeness, in such a position that it is impossible to avoid the
                    conclusion that the wall actually terminated there. Its entire length may be set
                    down at about 36 English miles.</p>
                <p>Of the sculptures found near or on the site of this wall a considerable number
                    are records of the different portions of the work executed by the legionaries
                    employed on it, and who mainly belonged to the second, sixth, and twentieth
                    legions. Some of these tablets are in the museum of the university of Glasgow,
                    and are of much interest, but the finest of them all is the Bridgeness one
                    already referred to. From the number of Roman paces mentioned on the
                    inscriptions, Horsley and others have attempted to determine the exact length of
                    the work. Unfortunately for their purpose, the paces on the stones already
                    discovered considerably exceed its w hole length, and as we cannot suppose that
                    all the monuments of this kind that were erected by the legionaries have been
                    preserved and brought to light, we must conclude with Stuart that they had
                    raised more than one memorial of the same piece of work.</p>
                <p>How many years Antonine’s wall continued to be the boundary of the Roman
                    territories in Britain it is impossible to say, but there is every reason for
                    believing that it was so for only a brief period.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
