<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0902-0897-0824-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ASTURIAS (9th edition, volume 2, page 824)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1140558">Swiss</term>
                    <term ref="fast:829042">Bays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028366">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1163841">Valleys</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20h7x">Valleys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x63b58d">Kindness</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3m81r">Swiss</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n897/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ASTURIAS</label>, one of the ancient provinces of Spain,
                    formerly (from 1388 downwards) conferred as a principality on the heir-apparent
                    to the throne. By the new division of Spain in 1833, the province took the name
                    of Oviedo, though not to the exclusion, in ordinary usage, of the older
                    designation. It is bounded on the N. by the Bay of Biscay, on the S. by Leon, on
                    the W. by Galicia, and on the E. by Santander, which is now incorporated with
                    Old Castile. It consists of a portion of the northern slope of what is properly
                    a part of the Pyrenean system, and is covered in all directions with offshoots
                    from the main chain, by which it is almost completely shut in on all sides. Only
                    a few of the passes across the mountains are practicable for carriages, and most
                    of them are difficult even for horses. Along the coast there is a narrow strip
                    of level ground, which consists largely of bare and moor-like reaches, covered
                    with furze. The province, as might be supposed, is watered by numerous streams
                    and rivers, which have hollowed out beautiful and picturesque valleys; but owing
                    to the narrowness of the level tract, their courses are short, rapid, and
                    subject to floods. The most important is the Nalon or Pravia, which receives the
                    waters of the Caudal, the Trubia, and the Narcea, and has a course of 62 miles;
                    after it rank the Navia and the Sella. Along the whole extent of the coast, a
                    distance of 130 miles, there is not one good port. In that of Riba de Sella a
                    large frigate may anchor, and Gijon will admit a vessel drawing 16 or 17 feet of
                    water; but the entrance is in both cases difficult and dangerous. The climate of
                    the district is generally mild, but overcharged with humidity, and in the higher
                    regions the winters are protracted and severe. The broken character of the
                    surface prevents anything like extensive agricultural industry, but abundant
                    pasturage is found in the valleys. The wheat crop frequently fails. Rye succeeds
                    better, and is often mixed with the maize which forms the principal food of all
                    but the higher classes. Chestnuts—here, as elsewhere in Spain, an important
                    article of diet—are very abundant on the hills, and the tree supplies valuable
                    timber. Other timbertrees, such as oak and beech, are found in the mountains,
                    along with various medicinal plants, such as hellebore, angelica, and valerian.
                    Apples are abundant, and cider forms the common drink of the people; but little
                    attention is paid to vines. The horses of Asturias are specially gentle and
                    sure-footed, ranking among the best in Spain, and excelling those of Andalusia
                    in strength, though surpassed by them in beauty. Wild deer, boars, and bears are
                    not uncommon among the mountains; and the sea-coasts, as well as the streams,
                    abound with fish of various kinds, including salmon and lampreys, which are sent
                    to the markets of Madrid.</p>
                <p>With regard to mineral wealth, Asturias can no longer boast, as it did in the
                    days of the Romans, of satisfying the quest of the “pale seeker after gold,” but
                    it possesses valuable coal-measures, which are worked at Langres, Mieres, Santo
                    Firme, &amp;c., and furnish a supply to Cadiz, Carthagena, and other ports in
                    the Mediterranean. The yield in 1868 was 2,720,000 met. quintals, or upwards of
                    267,000 tons. Beneath the coal-beds there is frequently a large development of
                    hematite or iron ore; copper mines are worked in the neighbourhood of the river
                    Aviles; and lead, magnesia, arsenic, cobalt, lapis lazuli, alum, antimony, jet,
                    marble, and rock-crystal are found in various parts of the province, while amber
                    and coral are gathered along the coast. Fuel of various kinds being plentiful,
                    several manufactories of copper utensils are maintained, which supply some parts
                    of Leon and Castile with kettles, pots, and similar articles. There used,
                    besides, to be a large royal cannon-foundry near Oviedo. Coarse cloth is
                    manufactured in the province, but not in sufficient quantity to supply the
                    inhabitants. The roads in Asturias are not of a very satisfactory description,
                    with the exception of the <hi rend="italic">Camino real,</hi> or royal highway,
                    leading from Gijon to Leon and Madrid, which was projected by
                    Jovellanos,—himself a native of Gijon,—and cost so much that Charles V. inquired
                    if it were paved with silver. It is carried by means of bridges and embankments
                    over every impediment of a rugged and mountainous territory. A railway has been
                    formed from Gijon to Langres, about twenty-five miles inland, where there are
                    mines; and a more important line uniting Gijon to Leon has for long been “in
                    course of construction.”</p>
                <p>The capital of the province is Oviedo, and the other towns of importance are
                    Gijon, Aviles, Llanes, and Luarca. Ten miles E.S.E. of Oviedo is the collegial
                    church and sanctuary of Covudonga, famous for its connection with the struggle
                    of Pelayo against the Moors. The people of Asturias have been called the Swiss
                    of Spain: they are robust, patient, and hardy; unenterprising, but laborious;
                    hospitable to strangers, and enthusiastic lovers of their country. Like the
                    Swiss, they leave their homes in large numbers, and make a living in the
                    southern cities as servants and water-carriers, the married women even often
                    hiring themselves as nurses in Madrid and elsewhere. The native dialect is
                    called Bable, and among other distinctive marks employs <hi rend="italic">f</hi>
                    for the usual Spanish <hi rend="italic">h</hi> in many words, thus approaching
                    nearer to the original Latin. There is a special clan among the Asturians called
                    the Baqueros, who lead a nomadic life, tending their cattle in winter on the
                    coast, and in summer on the mountains of Leytariegos. They never marry beyond
                    the bounds of the tribe. The ancient Asturians or A stures—so called, it is
                    supposed, from the old Spanish root <hi rend="italic">ast,</hi> a
                    hill-fortress—were in possession, not only of the present province, but also of
                    what is now the northern part of Leon, where they have left their name to the
                    city of Astorga. The district south of the Cantabrian mountains was subjugated
                    by the Romans <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n898/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0902-0898-0825"/> about 25 <hi rend="smallcaps">b,c.,</hi> but the
                    warlike natives maintained their independence in the north. And long after, when
                    the rest of Spain was in the hands of the Moors, this rugged region was a refuge
                    to the otherwise vanquished race, which at length acquired strength to break
                    forth from its fastnesses and beat back the invader.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
