<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0902-0563-0504-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ARISTIDES (9th edition, volume 2, page 504)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1156484">Tribes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1115719">Shells</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="fast:874582">Conducting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1128747">Spartanism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43f4kq7b">Descents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47659j0m">Descent</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cv4bt5f">Shells</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n563/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ARISTIDES</label>, surnamed the Just, was the son of
                    Lysimachus, a native of Athens, of the tribe Antiochis. His family appears to
                    have been of noble descent; at least it is known that Callias, the torch-bearer
                    at the Eleusinian mysteries, and reputedly the wealthiest man in Athens, was a
                    cousin or near kinsman. Plutarch maintains, in opposition to Demetrius
                    Phalereus, that Aristides was <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n564/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0902-0564-0505"/> very poor, and never enriched himself at the
                    expense of the state. His poverty, however, seems scarcely reconcilable with the
                    fact that he was made archon at a time when the possession of a certain amount
                    of property was an indispensable qualification for that office. But extremely
                    little is known of his early life. So far as political tendencies went, he had
                    been a companion and follower of Clisthenes, and it is also told that he had a
                    great veneration for the character and legislation of Lycurgus. He, therefore,
                    natnrally took the aristocratic side in questions of state policy, and
                    consequently found himself incessantly opposed to the great democratic leader,
                    Themistocles. Plutarch relates many anecdotes of the constant opposition between
                    the two, but in several points his account must be inaccurate.l</p>
                <p>The first certain appearance of Aristides in history was at the battle of
                    Marathon, 490 B.c., where he was one of the ten generals, and led his own tribe,
                    Antiochis. He is said to have been second in command to Miltiades. According to
                    custom each of the ten generals had supreme command of the whole army for one
                    day; Aristides saw the disadvantages of this system, which totally prevented any
                    fixed plan being carried out, and by his advice and example prevailed on the
                    other generals to relinquish their right in favour of Miltiades. This prudent
                    measure contributed largely to the success of the battle, in which also,
                    according to Plutarch, much was due to the valour of Aristides. He was left with
                    one tribe to collect the spoil from the field of battle, while Miltiades marched
                    to Athens to protect the city from the Persian fleet. He discharged the duty
                    intrusted to him with the most scrupulous honesty. Next year he was made archon
                    eponymus, and his reputation for justice appears to have been increased by the
                    manner in which he performed the duties of his office. But his great rival,
                    Themistocles, who had been meanwhile increasing his own power, grew jealous, and
                    gradually raised a strong feeling against him by representing how dangerous it
                    was for a democracy that any individual should be allowed to gain such influence
                    as that of Aristides. The Athenians, uneasy at this idea, banished him by
                    ostracism in 483. It is said that, on this occasion, an ignorant fellow, who did
                    not know Aristides, came up to him, and, giving him his shell, desired him to
                    write upon it the name of Aristides. The latter asked in surprise if Aristides
                    had done him any wrong. “No,” was the reply, “and I do not even know him, but it
                    irritates me to hear him everywhere called <hi rend="italic">the justP</hi>
                    Aristides made no answer, but took the shell and wrote his own name on it</p>
                <p>On the night before the battle of Salamis, Aristides, who was still in exile,
                    made a perilous journey through the enemy’s fleet, and reached the tent of
                    Themistocles. He told him that he had come to bury in oblivion their former
                    differences; that he had learned his plan for giving battle to the Persian fleet
                    in the narrow straits of Salamis, and highly approved of it; and that he would
                    assist him to the utmost of his ability. By his influence the other generals
                    were induced to assent to the plans of Themistocles, of whom they were somewhat
                    jealous. On the day of battle, Aristides collected some Athenian volunteers, and
                    made a descent on the little island of Psyttalea, which was filled with the
                    forces of the enemy. These he routed and almost annihilated. After the victory
                    of Salamis he dissuaded Themistocles from his ambitious plan of conquering Asia
                    by destroying the bridge which the Persians had built over the Hellespont, and
                    thereby cutting off their communications.</p>
                <p>About this time his sentence of exile appears to have been revoked, for in 479 he
                    was general of the Athenians in the campaign against Mardonius, and shared with
                    Pausanias the glory of the victory-at Plataea. By his prudent counsels before
                    the battle, he settled a dangerous dispute with the Tegetae; and after the
                    victory, when the Athenians and Lacedaem onians were contending as to the right
                    of erecting the trophy, he prevailed on the Athenians to give up their claim.
                    The Lacedaemonians immediately followed this example, and the honours of the day
                    were given to the Plataeans. He also instituted yearly sacrifices and
                    quinquennial games at Plataea, to celebrate the victory over the barbarians and
                    the liberation of Greece. On his return to Athens, Aristides introduced the
                    famous measure by which the archonship was thrown open to all classes of
                    citizens. In 477, he was sent along with Cimon, over whom he had great
                    influence, to take command of the Athenian contingent, under the general command
                    of Pausanias the Lacedaemonian. The haughtiness and oppressive conduct of the
                    Spartans had disgusted the allies, who were completely won over by the mildness
                    and prudence of Aristides and Cimon. In a body the allied Greeks threw off the
                    hegemony of Sparta, and formed a confederation under the Athenians. To Aristides
                    was committed the task of drawing up the laws for this confederacy, and settling
                    the amount of tribute which should be paid by each state. This duty he
                    discharged to the complete satisfaction of the allies, who were delighted to be
                    assessed at only 460 talents. The first instalment of the tax was paid into the
                    national treasury, then situated on the sacred island of Delos, but afterwards
                    transferred to Athens, a measure which Aristides is said to have declared unjust
                    but expedient.</p>
                <p>The time and place of his death are uncertain. It is known, at least, that he
                    survived the banishment of Themistocles, for his generous conduct towards his
                    fallen rival is commemorated by Plutarch. He died, probably, about 468 B,c.,
                    according to some at Athens, according to others at Pontus. He is said to have
                    died in such poverty that he did not leave enough to defray his funeral
                    expenses, but had a tomb erected to him with funds from the public treasury.
                    This tomb at Phalerum was still to be seen in the time of Plutarch. His
                    daughters received marriage portions from the state, and his son, Lysimachus,
                    was granted a sum of money and a portion of land. Such was the respect of the
                    Athenians for the memory of their great statesman, that even his remote
                    descendants are said to have received assistance from the public treasury.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
