<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0707-5956-0668-09" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DEFOE, Daniel</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 7, page 668</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="13" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w922">Writers</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49k45v4z">Hymns</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1158235">Truth</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:869839">Commons</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:915437">Essays</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198491">Essay</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194755956" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DEFOE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Daniel</hi></label>, a man of
                    varied and original genius, who distinguished himself as a political writer,
                    and, above all, immortalized his name by the incomparable romance of <hi
                    rend="italic">Robinson Crusoe,</hi> was born in London about the year 1663. He
                    was the son of James Foe, butcher in the parish of St Giles, Cripplegate, and
                    grandson of Daniel Foe, of Elton, in Northamptonshire, yeoman. How he came to
                    take the name of <hi rend="italic">De</hi> Foe or Defoe, we are not informed;
                    but his enemies have asserted that he assumed the <hi rend="italic">De</hi> in
                    order to pass for a Frenchman. It appears, however, that in January 1688 he was,
                    under the name of Daniel Foe, admitted to the freedom of the city by reason of
                    his birth. The family of Defoe were Protestant dissenters; and Daniel, who had
                    received his education in an academy belonging to that body at Newington Green,
                    near London, became by reflection attached to those principles which he had
                    inherited by his birth, and approved himself through life their able and zealous
                    defender. Fortune seemed to have destined him to be merely an artisan, and,
                    accordingly, he was bound apprentice to a hosier; but his naturally active mind,
                    already expanded by his early studies, sought to exercise itself on other
                    objects than the details of a mechanical profession, and he read assiduously the
                    public papers, in which subjects of great interest were sometimes discussed. The
                    unpopular government of James the Second had begun to agitate the minds of men
                    on questions of religion and politics; and that of Defoe, who had not yet
                    attained his twenty-first year, partook largely of the general excitement. His
                    first publication, which appeared in 1683, was a <hi rend="italic">Treatise
                    against the Turks,</hi> written in order to combat the prevailing sentiment of
                    the time in favour of the Ottomans, as opposed to the house of Austria. But
                    Defoe soon showed that he could wield the sword as well as the pen, and that he
                    was as ready to fight as to write in defence of freedom. In June 1683, when he
                    had not yet completed his twenty-third year, he appeared in arms for the
                    unfortunate Duke of Monmouth; an exploit of which he was accustomed to boast, in
                    the latter period of his life, when it had ceased to be dangerous to avow
                    participation in that imprudent and ill-fated enterprise: and he had the good
                    fortune not merely to escape the hazards of the field, but the still more
                    imminent perils of Judge Jefferies’ sanguinary “western campaign.” In 1687 he
                    attacked the proclamation for the repeal of the penal laws, in a tract, in which
                    he exposed the unconstitutional measures pursued by King James, and warned the
                    dissenters against the insidious toleration with which the court had sought to
                    delude them. In common with all the friends of liberty, Defoe warmly greeted the
                    Revolution, which he had endeavoured to promote by his sword as well as his pen;
                    and when King William and Queen Mary were entertained by the city of London, on
                    the 29th of October 1689, he was one of the regiment of volunteers which,
                    commanded by the celebrated Earl of Peterborough, attended their majesties on
                    that occasion from Whitehall to the Mansion-house.</p>
                <p>At this period Defoe is said to have acted as a hosier in Freeman’s Court,
                    Cornhill: but with the imprudence which is too frequently the concomitant of
                    genius, he neglected business for pleasure; frequented companies, where the
                    readiness and vivacity of his wit made him always a welcome guest; and spent
                    those hours in social enjoyment or the cultivation of literature which ought to
                    have been devoted to the cares and calculations of the countinghouse. The
                    consequence was, that in 1692 he fell into difficulties, and being obliged to
                    abscond for a time, a commission of bankruptcy was issued against him; but this
                    was afterwards superseded on the petition of his principal creditors, who, on
                    his own personal bond, accepted a composition which, by efforts of unwearied
                    diligence, he punctually and honourably paid. Nor did even this satisfy the
                    scrupulous integrity of the author of <hi rend="italic">Robinson Crιιsoe.</hi>
                    For when, by the favour of King William, his circumstances<pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:194755969" xml:id="kp-eb0707-5969-0669"/> had been improved, he paid
                    such of his creditors as had themselves fallen into distress, their full claims,
                    and, exclusively of the composition already mentioned, at length reduced his
                    whole debts from seventeen to less than five thousand pounds; an instance of
                    probity admirable in itself, and, considering that it was exemplified by a man
                    who had to struggle with a numerous family, without assistance excepting his own
                    industry, often paralysed by misfortunes, deserving of unqualified commendation.
                    As yet he had mortified no great man by his keen satire, and offended no party
                    by his caustic pamphlets; whilst by his powers of pleasing, which never deserted
                    him, he had acquired friends who evinced a desire to serve him. Their . project
                    was that he should settle as a factor at Cadiz, a place with which he had
                    previously had some correspondence as a trader; but, as he himself remarks,
                    Providence, which had other work for him to do, placed a secret aversion in his
                    mind to quitting England.</p>
                <p>Defoe now began to meditate a variety of schemes for the benefit of his country,
                    and, in January 1697, published his <hi rend="italic">Essay upon Projects,</hi>
                    which shows an extensive range of knowledge; recommends the establishment of a
                    society for encouraging learning, refining the English language, and preventing
                    barbarisms in manners as well as in speech; and well deserves the commendation
                    which both Prior and Swift afterwards bestowed upon it. In 1695 Defoe was
                    appointed accountant to the commissioners for managing the duties on glass; but
                    this situation he lost in 1699, when the tax on glass was repealed by act of
                    parliament. In 1701 appeared <hi rend="italic">The True-born Englishman,</hi> a
                    poem in vindication of King W illiam, who had been attacked by one Tutchen, in a
                    scurrilous piece entitled <hi rend="italic">The Foreigners.</hi> This was the
                    first effort of his satirical muse, and it appears to have succeeded amazingly;
                    for it had a prodigious sale, and the author was admitted to several personal
                    interviews with the king, who certainly was not a frequent reader of poetry.
                    After the peace of Ryswick, he published an argument to prove that a standing
                    army, with consent of parliament, is not inconsistent with a free government;
                    and afterwards, when the grand jury of Kent, in May 1701, presented a petition
                    to the Commons, in which the honourable house were unceremoniously desired to
                    mind the public business more and their private heats less, Dcfoe dictated a
                    remonstrance, signed <hi rend="italic">Legion,</hi> against the commitment of
                    Culpepper, Polhill, Hamilton, and Champneys, who had avowed this intrepid paper,
                    and he imitated the courage of those whose cause he espoused, by speaking plain
                    truths in bold language. At this time also he published a treatise on the
                    original power of the collective body of the people of England, which he
                    dedicated to King William, in a strain of very vigorous eloquence, and which,
                    whilst it vies with Mr Locke’s celebrated tract in force of reasoning, greatly
                    transcends it in the graces of style. Soon after this appeared his pamphlet
                    “against stockjobbing elections of parliament men,” which was a very seasonable
                    production, and fully sustained his reputation. FI is <hi rend="italic">Reasons
                    against a War with France,</hi> which he next published, is one of the finest
                    tracts in the English language, and replete throughout with eloquence and
                    wisdom. He declares that he is not adverse to a war with France, provided it be
                    undertaken on justifiable grounds; but he trusts that England will never become
                    so inconsiderable a nation as to make use of dishonest pretences to bring about
                    any of her designs; and he observes with striking truth, that he who desires
                    that we should end the war honourably, ought also to desire that we should begin
                    it fairly. King William could scarcely be supposed to relish a treatise which,
                    however able, was diametrically opposed to his favourite line of policy; but he
                    never evinced the smallest resentment against the author on this account; and
                    his death, which happened soon afterwards,, deprived Defoe of a patron and
                    protector whom he revered, and whose memory he could never patiently hear
                    abused. In the midst of the furious party contests which took place on the
                    accession of Queen Anne, he engaged in a controversy concerning the occasional
                    conformity of dissenters ∙, a subject which then led to frequent disputes
                    between the two houses of parliament, but which is now probably at rest forever.
                    “During the first fury of high-flying,” says Defoe, “I fell a sacrifice for
                    writing against the madness of that high spirit,and in the service of the
                    dissenters.” This alludes to <hi rend="italic">The Shortest Way with the
                    Dissenters,</hi> which he published in 1702, and which is a piece of exquisite
                    irony, although, in the excited state of men’s minds at that time, it was
                    pertinaciously interpreted <hi rend="italic">ad</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >pedem</hi><hi rend="italic">literce</hi> both by churchmen and dissenters, and
                    being voted a gross libel by the House of Commons, was ordered to be burned as
                    such by the hands of the common hangman.</p>
                <p>It has been well observed that Defoe had, during the previous twenty years of his
                    life, been unconsciously charging a mine which now blew both himself and his
                    family into the air. He had fought for the Duke of Monmouth; he had opposed King
                    James; he had vindicated the revolution; he had done justice to the character
                    and memory of King William; he had displeased Godolphin and offended
                    Marlborough, by objecting to the war in Flanders; he had defended the rights of
                    the collective body of the people; he had bantered Sir Edward Seymour and Sir
                    Christopher Musgrave, the Tory leaders of the House of Commons; and he had
                    ridiculed all the high-flyers in the kingdom ;—in a word, by following a course
                    of undeviating political rectitude, and by constantly directing the force of his
                    great talents against every species of public delinquency or folly, he had
                    incurred the hatred of all parties, and was at last obliged to seek shelter from
                    their overpowering and resistless vengeance. A reward of fifty pounds was
                    offered to any one who should discover his retreat; and although he immediately
                    published an explanation of the alleged libel, yet, being apprehended, he was
                    tried, convicted, and sentenced to the pillory, fine, and imprisonment. Thus was
                    Defoe ruined a second time; for, by this prosecution, he asserts that he lost
                    above L.3500. Whilst in Newgate he amused some of his dreary hours by writing a
                    <hi rend="italic">Hymn to the Pillory,</hi> in which generous sentiments are
                    intermingled with pointed satire, and the most cutting sarcasms against his
                    persecutors. Defoe continued, in the solitude of his captivity, to pursue his
                    literary labours, and to write on various subjects. He corrected for the press a
                    collection of his writings, beginning with <hi rend="italic">The True-born
                    Englishman,</hi> and ending with <hi rend="italic">The Shortest Way to Peace and
                    Union</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and to this was prefixed a print of the
                    author, with the too appropriate motto, <hi rend="italic">Laudatur et
                    alget.</hi> In his prison also he projected <hi rend="italic">The Review,</hi> a
                    periodical paper far superior to any thing of the kind that had yet appeared,
                    and which formed the prototype of the Tatlers, Spectators, and Guardians, and
                    contained many things which, in point of wit, elegance, and purity of diction,
                    would have done honour to Steele or to Addison. In 1704 he published <hi
                    rend="italic">The Storm,</hi> being a collection of the most remarkable
                    casualties which had occurred during the tempest of the 23d November 1703; a
                    production which displays higher attainments in science and literature than
                    Defoe had generally been supposed to possess, and which is altogether
                    exceedingly interesting.</p>
                <p>While the author lay in Newgate, with his family ruined, and his hopes of
                    deliverance crushed, a verbal message was brought him from Harley, Speaker of
                    the House of Commons, and afterwards Earl of Oxford, desiring to know what could
                    be done for him. In a factious age, a political intriguer like Harley doubtless
                    foresaw that a man of Defoe’s genius and ability might be rendered
                    serviceable<pb break="no" facs="nls:194755982" xml:id="kp-eb0707-5982-0670"/> to
                    the purposes of his ambition; whilst, on the other hand, the captive and ruined
                    author was fain to intimate a wish for his release from durance. But this was by
                    no means easily nor speedily accomplished. Harley became secretary of state in
                    April 1704; yet four months elapsed before his representations to the queen and
                    the treasurer Godolphin, in favour of Defoe, produced the desired effect. The
                    queen, however, inquired into the circumstances of the distressed author;
                    Godolphin sent a considerable sum to his wife, and a further sum to Defoe
                    himself, to enable him to pay his fine and the expense of his discharge; and at
                    length, in August 1704, he was released from Newgate. Defoe was exceedingly
                    grateful for this deliverance, and ever afterwards, amidst all the vicissitudes
                    of party and faction, remained sincerely attached to the queen and to Oxford. In
                    1705 lie published <hi rend="italic">The Consolidator,</hi> or Memoirs of sundry
                    Transactions from the World in the Moon, in which he makes the lunar politicians
                    discuss the policy of Charles the Twelfth in pursuing the Saxons and the Poles:
                    he also engaged in a controversy respecting a project then brought forward for
                    employing the poor; and he published a second volume of the “Writings of the
                    Author of the <hi rend="italic">True-born Englishman,"</hi> containing eighteen
                    pieces in prose and verse. The persecutions of party rendered this a year of
                    disquiet to Defoe. For, when his affairs had led him to the west of England, a
                    project was formed to send him perforce as a soldier to the army; but being a
                    freeholder of England, and a liveryman of London, he knew that these characters
                    could not be violated with impunity; and when the western justices had resolved
                    to apprehend him as a rogue and vagabond, they were deterred from doing so by
                    the courage with which he asserted his rights, and denounced the meditated
                    attackon his personal liberty. In his absence, too, real suits were commenced
                    against him for fictitious debts; but he manfully advertised, that whilst
                    genuine claims would be fairly satisfied, such as were groundless and vexatious
                    would be resisted to the last. All these circumstances were published in his <hi
                    rend="italic">Review.</hi></p>
                <p>Defoe commenced the year 1706 with <hi rend="italic">A Hymn to Peace,</hi>
                    occasioned by the two houses of parliament uniting in an address to the queen;
                    in May he published an “Essay at removing national prejudices against an Union
                    with Scotland ;” and in July appeared his <hi rend="italic">Jure Oivino,</hi> in
                    which he attacked the doctrines of passive obedience and divine right,
                    respecting which the world then seemed to be running stark mad, from the sheer
                    fanaticism of servility. About this time, Godolphin, who knew how to
                    discriminate men, resolved to employ Defoe on a mission of importance; and he
                    was accordingly sent to Scotland, where his knowledge of commerce and revenue,
                    his powers of insinuation, and the aptitude of his pen, which was that of a
                    ready writer, proved of no small utility in promoting the great measure of the
                    union. He arrived in Edinburgh in October 1706; be attended the committees of
                    parliament, which he furnished with calculations on the subject of trade and
                    taxes; he endeavoured to confute all that was published against the project of
                    the union; and, though exposed to considerable danger, he escaped the vengeance
                    of the populace, by whom he was continually watched, and sometimes insulted. In
                    the midst of this agitating scene of business and tumult, he collected those
                    documents, which he afterwards published for the instruction of posterity,
                    respecting one of the most critical and important transactions in our whole
                    national annals. Towards the close of this year he published <hi rend="italic"
                    >Caledonia,</hi> a poem in honour of the Scottish nation; and soon after the act
                    of union had been passed by the parliament of Scotland, he returned to London.
                    How he was rewarded by the ministers for the important services he performed on
                    this difficult occasion, has not been ascertained; but Mr Chalmers is of opinion
                    that a pension was settled on him. He published his <hi rend="italic">History of
                    the Union</hi> in 1709; but it attracted little notice on its first appearance,
                    though it' was republished in 1712, and again in 1786, when the project of a
                    union with Ireland had become a topic of frequent discussion. In the year 1709
                    also appeared his <hi rend="italic">History of Addresses,</hi> which, in 1711,
                    was followed by a second volume, intended to abate the public ferment occasioned
                    partly by the mad harangues of Sacheverel, and still more by the incredible
                    folly which raised them into consequence by the parliamentary censure of their
                    author.</p>
                <p>Defoe now lived at Newington in comfortable circumstances, and employed himself
                    chiefly in writing the <hi rend="italic">Review,</hi> which, however, he at
                    length relinquished in order to commence <hi rend="italic">A General History of
                    Trade;</hi> but this last production, although it exhibits all the ingenuity and
                    strength of Defoe, extended only to two numbers; the author having been silenced
                    by noise, obloquy, and insult, and forced to withdraw for a time to the borders
                    of Lancashire. Here, observing the insolence of the Jacobite party, and
                    incapable of remaining an indolent or passive spectator of events, he published
                    several pamphlets, with ironical titles, which were much approved by the friends
                    of the Protestant succession, and diligently dispersed throughout the country;
                    yet, for writing these seasonable tracts, Defoe was arrested, held to bail in
                    the enormous sum of L.800, and ultimately committed to Newgate in Easter term of
                    1713. But on making a proper submission, he was soon released, and the Earl of
                    Oxford being still in power, interceded to procure him the queen’s pardon. Still
                    darker days were, however, at hand. “No sooner was the queen dead,” says he,
                    “but the rage of men increased upon me to that degree, that their threats were
                    such as I am unable to express. Though I have written nothing since the queen’s
                    death, yet a great many things are called by my name, and I bear the answerers’
                    insults. I have not seen or spoken with the Earl of Oxford since the king’s
                    landing but once; yet he bears the reproach of my writing for him, and I the
                    rage of men for doing it.” Stunned by factious clamour, and overborne though not
                    silenced by unmerited obloquy, Defoe appears to have lost his original
                    appointment on the final expulsion from power of the Earl of Oxford; and instead
                    of meeting with any reward for his zealous services in support of the Protestant
                    succession, he was, on the accession of George I. discountenanced even by those
                    who had derived most benefit from his active exertions. This cruel treatment
                    preyed on his mind, and brought him to the very verge of the grave. In 1715 he
                    published an <hi rend="italic">Appeal to Honour and Justice,</hi> containing an
                    account of his conduct in public affairs; and in stating his motives for doing
                    so, he affecting-ly says, “By the limits of mortality, and the infirmities of a
                    life of sorrow and fatigue, I have reason to think that I am very near to the
                    great ocean of eternity, and the time may not be long ere I embark on the last
                    voyage; wherefore I think I should make even accounts with the world before I
                    go, that no slanders may lie against my heirs, to disturb them in the peaceable
                    possession of their father’s inheritance, his character.” But before he had
                    finished his “appeal” he was struck with apoplexy; and as he languished for more
                    than six weeks in a state which held out but little prospect of recovery, his
                    friends judged it proper not to delay the publication any longer. The treatment
                    which he here complains of was undoubtedly the cause of this calamity: when he
                    reflected on what he had done and suffered, his heart yielded to despair, and he
                    sunk under the agony of his own desponding feelings. But this shock, severe as
                    it proved, was not altogether without its benefit on the mind of Defoe, which it
                    served to wean from politics, and to estrange from pursuits productive of
                    nothing but disappointment and sorrow. The death of <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:194755995" xml:id="kp-eb0707-5995-0671"/>Queen Anne, and the accession
                    of George the First, convinced him of the vanity of party-writing; and from this
                    period he appears to have studied, not how to mend the state, but how to improve
                    the human heart and to regulate the practice of daily life. The only other
                    production of Defoe’s which appeared in 1715, was <hi rend="italic">The Family
                    Instructor,</hi> in three parts; but <hi rend="italic">Religious Courtship,</hi>
                    which may be considered as the third volume, was not published until 1722.</p>
                <p>We have now reached that period in the life of Defoe when he gave to the world
                    the most remarkable, and perhaps the most lasting, of all his works; we mean the
                    <hi rend="italic">Life and surprising Adventures of Robinson Crusoe,</hi> which
                    appeared in 1719. This extraordinary production met with the most favourable
                    reception, and immediately became so popular, that Taylor, who purchased the
                    manuscript after every other bookseller had refused it, is said to have gained a
                    thousand pounds by the transaction. Seldom, indeed, has any immediate decision
                    of the public respecting a literary performance been so fully ratified by
                    posterity. At the distance of more than a century it has lost none of its
                    original attraction. There is an air of reality and truth about it which belongs
                    to no other work of fiction; we cannot indeed persuade ourselves that it is the
                    creation of fancy, nor divest ourselves of the conviction, which every
                    circumstance conspires to rivet on the mind, that we are perusing real
                    adventures, and conversing with actual personages. Hence, whilst it carries
                    captive the affections of childhood, it fixes the admiration of mature years; it
                    is the book of all countries, and of every age and class; it delights the
                    illiterate, and amuses as well as instructs persons of the most cultivated
                    minds; and it speaks in the resistless language of nature to all hearts. It also
                    contains, if not a treatise, at least a practical exemplification of a system of
                    natural education, detailed with matchless truth and simplicity. “Puisqu’il nous
                    faut absolument des livres,” says Rousseau in his <hi rend="italic">Emile,</hi>
                    “il en existe un qui fournit, à mon gré, le plus heureux traite d’éducation
                    naturelle. Ce livre sera le premier que lira mon Emile; seul il composera
                    long-temps toute sa bibliothèque, et il y tiendra toujours une place distinguée.
                    Il sera le texte auquel tous nos entretiens sur les sciences naturelles ne
                    serviront que de commentaires. Il servira d’épreuve durant nos progrès, à l’état
                    de notre jugement; et tant que notre goût ne sera pas gâté, sa lecture nous
                    plaira toujours. Quel est dont ce merveilleux livre? Est-ce Aristote? Est-ce
                    Platon? Non, c’est <hi rend="italic">Robinson</hi><hi rend="italic">Crusoe!</hi>
                    In a word, had all Defoe’s other writings perished, the history of the author of
                    this extraordinary production would still have been an object of literary
                    curiosity. As to the story that the author had surreptitiously obtained and
                    unceremoniously appropriated the papers of Alexander Selkirk, a Scottish
                    mariner, who, having suffered shipwreck, had lived for three or four years on
                    the island of Juan Fernandez, it is scarcely deserving of serious notice, and is
                    certainly as unworthy of reputation as the fable published by Mr James Stanier
                    Clarke, that the first volume of <hi rend="italic">Robinson Crusoe</hi> was
                    written by the Earl of Oxford during his imprisonment in the Tower of London.
                    Calumnies of this sort always track the footsteps of genius; and dull malignity,
                    where it dares not condemn a work, often seeks to tarnish the fame of its
                    author, by trying to fasten on him a charge of plagiarism. In the present case,
                    all that is needful to repel the accusation has been amply supplied by Chalmers
                    and Wilson, who have proved that Selkirk had in truth no papers to lose, and,
                    moreover, shown that the internal evidence is decidedly in favour of the entire
                    originality of Defoe’s inimitable fiction. How, indeed, could the rude journal
                    of a rough sailor ever be supposed to have entered into the composition of such
                    a finished mas terpiece? or even allowing that some hints had been derived from
                    such a source, how can that be held as in any degree detracting from the genius
                    of him who bade these dry bones live?</p>
                <p>The success of <hi rend="italic">Robinson Crusoe</hi> induced Defoe to publish,
                    in 1720, <hi rend="italic">The Life arid Piracies of Captain Singleton,</hi> a
                    romance of the same description, but much inferior in all respects. In 1725, he
                    brought out another fictitious narrative, entitled <hi rend="italic">A New
                    Voyage round the World by a Course never sailed before,</hi> a work which
                    displays uncommon skill, and is highly interesting throughout. The <hi
                    rend="italic">History of Duncan Campbell,</hi> who was born deaf and dumb, and
                    who taught others in the same unfortunate situation with himself, had appeared
                    in 1720; and the <hi rend="italic">Fortunes and Misfortunes of Moll
                    Flanders,</hi> the morality of which cannot be commended, followed in 1721, when
                    he also published the <hi rend="italic">Life of Colonel</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Jaque,</hi> a work of a similar tendency. <hi rend="italic">The Adventures of
                    Roxana,</hi> which appeared in 1724, is likewise a production by which few will
                    be made wiser, and none better. But the <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of a
                    Cavalier</hi> is a work of a very different description. This romance is so like
                    truth that it has been mistaken for real history; and in fact it contains the
                    best account extant of the civil wars, the narrative being drawn up with great
                    simplicity, and enlivened with such just and natural reflections as at once to
                    instruct the ignorant and entertain the instructed. The <hi rend="italic">Family
                    Instructor</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Religious Courtship</hi> have been already
                    noticed. But there are other performances of his possessing not inferior merit.
                    In 1722, he published <hi rend="italic">A Journal of the Plague,</hi> which,
                    like his <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of a Cavalier,</hi> is, in its frame-work, a
                    pure fiction; <hi rend="italic">The great Laic of Subordination</hi> appeared in
                    1724; the <hi rend="italic">Political History of the Devil,</hi> and a <hi
                    rend="italic">System of Magic,</hi> which may be regarded as a supplement
                    thereto, came out in 1726; and the <hi rend="italic">Treatise on the Use and
                    Abuse of the Marriage-bed,</hi> an excellent book, with an absurd title, was
                    given to the world in 1727. He also published a <hi rend="italic">Tour</hi>
                    through England in 1724 and 1725, and one through Scotland in 1727. But the
                    reader must not be misled by this title; for Defoe was one of those travellers
                    who seldom quit the banks of the Thames. His last works were the <hi
                    rend="italic">Complete English Tradesman,</hi> published in 1727, and a <hi
                    rend="italic">Plan of the English Commerce,</hi> which appeared in 1728. In
                    these treatises are many directions for the conduct of business, and many
                    lessons of prudence and economy, which cannot be too frequently and earnestly
                    inculcated.</p>
                <p>But the glass of the indefatigable Defoe was now nearly run. After a laborious
                    and checkered life, he died in April 1731, in the parish of St. Giles,
                    Cripplegate, leaving a widow, who did not long survive him, and six sons and
                    daughters. From several circumstances, it is more than probable that he died
                    insolvent; and it is at least certain that he left no other inheritance to his
                    children but his good name and high literary reputation. Defoe was a man of
                    strong natural parts and of clear good sense; ingenious and lively in
                    conversation; bold and enterprising in spirit, but scantily gifted with
                    prudence; and withal possessed of good nature and of real honesty. As a writer
                    he is distinguished for the fertility of his invention, the vivid distinctness
                    of his conceptions, the transparent perspicuity of his style, the keenness of
                    his wit, the justness and originality of his reflections, and the inimitable
                    ease and simplicity which more or less characterize all his performances. But
                    though his merits both as a man and as a writer were undoubtedly great, yet few
                    men have experienced more unjust treatment at the hands of their contemporaries;
                    and, notwithstanding the general integrity of his conduct, he was repeatedly
                    represented as an unprincipled writer, who had no view but to his own advantage,
                    and who would employ his pen for any party which <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:194756008" xml:id="kp-eb0707-6008-0672"/>chose to hire his services.
                    These charges, however, are refuted by the whole tenor of his life; and, indeed,
                    they are in all probability the offspring of political rancour, which, in fact,
                    no man ever did more to provoke. His readiness and power as a political writer,
                    and, above all, the unsparing use which he made of ridicule and sarcasm, weapons
                    which in his hands were peculiarly formidable, must have raised him up a host of
                    enemies; and those who might feel themselves unequal to contend with the gifted
                    writer, could at least find no difficulty in traducing the man. It has often
                    struck us as surprising that his political works, on which he employed the very
                    best of his days and his talents, should, comparatively speaking, be so little
                    known. They constitute a mine which none can explore without being enriched with
                    much that is precious in wisdom, impressive in eloquence, and striking in truth.
                    But still his fame must principally rest upon those works which were entirely
                    the offspring of imagination; and amongst these, and indeed all others of the
                    kind, whether we regard the felicity of the design, the truth of the incidents,
                    the variety and minute discrimination of the details, the natural justness of
                    the sentiments, or the beautiful simplicity of the whole narrative, <hi
                    rend="italic">Robinson Crusoe</hi> must ever occupy the first place. Defoe,
                    indeed, was an essentially original writer; and hence all his productions
                    possess a raciness and a freshness which add incalculably to their attraction.
                    But if he had any model at all, it was Bunyan, an author whom he must have read
                    in his youth, and from whose works he probably imbibed that taste for simplicity
                    in writing for which lie was throughout distinguished; and what renders this
                    still more certain is, that in the second volume of <hi rend="italic">Robinson
                    Crusoe</hi> may be discovered obvious traces of the religious principles so
                    beautifully unfolded in Bunyan’s admirable allegory. It must be admitted,
                    however, that Defoe borrowed from the <hi rend="italic">Pilgrims Progress</hi>
                    little else than the love of natural simplicity; and that in ħll which
                    essentially distinguishes him as a writer, he is remarkable for nothing so much
                    as for inexhaustible fertility, allied to extraordinary freshness and
                    originality. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
