<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0913-0861-0828-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">KÁLIDÁSA (9th edition, volume 13, page 828)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx0636c">Matter</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49g5gg1n">Clouds</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n861/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">KÁLIDÁSA</label> is the most illustrious name among the
                    writers of the second epoch of Sanskrit literature, which, as contrasted with
                    the age of the Vedic hymns, may be characterized as the period of artificial
                    poetry. Owing to the utter absence of the historical sense in the Hindu race, it
                    is impossible to fix with chronological exactness the lifetime of either
                    Kâlidâsa or any other Sanskrit author. Native tradition places him in the 1st
                    century B.c.; but the evidence on which this belief rests has been shown to be
                    wholly worthless. The works of the poet have been found to contain no allusions
                    by which their date can be directly determined; yet the extremely corrupt form
                    of the Prâkrit or popular dialects spoken by the women and the subordinate
                    characters in his plays, as compared with the Prâkrit in inscriptions of
                    ascertained age, has led the chief authorities, Weber and Lassen, to agree in
                    fixing on the 3d century of our era as the approximate period to which the
                    writings of Kâlidâsa should be referred.</p>
                <p>The richness of his creative fancy, his delicacy of senti ment, and his keen
                    appreciation of the beauties of nature, combined with remarkable powers of
                    description, which are conspicuous throughout his works, place Kâlidâsa in the
                    first rank of Oriental poets. The effect, however, of his productions as a whole
                    is greatly marred by extreme artificiality of diction, which, though to a less
                    extent than in other Hindu poets, not unfrequently takes the form of puerile
                    conceits, and plays on words, the matter being treated merely as a means for
                    displaying dexterity in the manipulation of the language. In this respect his
                    writings contrast very unfavourably with the more genuine poetry of the Vedas.
                    Though a true poet, he is wanting in that artistic sense of proportion so
                    characteristic of the Greek mind, which exactly adjusts the parts to the whole,
                    and combines form and matter into an inseparable poetic unity. Kâlidâsa’s fame
                    rests chiefly on his dramas, but he is also distinguished as an epic and a lyric
                    poet.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n862/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0913-0862-0829"/>
                <p>He wrote three plays, the plots of which all bear a general resemblance to each
                    other, inasmuch as they consist of love intrigues, which, after numerous and
                    seemingly insurmountable impediments of a similar nature, are ultimately brought
                    to a successful conclusion.</p>
                <p>Of these, <hi rend="italic">Çakuntalâ</hi> is that which has always justly
                    enjoyed the greatest fame and popularity. The unqualified praise bestowed upon
                    it by Goethe sufficiently guarantees its poetic merit. There are two recensions
                    of the text in India, the Bengali and the Devanâgari, the latter being generally
                    considered older and purer. <hi rend="italic">Çakuntalà</hi> was first
                    translated into English by Sir William Jones (Calcutta, 1789), who used the
                    Bengali recension. It was soon after translated into German by G. Forster
                    (1791), and by Herder in 1803. An edition of the Sanskrit original, with French
                    translation, was published by Chézy at Paris in 1830. This formed the basis of a
                    translation by Hirzel (Zurich, 1830). Another edition of the Bengali recension
                    was published by Prema Chandra (Calcutta, 1860) for the use of European
                    students. The Devanâgari recension was first edited by Bohtlingk (Bonn, 1842),
                    with a German translation. On this were based the successive German translations
                    of Meyer (Tübingen, 1851) and Lobedanz (2d ed., Leipsic, 1861). The same
                    recension has been edited by Dr C. Burkhard with a Sanskrit-Latin vocabulary and
                    short Prakrit grammar (Breslau, 1872), and by Professor Monier Williams (Oxford,
                    2d ed., 1872). Another edition was published at Bombay in 1861.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Vikramorvaçi,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Urvaçl</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">won by Valour,</hi> abounds with fine lyrical passages, and is of
                    all Indian dramas second only to <hi rend="italic">Çakuntalà</hi> in poetic
                    beauty. It was edited by Lenz (Bonn, 1833) and translated into German by Hofer
                    (Berlin, 1837), by Hirzel (1838), and by Lobedanz (Leipsic, 1861). The best
                    edition is by Bollensen (Petersburg, 1845). There is also an English edition by
                    Monier Williams, a metrical and prose version by the late Professor H. H.
                    Wilson, and a literal prose translation by Professor E. B. Cowell (1851).</p>
                <p>The third play, entitled <hi rend="italic">Mdlavikdgnimiira,</hi> has
                    considerable poetical and dramatic merit, but is confessedly inferior to the
                    other two. It possesses the advantage, however, that its hero Agnimitra and its
                    heroine Mâlavikâ are more ordinary and human characters than those of the other
                    plays. It was edited by Dr Tullberg at Bonn, 1840, and more correctly by Shankar
                    P. Pandit, with English notes, in 1869, and ably translated into German by
                    Professor Weber in 1856.</p>
                <p>Two epic poems are also attributed to Kalidasa. The longer of these is entitled
                    <hi rend="italic">Raghuvança,</hi> the subject of which is the same as that of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Rdmdyana,</hi> viz., the history of Hama, but beginning
                    with a long account of his ancestors, the ancient rulers of Ayodhya (edited by
                    Stenzler, London, 1832). The other epic is the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Kumd-rasambhaνa,</hi> the theme of which is the birth of Kumâra, otherwise
                    called Kârttikeya or Skanda, god of war (edited by Stenzler, London, 1838, and
                    by the Rev. K. Μ. Banerjea, 3d ed., Calcutta, 1872). Though containing many fine
                    passages, it is tame as a whole.</p>
                <p>His lyrical poems are the <hi rend="italic">McghadMa</hi> and the <hi
                    rend="italic">Rilasamhàra.</hi> The <hi rend="italic">MeghadMa,</hi> or the
                    Cloud-Messenger, describes the complaint of an exiled lover, and the message he
                    sends to his wife by a cloud. It is full of deep feeling, and abounds with fine
                    descriptions of the beauties of nature. It was edited with free English
                    translation by H. H. Wilson (Calcutta, 1813), and by Gildemeister (Bonn, 1841);
                    a German adaptation by Μ. Müller appeared at Königsberg (1847), and one by
                    Schmitz at Bielefeld (1859). It was edited by Johnson, with vocabulary and
                    Wilson’s metrical translation (London, 1867). The <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ritusamhàra,</hi> or Collection of the Seasons, is a short poem, of less
                    importance, on the six seasons of the year. There is an edition by Bohlen, with
                    prose Latin and metrical German translation (Leipsic, 1840).</p>
                <p>Another poem, entitled the <hi rend="italic">Nalodaya,</hi> or Rise of Nala,
                    edited by Benary (Berlin, 1830) and by Yates (Calcutta, 1844), which is a
                    treatment of the story of Nala and Damayanti, but describes especially the
                    restoration of Nala to prosperity and power, has been ascribed to the celebrated
                    Kalidasa, but was probably written by another poet of the same name. It is full
                    of most absurd verbal conceits and metrical extravagances.</p>
                <p>So many poems, partly of a very different stamp, are attributed to Kalidasa that
                    it is scarcely possible to avoid the necessity of assuming the existence of more
                    authors than one of that name. It is by no means improbable that there were
                    three poets thus named; indeed modern native astronomers are so convinced of the
                    existence of a triad of authors of this name that they apply the term Kalidasa
                    to designate the number three. (A. A. Μ.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
