<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0913-0847-0814-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">KABYLES, or more correctly Kabâil (9th edition, volume
                    13, page 814)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49882n4f">Berbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4nk3693f">Iberians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sf2mc0b">Aryans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86v83">Race</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fr3m">Racing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812576">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:830652">Berbers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1086604">Racing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1086436">Race</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205459">Algeria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n847/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">KABYLES, or more correctly <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Kabâil</hi></label>, a number of tribes in the Algerian region of northern
                    Africa, of special interest to the politician from the peculiarity of their
                    institutions and from the part they will probably play in the development of the
                    French colony, and to the ethnologist as the best known branch of the great
                    Berber race. In 1864 it was estimated that they amounted to 2,200,000. The
                    country which they inhabit is usually regarded as consisting of two
                    divisions—Great Kabylia and Lesser Kabylia—the former being also known as the
                    Kabylia of the Jurjura (also called Adrar Budfel, “Mountain of Snow”). It is
                    admitted on all hands that the Berbers form the main aboriginal element in the
                    population of northern Africa, that at one time or other they have occupied the
                    whole tract of country from Egypt in the east to the Canary Islands in the west,
                    and that they are still represented not only by the Tuâreg (Amashir, &amp;c.),
                    who retain their native speech, but by many tribes that have become altogether
                    Arab in language. In regard to their real ethnic relations, however, there has
                    been much discussion and theory: Kaltbrunner includes the Berbers in the
                    Mediterranean race in which Haeckel places the Semites, Iberians, &amp;c. M. G.
                    Olivier<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>“Recherches sur
                    l’origine des Berbères,” <hi rend="italic">Bull, de</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >ΐ</hi><hi rend="italic">Acad. d'Hippone,</hi> 1867, 1868.</p></note> recognizes
                    the Berbers as Aryans, and Faidherbe regards them as the indigenous Libyans
                    mingled with a fair-skinned people of European origin; while Pruner Bey and
                    Duveyrier maintain the close relation of the Berbers with the ancient Egyptians,
                    and consider them as forming together the white African race.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See Henri Duveyrier, “Les
                    Progrès de la géographie en Algérie, 1868-71,” <hi rend="italic">Bull. de la
                    Soc. Khédiviale de Géogr.,</hi> Cairo, 1876.</p></note> Be this as it may, the
                    Kabyles are a Berber stock, and more particularly correspond to that part of the
                    race which was known to the Romans as Numidians. Physically they do not present
                    any very prominent contrast to the Arabs of Algeria. Both Kabyle and Arab are
                    white at birth, but rapidly grow brown through exposure to air and sunshine.
                    Both have in’ general brown eyes and wavy hair of coarse quality, varying from
                    dark brown to jet black. In stature there is perhaps a little difference in
                    favour of the Kabyle, and he appears also to have a stouter trunk and bulkier
                    muscles. Both are clearly dolichocephalic. Among the Kabyles, it is worthy of
                    particular notice, there exists a varying proportion of individuals with fair
                    skins, ruddy complexions, and blue or grey eyes. As to the ethnic origin of this
                    peculiar element many conjectures have been hazarded,— one theorist seeing in
                    them the Vandals, another the Gallic mercenaries of Rome, another an aboriginal
                    fair-skinned race, another the dolmen-building people from Europe. In the whole
                    domain of life and character the contrasts between Arab and Kabyle are of the
                    most radical and striking kind. The Kabyle lives in a house of stone or clay,
                    forming part of a fixed village or hamlet; the Arab’s tent is moved from place
                    to place. The Kabyle enjoys the individual proprietorship of his garden and his
                    orchards; with the Arab the ownership of the soil is an attribute of the tribe.
                    While cereals alone are cultivated by the Arab, the Kabyle has his fig trees,
                    olives, and vines, vegetables and tobacco. Active, energetic, and enterprising,
                    the Kabyle is to be found far from home—as a soldier in the French army, as a
                    workman in the towns, as a field labourer, or as a pedler or trader earning by
                    steady effort the means of purchasing his bit of ground in his native village.
                    Nor, however insignificant they may appear when measured by a high European
                    standard, are the native industries to be despised. Not only do they comprise
                    the making of lime, tiles, woodwork for the houses, domestic utensils, and
                    agricultural implements, but also the weaving and dyeing of several kinds of
                    cloth, the tanning and dressing of leather, and the manufacture of oil and soap.
                    Without the assistance of the wheel, the women turn out a variety of earthenware
                    articles; before it became a sort of proscribed industry the production of
                    gunpowder was <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n848/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0913-0848-0815"/> regularly carried on; the native jewellers make
                    excellent ornaments in silver, coral, and enamel; in some places wood carving
                    has been brought to considerable perfection; and native artists know how to
                    engrave on metal both by etching and the burin. Like the Arabs of Algeria, the
                    Kabyles are Mahometans of the Sunnite branch and the Malekite rite, looking to
                    Morpcco as the nearer centre of their religion; but, whereas the Arabs are
                    fatalistic and superstitious, the Kabyles show a more independent and
                    rationalistic turn of mind. In spite of the Koran and its administrators the
                    Kabyles are essentially democratic. In the words of Renan,<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>“La société berbère,” <hi rend="italic">Revue
                    des Deux Mondes,</hi> 1873.</p></note> “the people is everything and suffices
                    for everything; government, police, administration of justice, cost nothing to
                    the community. It is the ideal of democracy, the direct government of the people
                    by the people.” The political unit is the village or commune <hi rend="italic">;
                    so</hi> many villages constitute a fraction, so many fractions a tribe; and the
                    tribes again are combined in the Kabaïla or confederation. The governing
                    authority in the commune is the Jemâ'a or general gathering of the citizens,—
                    every man old enough to keep the fast of the Ramadhan having a right to take
                    part in its proceedings. Its chief executive officer, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >amin,</hi> is chosen by the goodwill of his fellows, receives no remuneration,
                    and withdraws from his functions as soon as he loses the confidence of the
                    electorate. Some of the Kabyles retain their vernacular speech, while others
                    have more or less completely adopted Arabic. The best known dialect is that of
                    the Igaouaouen, or Zouaoua,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>The Arabic Zouaoua (to use the French transliteration) has given rise to the
                    well-known “Zouaves” of the French army.</p></note> who, at least from the time
                    of Ibn Khaldoun, have been settled on the northern side of the Juιjura; it is
                    the principal basis of Hanoteau’s <hi rend="italic">Essai de Grammaire
                    Kabyle</hi> (Paris, 1858). Unlike their southern brethren, the Kabyles have no
                    alphabet, and their literature is still in the stage of oral transmission for
                    the most part by professional reciters. Hanoteau’s <hi rend="italic">Poésies
                    populaires de la Kabylie du Jurjura</hi> (Paris, 1867) gives the text and
                    translation of a considerable number of historical pieces, proverbial couplets
                    and quatrains, dancing songs, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>The best résumé of ascertained facts in regard to the Kabyles is the <hi
                    rend="italic">Instructions sur</hi><hi rend="italic">V</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Anthropologie de l’Algérie,</hi> by General Faidherbe and Dr Paul Topinard,
                    Paris, 1874. See also Daumas, <hi rend="italic">Le Sahara Algérien,</hi> Paris,
                    1845; De Slane’s translation of Ibn Khaldoun’s <hi rend="italic">Hist,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">des Berbères,</hi> Algiers, 1852; Aucapitaine, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Les Kabyles et la Colon, de l'Algérie,</hi> Paris, 1864, and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Les Béni M’zab,</hi> 1868; Hanoteau and Letourneaux, <hi rend="italic">La
                    Kabylie et les Coutumes Kabyles,</hi> Paris, 1873; a paper by Charmetant, the
                    head of the Roman Catholic mission, in <hi rend="italic">Jahrbücher der
                    Verbreitung des Glaubens,</hi> 1874; Dugas, <hi rend="italic">La</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Kabylie·</hi><hi rend="italic">et le peuple Kabyle,</hi> Paris,
                    1878; Récoux, <hi rend="italic">La démographie de l'Algérie,</hi> Paris,
                    1880.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
