<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0596-0535-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BURGUNDY (9th edition, volume 4, page 535)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1211813">Luxembourg</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:836795">Bosons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1086604">Racing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1086436">Race</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888134">Daughters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:841747">Burgundians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1140558">Swiss</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86v83">Race</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fr3m">Racing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rb6w453">Counting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qn6g">Crowns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50fz6v">Carlovingians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3m81r">Swiss</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47s7hr9r">Alemanni</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r392">Baldness</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n596/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BURGUNDY</label> (French, <hi rend="italic">Bourgogne}</hi>
                    has at various periods been the name of different political and geographical
                    areas. The Burgundians <hi rend="italic">(Burgundi</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >Burgundiones}</hi> seem to have been a people of German race, who are first
                    found settled between the Oder and the Vistula. At an early period they came
                    into conflict with the Alemanni, whom they defeated; and in the beginning of the
                    5th century they crossed into Roman Gaul under their leader Gundicar. The Romans
                    not only permitted them to settle within the limits of the empire, but caused
                    the inhabitants of the district to yield up to them one-half of their houses,
                    two-thirds of the cultivated land, and a third of their slaves. The new-comers
                    thus founded, in the country between the Aar and the Rhone, what is usually
                    known as the first kingdom of Burgundy, which lasted till 534, when it was
                    incorporated in the Frankish empire. Gundicar was succeeded in 436 by Gunderic,
                    who somewhat extended his kingdom. In 470 it was parcelled out among his four
                    sons—Chilperic, Gundibald,. Godegisil, and Gondemar, who had their headquarters
                    respectively at Geneva, Besançon, Lyons, and Vienne; but it was ultimately
                    reunited in the hands of Gundibald, who is famous for his patronage of the
                    Catholic ecclesiastics and his codification of the Burgundian law, which is
                    consequently known as <hi rend="italic">Lex Gundibaldia,</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">Loi Gombette.</hi> Gundibald was succeeded in 516 by his son
                    Sigismund, who in turn gave place to Gundimar, the last of the dynasty. On the
                    disintegration of the Carlovingian empire, Boson, the husband of Ermengarde, the
                    daughter of the Emperor Louis IL, founded the kingdom of Cisjuran or Lower
                    Burgundy, but in 882 he recognized the overlordship of Charles the Stout. His
                    territory included what was afterwards known as Franche Comté, a part of the
                    later province of Burgundy, Dauphiné, Provence, and part of Languedoc and Savoy.
                    In 888 Boson’s example was followed by Rudolph, a Swiss count of Guelf race,
                    who, supported by a large body of civil and ecclesiastical dignitaries called
                    together by him at St Moritz in Valais, established a kingdom known as
                    Transjuran or Upper Burgundy, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n597/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0597-0536"/> His son, Rudolph, bartered his rights to the
                    Italian crown for the Cisjuran kingdom, and thus united both Burgundies into
                    what is frequently called the kingdom of Arles, which after various vicissitudes
                    was finally united to the German empire by Conrad II. in 1033.</p>
                <p>On the foundation of the Lower Burgundian kingdom by Boson, his brother Richard
                    remained faithful to Charles the Bald of France, and was invested with the duchy
                    of Burgundy, which had been held by various members of the Carlovingian family.
                    King Robert II., however, took possession of it, and bestowed it in 1015 on his
                    son, afterwards Henry I. On the accession of the latter to the throne of France,
                    he gave the duchy to his brother Robert, with whose descendants it continued for
                    a considerable period. In 1361 that elder line of dukes expired, and the duchy
                    was seized by king John, and in 1363 presented by him to his son Philip the Bold
                    as a reward for his bravery at the battle of Poitiers. Thus commenced that
                    famous line of dukes which played so great a part in the history of France
                    during the 14th and 15th centuries, and by the splendour of its achievements and
                    the magnificence of its patronage rivalled the greatest dynasties of the time.
                    Philip’s marriage with Margaret of Flanders brought him the countships of
                    Burgundy (Franche Comté), Flanders, Artois, Réthel, and Nevers; and at a later
                    period he purchased the countship of Charolais from the count of Armagnac. He
                    was succeeded in 1404 by John the Fearless <hi rend="italic">{Jean sans
                    Peur),</hi> who was assassinated at the Bridge of Montereau in 1419, and left
                    the duchy to his son Philip the Good. This duke survived till 1467, and during
                    that time had greatly extended his territory. By very questionable proceedings
                    he obtained possession of Hainault and Holland. Namur was purchased in 1429; and
                    in the following year Brabant and Limburg also fell into his grasp. In 1435
                    there were further yielded to him, by treaty with France, Macon, Auxerre,
                    Bar-sur-Seine, and various other towns in that district. His son, Charles the
                    Bold, followed in the same course of territorial aggrandizement, and his
                    ambitious projects gradually extended, till lie began to aim at the founding of
                    a great Gallo-Belgian kingdom; but his splendid plans came to an untimely end
                    with his own death at the battle of Nancy in 1477, when he was trying to wipe
                    off the disgrace inflicted on his arms by the Swiss at Morat. His daughter and
                    heiress, Mary, married the Archduke Maximilian, son of Frederick III. J and with
                    the exception of the duchy of Burgundy proper, which remained a fief of the
                    French crown, brought with her all the vast inheritance of her father. In 1512
                    Maximilian incorporated the territory with the German empire under the title of
                    the circle of Burgundy. It was gradually diminished by the encroachments of
                    France, and by the liberation of the Netherlands, so that at the Revolution it
                    only consisted of Brabant, Limburg, Luxembourg, and parts of Flanders, Hainault,
                    Namur, and Guelders.</p>
                <p>The duchy meanwhile had been raised with some additions to the rank of a
                    province, and formed a military governorship. It was bounded on the N. by
                    Champagne, E. by Franche Comté and Bresse, S. by Lyonnais and Dauphiné, and W.
                    by Bourbonnais and Nivernais. It was divided into eight districts—Auxerrais, the
                    country of the Mountain, Auxais, Dijonnais, Autunais, Châlonnais, Charolais, and
                    Méconnais. It possessed a separate assembly of states general, which met every
                    three years at Dijon, the capital, under the presidency most frequently of the
                    governor of the province. The bishop of Autun was at the head of the clergy; the
                    nobility and gentry had a leader of their own election; and the corresponding
                    place in the third estate belonged to the mayor of Dijon.</p>
                <p>See Derichsweiler’s <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Burgundcn,</hi> 1863; Barante’s <hi rend="italic">Histoire</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">des dues de Bourgogne,</hi> 10 vols. 1824; and De Laborde’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Les dues de Bourgogne,</hi> 1871.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
