<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0436-0389-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BROWNE, Sir Thomas (9th edition, volume 4, page
                    389)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:915038">Errors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:915026">Error</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1043068">Occasionalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1162994">Urns</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:937895">Gardens</term>
                    <term ref="fast:937852">Gardening</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bh84">Gardens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xs5jg6k">Gardening</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20m3b">Moralities</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40k55d">Morals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w922">Writers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m6299t">Urns</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n436/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BROWNE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Thomas</hi></label>, a
                    distinguished English writer, was born in London on the 19th October, 1605. He
                    was educated at Winchester School, and afterwards at Broadgate Hall (Pembroke
                    College), Oxford, where he graduated B.A. in January 1626. He took the further
                    degree of Μ. A. in 1629, studied medicine, and practised for some time in
                    Oxfordshire. Between 1630 and 1633 he left England, travelled through Ireland,
                    France, and Italy, and on his way home received the degree of M.D. at the
                    university of Leyden. He returned to London in 1634, and two years later, after
                    a short residence in Yorkshire, settled in practice at Norwich. In 1642 a copy
                    of his <hi rend="italic">Religio</hi><hi rend="italic">Medici</hi> was printed
                    from one of his MSS. without his knowledge, and he was compelled to put forth a
                    correct edition of the work, which appears to have been composed as early as
                    1634. Its success was very great, and the author at once became celebrated as a
                    man of letters. In 1646 appeared his <hi rend="italic">Pseudodoxia</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Epidemica,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Enquiries into Vulgar and
                    Common Errors,</hi> which added to his fame. In 1658, on the occasion of the
                    discovery of some ancient urns in Norfolk, he wrote his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Hydriotaphia</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Umburial,</hi> to which was appended <hi
                    rend="italic">The Garden of Cyrus.</hi> These four works were all that he
                    published, though several tracts, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n437/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0437-0390"/> notably the <hi rend="italic">Christian
                    Morals</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Antiquities of Norwich,</hi> were prepared for
                    publication, and appeared after his death. In 1671 he received the honour of
                    knighthood from Charles II. on his visit to Norwich; and in 1682 he died on his
                    seventy-seventh birthday.</p>
                <p>Browne is in every way a remarkable and peculiar writer. His writings are among
                    the few specimens of purely literary work produced during a period of great
                    political excitement and discord. England was passing through, its greatest
                    convulsion; events of mighty moment were being transacted round him, and he
                    remained placidly indifferent. While the grandest minds of his country were
                    busied with the important affairs of state, he was revising his <hi
                    rend="italic">Religio</hi><hi rend="italic">Medici,</hi> and his book was
                    published in the very year in which the civil war broke out. While England was
                    torn with civil discord, and the liberty of her children was being bought with
                    their blood, Browne serenely pursued his studies at Norwich, to all appearance
                    as indifferent to contemporary events as if he had belonged to another planet.
                    Just when there came a lull in the conflict, when the royal power was broken,
                    and the air was filled with doubts, anxieties, and negotiations, Browne
                    published his <hi rend="italic">Pseudodoxia</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Epidemica.</hi> The death of the king, the expulsion of the parliament, the
                    establishment of the protectorate, passed by him like a breath which he heeded
                    not. But the unearthing of some sepulchral urns at once roused his attention,
                    and furnished occasion for a train of most magnificent and majestic reflections
                    on the short space of human life, on the signs and symbols of mortality. A mind
                    like this is a psychological curiosity, and its peculiarities are faithfully
                    reflected in the form and matter of his - works. In some respects, of course, he
                    resembles his contemporaries; in his, as in all other writings of the 17th
                    century, there is a plentiful display of erudition, copious citation of
                    authorities, and lavish quotation from older writers. Some part also of the
                    peculiarity of his style may be ascribed to the general tendency of the language
                    at that period. It was a time of unusual richness of diction; great writers did
                    not hesitate to coin words and phrases as occasion required them, and ample raw
                    material was supplied by the great mass of literature, which had been but
                    recently opened up, and which was then being assimilated. But Browne stands
                    apart from his contemporaries by reason of the peculiar and unique cast of his
                    mind. Deeply speculative, imbued with the Platonic mysticism which taught him to
                    look upon this world as only the image, the shadow of an invisible system, he
                    regarded the whole of experience but as food for contemplation. Nothing is too
                    great or too small, too far removed or too near at hand for him; all finds a
                    place in the universe of being, which he seems to regard almost from the
                    position of an outsider. His general mood may be characterized as the
                    metaphysical; not that he speculated systematically on the problems 'of
                    existence, but because lie dwells repeatedly, and with evident delight, upon
                    what transcends the little sphere of our life, and, like Shakespeare, is fond of
                    meditating on the outward and visible signs of mortality, and on what lies
                    beyond the grave.</p>
                <p>Of Browne, however, as of our greatest writers, it is true that the style is the
                    man. The form of his thought is as peculiar and remarkable as the matter; the
                    two, indeed, react upon one another. It is a style altogether unique,— rich,
                    with a lavish use of metaphor and analogy—majestic and swelling, and with a fine
                    antique flavour about it. Much of its quaintness, no doubt, depends on the
                    excessive employment of Latinized words, great part of which have never
                    succeeded in making their way into the standard language; but the peculiarities
                    of the vocabulary do not entirely exhaust those of the style. Of his four
                    masterpieces the <hi rend="italic">Religio</hi><hi rend="italic">Medici</hi> is
                    that in which we are most in contact with the writer himself. The book was a
                    puzzle to contemporaries, and is still hard to understand. It is the confession
                    of faith of a mind keen and sceptical in some aspects, but on the whole deeply
                    imbued with the sense of the mysteriousness of true religion, and willing to
                    yield itself up without reserve to the requirements of faith. “I love/’ he says,
                    “to lose myself in a mystery, to pursue my reason to an <hi rend="italic"
                    >0,</hi><hi rend="italic">Altitudo</hi><hi rend="italic">!”</hi> The <hi
                    rend="italic">Vulgar Errors</hi> is a wonderful storehouse of out-of-the-way
                    facts and scraps of erudition, exhibiting a singular mixture of credulity and
                    shrewdness. The style is more direct and simple than in the other works. The <hi
                    rend="italic">Garden of Cyrus</hi> is a continued illustration of one quaint
                    conceit. The whole universe is ransacked for examples of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Quincunx,</hi> and he discovers, as Coleridge says, “quincunxes in heaven
                    above, quincunxes in earth below, quincunxes in the mind of man, quincunxes in
                    tones, in optic nerves, in roots of trees, in leaves, in everything !” But the
                    whole strength of his genius and the wonderful charm of his style are to be
                    sought in the <hi rend="italic">Vmburial,</hi> the concluding chapter of which,
                    for richness of imagery and majestic pomp of diction, can hardly be paralleled
                    in the English language. For anything at all resembling it we must turn to the
                    finest passages of Jeremy Taylor or of Milton’s prose writings.</p>
                <p>The best edition of Sir T. Browne is that by Simon Wilkin, 4 vols., 1836,—3 vols.
                    (Bohn), 1851, where full biographical and bibliographical information will be
                    found. Prefixed to it is Johnson’s celebrated <hi rend="italic">Life.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
