<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0441-0394-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BRUCKER, James (9th edition, volume 4, page
                    394)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:825145">Bacon</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1353832">Miscellanea</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:957686">Historians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wp9tb5s">Historians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n441/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BRUCKER, <hi rend="smallcaps">James</hi></label>, theologian,
                    historian, philologer, and biographer, was born at Augsburg on the 22d of
                    January 1696. His father, who was a respectable burgher, destined him for the
                    church; and his own inclinations according with his father’s wishes, he was sent
                    at the usual age to pursue his studies in the university of Jena. Here he took
                    the degree of master of arts in 1718; and in the following year he published his
                    <hi rend="italic">Tentamen Introductionis</hi><hi rend="italic">in</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Historiam Doctrinae</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Ideis,</hi> in 4to,—a work which he afterwards amplified and completed, and
                    republished under the title of <hi rend="italic">Historia Philosophica
                    Doctrinae</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic">Ideis,</hi> at Augsburg
                    in 1723. He returned to his native city in 1720; but here his merit having
                    attracted envy rather than recompense, he was induced to accept of the office of
                    parish minister of Kaufbevern in 1723. In the same year he published a memoir
                    <hi rend="italic">De Vita</hi><hi rend="italic">et Scriptis</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Cl.</hi><hi rend="italic">Etringeri,</hi> Augs. 8vo. His
                    reputation having been at length established by these learned works, in 1731 he
                    was elected a member of the Academy of Sciences at Berlin; and soon afterwards
                    he was invited to Augsburg to fill the honourable situation of pastor and senior
                    minister of tne church of St Ulric. He published in the same year three
                    dissertations relating to the history of philosophy, under the title of <hi
                    rend="italic">Otium Vindelicum sive</hi><hi rend="italic">Meletematum
                    Histoi'ico-philoso-phicorum</hi><hi rend="italic">Triga,</hi> Augsburg, 1731,
                    8vo. Besides several smaller dissertations on biography and literary history,
                    printed at different times, and which he afterwards collected in his <hi
                    rend="italic">Miscellanea,</hi> he published at Ulm, in 1737, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Neue Zusätze verschiedener Vermehrungen,</hi> &amp;c., <hi rend="italic">zu den
                    kurtzen Fragen aus der philosophischen Historie,</hi> 7 vols. 12mo. This work
                    being a history of philosophy in question and answer, contains many details,
                    especially in the department of literary history, which he has chosen to omit in
                    his greater work on the same subject. He was forced by the booksellers, in
                    opposition to his own opinion, to adopt the erotematic method, which at that
                    time had been rendered popular by the writings of Hubner and Rambach.</p>
                <p>In 1741, at Leipsic, appeared the first volume of his great work, <hi
                    rend="italic">Historia Critica Philosophiae, a mundi incunabulis ad nostram
                    usque aetatem deducta.</hi> Four other ponderous quartos, completing the first
                    edition of this elaborate history, followed in 1744. Such was the success of
                    this publication, that the first impression, consisting of four thousand copies,
                    was exhausted in twenty-three years, when a new and more perfect edition, the
                    consummation of the labours of half a century devoted to the history of
                    philosophy, was in 1767 given to the world in six volumes quarto. The sixth
                    volume, consisting entirely of supplement and corrections, is applicable to the
                    first as well as to the second edition. Of the merits of this work we shall
                    speak in the sequel.</p>
                <p>His attention, however, was not wholly occupied by this stupendous undertaking.
                    The following books would of themselves have been sufficient to exhaust the
                    industry of any ordinary author :— <hi rend="italic">Pinacotheca</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Scriptorum</hi><hi rend="italic">nostra</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >aetate</hi><hi rend="italic">literis</hi><hi rend="italic">illustrium,</hi>
                    &amp;c., Ausgburg, 1741-55, folio, in five decades. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ehrentempel der Deutschen Gelehrsamkeit in welchem die Bildnisse gelehrter
                    Männer unter den Deutschen aus dem XV., XVI., und XVII. Jahrhundert
                    aufgestellet, undihre Geschichte,</hi><hi rend="italic">&lt;kc.,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">entworfen sind,</hi> Augsburg, 1747-49, 4to, five decads. <hi
                    rend="italic">Institutiones Historice Philosophicae,</hi> Leipsic, 1747, 8vo,
                    second edition, <hi rend="italic">ibid,</hi> 1756; a third has been published
                    since Brucker’s death, with a continuation by Professor Born of Leipsic, in
                    1790. <hi rend="italic">Miscellanea</hi><hi rend="italic">Historice
                    Philosophicae</hi><hi rend="italic">Literarioe Criticae</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >olim</hi><hi rend="italic">sparsim</hi><hi rend="italic">edita, nunc uno fasce
                    collecta,</hi> Augsburg, 1748, 8vo. <hi rend="italic">Erste Anfangsgrunde der
                    philosophischen Geschichte, als ein Auszug seiner grossem Werke, zweyte
                    Ausgabe,</hi> Ulm, 1751, 8vo. He likewise superintended and corrected an edition
                    of Luther’s translation of the Old and New Testment, with a Commentary extracted
                    from the writings of the English theologians, Leipsic, 1758-70, folio, six
                    parts. His death ensued before the completion of this work, which has since been
                    accomplished by Teller. He died at Augsburg in 1770; and he may be added to the
                    catalogue of Huetius, to prove that literary labour is not incompatible with
                    sound health and longevity. (See Saxii <hi rend="italic">Onomasticon;</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Biographie Universelle;</hi> Gesner’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Isagoge.}</hi></p>
                <p>Itis only by his writings on the history of philosophy that Brucker is now known
                    in the literature of Europe. In this study his great work forms an important
                    era, and even at the present day it is the most extensive and elaborate upon the
                    subject. It is, however, a work of which the defects are great, and its errors
                    have been important in their consequences, in proportion to the authority it has
                    acquired. We shall, therefore, hazard a few general observations on the defects
                    which chiefly detract from the perfection and utility of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Critical History of Philosophy,</hi></p>
                <p>If Brucker had carried into this study a penetration equal to his diligence, and
                    had his general comprehension of the scope and <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n442/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0442-0395"/> nature of the subject corresponded with the
                    elaborate minuteness of his details, he would have left us a work which might
                    have had some pretensions to be considered as a rational history of human
                    opinion. He lived, however, at a period when these different qualities were only
                    beginning to be conjoined, and when as yet the history of philosophy had been
                    written merely as a chronicle of the passing theories of individuals and sects.
                    To give to the science cf history a regular and connected form, and to arrange
                    thé narrative of successive events, and still more of successive opinions,
                    according to the relation they bear to principles of established influence, was
                    an attempt of which few in that age had any conception, and of which Brucker
                    certainly had none. In civil history it was then believed that the historian had
                    fulfilled all the duties of his office if he strung together the events which
                    were known or believed to have occurred, in good language, and garnished them
                    occasionally by a few general reflections on the absolute motives of human
                    action. A very different notion is now held of the functions of the historian.
                    He who at present attempts to write the history of any country must reflect,
                    before he begins, what were the chief occurrences in that history, and what were
                    the revolutions which the manners and constitution of that particular nation
                    have undergone. He must bear with him, from the commencement to the conclusion
                    of his labours, a constant impression that every occurrence should be more or
                    less considered, not only as it took place, and as it bore an influence on
                    contemporary affairs, but as it may have remotely contributed to the events, and
                    the opinions, and the character of succeeding times. But if this be true in
                    regard to the histories of particular nations, it is evident that, by how much
                    the traces of opinions are more light and evanescent than those of events, by
                    how much the speculations of philosophers whose writings have either perished or
                    come down to us mutilated and obscure are more difficult to be appreciated in
                    their causes, and connections, and consequences, than the actions of warriors
                    and statesmen,—by so much the more is it necessary in philosophical than in
                    civil history to combine reasoning with erudition, and to substitute the
                    researches of the philosopher for the details of the chronicler. History and
                    philosophy are two different things; and he who would write the history of
                    philosophy must excel in both. Bacon had long ago required this union, and had
                    pointed out the manner in which the historian of literature should endeavour to
                    establish those principles of connection which constitute the soul and charm of
                    such a history; how, by detecting the union of effects and causes, he might be
                    enabled to determine the circumstances favourable or adverse to the sciences;
                    and how, in short, by a species of enchantment, he might evoke the literary
                    genius of each different age. The fulfilment of this plan was, however, far
                    beyond the capacity of Brucker, and was an undertaking of which he had even no
                    conception. Better qualified by nature and education for amassing than arranging
                    materials, he devoted his principal attention to a confused compilation of
                    facts, leaving to others their application, the discovery of their mutual
                    connections, and the formation of the scattered fragments into a whole.</p>
                <p>The merit of his great work consists entirely in the ample collection of
                    materials. The reader who would extract any rational view of the progress of
                    opinion must peruse it with a perpetual commentary of his own thoughts. He will
                    find no assistance from his author in forming any general views, or in tracing
                    the mutual dependencies of the different parts of the subject. Brucker has
                    discovered the fountains of history, but he has made us drink of them without
                    purifying the draught. Even in this respect his merit has been greatly
                    overrated. Vast as is the body of materials which he has collected, we are
                    always missing those very things which we might reasonably have expected would
                    have beén the first objects of a rational inquirer, and we are continually
                    disappointed of the information we are most anxious to acquire. The idle and
                    slavish attention which he has bestowed on previous compilers has frequently
                    diverted him from the study of the original authors themselves. Quoting the
                    passages of the ancients from others, or trusting perhaps to the reference of an
                    index, he has frequently overlooked those very testimonies which could have
                    given us the most authentic knowledge of the opinions or characters of ages and
                    individuals. He has often presented the authorities he has adduced, mutilated or
                    misapplied; and this either from not having sufficiently studied these passages
                    in their general c.onnection with the system they illustrate, or from having
                    been unable to withdraw them from the obscurity in which they were involved. He
                    has shown no critical sagacity in distinguishing the spurious from the
                    authentic, or in balancing the comparative weight of his authorities. He has
                    frequently transcribed where he ought to have explained the words of the
                    original authors; and, without taking into account the different value of the
                    same term in different nations and ages, he has left us to apply a doubtful or
                    erroneous meaning to words which might have been easily rendered by other
                    expressions, and to suppose a distinction in the sense where there only existed
                    a difference in the language. The glaring errors, even, which occasionally occur
                    in his expositions of the Grecian philosophy, while they are inconsistent with
                    any critical knowledge of the tongue, would make us suspect that he was in the
                    habit of relying on the treacherous aid of translations. In short, if we knew
                    nothing more of the ancient philosophers than what we acquire from Brucker, we
                    should be often obliged to attribute to them opinions so obscure, or so absurd,
                    that we must either believe ourselves wrong in the interpretation, or be unable
                    to comprehend the cause of all the admiration and reverence they have
                    received.</p>
                <p>He has discovered little skill in his analysis of the different systems of
                    philosophy; and the confusion of what is essential and principal with what is
                    accidental and subordinate clearly evinces that these abridgments were thrown
                    together while acquiring, in detail, a knowledge expressly for the purpose,
                    instead of being the consummation of a long and familiar meditation on the
                    subjects in all their modifications and dependencies. He has dwelt with the most
                    irksome minuteness on every unimportant and doubtful circumstance in the lives
                    of the philosophers; but he has too often overlooked the particular and general
                    causes that produced an influence on the destinies of their philosophy. The
                    aphoristic method which he has adopted prevents him from following a consecutive
                    argument throughout its various windings. The most convincing reasoning in his
                    hands loses much of its demonstration and beauty; and every ingenious paradox
                    comes forth from his alembic a mere <hi rend="italic">caput</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">mortuum,</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> a residue from which every
                    finer principle has been expelled. Where the genius of the philosopher is
                    discovered more in the exposition and defence than in the original selection and
                    intrinsic stability of his tenets, Brucker has not found the art of doing
                    justice both to the philosopher and to his opinions, or of conveying to the
                    reader any conception of the general value of the original. This last defect, it
                    must, however, be acknowledged, is more or less inseparable from every abstract
                    of opinions, where it is always necessary to separate in some degree what is
                    essential to the subject from what is peculiar to the man. He has relieved the
                    sterility of his analysis by none of the elegancies of which the subject was
                    susceptible. Without any pretension to purity, his diction is defective even in
                    precision; and his sentences, at all times void of harmony and grace, are
                    abrupt, and often intricate in their structure. (W. H.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
