<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0574-0513-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BUILDING SOCIETIES (9th edition, volume 4, page
                    513)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1115271">Sharing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:976135">Interest</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1025265">Money</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1090626">Reading</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1085637">Queens</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204598">Pennsylvania</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205049">Victoria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204543">Australia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4nc5sc8g">Money</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4td9n76g">Loans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62f7n">Reading</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n574/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BUILDING SOCIETIES</label>, ör societies “forthe purpose of
                    raising, by the subscriptions of the members, a stock or fund for making
                    advances to members out of the funds of the society upon freehold, copyhold, or
                    leasehold estate by way of mortgage,” may be “either terminating or permanent”
                    (37 and 38 Vict. c. 42, § 13).</p>
                <p>A “terminating” society is one “which by its rules is to terminate at a fixed
                    date, or when a result specified in its rules is attained;” a “permanent”
                    society is one “which has not by its rules any such fixed date or specified
                    result, at which it shall terminate” (§ 5).</p>
                <p>A more popular description of these societies would be,—Societies by means of
                    which every man may become “his own landlord,” their main purpose being to
                    collect together the small periodical subscriptions of a number of members,
                    until each in his turn has been able to receive a sum sufficient to aid him
                    materially in buying his dwellinghouse.</p>
                <p>The origin and early history of these societies is not very clearly traceable. A
                    mention of “building clubs” in Birmingham occurs in 1795; one is known to have
                    been established by deed in the year 1809 at Greenwich; another is said to have
                    been founded in 1825, under the auspices of the earl of Selkirk at Kirkcudbright
                    in Scotland, and we learn (Scratchley <hi rend="italic">On Building
                    Societies,</hi> p. 5) that similar societies in that kingdom adopted the title
                    of “ménagés.”</p>
                <p>When the Friendly Societies Act of 1834 gave effect to the wise and liberal
                    policy of extending its benefits to societies for frugal investment, and
                    generally to all associations having a similar legal object, several building
                    societies were certified under it,—so many, indeed, that in 1836 a short Act was
                    passed (6 and 7 Will. IV. cap. 32), confirming to them the privileges granted by
                    the Friendly Societies Act, and according to them the additional privileges
                    (very valuable at that time) of exemption from the usury laws, simplicity in
                    forms of conveyance, power to reconvey by a mere endorsement under the hands of
                    the trustees for the time being, and exemption from stamp duty. This Act
                    remained unaltered till 1874.</p>
                <p>The early societies were all “terminating,”—consisting of a limited number of
                    members, and coming to an end as soon as every member had received the amount
                    agreed, upon as the value of his shares.</p>
                <p>Take, as a simple typical example of the working of such a society, one the
                    shares of which are £120 each, realizable by subscriptions of 10s. a month
                    during 14 years. Fourteen years happens to be nearly the time in which, at 5 per
                    cent, compound interest, a sum of money becomes doubled. Hence the present
                    value, at the commencement of the society, of the £120 to be realized at its
                    conclusion, or (what is the same thing) of the subscriptions of 10s. a month by
                    which that £120 is to be raised, is £60. If such a society had issued 120
                    shares, the aggregate subscriptions for the first month of its existence would
                    amount to exactly the sum required to pay one member the present value of one
                    share. One member would accordingly receive a sum down of £60, and in order to
                    protect the other members from loss, would execute a mortgage of his
                    dwelling-house for ensuring the payment of the future subscription of 10s. per
                    month until every member had in like manner obtained an advance upon his shares,
                    or accumulated the £120 per share.</p>
                <p>As £60 is not of itself enough to buy a house, even of the most modest kind,
                    every member desirous of using the society for its original purpose of obtaining
                    a dwelling-house by its means would require to take more than one share. In this
                    respect the Act of 1836 presented a curious inconsistency; it limited the amount
                    of each share to £150, and the amount of the monthly contributions on each share
                    to £1, but did not limit the number of shares a member might hold. If its
                    purpose in this respect was to confine the operation of these societies to the
                    industrial classes, it was defective. The only rational explanation of the
                    provision is that it was an anticipation of the modem system of limited
                    liability.</p>
                <p>The earlier formed societies (in London at least) did not usually adopt the title
                    “Building Society ;” or they added to it some further descriptive title, as
                    “Accumulating Fund,’·' “Savings’ Fund,” or “Investment Association.” Several are
                    described as “Societies for obtaining freehold property,” <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n575/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0575-0514"/> or simply as “Mutual Associations,” or “Societies
                    of Equality.” The building societies in Scotland are mostly called “Property
                    Investment Companies,” or by some similar name. Although the term “Benefit
                    Building Society” occurs in the title to the Act of 1836, it was not till 1849
                    that it became in England the sole distinctive name of these societies; and it
                    cannot be said to be a happy description of them, for as ordinarily constituted
                    they undertake no building operations whatever, and merely advance money to
                    their members to enable them to build or to buy dwelling-houses or land.</p>
                <p>The name “Building Society,” too, leaves wholly out of sight the important
                    functions these societies fulfil as means of investment of small savings. The
                    Act of 1836 defined them as societies to enable every member to receive the
                    amount or value of a share or shares to erect or purchase a dwelling-house,
                    &lt;fcc., but a member who did not desire to erect or purchase a dwelling-house
                    might still receive out of the funds of the society the amount or value of his
                    shares, improved by the payments of interest made by those to whom shares had
                    been advanced.</p>
                <p>About 1846 an important modification of the system of these societies was
                    introduced, by the invention of the “permanent” plan, which was adopted by a
                    great number of the societies established after that date. It was seen that
                    these societies really consist of two classes of members; that those who do not
                    care to have, or have not yet received, an advance upon mortgage security are
                    mere investors; and that it matters little when they commence investing, or to
                    what amount, while those to whom advances have been made are really debtors to
                    the society, and arrangements for enabling them to pay off their debt in various
                    terms of years, according to their convenience, would be of advantage both to
                    themselves and the society. By permitting members to enter at any time without
                    back-payment, and by granting advances for any term of years agreed upon, a
                    continuous inflow of funds, and a continuous means of profitable investment of
                    them, would be secured. The interest of each memoer ⅛ the society would
                    terminate when his share was realized, or his advance paid off, but the society
                    would continue with the accruing subscriptions of other members employed in
                    making other advances.</p>
                <p>Under this system Building Societies have largely increased and developed. In the
                    county of Middlesex alone, 1600 societies were certified between 1836 and 1874;
                    in that of Lancaster, 1300; and the total number of societies established in
                    England and Wales cannot be less than between 5000 and 6000.</p>
                <p>Deducting the terminating societies which have reached their termination, and the
                    permanent societies which have failed or been dissolved, it is estimated that
                    more than 2000 societies are still in existence. The operations of some of these
                    societies are very extensive. The Queen’s Building Society at Manchester has an
                    income of £734,578, and assets amounting to £910,224; a society at Halifax has
                    an income of £261,654, and assets £430,683; one at Burnley £221,508 income, and
                    £324,919 assets <hi rend="italic">{Report of Registrar,</hi> 1875) There are
                    also several large societies in Scotland,</p>
                <p>The total funds and income of building societies cannot be accurately
                    ascertained; but the Royal Commissioners who inquired into the subject in 1872,
                    estimated the total assets of the societies in 1870 at 17 millions, and their
                    annual income at 11 millions. The larger societies are in the North of England,
                    where, indeed, all classes of provident associations, notably friendly societies
                    and co-operative societies, are more fully developed than in the South. To this
                    remark, however, there is one exception, viz., the Birkbeck Building Society,
                    London, whose receipts for the year 1874 amounted to 4⅜ millions, but by far the
                    larger portion of that enormous sum consisted of deposits paid to the society as
                    a banker.</p>
                <p>A variety of the terminating class of societies has met with some favour of late
                    years, under the name of “Stan· Bowkett” or “mutual” societies, of which about
                    200 have been established. They differ from the typical society above described,
                    in the contribution of a member who has not received an advance being much
                    smaller, while the amount of the advance is much larger, and it is made without
                    any calculation of interest. Thus a society will issue say 500 shares, on which
                    the contributions are to be Is. 3d. per week, and, as soon as a sum of £300 has
                    accumulated, will allot it by ballot to one of the shareholders, on condition
                    that he is to repay it without interest by instalments in 10 or 12⅜ years, and
                    at the same time to keep up his share-contributions. The fortunate recipient of
                    the appropriation is at liberty to sell it, and frequently does so at a profit;
                    but (except from fines) no profit whatever is earned by those who do not succeed
                    in getting an appropriation, and as the number of members successful in the
                    ballot must necessarily be small in the earlier years of the society, the others
                    frequently become discontented and retire. These societies cannot, of course,
                    borrow money, for as they receive no interest they cannot pay any. The plan has
                    recently been modified by granting the appropriations alternately by ballot and
                    sale, so that by the premiums paid on the sales (which are the same in effect as
                    payments of interest on the amount actually advanced) profits may be earned for
                    the investing members.</p>
                <p>A further modification of the “mutual” plan is to make all the appropriations by
                    sale. The effect of this is to bring the mutual society back to the ordinary
                    form; for it amounts to precisely the same thing for a man to pay 10s. a month
                    on a loan of £60 for 14 years, as for him to borrow a nominal sum of £84 for the
                    same period, repayable in the same manner, but to allow £24 off the loan as a
                    “bidding” at the sale. The only difference between the two classes of societies
                    is that the interest which the member pays who bids for his advance depends on
                    the amount of competition at the bidding, and is not fixed by a rule of the
                    society.</p>
                <p>In 1874 an Act was passed at the instance of the building societies conferring
                    upon them several valuable privileges, and relieving them of some disabilities
                    and doubts, which had grown up from the judicial expositions of the Act of 1836.
                    Building societies are now incorporated bodies, and the members, and all who
                    derive title through them, henceforth will not have to trace that title through
                    a succession of trustees for a society. Again, a distinct declaration is given
                    to the members of entire freedom from liability to pay anything beyond the
                    arrears due from them at the time of winding up, or the amount actually secured
                    by their mortgage deeds. Power to borrow money is also expressly given to the
                    societies by the Act, but upon two conditions :—that the limitation of liability
                    must be made known to the .lender, by being printed on the acknowledgment for
                    the loan, and that the borrowed money must not exceed two-thirds of the amount
                    secured by mortgage from the members, or, in a terminating society, one year’s
                    income from subscriptions.</p>
                <p>Previous to the passing of the Act (or rather to the judicial decision in <hi
                    rend="italic">Laing</hi> v. <hi rend="italic">Read,</hi> which the clause of the
                    Act makes statutory) there had been, on the one hand, grave doubts on high legal
                    authority whether a society could borrow money at all; while, on the other hand,
                    many societies in order to raise funds carried on the business of deposit banks
                    to an extent far exceeding the amounts used by them for their legitimate purpose
                    of investment on mortgage. It is now enacted, that if a society borrow more than
                    the statute authorizes, the directors accepting the loan shall be personally
                    responsible for the excess.</p>
                <p>The history of building societies thus briefly traced shows great progress in the
                    past and equal promise for the future. The social and moral utility of societies
                    established for the direct purpose of aiding a man to become proprietor of his
                    dwelling-house is obvious, and the extent to which that purpose has been
                    effected is very considerable.</p>
                <p>It may be mentioned that building societies flourish in America (notably in
                    Massachusetts, where they are called “Mutual Loan Fund Associations,” and
                    Pennsylvania), and in the British colonies, especially that of Victoria,
                    Australia. (E, W. B.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
