<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0489-0442-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BUFFALO (9th edition, volume 4, page 442)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bn9x40m">Buffaloes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m9h">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r851">Tigers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q814s63">Beasts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4599z60x">Hindoos</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6j808">Gaming</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42r3nw89">Games</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:840456">Buffaloes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:960336">Horns</term>
                    <term ref="fast:832970">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:955408">Herding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150843">Tigers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:799938">Africans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:799932">Africanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n489/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BUFFALO</label>, the English name of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Bubalus,</hi> a genus of Ruminant Mammals, belonging to the family <hi
                    rend="italic">Bovidoe,</hi> and including the well-known Indian and South
                    African species. The Indian Buffalo <hi rend="italic">(Bubalus</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">buffalus)</hi> is characterized by its arched forehead, large
                    horns compressed at the base, slightly triangular, and curved in the form of a
                    half moon, and its thick hide covered sparingly with coarse hairs, which become
                    still more scanty in aged individuals. It is a native of India and of the
                    islands forming the Indo-Malay Archipelago, where it now occurs in a state of
                    domestication, and forms a valuable beast of burden; but although it has for
                    ages been under the control of man, the <hi rend="italic">Bainsha</hi> or tame
                    buffalo shows little or no variation from the wild form. The <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ama</hi> or Wild Buffalo is found in great herds throughout India and the
                    adjacent islands, frequenting swampy grounds in the neighbourhood of woods,
                    eating the long, coarse grass which abounds in such localities, and loving above
                    all things to roll itself in mire, or to plunge up to the ears in any pool or
                    stream it may come upon. This fondness for moisture is equally marked in the
                    tame variety, and is decidedly inconvenient when the animal, laden with goods,
                    yields to its instinct and lies down in any stream that may cross its path. The
                    rutting season occurs in autumn, when several females follow a single male,
                    forming for the time a small herd. The period of gestation lasts for ten months,
                    and the female produces one or two calves at a birth. The <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ama</hi> is a powerful and courageous animal, capable it is said of
                    overthrowing an elephant, and generally more than a match even for the male
                    tiger, which usually declines the combat when not impelled to it by hunger. The
                    Indian driver of a herd of tame buffaloes does not shrink from entering a
                    tiger-frequented jungle, his cattle, with their massive horns, making short work
                    of any tiger that may come in their way. Buffalo fights and fights between
                    buffaloes and tigers form principal features in the public entertainments of
                    Indian princes. In Ceylon the buffalo is put to more useful purposes, where,
                    according to Tennent, the natives make an ingenious use of it when shooting
                    waterfowl in the salt marshes, <hi rend="superscript"> ii</hi> Being an object
                    to which the birds are accustomed, the Singhalese train the buffaloes to the
                    sport, and concealed behind the animal, browsing listlessly along, they guide it
                    by ropes attached to its horns, and thus creep undiscovered within shot of the
                    flock.” These are known as “sporting buffaloes.” The domestic buffalo has spread
                    from its original home in India over the greater part of Southern Asia and of
                    North Africa, and was introduced towards the close of the 6th century into
                    Greece and Italy, forming an invaluable beast of burden in the marshy districts
                    of those countries, where the great breadth of its feet, somewhat resembling in
                    this respect those of the reindeer, give it a decided advantage over the horse
                    and ox. It grazes in herds in the Pontine marshes, where, according to Scaliger,
                    it will lie for hours submerged almost to the muzzle. The milk of the buffalo is
                    plentiful and of excellent quality, the Hindoos making it into a kind of butter
                    called <hi rend="italic">ghee;</hi> its flesh, however, is not held in much
                    estimation.</p>
                <p>The Cape Buffalo <hi rend="italic">(Bubalus</hi><hi rend="italic">caffer)</hi> is
                    nearly equal in size and fully equal in strength and courage to its Indian
                    congener, from which it is readily distinguished by the form of its horns, these
                    being immensely broad at the base, where they approximate so closely as almost
                    to meet, thus forming, especially in old bulls, a solid rugose mass impenetrable
                    to bullet, and extending from the eye to the back of the head, then spreading
                    horizontally and curving upwards and inwards to the tips, which are usually <hi
                    rend="italic">4 feet</hi> apart. The hide, which is thick and tough, is thinly
                    clad with hair, old animals being entirely naked with the exception of a slight
                    fringe along the back and withers. This buffalo roams in herds over the plains
                    of Central and Southern Africa, always in the near vicinity of water. Formerly
                    herds sometimes numbered five or six hundred, but such has been the havoc
                    wrought among them in recent years by hunters that rarely are they to be seen in
                    companies of more than ten, while in the colonized portion of South Africa they
                    are rapidly dying out. Nor is man their only enemy, for by night when he ceases
                    to disturb they are liable to the attack of the lion, and by this means the
                    wounded, of which there are great numbers, and the diseased are cut off. The
                    Hon. W. H. Drummond, in his work on <hi rend="italic">The Large Game of South
                    Africa</hi> (1875), gives it as his opinion that in “a few years a buffalo will
                    be as scarce as an elephant now is.” This species has never been domesticated,
                    probably owing more to the uncivilized condition of the native inhabitants than
                    to any special intractability in the buffalo itself. Like its Indian ally it is
                    fond of the water, which it visits at regular intervals during the twenty-four
                    hours; it also plasters itself with mud which, when hardened by the sun,
                    protects it from the bite of the great gadflies which in spite of its thick hide
                    seem to cause it considerable annoyance. It is also relieved of a portion of the
                    parasitic ticks, so common on the hides of thick-skinned animals, by means of
                    the red-Deaked rhinoceros birds, a dozen or more of which may be seen partly
                    perched on its horns and partly moving about on its back, and picking up the
                    ticks on which they feed. The hunter is often guided by these birds in his
                    search for the buffalo, but offener still they give timely warning to their host
                    of the dangerous proximity of the hunter, and have thus earned the title of “the
                    buffalo’s guardian birds.” The Cape Buffalo is the most formidable of the large
                    game of South Africa. Generally, however, it attacks only when wounded,
                    although“rogues” or “solitaires ”—terms applied to old bulls which for some
                    reason or other have been expelled from the herd and which wander about morose
                    and savage— often attack without <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n490/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0490-0443"/> provocation. When wounded they immediately charge
                    in the direction from which the fire proceeded, and on his skill in avoiding
                    this charge the life of the hunter depends. In buffalo hunting, as in bison
                    hunting, it is specially important “to kill with a single bullet.” The hide of
                    the Cape Buffalo is made by the Kaffres into shields impervious to musket
                    shot.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
