<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0225-0184-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BOYLE, Robert (9th edition, volume 4, page 184)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:802066">Air</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1048190">Originality</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:825145">Bacon</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1002769">Love</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jd4pp0f">Air</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z196">Love</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41834445">Cold</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n225/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BOYLE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert</hi></label>, one of the
                    greatest natural philosophers of his age, and one of the founders of the Royal
                    Society of London, was the seventh son and fourteenth child of Richard Boyle,
                    earl of Cork, and was born at Lismore Castle in the province of Munster,
                    Ireland, January 25, 1627. In his earliest years he learnt to speak Latin and
                    French, and he was only eight years old when he was sent to Eton, his father’s
                    friend, Sir Henry Wotton, being then provost of the college. Here he studied
                    about three years, and was next placed as private pupil with the rector of
                    Stalbridge in Dorsetshire, where his father had just taken up his residence. In
                    1638 after a visit to London he travelled in France accompanied by a French
                    tutor, and studied above a year at Geneva. In the autumn of 1641 he visited
                    Switzerland and Italy, spending the winter of 1641-42 at ’Florence. Here he
                    studied the works of Galileo, who died near Florence the same winter. On
                    reaching Englaud in 1644 he learnt the death of his father, who had left to him
                    the manor of Stalbridge and estates in Ireland. It was in the following year
                    that be became a member of a society of scientific men, who in consequence of
                    the political agitation of the times used to hold their meetings with as much
                    privacy as possible, first in London and afterwards at Oxford; this became
                    subsequently famous as the Royal Society. In 1646 he settled at Stalbridge, and
                    from that time his whole life was devoted to study, scientific research and
                    experiments, and authorship. After making several visits to his estates in
                    Ireland he took up his abode at Oxford in 1654, and there enjoyed the society of
                    many learned men. He resided at Oxford for fourteen years; and it was during
                    this period that he made important improvements in the air-pump, and by a long
                    series of experiments with it made various discoveries on the properties of air,
                    the propagation of sound, &lt;fcc., which are recorded in his voluminous
                    writings. Boyle was at the same time an ardent student of theology, and numbered
                    among his friends the eminent Orientalists Pococke, Hyde, and Clarke, and Dr
                    Thomas Barlow, Bodleian librarian and bishop of Lincoln. At the Restoration he
                    was favourably received at court, and was advised to enter the church; but this
                    he declined to do, alleging that it was not his vocation, and that he believed
                    his writings on religious subjects would have greater weight coming from a
                    layman than from a paid minister of the church. His anxiety to promote the
                    spread of Christianity appeared in various munificent acts. He bore the expense
                    of preparing a Malay translation of the Gospels and the Acts of the Apostles,
                    and of an Irish version of the Bible. He contributed largely to the cost of the
                    Welsh Bible and of a Turkish New Testament, and gave a large sum to the
                    translator of the work of Grotius <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Veritate</hi> into Arabic. He supported liberally the projects for spreading
                    the Gospel in India and in America, and gave away annually a large sum for
                    charitable purposes. He made his first appearance as author in 1660, by the
                    publication at Oxford of a volume entitled <hi rend="italic">New Experiments,
                    Physico-Mechaniccd,</hi><hi rend="italic">touching the Spring of Air and its
                    Effects,</hi> and of a devotional work entitled <hi rend="italic">Seraphic Love,
                    or some Motives and Incentives to the Love of God.</hi></p>
                <p>When the Royal Society was incorporated (1663) Boyle was named a member of the
                    council. He communicated many important memoirs to the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Philosophical Transactions,</hi> and, in 1680, was elected president of the
                    society, but from a scruple about oaths he declined this honour. Boyle was at
                    one time deeply interested in alchemy, and carried on experiments on the
                    transmutation of metals, in which Newton also took much interest. It was through
                    his efforts that the statute of Henry IV. cap. 4, against the multiplying of
                    gold and silver was repealed in 1689. After leaving Oxford in 1668 he settled in
                    London; and here he spent the rest of his days, residing in the house of his
                    sister Lady Ranelagh. He was never married. In person he was tall, slender, and
                    of a pale countenance. His constitution was far from robust, and throughout his
                    life he suffered from feeble health and low spirits. While his scientific
                    discoveries procured him wide and lasting renown, his private character and
                    virtues, the charm of his social manners, his wit and conversation, endeared him
                    to a large number of personal friends. As a man of science he was ranked by his
                    contemporaries among the greatest; and although some abatement of this very high
                    estimate has since been admitted, he still holds a place of distinction as the
                    first great investigator who carried out in his labours the principles of the
                    <hi rend="italic">Novum</hi><hi rend="italic">Organum.</hi> So earnest was his
                    devotion to Bacon that for many years he could not be persuaded to read the
                    works of Descartes, lest he should be tempted out of his chosen path. His
                    strength lay in the patient research and observation of facts. He did not
                    display that power of divination of their meaning and of detection of their
                    relations which is the characteristic of genius. His desire was to contribute by
                    his researches, in the true spirit of the Baconian philosophy, to the service of
                    man’s life; and in this he had a large measure of success. The same practical
                    aim is apparent in his theological writings. He was no controversialist, and
                    does not appear to have taken much, if any interest in the great political and
                    religious movements of his day. About 1690 his health began seriously to fail,
                    and he was obliged gradually to withdraw from his public engagements. He
                    discontinued the communication of memoirs of new discoveries to the Royal
                    Society, resigned the post which he had long held of governor of the corporation
                    for propagating the Gospel in New England, and announced by public advertisement
                    his intention no longer to receive visits. The “retired leisure” which he thus
                    secured was devoted to important chemical investigations, the account of which
                    he left “as a kind of hermetic legacy to the studious disciples of that art.”
                    His health became worse in 1691. On the 23d of December of this year his sister,
                    Lady Ranelagh, with whom he had lived for more than twenty years, died; and a
                    week later, December 30, Boyle died himself. His remains were interred in the
                    churchyard of St Martin’s in the Fields, and his funeral sermon was preached by
                    his friend Dr Burnet, bishop of Salisbury, author of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >History of the Reformation.</hi> By his will he founded and endowed the “Boyle
                    Lectures,” the purpose of which is the demonstration of the truth of the
                    Christian religion against atheists, theists, pagans, Jews, and Mahometans.</p>
                <p>It is unnecessary to do more than enumerate the more important publications of
                    this laborious investigator. His first work has already been mentioned. It was
                    followed, in 1662, by <hi rend="italic">The Sceptical Chemist,</hi> subsequently
                    reprinted with additions. His <hi rend="italic">Considerations touching the
                    Usefulness of Experimental Natural Philosophy</hi> appeared in 1663, and was
                    followed by a second part in 1671. His <hi rend="italic">Experiments and
                    Considerations upon colours, with Observations on a Diamond that Shines in the
                    Dark,</hi> also appeared in 1663—a treatise which broke ground on a theme
                    afterwards more profoundly treated by Newton.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n226/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0226-0185"/>
                <p>His next scientific work was entitled, <hi rend="italic">New Experiments and
                    Observations upon Cold</hi> (1665). This was followed by the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Origin of Forms and Qualities according to the Corpuscular Philosophy</hi>
                    (1666); a continuation of his first work on the air (1669); <hi rend="italic"
                    >Tracts about the Cosmical Qualities of things, the Temperature of the
                    Subterraneous Regions, and the Bottom of the Sea</hi> (1669), a volume which
                    gave rise to much discussion, its statements being founded on experiment; <hi
                    rend="italic">Origin and Virtues of Gems</hi> (1672); <hi rend="italic">Essays
                    on the Subtilty and Determinate Nature of Effluvia</hi> (1673); tracts on the
                    <hi rend="italic">Saltness of the Sea,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Moisture of
                    the Air,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Natural and Preternatural State of Bodies,
                    Cold, Hidden Qualities of the Air, Celestial Magnets, Hobbes’s Problem of a
                    Vacuum,</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Cause of Attraction and Suction</hi>
                    (1674); <hi rend="italic">Experiments and Notes about the Mechanical Origin or
                    Prodτιxtion of Particular Qualities,</hi> including a discourse on electricity
                    (1676); the <hi rend="italic">Aerial</hi><hi rend="italic">Noctiluca,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">or some neιo Phenomena., and a Process of a Factitious
                    Self-shining Substance</hi> (1680); <hi rend="italic">New Experiments and
                    Observations upon the Icy</hi><hi rend="italic">Noctiluca,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >to which is added a Chemical Paradox</hi> (1682); a further continuation of his
                    first work on the air (1682); <hi rend="italic">Memoirs for the History of Human
                    Blood</hi> (1684); <hi rend="italic">Short Memoirs for the Natural Experimental
                    History of Mineral Waters</hi> (1685); <hi rend="italic">Medicina</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Hydrostatica {169Q)</hi>; and <hi rend="italic">Experimenta et
                    Observationes</hi><hi rend="italic">Physicae</hi> (1691). Of his religious and
                    theological writings we may mention, <hi rend="italic">An Essay on
                    Scripture,</hi> of which one portion was published in 1663, and the whole at a
                    later date by his friend Sir Peter Pett; <hi rend="italic">Occasional
                    Reflections upon several Subjects</hi> (1665), a strange medley of trivialities
                    and grave thoughts, amusing, yet not wholly unwise, which was assailed and
                    ridiculed by Dean Swift in <hi rend="italic">A Pious Meditation upon a
                    Broomstick, in the Style of the Honourable Mr Boyle,</hi> and by Butler in <hi
                    rend="italic">An Occasional Reflection on Dr Charlton’s feeling a Dog's Pulse at
                    Gresham College</hi> (a neat reprint of the <hi rend="italic">Occasional
                    Reflections</hi> was published at Oxford in 1848); <hi rend="italic">The
                    Excellency of Theology, compared with Philosophy,</hi> written in the year of
                    the Great Plague, but not published till 1673; <hi rend="italic">Considerations
                    about the Reconcilablencss of Reason and Religion, with a Discourse about the
                    Possibility of the Resurrection</hi> (1655); <hi rend="italic">A Discourse of
                    Things above Reason, inquiring whether a Philosopher should admit any such</hi>
                    (1681); a tract on the <hi rend="italic">High Veneration Man's Intellect owes to
                    God</hi> (1685); <hi rend="italic">A Free Inquiry into the vulgarly received
                    notion of Nature</hi> (1686); and <hi rend="italic">The Christian Virtuoso</hi>
                    (1690). Several other works appeared after his death, and among these were— <hi
                    rend="italic">The General History of the Air designed and begun;</hi> an account
                    of his making the phosphorus, September 30, 1680; and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Medicinal Experiments.</hi> An incomplete edition of Boyle’s works appeared at
                    Geneva some years before his death. A useful classified abridgment was published
                    by Dr Peter Shaw, editor of an abridgment of Bacon’s Philosophical Works. The
                    first complete edition was that of Dr Birch, which appeared, with a Life of the
                    author, in 5 vols, folio, in 1744. Another complete edition was issued in 6
                    vols. 4to, in 1772. A portrait of Boyle, by Kerse-boom, which is in the
                    possession of the Royal Society, formed part of the National Portrait Exhibition
                    at South Kensington in 1866. Boyle bequeathed his natural history collections to
                    the Royal Society.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
