<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0625-0564-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BURNEY, Charles (9th edition, volume 4, page
                    564)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2ch0v">Music</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4930p22j">Organists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xn21">Sonata</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1030269">Music</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1030814">Musicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1047772">Organists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n625/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BURNEY, <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles</hi></label>, Doctor of
                    Music (1726-1814), was born in the ancient city of Shrewsbury, the capital of
                    Shropshire, on the 7th of April 1726. He received his earlier education at the
                    excellent free school of that city, and was afterwards sent to the public school
                    at Chester. His first music master was Mr Baker, organist of Chester Cathedral,
                    and a pupil of Dr John Blow. Returning to Shrewsbury when about fifteen years
                    old, he continued his musical studies for three years under his half-brother, Mr
                    James Burney, organist of St Mary’s Church, and was then sent to London as a
                    pupil of the celebrated Dr Arne, with whom he remained three years. In 1749 he
                    was appointed organist of a church in the city, with a salary of £30 a year; and
                    he was also engaged as conductor of a concert established at the King’s Arms,
                    Cornhill. In that year and the next he composed the music of three dramas for
                    Drury Lane theatre— <hi rend="italic">Alfred, Robin Hood,</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Queen Mab.</hi> Being threatened with a pulmonary affection he
                    went, on the advice of his physician, in 1751 to Lynn, in Norfolk, where he was
                    elected organist, with an annual salary of £100, and where he resided for the
                    next nine years. During that time he began to entertain the idea of writing a
                    general history of music. In 1760 he returned to London in good health, and with
                    a young family; the eldest of whom, a girl of eight years of age, surprised the
                    public by her attainments as a harpsichord player. In 1766 he produced, at Drury
                    lane, a free English version and adaptation of J. J. Rousseau’s operetta <hi
                    rend="italic">Le</hi><hi rend="italic">Devin du Village,</hi> under the title of
                    <hi rend="italic">The Cunning Man,</hi> which was favourably received. The
                    university of Oxford conferred <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n626/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0626-0565"/> upon him, on 23d June 1769, the degrees of
                    bachelor and doctor of music, on which occasion he presided at the performance
                    of his exercise for these degrees. This consisted of an anthem, with an
                    overture, solos, recitatives, and choruses, accompanied by instruments, besides
                    a vocal anthem in eight parts, which was not performed. His friend, C. P. E.
                    Bach, requested a copy of this exercise, and had it performed in St Catharine’s
                    Church at Hamburg, under his own direction, in 1773. It was repeatedly performed
                    at Oxford, “after it had fufilled its original destination,” as Burney tells us
                    <hi rend="italic">(Hist. of Music,</hi> vol. iii. p. 329); and he apologizes as
                    follows for saying so much about it :—“It is hoped that the reader will pardon
                    this <hi rend="italic">egotism,</hi> which has been extorted from me by
                    occasional and sinister assertions, ‘that I neither liked nor had studied church
                    music.’” <hi rend="italic">(Ibid).</hi> In 1769 he published <hi rend="italic"
                    >An Essay towards a History of Comets.</hi> Amidst his various professional
                    avocations, Burney never lost sight of his favourite object,—his <hi
                    rend="italic">History of Music,—</hi> and therefore resolved to travel abroad
                    for the purpose of collecting materials that could not be found in Great
                    Britain. Accordingly, he left London in June 1770, furnished with numerous
                    letters of introduction, and proceeded to Paris, and thence to Geneva, Turin,
                    and the principal cities of Italy. The results of his observations he published
                    in <hi rend="italic">The Present State of Music in France and Italy</hi> (1 vol.
                    8vo, London, 1771). Dr Johnson thought so well of this work, that, alluding to
                    his own <hi rend="italic">Journey to the Western Islands of Scotland,</hi> he
                    said, “I had that clever dog Burney’s Musical Tour in my eye.” In July 1772
                    Burney again visited the Continent, to collect further materials, and, after his
                    return to London, published his tour under the title of <hi rend="italic">The
                    Present State of Music in Germany, the Netherlands, and United Provinces</hi> (2
                    vols. 8vo, London, 1773). In 1773 he was chosen a Fellow of the Royal Society of
                    London. In 1776 appeared the first volume (in 4to) of his long-projected <hi
                    rend="italic">History of Music;</hi> in 1782 the second volume; and in 1789 the
                    third and fourth. Though severely criticised by Forkel in Germany and by the
                    Spanish ex-Jesuit, Requeno, who, in his Italian work <hi rend="italic">Saggj sul
                    Ristabilimento dell' Arte Armonica de' Greci e Romani Cantori,</hi> Parma, 1798
                    (2 vols. 8vo), attacks Burney’s account of the ancient Greek music, and calls
                    him <hi rend="italic">lo scompigliato Burney,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">History
                    of Music</hi> was generally recognized as possessing great merit. The least
                    satisfactory volume is the fourth, the treatment of Handel and Bach being quite
                    inadequate. Burney’s first Tour was translated into German by Ebeling, and
                    printed at Hamburg in 1772; and his second Tour, translated into German by Bode,
                    was published at Hamburg in 1773. A Dutch translation of his second Tour, with
                    notes by J. W. Lustig, organist at Groningen, was published there in 1786 The
                    Dissertation on the Music of the Ancients, in the first volume of Burney’s <hi
                    rend="italic">History,</hi> was translated into German by J. J. Eschenburg, and
                    printed at Leipsic, 1781. Burney derived much aid from the first two volumes of
                    Padre Martini’s very learned <hi rend="italic">Storia</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >della</hi><hi rend="italic">Musica,</hi> Bologna, 1757-1770. One cannot but
                    admire his persevering industry, and his sacrifices of time, money and personal
                    comfort, in collecting and preparing materials for his <hi rend="italic"
                    >History;</hi> and few will be disposed to condemn severely errors and
                    oversights in a work of such extent and difficulty. In 1779 he wrote for the
                    Royal Society an account of the infant Crotch, whose remarkable musical talent
                    excited so much attention at that time In 1784 he published, with an Italian
                    titlepage, the music annually performed in the Pope’s chapel at Rome during
                    Passion Week. In 1785 he published, for the benefit of the Musical Fund, an
                    account of the first commemoration of Handel in Westminster Abbey in the
                    preceding year, with an excellent life of Handel. In 1796 he published <hi
                    rend="italic">Memoirs and Letters of Metastasio,</hi> 3 vols. 8vo. Towards the
                    close of his life, Burney contributed to the Rev. Dr Rees’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cyclopaedia</hi> all the musical articles not belonging to the department of
                    Natural Philosophy and Mathematics. For these articles he received £1000, which
                    seems a remarkable remuneration, considering that most of his materials were
                    merely transcribed from his own <hi rend="italic">History of Music.</hi> In
                    1789, through the treasury influence of his friend Edmund Burke, he was
                    appointed organist to the chapel of Chelsea Hospital, and he resided in the
                    hospital for the remainder of his life. He was made a member of the Institute of
                    France, and nominated a correspondent in the class of the Fine Arts, in the year
                    1810. He died at Chelsea College on the 12th of April 1814, and was interred in
                    the burying-ground of the college on the 20th of the same month.</p>
                <p>Burney had a wide circle of acquaintance among the distinguished artists and
                    literary men of his day. At one time he thought of writing a life of his friend
                    Dr Samuel Johnson; but he retired before the crowd of biographers who rushed
                    into that field. His character in private as well as public life appears to have
                    been very amiable and exemplary. Dr Burney’s eldest son, James, was a
                    distinguished officer in the royal navy, and died a rear-admiral in 1821. He
                    published several works of merit. A notice of his second son, the Rev. Charles
                    Burney, D.D., an eminent Greek scholar, will be found below, and of his second
                    daughter Frances (Madame D’Arblay) under the heading <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >D’Arblay.</hi> The <hi rend="italic">Diary and Letters</hi> of Madame D’Arblay
                    contain many minute and interesting particulars of her father’s public and
                    private life, and of his friends and contemporaries. A life of her father, by
                    Madame D’Arblay, appeared in 1832.</p>
                <p>Besides the operatic music above mentioned, Burney’s known compositions consist
                    of—1. <hi rend="italic">Six Sonatas for the harpsichord;</hi> 2. <hi
                    rend="italic">Two Sonatas for the harp or piano, with accompaniments for violin
                    and violoncello;</hi> 3. <hi rend="italic">Sonatas for two violins and a bass:
                    two sets;</hi> 4. <hi rend="italic">Six Lessons for the harpsichord;</hi> 5. <hi
                    rend="italic">Six Duets for two German flutes;</hi> 6. <hi rend="italic">Three
                    Concertos for the harpsichord;</hi> 7. <hi rend="italic">Six concert pieces with
                    an in-trodτuΛιon and fugue for the organ;</hi> 8. <hi rend="italic">Six
                    Concertos for the violin, &amp;</hi> c., <hi rend="italic">in eight parts;</hi>
                    9. <hi rend="italic">Two Sonatas for pianoforte, violin, and violoncello;</hi>
                    10. <hi rend="italic">A Cantata, Ac.;</hi> 11. <hi rend="italic">Anthems,
                    Ac.;</hi> 12. <hi rend="italic">XII. Canzonetti a due voci in</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Canone,</hi><hi rend="italic">poesia dell' Abate
                    Metastasio.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
