<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0212-0171-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BOULOGNE SUR MER (9th edition, volume 4, page
                    171)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1028427">Mouth</term>
                    <term ref="fast:827721">Barracks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1030128">Museums</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100369">Rooms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:926361">Fishes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821510">Australians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821509">Australianisms</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94c35">Extents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q52fm3g">Ports</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f39x">Mouth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16q19">Barracks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s53t">Normans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g68c">Virginal</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44m91m0x">Virginity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210572">Iceland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n212/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BOULOGNE SUR MER</label>, a fortified seaport of France, and
                    the chief town of an arrondissement in Pas-de-Calais, is situated on the shore
                    of the English Channel at the mouth of the River Liane (anciently Elna), in 50°
                    44' N. lat. and l <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> 36' E. long., 157 miles from
                    Paris by railway and 28 from Folkestone, Kent. It consists of two parts, the
                    High or Old Town and the Lower or New Town. The former, situated on the top of
                    the bill, is of comparatively small extent, and forms almost a parallelogram,
                    surrounded by ramparts of the 15th century, and entered by ancient gateways. In
                    this part are the Palais de Justice, the Chateau, the cathedral, and the Hotel
                    de Ville,—the last built in 1774,—and the belfry tower of the 13th century is in
                    the immediate neighbourhood. In the Chateau, now used as barracks, the Emperor
                    Napoleon III. was confined after his famous attempt to effect a landing in 1840.
                    At some distance north-west stands the cathedral church of Notro <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n213/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0213-0172"/> Dame, built (1827-1866) on the site of an old
                    building destroyed in the Revolution, having underneath an extensive crypt which
                    still remains. The New Town extends from the foot of the hill to the harbour and
                    along the shore, and contains several good streets, some of which are, however,
                    very steep. A main street, named successively Rue de la Lampe, St Nicholas, and
                    Grande Rue, extends from the bridge across the Liane (near the railway station)
                    to the promenade by the side of the ramparts and the Hôtel de Ville. This is
                    intersected first by the shoreway named Quai de la Flotille, Quai de la
                    Victoire, &amp;c. (where there are numerous hotels), and further back by the Rue
                    Napoléon and Rue Royale, the principal business part of the town, and where the
                    best shops are situated. The principal buildings comprise a museum, formerly the
                    great seminary, a hospital, a theatre, an elegant <hi rend="italic"
                    >établissement</hi> (opened in 1863, containing ball-room, reading-room,
                    &amp;c.), a custom-house, barracks, various churches and convents, and a
                    fish-market. Connected with the museum is a public library with 30,000 volumes
                    and a large number of very valuable manuscripts, many of them richly
                    illuminated. Boulogne has for a long time been one of the most Anglicized of
                    French cities; and in the tourist season a continuous stream of English
                    travellers reach the Continent at this point. There is regular steamboat service
                    between the port and Folkestone, the average passage occupying 2∣ hours, or
                    about three-quarters of an hour longer than from Calais to Dover. There are two
                    English chapels in the town, and numerous boarding-schools intended for English
                    pupils. Churchill, who died while on a visit to his friend Wilkes, in 1765, is
                    buried in the cemetery, and the house is pointed out where Thomas Campbell
                    expired in 1843. The shore is lined with extensive flat sands, where bathing is
                    facilitated by the use of machines. Among the objects of interest in the
                    neighbourhood the most remarkable is the Napoleon column or Colonne de la Grande
                    Armée, erected on the high ground above the town, in honour of Napoleon L, on
                    occasion of the projected invasion of England, for which he here made great
                    preparations. The pillar, which is of the Doric order, 166 feet high, is
                    surmounted by a statue of the emperor by Bosio. Though commenced in 1804, the
                    monument was not completed till 1841. Ou the edge of the cliff to the east of
                    the port are some rude brick remains of an old building called Tour d’Ordre,
                    said to be the ruins of a tower built by Caligula at the time of his intended
                    invasion of Britain. The entrance to the harbour of Boulogne, which is tidal, is
                    formed by two long piers running out from the mouth of the river, and serving
                    during fine weather as excellent promenades. On the western side is the basin
                    excavated by Napoleon for his flotilla of flat-bottomed boats in 1804. A large
                    wet dock, constructed at a cost of upwards of £250,000, was opened iu 1872, and
                    adds greatly to the facilities of the port, its area being 17 acres and the
                    length of its quay-wall 1150 yards. The depth of water in the harbour is 23 feet
                    at spring-tide and nearly 20 at neap-tide; in the sluice of the floating basin
                    the numbers are 29 j and 23⅜ respectively. The foreign commerce of Boulogne,
                    which is almost wholly carried on in British ships, consists chiefly in the
                    importation of manufactured goods, jute, silk, Australian wool, coal, machinery,
                    hardwares, paper-hangings, malt, beer, and chemicals; and the exportation of
                    wine, brandy, eggs, artificial flowers, haberdashery, and musical instruments.
                    The total value of the exports in 1871 was £12,709,675, and of the imports
                    £11,762,500. How rapid the development of the commerce with Britain has been may
                    be seen from the fact, that while in 1840 the British sailing vessels thus
                    engaged amounted only to 66, and the steam-ships to 678, in 1860 the
                    corresponding numbers were 341 and 863, and in 1871, 541 and 1061. In the extent
                    and value of its fisheries Boulogne is exceeded by no seaport in France. The
                    most important branch is the herring-fishery, which is prosecuted northwards
                    along the shores of Scotland; next in value is the mackerel fishery, and next
                    again the Iceland cod. Large quantities of fresh fish are transmitted to Paris
                    by railway, but an abundant supply is reserved to the town itself. The fishermen
                    live for the most part in a separate quarter called La Beurière. Among the
                    numerous industrial establishments in Boulogne and its environs may be mentioned
                    several foundries, with blastfurnaces, cement-manufactories, flax-mills, steam
                    saw-mills, steel-pen manufactories, carriage-works, tile-works, and a
                    fishing-net factory. Shipbuilding is also carried on to some extent. The
                    population of the town, which in 1821 was 16,607, amounted by the census of 1872
                    to 39,700.</p>
                <p>Boulogne is usually, though on somewhat dubious grounds, identified with the <hi
                    rend="italic">Gesoriacum</hi> of the Romans. At an early period it began to be
                    known as <hi rend="italic">Bononia,</hi> a name which has been gradually
                    modified into the present form. The town w as destroyed by the Normans in 882,
                    but restored about 912. From about that time till 1477 it was the head of a
                    separate countship, which was united to the crown of France by Louis XL, who
                    ingeniously recognized the Holy Virgin as the superior, and declared himself her
                    vassal. In 1544 Henry VIII.—more fortunate in this than Henry III. had been in
                    1347—took the town by siege; but it was restored to France in the following
                    reign.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
