<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0413-0366-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BRONZE (9th edition, volume 4, page 366)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4t727j1r">Copper</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m32nk3w">Tin</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45h7c14w">Tinning</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zz70">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k14n">Alloys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:878331">Copper</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1151376">Tinning</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1151272">Tin</term>
                    <term ref="fast:979089">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="fast:805706">Alloys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1030128">Museums</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916316">Etruscans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n413/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BRONZE</label> is an alloy formed wholly or chiefly of copper
                    and tin, in variable proportions. It has been used from a very early period.
                    Archaeologists distinguish a <hi rend="italic">bronze age</hi> in prehistoric
                    times in Western Europe (intermediate between those of stone and iron),
                    characterized by a general U3β of the alloy for cutting instruments and other
                    objects. The “brass” of the Bible was probably of the nature of bronze. The use
                    of bronze in early times is noticed more particularly below.</p>
                <p>The addition of tin to copper gives rise to a product more fusible than copper,
                    and thus better suited for casting. The alloy is also harder and less malleable.
                    The proportions in which copper and tin are combined to make bronze vary
                    according to the object for which the alloy is designed. With about 7 parts
                    copper to 1 part tin, bronze is very hard, brittle, and sonorous. Soft bronze,
                    again, which bears drifting, rolling, and drawing, is generally composed of 16
                    copper to 1 tin; while a flexible tenacious alloy, good for nails and bolts, is
                    made of 20 copper to 1 tin. In preparing bronze for statues,bas-reliefs,
                    &amp;c., the qualities chiefly looked at are fusibility and hardness, also
                    readiness to acquire a fine patina on exposure, though it appears this may be
                    acquired by bronzes differing widely in composition. A common statue bronze is
                    formed of copper 80, tin 20. Bellmetal, for large bells, is generally made with
                    about 3 parts copper to 1 part tin; for house bells, 4 copper to 1 tin. The
                    bronze of bells (as of various other objects) sometimes contains a little zinc,
                    lead, &amp;c., in addition to the primary ingredients. The Chinese <hi
                    rend="italic">tam tarns</hi> or <hi rend="italic">gongs,</hi> are made of bronze
                    forged by the hammer; they contain about 20 per cent, tin, the rest copper only.
                    The secret of their manufacture seems to have been revealed by MM. Julien and
                    Champion, who find that a bronze of this nature, though at the common
                    temperature brittle as glass, may, at a dull red heat, be forged and beaten out
                    as easily as soft tin. The speculum metal employed in telescopes is of 2 copper
                    to 1 tin; andon the other hand, with larger proportions of copper, we have an
                    alloy suitable for machinery bearings, and also for medals, 8 copper to 1 tin;
                    another for brass ordnance or bronze cannon, 9 copper to 1 tin; another for
                    mathematical instruments, 12 copper to 1 tin, &amp;c. The hardness and
                    resistance to oxidation of bronze fit it admirably for coins, and many ancient
                    bronze coins have come to us but little deteriorated, though buried for ages in
                    damp soil, or immersed in water. The composition of the present bronze British
                    coinage is (in 100 parts) 95 copper, 4 tin, 1 zinc.</p>
                <p>A few years ago some very beautiful Chinese and Japanese bronzes were exhibited
                    in Paris, remarkable chiefly for the dead black colour of their patina. From
                    analyses by Μ. Morin it appeared that they contained a large proportion of lead,
                    the average composition being copper 80 parts, lead 10, tin 4, zinc 2, and the
                    remaining four parts consisting of iron, nickel, arsenic, silver, and gold.
                    According to Μ. Christofle, lead is not essential for production of a fine black
                    patina; and it renders the alloy brittle. Bronze can be covered with a black,
                    red, brown, or green patina, as desired, by suitable oxidation or
                    sulphurization.</p>
                <p>Some important researches on bronze for field-guns have lately been made by
                    Colonel Uchatius of Vienna; and the <hi rend="italic">steel bronze</hi> he
                    produces is said to be quite equal to steel in hardness, homogeneousness,
                    resistance, and other qualities; while it is less affected by atmospheric
                    agency, and less costly. He casts the bronze (which contains 8 per cent, tin,
                    the rest copper) in a cast-iron ingot mould, with a core of wrought-copper 50
                    mm. in diameter. Then after boring out the hollow ingot to a diameter of 80 mm.
                    he forces through it a series of six conical pistons of hardened steel, slightly
                    larger in diameter than the bore. The interior is then excessively hard and
                    ready for rifling. The hardness, elasticity, and solidity diminish from within
                    outwards. These new bronze guns have been found to bear several hundred
                    discharges successively without the slightest apparent deformation or other
                    injury.</p>
                <p>It is only of late years that the changes produced in bronze by addition of
                    phosphorus have been scientifically investigated; and from experiments by Messrs
                    Montefiore, Künzel, Kirkaldy, and others, <hi rend="italic">phosphor bronze</hi>
                    is proved to have great superiority to ordinary bronze in tenacity, elasticity,
                    and tensile strength (being to it much what.steel is to wrought iron). The
                    presence of oxides in ordinary bronze accounts for its possessing these
                    qualities in less degree, and phosphorus increases them by reduction of the
                    metal. Phosphor bronze is further greatly improved in tensile strength by being
                    drawn into wire or rolled into sheets; and it resists the action of sea-water
                    much better than copper. Such a substance cannot fail to find many important
                    applications, military, industrial, and domestic. In virtue of its reducing
                    properties, we may add, phosphor bronze can be platinized better than any other
                    metal.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n414/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0414-0367"/>
                <p>The alloy known as <hi rend="italic">aluminium bronze</hi> is one endowed with
                    great strength, malleability, and ductility. It is formed of 10 parts aluminium
                    and 90 of copper.</p>
                <p>In the melting of ordinary bronze, reverberatory furnaces have long been used, as
                    rapid fusion is desirable in order to prevent loss of tin, zinc, or lead by
                    oxidation. Bellfounders often use dome-topped furnaces, as their alloy does not
                    require so intense a heat for fusion; but there is some waste of material with
                    these. The copper is melted first, and covered with small charcoal or coke; and
                    the tin is rapidly thrust down to the bottom of the melted mass. After stirring,
                    the alloy is poured into the moulds, in which the cooling should be as rapid as
                    possible. Sometimes pressure is applied during cooling, in order to make the
                    cast free from pores.</p>
                <p>In the old method of bronze casting, known as the <hi rend="italic">cire</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">perdue,</hi> wax is first used for the thickness of the statue
                    (between core and mould, which are of baked clay), and is melted and run off
                    before the metal is poured in,—the core and mould being held apart by stays of
                    iron wire. In the present day large works are never cast in one piece, but in
                    several, which are afterwards united by heating and application of fused metal.
                    A model is made in plaster, and a piece mould of Caen sand, about 1⅜ or 2 inches
                    thick, made round it, the sizes of the pieces being determined by the shape and
                    character of the portions they occupy. These pieces are backed with plaster of
                    Paris to about a foot in thickness, with indentations cut in their horizontal
                    thickness, into which the succeeding portion of the mould fits. The mould is
                    then taken to pieces, dried, and rebuilt in the casting-pit. It is then filled
                    with core-composition in a liquid state, and when this is sufficiently hardened,
                    again taken to pieces. The core thus obtained is thoroughly dried, and reduced
                    in size by scraping away as much of the material as would represent the
                    thickness of the metal to be cast. This done, the mould is again built up over
                    the core, and the pit filled, &lt;fcc., as in the other process. The statue is
                    completed after its removal from the mould by cutting off the jets, removing
                    roughnesses where they occur, and giving greater sharpness to the details when
                    necessary.</p>
                <p>Statues and various ornamental objects may also be manufactured by the process of
                    electro-deposition from a metallic solution; and some excellent results have
                    been obtained in this way by Oudry, Christofle, Elkington, and others. While the
                    method offers some advantages in regard to cheapness, lightness, &lt;fcc., of
                    the products, the bronzes thus produced are not so hard and durable as those got
                    by casting, and are thus less suited for exposure.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Bronzing</hi> is the process by which a bronze-like surface is
                    produced on objects made of metal, plaster, wood, or other material. It may be
                    done variously. The green bronze colour is sometimes produced on metal with
                    vinegar alone, or dilute nitric acid, or sal-ammoniac. To give an antique
                    appearance to newly made articles of bronze or brass, it is recommended to
                    dissolve three-quarters of an ounce of sal-ammoniac and a drachm and a half of
                    binoxalate of potash (salt of sorrel) in a quart of vinegar, moisten a soft rag
                    or brush with the solution, and rub over the clean bright metal till its surface
                    becomes quite dry through the friction. This process should be repeated several
                    times, and the object should be kept a little warm. With a solution of chloride
                    of platinum (which is, however, an expensive liquid) almost any colour can be
                    imparted to copper, brass, iron, or new bronze, according to the degree of
                    dilution and number of applications. The following solution is suitable for
                    bronzing coins and medals :—Two parts of verdigris and one part of sal-ammoniac
                    are dissolved in vinegar, the solution is boiled, skimmed, and diluted with
                    water till it has only a weak metallic taste, and on further dilution lets fall
                    no precipitate. This solution is made to boil briskly and poured on the objects.
                    These are well washed with clean water and then lacquered.</p>
                <p>Objects of cast-iron may be made to assume a fine bronze appearance by being
                    coated with a very thin layer of vegetable oil, and then placed in a drying
                    oven, the tempera ture being such that oxidation of the iron and decomposition
                    of the oil take place simultaneously. Another mode of bronzing iron (lately
                    recommended by Weiskopf) is with a solution of one part sylvate of silver in
                    twenty parts of oil of lavender. The object is lightly coated with this, and
                    warmed rapidly up to 302° C. For bronzing tin or white metal a solution may be
                    used consisting of 1 oz. salammoniac, ⅜ oz. alum, and ⅜ oz. arsenic, dissolved
                    in 1 pint of strong vinegar.</p>
                <p>A good method of bronzing wood, porcelain, stoneware, composition picture and
                    looking-glass frames, &lt;fcc., is first to coat the article with a thin
                    solution of water glass, using a soft brush, Bronze powder is then dusted on,
                    and any excess not adherent is knocked off by a few gentle taps. The article is
                    next heated to dry the silicate, and the bronze becomes firmly attached. Bronze
                    powders are prepared of many different shades. In Messrs Brandeis’s process the
                    alloy used (generally copper-zinc) is laminated into very fine leaves, which are
                    then ground. The powder is washed out and dried, and by revolving in a box,
                    which contains some mineral varnish, the particles receive a coating of the
                    varnish. Bronze powders are also prepared from leaf gold ground with honey on a
                    stone, mosaic gold ground with bone ashes, compounds of tungsten and soda, and
                    in other ways.</p>
                <p>As regards cleansing of bronze statues.that have become coated with dirt in large
                    towns, it has been found that a dilute solution of caustic alkalies removes the
                    overlying dirt and allows the green patina to become visible. Where the metal
                    was not originally oxidized, the alkali simply cleanses it and does not promote
                    any formation of green rust. An occasional rubbing with oil (all excess being
                    carefully removed) is also found to preserve a fine bronze surface. The shining
                    brown colour of gun barrels or other arms, is sometimes imparted by first
                    producing a very thin uniform film of oxide or rust on the iron, <hi
                    rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> with .vapour of muriatic acid, and giving a gloss to
                    the surface by rubbing wax over it, or coating it with a shellac varnish. But
                    the most common material for browning is the butter or chloride of antimony,
                    sometimes called <hi rend="italic">bronzing-salt.</hi> It is mixed with olive
                    oil and rubbed on the iron, which is slightly heated. A little aquafortis is
                    then rubbed on to quicken the operation; the barrel is then cleaned, washed with
                    water, dried and polished, either with a steel burnisher, or by rubbing with
                    white wax, or is varnished with a very weak solution of shellac and spirit of
                    wine. (See Ure’s <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of Arts,</hi> &amp;c.)</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Greek and Roman Bronze.</hi></p>
                <p>The bronze (Greek, χαλκός; Latin, <hi rend="italic">oes)</hi> of <hi
                    rend="italic">classical antiquity</hi> consisted chiefly of copper, with an
                    alloy of one or more of the following metals, zinc, tin, lead, and silver, the
                    quantity and the character of the alloy changing as times changed, or as was
                    required for different purposes. Among existing bronze remains the copper is
                    found to vary from 67 to 95 per cent. At present the only valuable results which
                    we possess are derived from the analysis of coins (Von Bibra, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Die</hi><hi rend="italic">Bronzen und</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Kupferlegirungen</hi><hi rend="italic">der alten und ältesten Völker,</hi>
                    Erlangen, 1869), from which it appears that for their, bronze coins the Greeks
                    adhered to an alloy of copper and tin till 400 B.c., after which time they used
                    also lead with increasing frequency. Silver is rare in their bronze coins. The
                    Romans also used lead as an alloy in their bronze coins, but gradually reduced
                    the <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n415/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0415-0368"/> quantity, and under Caligula, Nero, Vespasian,
                    and Domitian, coined pure copper coins; afterwards they reverted to the mixture
                    of lead. So far the words χαλκό? and <hi rend="italic">oes</hi> may be
                    translated as bronze. Originally, no doubt, χαλκό? was the name for pure copper.
                    It is so employed by Homer, who calls it <hi rend="italic">epvθpo&lt;s</hi>
                    (red), <hi rend="italic">αίθωψ</hi> (glittering), <hi rend="italic">φαχννός</hi>
                    (shining), terms which apply only to copper. But instead of its following from
                    this that the process of alloying copper with other metals was not practised
                    then, or was unknown to the poet, the contrary would seem to be the case from
                    the passage <hi rend="italic">(Iliad,</hi> xviii. 474) where he describes
                    Hephaestus as throwing into his furnace, copper, tin, silver, and gold, to make
                    the shield of Achilles, so that it is not always possible to know whether when
                    he uses the word χαλκό? he means copper pure or alloyed. Still more difficult is
                    it to make this distinction when we read of the mythical Dactyls of Ida in Crete
                    or the Telchines or Cyclopes being acquainted with the smelting of χαλκό?. It is
                    not, however, likely that later Greek writers, who knew bronze in its true
                    sense, and called it χαλκό?, would have employed this word without qualification
                    to objects which they had seen unless they had meant it to be taken as bronze.
                    When Pausanias (iii. 17, 6) speaks of a statue, one of the oldest figures he had
                    seen of this material, made of separate pieces fastened together with nails, we
                    understand him to mean literally bronze, the more readily since there exist very
                    early figures and utensils of bronze so made. The earliest employment of bronze
                    for artistic purposes was to hammer it out in thin plates and fasten them
                    together with nails. This process was called <hi rend="italic">sphyrelaton.</hi>
                    The next stage was casting, in connection with which the earliest Greek artists
                    of fame are Theodorus and Rhcecus of Samos (Pausanias, viii. 14, 8, and x. 38,
                    5). It has been supposed that their merit consisted in introducing the process
                    of casting statues hollow, that is, with an inner core of some material which
                    could afterwards be removed and leave the figure light, less costly, and no less
                    durable. There are remains of Assyrian bronze, probably older than the time of
                    Theodorus and Rhcecus, cast with an inner core of iron; and there is also in the
                    British Museum an early Etruscan statuette from Sessa on the Volturno, with a
                    core of this metal, which from its being split down the side, owing to the
                    expansion of the iron, shows how unserviceable the iron was for this purpose.
                    Obviously the power of casting in bronze, whether solid or hollow, was a very
                    great gain to sculptors, whose models worked in the clay with the rapidity of
                    their inspiration could thus be accurately and at once reproduced. The
                    difficulty and expense of the process must have been against it as compared with
                    marble; yet it was frequently employed, and in the case of colossal statues it
                    had no rival. Of these the Colossus of Rhodes —a figure of the sun-god Helios,
                    said to have been 70 cubits high—was an example of the utmost that art could do
                    with bronze. It was thrown down by an earthquake after standing fifty-six years.
                    A statue of Zeus at Tarentum by Lysippus was 40 cubits high, and though it could
                    be moved with a touch of the hand, yet it resisted the force of storms by means
                    of a support at the point of the greatest stress. The oldest seat of
                    bronze-founding, at least to any extent, was the island of Delos, and next to
                    that the island of Aegina, and yet copper does not appear to have been found in
                    either. Between the two there existed a rivalry in the time of the sculptors
                    Myron and Polycletus, of whom the former used the bronze of Delos, the latter
                    that of Aegina. More celebrated than either was the bronze of Corinth, which
                    some believed to have been first obtained by the melting together of statues of
                    ordinary bronze, gold, and silver at the burning of that town. Pliny says that
                    it consisted of gold, silver, and copper, and was considered more precious than
                    silver and little less valuable than gold.</p>
                <p>There were three kinds of it—one white, having almost the appearance of silver,
                    in which silver predominated; another yellow, because of the great quantity of
                    gold in it; and a third in which all three metals were equally represented. But
                    the Corinthian bronze was used rather for drinking cups and utensils than for
                    statues. The process of casting statues as given by Pliny was to bring the mass
                    of copper to a liquid state, and then to throw into it a third part of old
                    bronze and 12⅜ per cent, of <hi rend="italic">plumbum,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >argentarium,</hi><hi rend="italic">ι.e.,</hi> tin and lead in equal parts.</p>
                <p>Of the vast number of bronze statues by ancient sculptors nothing beyond a few
                    fragments remain; but if the colossal bronze head of Venus in the British Museum
                    be taken as a typical example, it will show with what fineness and thinness
                    those figures were cast; or, again, as an instance of tho quality of Greek
                    bronze we may take the bronzes of Siris, also in the British Museum, on which a
                    very thin plate of bronze will be seen in some parts of the figures beaten out
                    nearly half an inch till it reaches the thinness of^note-paper. Works in relief
                    (τόρευμα), whether beaten out or chased, like those just mentioned, or cast, are
                    comparatively rare, though this branch of art was largely practised even by the
                    greatest sculptors. On the other hand, it does not appear to have been carried
                    out by them to the extent in which it is found in Germany and Italy after the
                    beginning of the lltlι century,—for instance, in the reliefs on cathedral gates.
                    The temple of Athene Chalkioikos in Sparta, with its walls covered with bronze
                    reliefs, stands out as an exception. By the time of the Byzantine empire, when
                    the power of modelling had declined, and a taste for glittering appearance took
                    its place, the process of ornamenting bronze with reliefs was superseded by
                    inlaying it with silver and other materials. As to the colour of the ancient
                    bronzes little can now be said, because from lying so long in the earth they
                    have become covered with what is technically called a <hi rend="italic"
                    >patina,</hi> which is generally some shade of green, though sometimes also
                    nearly blue, and at other times drab. This blue colour is very brilliant in
                    bronzes from Herculaneum and Pompeii. A difference of soil very probably makes a
                    different patina, but something may also be due to varieties in the alloy.
                    Perhaps the finest examples of patina are to be found among the bronze mirrors,
                    in which there seems to have been generally a considerable quantity of silver
                    for the sake of obtaining a highly reflecting surface. It does not appear that
                    the process of gilding bronze was carried to any extent in classical times,
                    unless, perhaps, in the production of finger-rings, of which a considerable
                    number remain. But if larger works in bronze fail, there is an abundance of
                    statuettes, candelabra, mirrors, <hi rend="italic">cistce,</hi> and vessels of
                    all kinds—Greek, Roman, and Etruscan. One fact to be noticed is that the great
                    number of bronze mirrors which exist are nearly all Etruscan. A few may be Roman
                    from the Latin inscriptions which they bear, and a few also come from Greece.
                    But the general rule of their being Etruscan reminds us of the reputation which
                    the Etruscans enjoyed for the production of works in bronze, not of high art,
                    but of what might be called industrial art. They were celebrated also for
                    modelling in clay; and that, as Pliny states, was the stage of art which
                    immediately preceded casting in bronze, and went hand in hand with it.</p>
                <p>The art of bronze · casting, which had sunk with the Byzantine empire, was again
                    revived with great vigour in Germany in the 11th century, from which period are
                    the bronze gate of the cathedral at Hildesheim (1015) and the column decorated
                    with reliefs on the model of the column of Trajan in Rome (1022). In the 12th
                    century the art spread southward to Italy, and at first was taken up
                    energetically in'Lower Italy. But though many interesting works of this kind
                    exist also from the 13 th and 14th <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n416/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0416-0369"/> centuries, it was not till the 15th that the art
                    obtained its complete mastery under the Florentine artists. In the following
                    century, again, it is found carried with extraordinary skill in Germany at
                    Nuremberg, Augsburg, Munich, and Coburg. Since then, however, the higher order
                    of sculpture in bronze may be said to have reverted to nearly its ancient
                    limits, that is, the production of statues and groups in the round. (See Dr C.
                    Bischoff, <hi rend="italic">Das Kupfer</hi><hi rend="italic">in</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">der vorchristlichen Zeit,</hi> Berlin, 1865; and L. R. v.
                    Fellenberg, <hi rend="italic">Analysen von antiken Bronzen,</hi> 1865.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
