<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0432-0385-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BROWN, Robert (9th edition, volume 4, page 385)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4086358z">Medals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6pc2x">Planting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q79t">Plants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4js9h84m">Botanists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62f7n">Reading</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1198483">Brown</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1030128">Museums</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1065823">Plants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:920123">Fame</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n432/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BROWN, <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert</hi></label>, a celebrated
                    botanist, who may be said to be the founder of the modern science of vegetable
                    physiology, and to have placed the natural system of the classification of
                    plants, originally introduced by Jussieu, upon that sure and ever-widening basis
                    on which it has ever since remained. With the exception of the early years of
                    his life his career was uneventful. His private life is little known; and though
                    his researches were familiar to the learned members of nearly all the European
                    and American academies, which numbered him among their members, his very
                    existence, until the journals of the day proclaimed his decease, was almost
                    unsuspected by the fashionable world of the great city in which he had passed
                    upwards of half a century. His biography may be best read in his works,—a very
                    few words sufficing to record the salient points of his life. Robert Brown was
                    the second and only surviving son of the Rev. Jas. Brown, Episcopalian minister
                    of Montrose, by Helen, daughter of the Rev. Robert <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n433/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0433-0386"/> Taylor, and was born on the 21st December 1773.
                    He was educated at the grammar school of his native town, where he had as
                    contemporaries, among others less known to fame, Joseph Hume and James Mill. In
                    1787 he entered Marischal College, Aberdeen, where he soon distinguished
                    himself. Two years afterwards, his father quitting Montrose for Edinburgh, Brown
                    removed to the university of that city, and there continued his studies for
                    several years, but without taking a degree, though destined for the medical
                    profession. In 1791 his father died, and in 1816 his mother; both are interred
                    in the Canongate churchyard, in the burying ground belonging to Bishop Keith. It
                    was about 1790 that young Brown’s taste for botany attracted the attention of Dr
                    Walker, then professor of natural history in the university. His first
                    contribution to the science of which he was destined to be so eminent a
                    cultivator was made on the 26th June 1792, in the shape of a paper on the plants
                    of Forfarshire, read before the Natural History Society; the MS. is still
                    contained in the archives of the Royal Physical Society <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Journal of Botany,</hi> 1871, p. 321). During his student days he also
                    discovered many plants new to Scotland, which were communicated to Withering for
                    his <hi rend="italic">Arrangement of British Plants.</hi></p>
                <p>In 1795 he obtained a commission in the Forfarshire regiment of Fencible Infantry
                    as “ensign and assistant surgeon,” and while serving in the North of Ireland
                    steadily pursued his botanical studies, and had the advantage of the
                    companionship of Capt. Dugald Carmichael of Appin, afterwards well known as an
                    investigator of the lower orders of plants. Having occasion to pass several
                    months of 1798 and of subsequent years in London, he studied in the library and
                    museum of Sir Joseph Banks, P.R.S., whose acquaintance he had been fortunate
                    enough to make by the discovery of a rare moss, <hi rend="italic">Glyphomitrwn
                    Daviesii.</hi> The result of this friendly intercourse was that he was recalled
                    from Ireland, and in the summer of 1801 quitted his not altogether congenial
                    medico-military pursuits, to take the more agreeable post of naturalist to the
                    expedition fitted out under Capt. Flinders for the survey of the then almost
                    unknown coasts of New Holland. Ferdinand Bauer, afterwards familiarly associated
                    with Brown in his botanical discoveries, was draughtsman; Wm. Westall was
                    landscape painter; and among the midshipmen was one afterwards destined to rise
                    into fame as Sir John Franklin. The narrative of that expedition is part of the
                    biography of its botanist. In 1805 the expedition returned to England, having
                    obtained, among other acquisitions, nearly 4000 species of dried plants, many of
                    which were new. Brown was almost immediately appointed librarian of the Linnean
                    Society, of which learned body he had been an associate since 1798, and to the
                    presidency of which he afterwards attained. In this position, though one of no
                    great emolument, he had abundant opportunities of pursuing his studies; but it
                    was not until 1810 that the first volume of his great work, in Latin, the <hi
                    rend="italic">Prodromus</hi><hi rend="italic">Florae Novoe Hollandiae et</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Insulae Van Diemen,</hi> appeared. It at once revolutionized
                    systematic botany, not only by the great number of new species it described, but
                    also by the novel views of the general affinities of plants which were
                    promulgated in its pages. Almost immediately it took the rank it has ever since
                    maintained as one of the canons of botanical science. Humboldt soon after its
                    publication dedicated his well-known work on the plants of the New World to
                    Brown <hi rend="italic">(Roberto Brownio, Britanniarum glori&lt;e</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">atque ornamento, totam</hi><hi rend="italic">Botanices</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Scientiam ingenio mirifico complectant!)</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >,</hi> and long after, in his <hi rend="italic">Kosmos,</hi> styled him <hi
                    rend="italic">facile</hi><hi rend="italic">princeps botanicorum.</hi> The <hi
                    rend="italic">Prodromus</hi> is now rare in its original edition, the author
                    having suppressed it, hurt at the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Review</hi> having
                    fallen foul of its Latinity; it is chiefly known through a German reprint. With
                    the exception of a supplement published in 1830, no more of the work appeared.
                    In 1810 Brown became librarian to Sir Joseph Banks, who on his death in 1820
                    bequeathed to him the use and enjoyment of his library and collections for life.
                    In 1827 an arrangement was made by which these were transferred to the British
                    Museum, with Brown’s consent and in accordance with Sir Joseph’s will. Brown now
                    became keeper of this new botanical department, an office which he held until
                    his death thirty years afterwards. Soon after Banks’s decease he resigned the
                    librarianship of the Linnean Society, and in 1849 became president, in which
                    office he continued until 1853. His subsequent life was occupied with numerous
                    brilliant discoveries and researches in vegetable anatomy, physiology, and
                    classification; these are familiar to every student, and may be read in any
                    botanical text-book. Long before his death they secured his fame as the first
                    botanist of the day. Honours flowed thickly in upon him. In addition to being a
                    fellow of the Royal Society he received its Copley Medal in 1839. In 1833 he was
                    elected one of the five foreign associates of the Institute of France,—the other
                    competitors, nearly all of whom afterwards attained the same honour, being
                    Bessell, Von Buch, Faraday, Herschel, Jacobi, Meckel, Mitscherlich, Oersted, and
                    Plana. He was also a member of nearly all the learned societies and academies of
                    this and other countries, D.C.L. of Oxford, LL.D, of Edinburgh, and knight of
                    numerous orders, among others of the Order “pour le Mérite” of Prussia. In the
                    “Academia Caesarea Naturae Curiosorum” he sat under the cognomen of Ray.</p>
                <p>On the 10th June 1858 he died in the 85th year of his age, in his house in Soho
                    Square, bequeathed to him by Sir Jos. Banks. His. place in botanical science has
                    long been fixed; it is not necessary now to discuss it. His works are all
                    standards, being distinguished by their thoroughness and conscientious accuracy,
                    and displaying powers at once of minute detail and of broad generalization,
                    —qualities rarely combined. Indeed, so careful was he in preparing his
                    discoveries for the press that he directed in his will that, should any of his
                    writings be republished, they should be printed <hi rend="italic"
                    >verbatim</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">literatim.</hi> In
                    private life he was exceedingly modest, and he shrank from notoriety of every
                    kind. Sensationalism and self-seeking he despised; fame came to him unsought.
                    His reserved manner to those not intimately acquainted with him could never make
                    him universally popular; but few will deny his warmheartedness to his friends,
                    the singleness of his purpose, and the purity of his life. Those who knew him in
                    his most intimate relations bear witness that in mind he was simple, truthful,
                    and upright, and that he was wise and faithful in council.</p>
                <p>In 1825-34 Dr Brown’s works up to that date were collected and published in four
                    divisions by Nees von Esenbeck, in German, under the title of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Vermischte botanische Schriften</hi> (Leipsic and Nuremberg). In 1866 the Ray
                    Society reprinted, under the editorship of his friend and successor in the
                    keepership of the Botanical Department of the British Museum, Mr J. J. Bennet,
                    his complete writings, the <hi rend="italic">Prodromus</hi> alone excepted. In
                    these <hi rend="italic">Miscellaneous Works</hi> (2 vols., with atlas of
                    plates), the history of his discoveries can be best followed. No special
                    biography of him is ever likely to appear, as his career contained few of the
                    elements essential to a continuous narrative of general interest. In the
                    necrologies of the societies and academies which numbered him among their
                    members, there will, however, be found sketches of his life more or less
                    complete.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
