<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0219-0178-11" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BOWLES, William Lisle (9th edition, volume 4, page
                    178)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55t8q">Sonnets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bw6x">Spirits</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gb1xr6p">Spirit</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z892p9k">Spiritism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126608">Sonnet</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126610">Sonnets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1093056">Regents</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n219/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BOWLES, <hi rend="smallcaps">William Lisle</hi></label>, poet
                    and critic, was born at King’s Sutton, of which his father was vicar, in 1762.
                    At <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n220/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0220-0179"/> the age of fourteen he was entered on the
                    foundation at Winchester school, the head-master at the time being Dr Joseph
                    Warton. Iu 1781 he left as captain of the school, and proceeded to Trinity
                    College, Oxford, to a scholarship to which he had been elected. Two years later
                    he gained the chancellor’s prize for Latin verse, and soon after left the
                    university, not taking his degree as master till 1792. Iu 1789 he published, in
                    a small quarto volume, <hi rend="italic">Fourteen Sonnets,</hi> which met with
                    considerable favour at the time, were hailed with delight by Coleridge and his
                    young contemporaries, and have since been recognized as the first notes of the
                    modern revolt against the artificial school of poetry, the traditions of which
                    had descended from Pope. The <hi rend="italic">Sonnets</hi> even in form were a
                    revival, a return to the older and purer poetic style, and by their grace of
                    expression, melodious versification, tender tone of feeling, and vivid
                    appreciation of the life and beauty of nature, stood out in strong contrast to
                    the affected common-places which at that time formed the bulk of English poetry.
                    A second edition of the little volume was called for in the same year in which
                    it had appeared, and there have been many subsequent editions. A few short
                    pieces were published in 1790 and 1792, which were also received with favour.
                    After taking his degree at Oxford he entered the church, and was soon appointed
                    to the vicarage of Chicklade in Wiltshire. In 1797 he received the vicarage of
                    Dumbleton in Gloucestershire, and in 1801 was presented to the vicarage of
                    Brem-hill in Wiltshire. In the same year he was collated by Bishop Douglas to a
                    prebendal stall in the cathedral of Salisbury. In 1818 he was made chaplain to
                    the Prince Regent, and in 1828 he was elected residentiary canon of Salisbury.
                    He died at Salisbury in April 1850, aged 88. Of the longer poems published by
                    Bowles none attain a very high standard of excellence, though all are
                    distinguished by purity of imagination, cultured and graceful diction, and great
                    tenderness of feeling. The most extensive were <hi rend="italic">The Spirit of
                    Discovery,</hi> 1804, which was mercilessly ridiculed by Byron; <hi
                    rend="italic">The Missionary of the Andes,</hi> 1815; <hi rend="italic">The
                    Grave of the Last Saxon,</hi> 1822; and <hi rend="italic">St John in
                    Patmos,</hi> 1833. Bowles is perhaps more celebrated as a critic of poetry than
                    as a poet. In 1807 he published an edition of Pope’s works with notes and an
                    essay on the poetical character of Pope. In this essay he laid down certain
                    canons as to poetic imagery which, with slight modification, have been since
                    recognized as true and valuable, but which were received at the time with strong
                    opposition by all admirers of Pope and his style. The “Pope and Bowles”
                    controversy brought into sharp contrast the opposing views of poetry, which may
                    be roughly described as the natural and the artificial. Bowles maintained that
                    images drawn from nature are poetically finer than those drawn from art; and
                    that in the highest kinds of poetry the themes or passions handled should be of
                    the general or elemental kind, and not the transient manners of any society.
                    These positions were vigorously assailed by Byron, Campbell, Roscoe, and others
                    of less note, while for a time Bowles was almost solitary. Hazlitt and the
                    Blackwood critics, however, came to his assistance, and on the whole Bowles had
                    reason to congratulate himself on having once for all established certain
                    principles which might serve as the basis of a true method of poetical
                    criticism, and of having inaugurated, both by precept and by example, a new era
                    in English poetry. Among other prose works from his prolific pen was a <hi
                    rend="italic">Life of Bishop Ken,</hi> 2 vols., 1830-31.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
