<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0392-0345-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BRIGHT’S DISEASE (9th edition, volume 4, page
                    345)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:987372">Kidneys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:804221">Albuminuria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:834550">Blood</term>
                    <term ref="fast:875336">Connectionism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4f76663x">Kidneys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fb4wk7b">Albuminuria</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c374">Blood</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2th4x">Resultants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cn1s">Caste</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n392/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BRIGHT’S DISEASE</label>, a term in medicine applied to a
                    clas3 of diseases of the kidneys which have as their most prominent symptom the
                    presence of albumen in the urine, and frequently also the co-existence of
                    dropsy. These associated symptoms in connection with kidney disease were first
                    described in 1827 by Dr Richard Bright. Since that period the subject has been
                    investigated by many able physicians, and it is now well established that the
                    symptoms above named, instead of being as was formerly supposed the result of
                    one form of disease of the kidneys, may be dependent on various morbid
                    conditions of those organs. Hence the term Bright’s disease, which is retained
                    in medical nomenclature in honour of Dr Bright, must be understood as having a
                    generic application.</p>
                <p>Two varieties of Bright’s disease are described, the <hi rend="italic">acute</hi>
                    and the <hi rend="italic">chronic,—</hi> the former representing the
                    inflammatory and the latter the degenerative form of kidney disease.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Acute Bright's Disease</hi> (synonyms— <hi rend="italic">acute
                    desquamative nephritis, acute albuminuria,</hi> Ac.) commonly arises from
                    exposure to cold, from intemperance, or as a complication of certain acute
                    diseases, such as .erysipelas, diphtheria, and especially scarlet fever, of
                    which it is one of the most frequent and serious consequences. In this form of
                    the disease the kidneys become congested, their blood-vessels being gorged with
                    blood, while the tubules are distended and obstructed by accumulated epithelium,
                    as also by effused blood and the products of inflammation, all which are shed
                    off and appear in the urine on microscopic examination as <hi rend="italic"
                    >casts of</hi> the uriniferous tubes.</p>
                <p>The symptoms to which the condition gives rise are usually of a severe character.
                    Pain in the back, vomiting, and febrile disturbance commonly usher in the
                    attack. Dropsy, varying in degree from slight puffiness of the face to an
                    accumulation of fluid sufficient to distend the whole body, and to occasion
                    serious embarrassment to respiration, is a very common accompaniment. The urine
                    is reduced in quantity, is of dark, smoky, or bloody colour, and exhibits to
                    chemical reaction the presence of a large amount of albumen, while, under the
                    microscope, blood corpuscles and casts, as above mentioned, are found in
                    abundance.</p>
                <p>This state of acute inflammation may by its severity destroy life, or, short of
                    this, may by continuance result in the establishment of one of the chronic forms
                    of Bright’s disease. On the other hand an arrest of the inflammatory action
                    frequently occurs, and this is marked by the increased amount of the urine, and
                    the gradual disappearance of its albumen and other abnormal constituents; as
                    also by the subsidence of the dropsy and the rapid recovery of strength.</p>
                <p>Of <hi rend="italic">chronic Bright’s Disease</hi> there are several forms, named
                    according to the structural changes undergone by the kidneys. The most frequent
                    of these is the <hi rend="italic">large white kidney,</hi> which is the chronic
                    form of the desquamative nephritis above mentioned.</p>
                <p>Another form of chronic Bright’s disease is the <hi rend="italic">waxy</hi> or
                    <hi rend="italic">amyloid kidney,</hi> due to the degenerative change which
                    affects first the blood-vessels and subsequently also the tubular structures of
                    the organ. This condition is usually found associated with some chronic ailment
                    of an exhausting character, such as disease of bones and other scrofulous
                    affections, or with a generally enfeebled state of health. It is marked by the
                    passage of large quantities of albuminous urine, and is frequently accompanied
                    with general dropsy, as also with diarrhoea and consequent loss of strength. A
                    third form of chronic Bright’s disease is the <hi rend="italic">contracted
                    kidney,</hi> depending on the condition known as <hi rend="italic"
                    >cirrhosis,</hi> in which the kidneys become reduced in bulk, but dense in
                    texture, from an abnormal development of their connective tissue and relative
                    atrophy of their true structure. This form of the disease, which is commonly,
                    though not exclusively connected with a gouty constitution, is apt to escape
                    detection in its earlier stages from the more obscure character of the symptoms,
                    there being less albuminuria and less dropsy than in the other varieties. Its
                    later progress, however, enables it to be readily recognized. Dimness of vision,
                    due to a morbid condition of the retina, and also hypertrophy of the heart
                    leading to fatal apoplexy, are frequent accompaniments of this form of the
                    disease.</p>
                <p>A fourth variety of chronic Bright’s disease is described by authors on the
                    subject, viz., <hi rend="italic">fatty degeneration of the kidneys,</hi>
                    occasionally occurring in old age and in connection with a similar degeneration
                    of other organs.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n393/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0393-0346"/>
                <p>The kidneys being among the most important excretory organs of the body, it
                    follows that when their function is interrupted, as it is alike in acute and
                    chronic Bright’s disease, serious results are apt to arise from the retention in
                    the economy of those effete matters which it is the office of the kidneys to
                    eliminate. The blood being thus contaminated, and at the same time impoverished
                    by the draining away of its albumen from the kidneys, is rendered unfit to carry
                    on the processes of healthy nutrition; and, as a consequence, various secondary
                    diseases are liable to be induced. Inflammatory affections within the chest are
                    of frequent occurrence, but the most dangerous of all the complications of
                    Bright’s disease are the nervous symptoms which may arise at any stage, and
                    which are ascribed to the effects of uraemic poisoning.</p>
                <p>In the treatment of acute Bright’s disease, good results are often obtained from
                    local depletion, from warm baths, and from the careful employment of diuretics
                    and purgatives. Chronic Bright’s disease is much less amenable to treatment, but
                    by efforts to maintain the strength and improve the quality of the blood by
                    strong nourishment, and at the same time by guarding against the risks of
                    complications, b'fe may often be prolonged in comparative comfort, and even a
                    certain measure of improvement be experienced.</p>
                <p>See <hi rend="italic">Report on Medical Cases,</hi> by Richard Bright, London,
                    1827; <hi rend="italic">On Granular Degeneration of the Kidneys,</hi> by Robert
                    Christison,</p>
                <p>M. D., Edinburgh, 1839; <hi rend="italic">Diseases of the Kidney,</hi> by Dr G.
                    Johnson,</p>
                <p>London, 1866; <hi rend="italic">Practical Treatise on Urinary and Renal
                    Diseases,</hi> by Wm. Roberts, M.D., London, 1865; <hi rend="italic">On the
                    Pathology and Treatment of Albuminuria,</hi> by W. H. Dickinson, M.D., London,
                    1868; <hi rend="italic">Practical Treatise on Bright's Diseases of the
                    Kidneys,</hi> by T. Grainger Stewart, M.D., Edin. 1871. (J. 0. A.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
