<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0295-0252-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BREHON LAW (9th edition, volume 4, page 252)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx06c7f">Welsh</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k06x16n">Bailiffs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1173757">Welsh</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795379">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795510">Accounts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:825514">Bailiffs</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n295/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BREHON LAW</label>, the law of Ireland previous to the
                    Conquest, and of some communities of the Irish down to the 17th century (from
                    <hi rend="italic">breitheam,</hi> genitive <hi rend="italic">breitheamain,</hi>
                    a judge; root, <hi rend="italic">breith,</hi> a judgment; compare <hi
                    rend="italic">Vergobretus,</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> tl</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">vir-ad-judicandum,”</hi> Caes., <hi rend="italic">De Bell.
                    Gall.,</hi> i. 16). Three volumes of these laws, comprising the code called the
                    <hi rend="italic">Scnchus Mor,</hi> alleged to have been revised by St Patrick,
                    have been published by a Royal Commission appointed in 1852, and other portions
                    in the second series of O’Curry’s <hi rend="italic">Lectures on the Materials of
                    Ancient Irish History,</hi> edited, with a learned introduction, by Dr W. K.
                    Sullivan in 1873. The antiquated and often obsolete language both of the
                    original text and of the interlined glosses, coupled with the fact that portions
                    of both are cited in compilations considered not later than the 10th century,
                    are arguments for their acceptance as fragments of a primitive system unmodified
                    by Anglo-Saxon, Danish, or Norman influences. The Roman (or civil) law is hardly
                    traceable in them, except as regards ecclesiastical affairs, and that <hi
                    rend="italic">sub</hi><hi rend="italic">modo</hi> only. From the first-mentioned
                    cause also, the provisions are often obscure and sometimes unintelligible; but
                    enough appears to indicate the general nature and much of the details of these
                    laws.</p>
                <p>As compared with the collections known under the generic title <hi rend="italic"
                    >leges</hi><hi rend="italic">barbarorum,</hi> they are remarkable for their
                    copiousness, and furnish a striking example of the length to which moral and
                    metaphysical refinements may be carried under rude social conditions. They
                    present a stâtte of society such as may be conceived to have existed under the
                    older manorial organization, when the land was to a greater extent “folk’’-land
                    than <hi rend="superscript"> u</hi> boc <hi rend="superscript"> ,,</hi>-land,
                    and comprised commons of tillage as well as of pasture. This kind of occupancy
                    entailed annual repartitions of the tillage, recalling the usage of the ancient
                    Germans (Caes., <hi rend="italic">Bel. Gall.,</hi> vi. 20), and of which, as
                    practised on a minor scale in Ireland in 1782, Sir Henry Piers has given an
                    account in his description of Westmeath (Vallancey, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Coll.,</hi> vi. p. 115). Traces of such repartitions survived under the name of
                    Rundale (Irish ranncfαcA, “partire ”) in the Highlands of Scotland and in some
                    parts of the West of England till recent times (Maine, <hi rend="italic">Early
                    Inst.,</hi> p. 101). There is no evidence, however, in the Brehon code, as now
                    published, of merely family occupancy, in which one household living together,
                    or even one village community, enjoyed the land and its produce in common,
                    although such an origin may be theoretically conjectured for the institutions
                    described. The social unit comprised separate families and households numerous
                    enough to occupy a <hi rend="italic">crich or quasi</hi> manor, within which
                    existed a court and complete system of primary social organization. In each of
                    these, mensal lands were set permanently apart for the chief, and means existed
                    by which portions of the common land could, within certain limits, be acquired
                    in severalty by individual owners. The <hi rend="italic">crich</hi> formed
                    portion of the <hi rend="italic">tuath,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">quasi</hi>
                    barony, one or more of which constituted the <hi rend="italic">mor tuath,</hi>
                    or petty kingdom, equivalent to a county or several counties, governed by a <hi
                    rend="italic">ri</hi> or <hi rend="italic">regulus,</hi> who, in theory at
                    least, bore allegiance, through superior <hi rend="italic">reguli,</hi> to the
                    monarch. The grades of rank were numerous, but the distinctions of wealth which
                    grounded them appear very arbitrary. The upper classes were all “Aires.” To be
                    eligible to the <hi rend="italic">aire</hi> grade, the freeman should possess,
                    besides a certain amount of wealth in cattle, a prescribed assortment of
                    agricultural implements and household goods, the meagreness of which exemplifies
                    the slow progress of the arts of life in early states of society, and he should
                    have a house of given dimensions, ranging from 17 to 27 feet in length, and
                    containing a given number of compartments. The houses were of timber and
                    wattle-work, surrounded by open spaces of prescribed extent for each class. The
                    lower limit for this space was the distance to which the owner seated at his
                    door could throw a missile of given weight; multiples of that distance
                    determined its extent for the higher classes. Tacitus has noticed a like custom
                    of keeping clear spaces round the several dwellings among the early Germans; and
                    this regulation has probably contributed to retard the progress of the early
                    Irish out of pastoral and agricultural into civic habits. There was a serf and
                    slave population, who were designated <hi rend="italic">ernaans,</hi> as
                    representing the earlier Firbolg and Pictish colonists, who did not enjoy these
                    privileges, except by the process of becoming <hi rend="italic">fuidhirs</hi> or
                    tenants of the separate lands of the nobles, who called themselves <hi
                    rend="italic">Gaidel,</hi> or Gael, and claimed a different descent. Besides
                    these tenants, or “feuers,” there λvere dependants called <hi rend="italic"
                    >ceiles,</hi> who stood to the wealthy classes in a relation resembling that of
                    the <hi rend="italic">clients</hi> of the Roman commonalty to their patrons.
                    Both they and the <hi rend="italic">fuidhirs</hi> owed suit and homage to their
                    <hi rend="italic">flat!cs</hi> or lords, as well as services and rents in kind
                    and in refections. The food-rents, <hi rend="italic">biadh,</hi> corresponding
                    to the Anglo-Saxon <hi rend="italic">feorme</hi> (whence “farmer”), were
                    supplied both at the residences of the chiefs and at the tables of their
                    tenants, whence originated the customs of <hi rend="italic">coyne</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">livery</hi> of later times.</p>
                <p>The use of coined money waβ practically unknown, and the unit of value <hi
                    rend="italic">(sed, seota,</hi> “assets ”) was the cow. The <hi rend="italic"
                    >cedes</hi> appear to have been attached to their lords by largesses, or
                    “commendations” of cattle which they used in their own tribal lands. It is in
                    the <hi rend="italic">fuidhir</hi> class that a law of tenure of land
                    originated, and possibly in these relations we may discover the rudiments of a
                    partly-developed feudalism.' The <hi rend="italic">fuidhir</hi> is, in the
                    theory of the native etymologists, the <hi rend="italic">fo-tir</hi> or
                    “landunderling,” as one who holds land of another. The rules regulating these
                    several kinds of enjoyment of the land are peculiar to the Brehon eode, and, as
                    may be observed of all its provisions, are extraordinarily minute, being
                    designed to fix all rights and liabilities, under every probable state of
                    circumstances, in values numbered, which may be one cause for the slow social
                    progress made under their operation. For each supply of cattle to the <hi
                    rend="italic">cede</hi> a definite return to the <hi rend="italic">aire</hi> is
                    fixed to the end of seven years, when the property vests in the <hi
                    rend="italic">cede.</hi> But the supply should not exceed fixed limits if the
                    recipient would preserve his <hi rend="italic">status</hi> as a freeman. The <hi
                    rend="italic">fuidhir,</hi> or base tenant, was bound to larger returns in rent
                    and services, and the lord might, on violation of the tenant’s engagements,
                    resume the possession of the land; but it would appear that during the <hi
                    rend="italic">fuidhir's</hi> occupation he could not be otherwise disturbed
                    without a measure of compensation. On the death of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >cede</hi> or of the <hi rend="italic">fuidhir,</hi> a <hi rend="italic"
                    >quasi</hi> heriot was payable to the lord.</p>
                <p>The succession to the territorial headships was elective within hereditary
                    limits; the succession to tribal rights of occupancy, and individual rights of
                    ownership in the separate hereditaments acquirable by individuals, was
                    hereditary. The law of <hi rend="italic">distribution</hi> of a deceased
                    person’s property is very minute in its provisions, though obscure, owing to the
                    technical description of the classes and persons entitled; but it appears to
                    have contemplated divisions <hi rend="italic">per capita</hi> and not <hi
                    rend="italic">per stirpes.</hi> The law of <hi rend="italic">marriage</hi> is
                    remarkable for the variety of irregular relations which it appears to sanction,
                    and for its careful protection of the separate pro <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n296/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0296-0253"/> perty of the irregular as well as of the lawful
                    wife, both during cohabitation and on separation, which appears to have been
                    frequent. The lawful wife seems to have had no other protection against the
                    introduction of the “adal-traich” wife than the withdrawal of her separate
                    property, in addition to certain mulcts payable to her on the occasion. She
                    possessed independent rights of alienating a portion of her separate property,
                    and could, to some extent, control the rights of alienation of her husband. The
                    looseness of the marriage tie evidenced by these laws was one of the evils
                    calling for reform alleged by the Irish prelates in their letter moving Pope
                    Alexander III. to ratify the grant of the island made by Adrian IV. to king
                    Henry II.</p>
                <p>The practice of putting out the children of the wealthier classes to be nursed
                    and educated may have contributed to make such relations less incompatible with
                    domestic peace. The law of <hi rend="italic">fosterage,</hi> of which few if any
                    recognizable traces, outside the law of apprenticeship, have survived elsewhere,
                    provides for the external nursing and educating of the children of the upper
                    class by poorer members of the community, who, besides the fosterage-fee
                    received with the infan¼ had a claim on the foster-child for support in old age.
                    The fostering began from infancy, and terminated, in the case of daughters, at
                    thirteen, and of sons, at seventeen years of age. A certain amount of
                    instruction should be imparted. Girls of the less wealthy class should be taught
                    to use the handmill and sieve, to bake, and to rear young cattle; those of the
                    higher class to sew, cut out, and embroider. The boys should learn kiln-drying
                    and wood-cutting, and those of the upper class chess-playing, the use of
                    missiles, horsemanship, and swimming. The lawful food for all was porridge.
                    Their clothing, besides the nursing clothes supplied by the parents, was
                    according to their status, from sober coloured stuffs for the children of the
                    less wealthy to scarlet cloth and silks for the children of those of the rank of
                    king. Provision was made for the necessary correction of the pupil, with mulcts
                    for excess. During the pupilage, the foster-father was entitled to all
                    compensation for injuries to his charge, and liable to all mulcts for their
                    offences. If the child died in its pupilage, another might be sent in its place.
                    If returned before the completion of the term, or imperfectly educated, the
                    foster-father should refund. The fixing of the proportionate amounts due in the
                    several cases gives rise to much minute regulation. The law of <hi rend="italic"
                    >military service</hi> like the others, was based on a system of fines leviable
                    for non-attendance and even for desertion in the field. To what has been said on
                    the land-law it may be added that public contributions were leviable for the
                    repair of roads and bridges, and the maintenance of the chief’s or king’s
                    fortresses; and that each community had a public mill, fishing-net, ferry-boat,
                    &amp;c., besides such objects of this kind as were possessed in severalty by the
                    wealthier members. There was also a law of waifs and strays, and of wrecks of
                    the sea, with provisions for the entertainment of shipwrecked seamen at the
                    common charge of the district entitled to the distribution of the wreck. There
                    is little mention of testamentary disposition; and from the language employed, a
                    Roman origin may be probably surmised for it. To counterpoise the excess of
                    privilege incident to the possession of wealth, the mulcts payable for
                    misfeasances and nonfeasances of all kinds were graduated in the interests of
                    the poorer classes. Crime and breach of contract might reduce from the highest
                    to the lowest grade.</p>
                <p>As regards the law of <hi rend="italic">contracts</hi> generally, the
                    disabilities arising from tribal partnership, infancy, imbecility, coverture,
                    and obligation to the lord give rise to many exceptions and qualifications, the
                    general rule being that acquiescence, after notice, by the parties jointly
                    interested, or standing in relations of protectorship, has the effect of
                    validating what would otherwise be void. Distinct periods are limited within
                    which the parties entitled to disagree may avoid the bargain; and, in all cases,
                    a <hi rend="italic">locus</hi><hi rend="italic">poenitentiae</hi> of twenty-four
                    hours is annexed to the oral agreement, within which time either party may
                    rescind it. The nature and effect of a <hi rend="italic">τcarranty</hi> on sale
                    appears also to have been understood and provided for; and frequent reference is
                    made to the cases arising on unsoundness, latent or supervening. There are some
                    traces of a law of the <hi rend="italic">market,</hi> but how far, if at all, it
                    qualified the ordinary rules of contract, does not appear. The ΛenαcΛ⅛, or great
                    fairs, were held at distant places and at long intervals of time. Various
                    immunities are given to the persons frequenting them; and a violation of some of
                    the necessary provisions for securing the peace and decorum of the meetings was
                    exceptionally punishable with death, while almost every other offence might be
                    condoned by a pecuniary payment. A highly interesting account of one of these
                    great assemblages, which was held triennially at Carman, near Wexford, is given
                    in a tract translated in the 2d series of O’Curry’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Lectures,</hi> where, among the various classes resorting there for amusement
                    and traffic, mention is made of Greek merchants bringing commodities for sale.
                    The laws themselves give little intimation of their own origin or sanctions.
                    They appear to have undergone no substantial changes from time immemorial; but
                    some evidence exists of local law-making authority exercised at meetings of the
                    freemen of the <hi rend="italic">crick,</hi> subject to revision by some higher
                    authority, and one of the objects of these fairs or <hi rend="italic"
                    >comitia</hi> was to publish such enactments as well as the general body of the
                    laws and customs from time to time. The law of <hi rend="italic">torts</hi>
                    regarded all offences, with the nominal exception of murder, as condonable by
                    fines until the offender and those liable for him could pay no more, when the
                    defaulter lost his <hi rend="italic">status</hi> and fell into the servile
                    class. For some of the offences of the individual, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >finné</hi> or family were responsible; for others, particular sureties. Whether
                    this system of <hi rend="italic">quasi</hi> frank-pledge did not extend to
                    breaches of contract, as well as to cases of non-feasance, misfeasance, and
                    breaches of the peace, appears uncertain. The scale of mulcts for the several
                    sorts of homicides, wounds, and personal hurts, is in outline the same with
                    those of the other western European nations; but, in addition to their definite
                    fine of so much for such and such a lesion or bruise, it provides by rateable
                    deductions for excusatory circumstances of intention, knowledge, contributory
                    negligence, accident, and necessity, all of which are considerable refinements
                    on the contemporaneous systems of the Continent. The penalty of death for murder
                    was of ecclesiastical introduction, and, like the law ordaining the payment of
                    tithes, appears to have fallen into desuetude before the Conquest. Chief Baron
                    Gilbert, in Dwyer’s case (Gilb., <hi rend="italic">Ev.,</hi> vol. i. p. 9) has
                    an observation apposite to the state of society disclosed by this system of
                    measured mulcts and mutual suretyship, in treating of the state of Britain
                    before murder had become punishable with death under the later law of
                    Canute:—</p>
                <p>“It is not very hard to conceive how the kingdom was maintained hy <hi
                    rend="italic">pecuniary mulcts</hi> only; for in those days every man was put in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Dcccnna</hi> (tything); and if found wandering three days
                    out of the <hi rend="italic">Decennary,</hi> he was taken up and imprisoned, and
                    he was presently to abjure the kingdom, or else he lay at the mercy of every one
                    that could lay hands on him. And if any offence was committed in any of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Decennaries,</hi> if the party was brought to answer, he was
                    obliged to pay his fine for his offence, or he was <hi rend="italic"
                    >imprisoned</hi> for ever; and, if he fled, the <hi rend="italic">tything</hi>
                    was answerable for his fine or mulct to the king. So that by this discipline men
                    were put under a necessity of being innocent, or paying a grievous fine, or
                    being totally deprived of the conversation of mankind. And the laying of the
                    fine on the tything, in case the offender fled, made it the interest of every
                    man to bring the offender to light, and made it exceeding difficult to conceal a
                    theft or a murther.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n297/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0297-0254"/>
                <p>Imprisonment, among the Irish at the period of these laws, does not appear as
                    detention in a common gaol, but as a personal fettering of the culprit; and some
                    of their subtlest distinctions concern the liability of the person bound to
                    provide the fetters, in case of the culprit’s escape. It has been suggested with
                    much appearance of reason, that refinements of this kind, <hi rend="italic"
                    >inter apices juris,</hi> with which the Brehon law abounds, are rather
                    exercises of the writer’s ingenuity in framing suppositional cases illustrating
                    classes of abstract rules than evidences of any actual application of law to the
                    particular subjects. Such are the law of the measure of damages for injuries by
                    bees, by cats, by the hunting hound, by traps for game, &lt;fcc., all which are
                    elaborated to a pedantic nicety. Of the c&lt;H&lt;rte in which these laws were
                    administered we have but an imperfect view. The primary local tribunal was a <hi
                    rend="italic">quasi</hi> court baron, called the <hi rend="italic">Airecht,</hi>
                    composed of freemen of a certain status. The inferior classes were <hi
                    rend="italic">ecoma airech,ta,</hi> that is, “impares curiae.” The office of
                    Brehon in the court is very obscurely indicated. The stays and imparlances
                    (αnαcZ, <hi rend="italic">esain, dithim),</hi> &amp;c., incident to the process
                    of bringing causes to final judgment, and the fact that damages were, in all
                    cases of ordinary occurrence, assessed beforehand by specific rule, gave
                    repeated opportunities for settling out of doors. There were professional
                    advocates and means of carrying the case to courts of higher jurisdiction, but
                    how these were constituted does not appear; but mention is made of several
                    gradations from the <hi rend="italic">airecht urnaidh</hi> (sheriff’s <hi
                    rend="italic">tourns ?)</hi> to the <hi rend="italic">cul-airecht,</hi> or
                    ulterior court, which indicates some resort by way of appeal. Their rules of <hi
                    rend="italic">evidence,</hi> in addition to the testimony of the eye, admitted,
                    in questions of title to land, that of the ear, <hi rend="italic">cluais,</hi>
                    or general report, and <hi rend="italic">laidlι</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >(cantus)</hi> or history in the form of a poem publicly recited (a remarkable
                    example of practical functions belonging to the office of a bard) as well as the
                    evidence of landmarks or mearing stones. These, it seems (O’Curry, 2d series,
                    Sullivan, Introd., clxxxvii.), should be sunk under the surface, as Martin in
                    his account of the Western Isles of Scotland (p. 114) has described: —</p>
                <p>“They preserve their boundaries from being liable to any debates by their
                    successors, thus. They lay a quantity of the ashes of burnt wood in the ground,
                    and put big stones above the same; and for carrying the knowledge of this to
                    posterity, they carry some boys from both villages next the boundary and then
                    whip ’em soundly and tell it to their children. A debate having arisen between
                    the villages of Ose and Groban in Skye, they found ashes as above mentioned
                    under a stone, which decided the controversy.”</p>
                <p>This gives countenance to the tradition that, prior to the reign of Aed Slaine in
                    the 7th century, there were no fences in the country, but all was open save the
                    walls and mounds surrounding dwellings. It is difficult to accept this statement
                    unreservedly, partly on account of the habit of assigning fabulous origins
                    indulged by all archaic, and notably so by the Irish writers, but chiefly
                    because the Brehon code comprises a very full law of <hi rend="italic"
                    >fences.</hi> The materials, dimensions, and several sorts of quick-setting of
                    these are laid down with great particularity, and the rights and liabilities of
                    adjoining owners are minutely described. Returning to the subject of judicial
                    administration, we have a much clearer view given of the nature and incidents of
                    <hi rend="italic">process</hi> by which the jurisdiction of the court was made
                    to attach, than of the constitution of the court itself. This was by <hi
                    rend="italic">distress,</hi> or the seizure of the goods of the defendant, in
                    some cases immediate, in others preceded by summons, and, in the case of the
                    privileged classes, by <hi rend="italic">trosgad</hi> or fasting on the part of
                    the plaintiff, a practice still known in some parts of India, and much relied on
                    as an evidence of common Aryan origin for the ancient Irish and present Hindu
                    legal systems. The distress might either remain in the hands of the defendant,
                    if of the superior grade, by way of attachment <hi rend="italic">(fornasc),</hi>
                    subject to a lien, on security for his appearing and abiding the award of the
                    court, or it might at once be driven to a pound <hi rend="italic">(forus).</hi>
                    Here it was kept during a certain time or “stay” <hi rend="italic">(anad),</hi>
                    varying with the nature of the complaint, during which the defendant might have
                    it back on like security. Failing this, a process of forfeiture <hi
                    rend="italic">(lobad)</hi> commenced, and ultimately the distress, or so much of
                    it as sufficed to satisfy the claim, vested in the plaintiff, the defendant
                    receiving back the balance, if any. On security being given, the merits of the
                    dispute were determined by the court. A proceeding analogous to the action of
                    <hi rend="italic">replevin</hi> was thus incidental to every litigation; and
                    this appears to have been the early course of the common law in all the local
                    courts, not proceeding on the king’s writs, both of England and Scotland, down
                    to the times of Bracton (fo. 156. 2, Reeves’s <hi rend="italic">Hist. Eng.
                    Law,</hi> 59), and of the enactment “Quoniam attachiamenta” <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Leges Bar. Scot.,</hi> i. and cxi.). One of the few eases cited in the Brehon
                    law (vol. i. p. 65) states the procedure in what was substantially an
                    inter-tribal action of ejectment for recovery of land, in the incidents of which
                    a resemblance is found to many principles of jurisprudence and methods of
                    procedure of the common law of England, such as prescription, limitation,
                    set-off, entry, ouster, distress, rescue, fresh pursuit, withernam, replevin,
                    surety in replevin, avowry, Welsh mortgage, writ of possession, and return of
                    distress. The case was this :—</p>
                <p>Land had been assigned by way of Welsh mortgage in part payment of a mulct or
                    fine. The mortgagee and his descendants remained in possession until it became a
                    question whether the law of prescription <hi rend="italic">(rudrad)</hi> had not
                    given them the absolute estate. To try the title, a bailiff of the claimant
                    tribe put his horses on the land. The bailiff of the tribe in possession drove
                    them off, accompanying the act with an admission that formerly the claimant
                    tribe had been in possession. The claimant’s bailiff then distrained three cows
                    of the occupier’s bailiff outside his cattle shed, and drove them to the border
                    of the territory, where they lay down. It would have been his duty here to give
                    public notification of his proceedings, and to have driven his distress to the
                    nearest pound of the external territory; but the cows, not having been milked,
                    escaped, and returned to their calves, which had been left behind. The
                    distrainer, making fresh pursuit by the traces of the milk dropped on the ground
                    (regarded probably as a constructive keeping in view), recaptured them at
                    daybreak at the homestead of the owner, and, with them, in addition, distrained
                    and impounded three [six q others, taken from [out of] the door of the
                    cattle-shed, by way of <hi rend="italic">aitherach gdbail,</hi> or second
                    caption, to double the amount for what seems to have been considered a
                    constructive rescue implied by the escaped beasts being again in the owner’s
                    custody. Notwithstanding these facts, the regularity of the proceeding was
                    admitted by the tribe in possession, whose <hi rend="italic">regulus</hi> now
                    came forward and had back the distress, on giving pledges to try the question at
                    law, and to return the cattle if unsuccessful. Further security was also given
                    by him for some other liability. The action which, so far, was in the nature of
                    replevin, now assumed the character of ejectment, and the personal wrong of
                    ousting the bailiff who had made the entry merged in the question of title to
                    the possession of the land. It was held that the period of prescription, being
                    the time of three successions to the kingship, had not expired, one of the
                    successions being irregular. The land was, therefore, still redeemable, and, on
                    taking an account and setting off the receipts, including a mulct of less amount
                    due by the mortgagee, against the original balance due to him, it was found he
                    had been fully paid, and a return of the cattle was awarded, and possession of
                    the lands delivered to the claimant. (See “On the Rudiments of the Common Law
                    discoverable in the published portion of the <hi rend="italic">Senchus
                    Mor,"</hi> in 7Yαπs. <hi rend="italic">Roy. Irish Academy,</hi> vol. xxiv. p.
                    83, 1867.)</p>
                <p>It appears from this that the provisions of the statute of Marlbridge (52 Henry
                    III. c. 4) in England, forbidding the driving of distresses beyond the bounds of
                    the county, and of the “Regiam Majestatem” (re-enacted by 1 Robert, i. c. 7) in
                    Scotland, requiring that when driven beyond the bounds of the territory the
                    distress shall be exhibited before witnesses, are to be regarded not as merely
                    introductive enactments, but as substantially declaratory of the previous state
                    of the common law; further, that the old opinion that “all administration of
                    justice was at first in <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n298/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0298-0255"/> the king’s hands, but afterwards, as the kingdom
                    was divided into counties, hundreds, &amp;c., so the administration of justice
                    was distributed among divers courts, of which the sheriff had the government of
                    the county court, &lt;fcc.,” is probably grounded on an inversion of the actual
                    progress of the facts; and that when it is said of the right to recover land in
                    a personal action, of set-off, and of other equitable incidents of justice, that
                    such rights did not exist at the common law, the words “in actions commenced by
                    original writ,” should probably be understood; for there is no difficulty in
                    conceiving how all the main incidents and principles of law disclosed by the
                    Irish case could have arisen regularly in the county court, always a court of
                    equity for the defendant, when the bishop was associated with the sheriff, and
                    the right of the suitor to be his own apparitor had not yet been abrogated by
                    the law of Canute, re-enacted by William I. <hi rend="italic">(Leg. Gul.
                    Conq.,</hi> xliv.). How these resemblances have come to exist in the early laws
                    of the two islands may be a question for the historian and ethnologist. It is
                    well to know that, whencesoever derived, the common law may to so great an
                    extent be recognized as substantially a common inheritance of all the
                    populations now organized into the United Kingdom. (s. F.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
