<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0702-4580-0367-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">AIR (7th edition, volume 2, page 367)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:802066">Air</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980998">Jackets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1064480">Pipe</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1064723">Piping</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1115061">Shafting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1030269">Music</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1030814">Musicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:834062">Bladder</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jd4pp0f">Air</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2ch0v">Music</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4f18sp5w">Shafting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xg19">Bladder</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j97h5v">Thread</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pg1hs5x">Gun</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ng4gw65">Gunning</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r90k">Pumps</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q52fm20">Pipe</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193034580?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">AIR</label>, in <hi rend="italic">Physics.</hi> See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Atmosphere, Meteorology,</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Pneumatics.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Air,</hi> in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Mythology,</hi> was adored by the heathens under the names of Jupiter and Juno;
                    the former representing the superior and finer part of the atmosphere, and the
                    latter the inferior and grosser part. The augurs also drew presages from the
                    clouds, thunder, &amp;c.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Air,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Painting,</hi> &amp;c.
                    denotes the manner and very life of action; òr it is that which expresses the
                    disposition of die agent. It is sometimes also used in a synonymous sense with
                    gesture or attitude.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Air,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Music,</hi> is taken in
                    different senses. It is sometimes contrasted with harmony, and in this sense it
                    is synonymous with melody in general.—Its proper meaning is, a tune, which is
                    set to words, or to short pieces of poetry, that are called <hi rend="italic"
                    >songs.</hi></p>
                <p>In operas we give the name of <hi rend="italic">air</hi> to such pieces of music
                    as are formed with measures and cadences to distinguish it from the recitative;
                    and, in general, every piece of music is called an <hi rend="italic">air</hi>
                    which is formed for the voice, or even for instruments, and adapted to stanzas,
                    whether it forms a whole in itself, or whether it can be detached from any whole
                    of which it forms a part, and be executed alone. *</p>
                <p>If the subject admits of harmony, and is set in parts, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >air</hi> is, according to their number, denominated a <hi rend="italic"
                    >duet,</hi> a <hi rend="italic">trio,</hi> a <hi rend="italic">quartetto,</hi>
                    &amp;c. We need not follow Rousseau and the other philologists in their
                    endeavours to investigate the etymon of the word <hi rend="italic">air.</hi> Its
                    derivation, though found and ascertained, would contribute little to illustrate
                    its meaning in that remote sense to which, through a long continuance of time,
                    and the various vicissitudes of language, it has now passed. The curious may
                    consult the same article in the <hi rend="italic">Dictionnaire de Musique</hi>
                    by Μ. Rousseau.</p>
                <p>In modern music, there are several different kinds of <hi rend="italic"
                    >airs,</hi> each of which agrees to a certain kind of dancing; and from these
                    dances the airs themselves take their specific names.</p>
                <p>The words to which <hi rend="italic">airs</hi> are adapted are not always
                    rehearsed in regular succession, nor spoken in the same manner with those of the
                    recitative; and though in general they are very short, yet they are interrupted,
                    repeated, transposed, at the pleasure of the artist. They do not constitute a
                    narrative, which once told is over; they either delineate a picture which it is
                    necessary to contemplate in different points of view, or inspire a sentiment in
                    which the heart acquiesces with pleasure, and from which it is neither able nor
                    willing to be disengaged; and the different phrases of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >air</hi> are nothing else than different manners of beholding the same image.
                    This is the reason why the subject of an <hi rend="italic">air</hi> should be
                    one. It is by these repetitions properly placed, it is by these redoubled
                    efforts, that an impression, which at first was not able to move you, at length
                    shakes your soul, agitates you, transports you out of yourself; and it is
                    likewise upon the same principle that the runnings, as they are called, or those
                    long, mazy, and inarticulated inflections of the voice, in pathetic <hi
                    rend="italic">airs,</hi> frequently seem, though they are not always so,
                    improperly placed; for whilst the heart is affected with a sentiment exquisitely
                    moving, it often expresses its emotions by inarticulate sounds, more strongly
                    and sensibly than it could do by words themselves.</p>
                <p>The form of <hi rend="italic">airs</hi> is of two kinds. The small airs are often
                    composed of two strains, which ought each of them to be sung twice; but the
                    important airs in operas are frequently in the form of rondeaus.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Air-</hi><hi rend="italic">Gun,</hi> a pneumatic
                    machine for exploding bullets, &amp;c. with great violence. See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Pneumatics.</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Air-</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Jacket,</hi> a sort of jacket made of leather, in which are
                    several bags or bladders, composed of the same materials, communicating with
                    each other. These are filled with air through a leather tube having a brass
                    stop-cock accurately ground at the extremity, by which means the air blown in
                    through the tube is confined in the bladders. The jacket must be wet before the
                    air be blown into the bags, as otherwise it will immediately escape through the
                    pores of the leather. By the help of these bladders, which are placed near the
                    breast, the person is supported in the water, without making the efforts used in
                    swimming.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">AiR-Pipes.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Ventilators.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">AiR-Pump,</hi> a machine by which the air contained in a proper
                    vessel may be exhausted or drawn out. See <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Pneumatics.</hi><hi rend="italic">Aιn-Shafts,</hi> among <hi rend="italic"
                    >Miners,</hi> denote holes or shafts let down from the open air to meet the
                    adits and furnish fresh <pb break="no" facs="nls:193034593?mode=fullsize"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0702-4593-0368"/> air. The damps, deficiency, and impurity of air
                    which occur, when adits are wrought 30 or 40 fathoms long, make it necessary to
                    let down air-shafts, in order to give the air liberty to play through the whole
                    work, and thus discharge bad vapours, and furnish good air for respiration: the
                    expense of which shafts, in regard of their vast depths, hardness of the rock,
                    drawing of water, &amp;c. sometimes equals, nay exceeds, the ordinary charge of
                    the whole adit.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ain-Threads,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Natural History,</hi> a
                    name given to the long filaments so frequently seen in autumn floating about in
                    the air.</p>
                <p>These threads are the work of spiders, especially of that species called the
                    long-legged field spider, which, having mounted to the summit of a bush or tree,
                    darts from its tail several of these threads, till one is produced capable of
                    supporting the creature in the air. On this it mounts in quest of prey, and
                    frequently rises to a very considerable height.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">AiR-Trunk,</hi> the name of a contrivance by Dr Hales, to
                    prevent the stagnation of putrid effluvia in jails and other places, where a
                    great number of people are crowded together in a small space. It consists only
                    of a long square trunk open at both ends, one of which is inserted into the
                    ceiling of the room, the air of which is required to be kept pure, and the other
                    extends a good way beyond the roof. Through this trunk a continued circulation
                    is carried on; and the reason is, that the putrid effluvia which do so much
                    mischief when collected, being much lighter than the pure atmosphere, arise to
                    the top of the room, and, if they there find a vent, will continually go out
                    through it. These effluvia arise in very considerable quantity, being calculated
                    by Dr Keil at no less than 39 ounces from one man in 24 hours.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">AIR-Vessels</hi> are spiral ducts in the leaves, &amp;c. of
                    plants, supposed to be analogous to the lungs of animals, in supplying the
                    different parts of a plant with air.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
