<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0702-8363-0658-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">AMMON (7th edition, volume 2, page 658)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17ss11">Trees</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40p0ww6s">Journeys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9q77g">Desertion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49z90f3q">Deserts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47s7ht9n">Walls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tx35b4z">Wells</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vq1n">Fountains</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1198483">Brown</term>
                    <term ref="fast:903991">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1173723">Wells</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1155984">Trees</term>
                    <term ref="fast:891230">Deserts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170190">Walls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:866956">Cold</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193038363?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">AMMON</label>, anciently a city of Marmarica. (Ptolemy.)
                    Arrian calls it <hi rend="italic">a place,</hi> not a city, in which stood the
                    temple of Jupiter Ammon, entirely surrounded by sandy wastes. Pliny states, that
                    the oracle of Ammon was 12 days’ journey from Memphis, and among the <hi
                    rend="italic">Nomi</hi> of Egypt he reckons the <hi rend="italic">Nomos</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Ammoniacus</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> Diodorus Siculus, that the
                    district where the temple stood, though surrounded with deserts, was watered by
                    dews which fell nowhere else in all that country. It was agreeably adorned with
                    fruitful trees and springs, and full of villages. In the middle stood the
                    Acropolis or citadel, encompassed with a triple wall; the first and inmost of
                    which contained the palace; the others the apartments of the women, the
                    relations, and children, as also the temple of the god, and the sacred fountains
                    for lustrations. Without the Acropolis stood, at no great distance, another
                    temple of Ammon, shaded by a number of tall trees; near which there was a
                    fountain, called that of the sun, or <hi rend="italic">Solis</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Fons,</hi> because subject to extraordinary changes according to
                    the time of the day; morning and evening warm, at noon cold, at midnight
                    extremely hot. A kind of fossil salt was said to be naturally produced here. It
                    was dug out of the earth in large oblong pieces, transparent as crystal. It was
                    thought to be a present worthy of kings, and used by the Egyptians in their
                    sacrifices. From this our sal-ammoniac has taken its name. The observations of
                    Brown and Hornemann prove that the oasis of Siwah is the district in which this
                    celebrated oracle was situated. Pliny places it at 12 days’ journey from
                    Memphis, and Hornemann reached Siwah in 12 days from Cairo. These travellers
                    found an old building 32 feet long, 15 broad, and 18 high, formed of large
                    stones, and with some hieroglyphics upon it. This is most probably the ancient
                    sanctuary of Jupiter, which was placed in an inclosure, and surrounded by an
                    outer wall. Near this old building is a spring, which still preserves, in
                    popular opinion, the qualities attributed by the ancients to the Fountain of the
                    Sun, and which in fact belong to all deep-seated cold springs: it is said to be
                    warm in the night and cold in the day. Our modern travellers found also the salt
                    incrustations, the numerous date-trees, and the sea-shells and fossil wood in
                    the neighbouring desert, which Strabo and other old writers notice. Arrian and
                    Diodorus describe the district as having a breadth of 40 or 50 stadia, with
                    which Brown’s estimate of 4 to 6 English miles nearly agrees. Hornemann makes
                    the circumference 50 miles, but he includes some patches of habitable land near
                    it, but not continuous with it. Siwah is inhabited by a considerable number of
                    people, who are Mahometans.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Ammon,</hi> or <hi rend="smallcaps">Hammon,</hi> in <hi
                    rend="italic">Heathen Mythology,</hi> the name of the Egyptian Jupiter,
                    worshipped under the figure of a ram. Bacchus having subdued Asia, and passing
                    with his army through the deserts of Africa, was in great want of water; but
                    Jupiter, his father, assuming the shape of a ram, led him to a fountain, where
                    he refreshed himself and his army; in gratitude for which favour, Bacchus built
                    there a temple to Jupiter, under the title of <hi rend="italic">Ammon,</hi> from
                    the Greek <hi rend="italic">auμος,</hi> which signifies <hi rend="italic"
                    >sand,</hi> alluding to the sandy desert where it was built. In this temple was
                    an oracle of great note, which Alexander the Great consulted, and which lasted
                    till the time of Theodosius.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Ammon,</hi> or <hi rend="smallcaps">Ammonius,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Andreas,</hi> an excellent Latin poet, born at Lucca in Italy, was
                    sent by Pope Leo X. to England, in the characters of prothonotary of the
                    apostolic see, and collector-general of that kingdom. He was a man of singular
                    genius and learning, and soon became acquainted with the principal literati of
                    those times; particularly with Erasmus, Colet, and others, for the sake of whose
                    company he resided some time at Oxford. The advice which Erasmus gives him, in
                    regard to pushing <pb break="no" facs="nls:193038376?mode=fullsize"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0702-8376-0659"/> his fortune, has a good deal of humour in it, and
                    was certainly intended as a satire on the artful methods generally practised by
                    the selfish and ambitious part of mankind. “In the first place,” says he, “throw
                    off all sense of shame; thrust yourself into every one’s business, and elbow out
                    whomsoever you can; neither love nor hate any one; measure every thing by your
                    own advantage; let this be the scope and drift of all your actions. Give nothing
                    but what is to be returned with usury, and be complaisant to every body. Have
                    always two strings to your bow. Feign that you are solicited by many from
                    abroad, and get every thing ready for your departure. Show letters inviting you
                    elsewhere, with great promises.” Ammon was Latin secretary to Henry VIII., but
                    at what time he was appointed does not appear. In 1512 he was made canon and
                    prebendary of the collegiate chapel of St Stephen, in the palace of Westminster.
                    He was likewise prebendary of Wells; and in 1514 was presented to the rectory of
                    Dychial in that diocese. About the same time, by the king’s special
                    recommendation, he was also made prebendary of Salisbury. He died in the year
                    1517, and was buried in St Stephen’s chapel in the palace of Westminster. He was
                    esteemed an elegant Latin writer, and an admirable poet. The epistles of Erasmus
                    to Ammon abound with encomiums on his genius and learning. His works are, 1.
                    Epistolae ad Erasmum, lib. i.; 2. Scotici Conflictus Historia, lib. i.; 3.
                    Bucolicae vel Eclogae, lib. i. Basil, 1546, 8vo; 4. De Rebus Nihil, lib. i.; 5.
                    Panegyricus quidam, lib. i.; 6. Varii Generis Epigrammata, lib. i.; 7. Poėmata
                    Diversa, lib. i.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
