<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0702-0888-0083-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ACCENT (7th edition, volume 2, page 83)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62f7n">Reading</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4707wx1r">Ships</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n5c">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4np1wt1r">Syrians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4959c77k">Cooperation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1090626">Reading</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1119311">Singing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1116352">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1116439">Ships</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193030888?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ACCENT</label>, in <hi rend="italic">reading</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">speaking,</hi> an inflection of the voice, which gives to each
                    syllable of a word its due pitch in-respect of height or lowness. See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Reading.</hi> The word is originally Latin, <hi rend="italic"
                    >accentus</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> a compound of <hi rend="italic">ad,</hi>
                    to, and <hi rend="italic">cano,</hi> to sing. <hi rend="italic">Accentus</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">quasi adcantus,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">juχtα can-turn.</hi> In
                    this sense, accent is synonymous with the Greek <hi rend="italic">τονος</hi>;
                    the Latin <hi rend="italic">tenor,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">tonor</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> and the Hebrew t□yto, <hi rend="italic">gustus,</hi> taste,
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Accent,</hi> among grammarians, is a certain mark, or <pb
                    break="no" facs="nls:193030901?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0702-0901-0084"/>
                    character placed over a syllable to direct the stress of its pronunciation. We
                    generally reckon three grammatical accents in ordinary use, all borrowed from
                    the Greeks, viz. the <hi rend="italic">acute accent ('),</hi> which shows when
                    the tone of the voice is to be raised; the <hi rend="italic">grave accent</hi>
                    ('), when the note or tone of the voice is to be depressed; and the <hi
                    rend="italic">circumflex accent (</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> a</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">),</hi> which is composed of both the acute and the grave, and
                    points out a kind of undulation of the voice. The Latins have made the same use
                    as the Greeks of these three accents.</p>
                <p>The Hebrews have a grammatical, a rhetorical, and a musical accent; though the
                    first and last seem, in effect, to be the same, both being comprised under the
                    general name of <hi rend="italic">tonic accents,</hi> because they give the
                    proper tones to syllables; as the rhetorical accents are said to be euphonic,
                    because they tend to make the pronunciation more sweet and agreeable. There are
                    four euphonic accents, and twenty-five tonic: of these some are placed above,
                    and others below the syllables; the Hebrew accents serving not only to regulate
                    the risings and fallings of the voice, but also to distinguish the sections,
                    periods, and members of periods, in a discourse, and to answer the same purposes
                    with the points in other languages. Their accents are divided into <hi
                    rend="italic">emperors, kings, dukes,</hi> &amp;c. each bearing a title
                    answerable to the importance of the distinction it makes. Their emperor rules
                    over a whole phrase, and terminates the sense completely; answering to our
                    point. Their king answers to our colon; and their duke to our comma. The king,
                    however, occasionally becomes a duke, and the duke a king, as the phrases are
                    more or less short. It must be noted, by the way, that the management and
                    combination of these accents in Hebrew poetry differ from their management and
                    combination in prose. The use of the tonic or grammatical accents has been much
                    controverted; some holding that they distinguish the sense, while others
                    maintain that they are only intended to regulate the music or singing, alleging
                    that the Jews sing rather than read the Scriptures in their synagogues.<note
                    anchored="true" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Cooper, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Dorn. Mosaic. Clav.</hi> p. 31.</p></note> Be this, however, as it will, it is
                    certain the ancient Hebrews were not acquainted with these accents. The opinion
                    which prevails amongst the learned is, that they were invented about the sixth
                    century, by the Jewish doctors of the school of Tiberias, called the <hi
                    rend="italic">Massorets.</hi></p>
                <p>As to the Greek accents, now seen both in manuscripts and printed books, there
                    has been no less dispute about their antiquity and use than about those of the
                    Hebrews. Isaac Vossius endeavours to prove them of modern invention; asserting,
                    that anciently they had nothing of this kind, but only a few notes in their
                    poetry, which were invented by Aristophanes the grammarian, about the time of
                    Ptolemy Philopater; and that these were of musical rather than grammatical use,
                    serving as aids in the singing of their poems, and being very different from
                    those afterwards introduced. He also shows, from several ancient grammarians,
                    that the manner of writing the Greek accents in those days was quite different
                    from that which appears in our books. The author of <hi rend="italic">Lα
                    Methode</hi><hi rend="italic">Grecque,</hi> p.546, observes, that the right
                    pronunciation of the Greek language being natural to the Greeks, it was needless
                    for them to mark it by accents in their writings; so that, according ţo all
                    appearance, they only began to make use of them about the time when the Romans,
                    wishing to learn the Greek tongue, sent their children to study at Athens,
                    thinking thereby to fix the pronunciation, and to facilitate it to strangers;
                    which happened, as the same author observes, a little before Cicero’s time.
                    Wetstein, Greek professor at Basil, in a learned dissertation, endeavours to
                    prove the Greek accents of an older standing. He owns that they were not always
                    formed in the same manner by the ancients, but he thinks that difference owing
                    to the different pronunciation which obtained' in the different parts of Greece.
                    He also brings several reasons, <hi rend="italic">a priori,</hi> for the use of
                    accents, even in the earliest days: as, that all writing being then in capital
                    letters equidistant from each other, without any distinction either of Words or
                    phrases, it could scarcely have been rendered intelligible without accents; and
                    that accents were necessary to distinguish ambiguous words, and to point out
                    their proper meaning, as appears from a dispute in regard to a passage of Homer,
                    mentioned by Aristotle in his <hi rend="italic">Poetics,</hi> qhap. V.
                    Accordingly, he observes that the Syrians, who have tonic, but not distinctive
                    accents, have yet invented certain points, placed either below or above the
                    words, to show their mood, tense, person, or sense.</p>
                <p>Mr Browne of Trinity College, Dublin, has entered more deeply into this
                    investigation; and as he had an opportunity of conversing with the crew of a
                    Greek ship from Patras, a town situated not far distant from the ancient
                    Corinth, which had been driven by stress of weather into the port of Dingle in
                    Ireland, the result of his inquiries was, that the practice of the modern Greeks
                    is different from any of the theories that have been delivered in books. “It is
                    true,” he observes, “they have not two pronunciations for prose and for verse,
                    and in both they read by accent; but they make accent the cause of quantity,
                    they make it govern and control quantity, they make the syllable long on which
                    the acute accent falls, and they allow the acute accent to change the real
                    quantity. They always read poetry as well as prose by accent. Whether any
                    inference can hence be drawn as to the pronunciation of the ancients, I must
                    leave, after what I have premised above, to men of more learning; but I think it
                    at least so probable as to make it worth while to mention the instances which
                    occurred in proof of this assertion more particularly. Of the two first persons
                    whom I met, one, the steward of the ship, an inhabitant of the island of
                    Cephalonia, had had a school education: he read Euripides, and translated some
                    easier passages, without much difficulty. By a stay in this country of near two
                    years, he was able to speak English very tolerably, as could also the captain
                    and several of the crew; and almost all of them spoke Italian fluently. The
                    companion, however, of the steward· could speak only modern Greek, in which I
                    could discover that he was giving a description of the distress in which the
                    ship had been; and though not able to understand the context, I could plainly
                    distinguish many words, such as <hi rend="italic">δενδξα, ξυλοv,</hi> and among
                    the rest the sound of <hi rend="italic">Aν6ξωττος</hi> pronounced short. This
                    awoke my curiosity, which w as still more heightened when I observed that he
                    said <hi rend="italic">Av0gωπων</hi> long, with the same attention to the
                    alteration of the accent with the variety of case, which a boy would be taught
                    to pay at a school in England. Watching therefore more closely, and asking the
                    other to read some ancient Greek, I found that they both uniformly pronounced
                    according to accent, without any attention to long or short syllables where
                    accent came in the way; and on their departure, one of them having bid me good
                    day, by saying <hi rend="italic">^Kαλημεgα,</hi> to which I answered <hi
                    rend="italic">^Kαλημεgα,</hi> he with strong marks of reprobation set me right,
                    and repeated <hi rend="italic">^Kαλημεgα</hi>; and with like censure did the
                    captain upon another occasion observe upon my saying Socrates instead of
                    Socrates.</p>
                <p>“I now had a strong wish to know whether they observed the distinction in this
                    respect usually between verse and prose; but from the little scholarship of the
                    two men with whom I had conversed, from the ignorance of a third whom I
                    afterwards met, (who however read Lucian with ease, though he did not seem ever
                    to have heard of <pb break="no" facs="nls:193030914?mode=fullsize"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0702-0914-0085"/> the book,) and on account of my imperfect mode of
                    conversing with them all, I had little hopes of satisfaction on the point-; nor
                    was I clear that they perfectly knew the difference between verse and prose. At
                    length, having met with the commander of the ship, and his clerk Athanasius <hi
                    rend="italic">Kονομος,</hi> and finding that the latter had been a schoolmaster
                    in the Morea, and had here learnt to speak English fluently, I put the question
                    to them in the presence of a very learned college friend, and at another time,
                    to avoid any error, with the aid of a gentleman who is perfectly master of the
                    Italian language. Both the Greeks repeatedly assured us that verse as well as
                    prose was read by accent, and not by quantity; and exemplified it by reading
                    several lines of Homer, with whose name they seemed perfectly well
                    acquainted.</p>
                <p>“I shall give an instance or two of their mode of reading:</p>
                <lg part="N">
                    <l part="N"><hi rend="italic">Βη</hi><hi rend="italic">δ'</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >ά£εων</hi><hi rend="italic">¶agà ⅛ινα τrολιrpλοισζοιο ⅛dKασσης,</hi></l>
                    <l part="N"> Tòv <hi rend="italic">δ' αvαμειZομενος πζοσf&lt;pη ποδας
                        ωκυς</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> ,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Aχιλλευς,</hi></l>
                    <l part="N"> ’ <hi rend="italic">Eς δ' εgετας επιτηδες αγειgoμεν, 'ες δ</hi> ’
                        <hi rend="italic">εκατoμζην.</hi></l>
                </lg>
                <p>They made the £ in αz≡wv, <hi rend="italic">πgοσε&lt;pη,</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">εgετctς,</hi> long. But when they read</p>
                <l part="N"><hi rend="italic">^Kλυ6ι μευ&gt;</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">Aξγυg6nζ,</hi>
                    íJ¢ <hi rend="italic">Xg{ισην</hi><hi rend="italic">άμφιζεζηκας,</hi></l>
                <p>they made the second syllable of the first word <hi rend="italic">~Kλυ0ι</hi>
                    short, notwithstanding the acute accent: on my asking why, they desired me to
                    look back on the circumflex on the first syllable, and said it thence
                    necessarily followed; for it is impossible to pronounce the first syllable with
                    the great length which the circumflex denotes, and not to shorten the second.
                    The testimony of the schoolmaster might be vitiated; but what could be stronger
                    than that of these ignorant mariners as to the vulgar common practice of modern
                    Greece? and it is remarkable that this confirms the opinion of Bishop Horsley,
                    that the tones of words in connection are not always the same with the tones of
                    solitary words, though in those of more than one syllable the accentual marks do
                    not change their position. I must here add, that these men confirmed an
                    observation which I have heard made, that we are much mistaken in our idea of
                    the supposed lofty sound of <hi rend="italic">πολv&lt;pλοισζοιο</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> ,</hi><hi rend="italic">i}αλασσης</hi>; that the
                    borderers on the coast of the Archipelago take their ideas from the gentle
                    laving of the shore by a summer wave, and not from the roaring of a winter
                    ocean; and they accordingly pronounced it <hi rend="italic">polyphlisveo
                    tkalasses.</hi></p>
                <p>“I own that the observations made by me on the pronunciation of these modern
                    Greeks brought a perfectly new train of ideas into my mind. I propose them, with
                    humility, for the consideration of the learned; but they have made a strong
                    impression upon me, and approached, when compared with other admitted facts,
                    nearly to conviction. In short, I am strongly inclined to believe, that what the
                    famous treatise so often mentioned on the prosodies of the Greek and Latin
                    languages mentions as the peculiarity of the English, that we always prolong the
                    sound of the syllable on which the acute accent falls, is true, and has been
                    true of every nation upon earth. We know it is true of the modern Italians: they
                    read Latin in that respect just as we do, and say, <hi rend="italic">Arma
                    virumque cano,</hi> and, <hi rend="italic">In nova fert animus,</hi> as much as
                    we. And when we find the modern Greeks following the same practice, surely we
                    have some cause to suppose that the ancients did the same. In the English
                    language, indeed, quantity is not affected, because accent and quantity always
                    agree. Bishop Horsley endeavoured to prove that they did so in Greek, but this
                    is on the bold supposition that the accent doth not fall where the mark is
                    placed. The objection to this hypothesis, which seems to have been admitted by
                    all writers, and considered as decisive by some as to prose, by all as to verse,
                    is, that such a mode of pronunciation or reading must destroy metre, or <hi
                    rend="italic">rhythmus.</hi> From this' position, however universal, or however
                    it may have been taken for granted, I totally dissent.^ That it will oppose the
                    metre or quantity I readily agréé; but that it will destroy the rhythmus, (by
                    which, whatever learned descriptions there may have been of its meaning, I
                    understand nothing more than the melody or smooth flowing of the verses, or
                    their harmony, if you please, if harmony be properly applied to successive and
                    not synchronal sounds,) I can by no means admit. On the contrary, nothing can be
                    more disagreeable or unmelodious than the reading verse by quantity, or scanning
                    of it, as it is vulgarly called. Let us try the line so often quoted—</p>
                <l part="N"><hi rend="italic">Armă vĭrūmqŭe cănō, Trōjaē qui prīmŭs ăb
                    ōrīs,</hi></l>
                <p>instead of</p>
                <l part="N"><hi rend="italic">Ārmă vĭrūmqūe cānŏ, Trōjaē qūi prīmŭs ăb
                    ōrīs.</hi></l>
                <p>“No man ever defined rhythmus better than Plato, <hi rend="italic"
                    >ordinem</hi><hi rend="italic">quendam</hi><hi rend="italic">qui</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">in</hi><hi rend="italic">motibus cernitur</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >;</hi> the motion or measure of the verse may be ėx'ąct, and yet the order,
                    arrangement, and disposition of the letters and syllables such as to be grating
                    and unmelbdiouś to the ear. In like manner the feet of the verse may be exact,
                    but the stress laid upon particular syllables of it which follows the quantity
                    may totally destroy the méßdy: in short, the radical error seems to be the
                    confusion'of quantity with melody, and the supposition that whatever is at war
                    with quantity and metre must be at war with melody.</p>
                <p>“It will be asked, then, what is the use of metre or measure in verse, if we are
                    not to read by it; and here is the grand difficulty; and I own with candour I
                    cannot answer it with perfect satisfaction to my own mind: to those, indeed, who
                    say wc are to read by accent in prose, it may be equally asked, what is the usé
                    of long or short syllables in prose, if we are not to attend to them when,
                    accent comes in the way; but to those who think otherwise, I can only answer,
                    that in the first place accent doth not always interfere, and then quantity is
                    our guide, and accent often accords with quantity. Secondly, metre determines
                    the number of feet or measures in each verse, and thereby produces a general
                    analogy and harmony through the whole; and it is to be observed, that, as I
                    apprehend, accent doth not change the number of feet, though it doth the nature
                    or species of them. Thus when we read</p>
                <l part="N"><hi rend="italic">Arma virumque cano, Trojae</hi><hi rend="italic">qui
                    primus ab</hi><hi rend="italic">oris,</hi> we do not make more feet than when we
                    scan the line, nor employ more time than in pronouncing the next line, in which
                    the accent happens to accord with the quantity, viz. </l>
                <l part="N"><hi rend="italic">Italiam fato</hi><hi rend="italic">profiιgus,
                    Lavinaque</hi><hi rend="italic">venit.</hi></l>
                <p>Thirdly, the poet in measuring his verse certainly must be confined to some
                    certain number and order of long and short syllables, in order to produce a
                    concordance through the whole, and even to regulate the position of accent,
                    which, though not subdued by quantity, will certainly have some relation to it,
                    <hi rend="italic">euphoniae gratia</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> but surely the
                    length or shortness of a syllable cannot determine where emphasis shall be
                    placed—that must depend on the meaning and the thought; and it would be most
                    absurd for the poet to say to the reader, you shall not rest upon this emphatic
                    and significative word because its syllables are short, and wherever there is a
                    rest, there must be length and intonation.” <hi rend="italic">(Irish Trans,</hi>
                    vol. vii.)</p>
                <p>The use of accents to prevent ambiguities is most remarkably perceived in some
                    eastern languages, particularly the Siameseand Chinese. Among the people of
                    China, every <pb break="no" facs="nls:193030927?mode=fullsize"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0702-0927-0086"/> word, or, which is the same thing, every
                    syllable, admits of five accents, according as it is spoken more acutely or re-
                    , missly; and thus standsformany different things. The same sound <hi
                    rend="italic">ya,</hi> according to the accent affixed to it, signifies <hi
                    rend="italic">God, a wall, excellent, stupidity,</hi> and a <hi rend="italic"
                    >goose.</hi> The Chinese have but 330 spoken words in their language; but these
                    being multiplied by the different accents or tones which’ affect the vowels,
                    furnish a language tolerably copious. By means of accents, their 330 simple
                    sounds come to denote 1650 things; but this being hardly sufficient, they are
                    increased further by aspirates added to each word, to double the number. The
                    Chinese only reckon four <hi rend="italic">accents,</hi> for which the
                    missionaries use the following marks, <hi rend="italic">aa, a, à, a</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> to which they have added a fifth, thus <hi rend="italic"
                    >α.</hi> They make a kind of modulation, wherein, prolonging the duration of the
                    sound of the vowel, they vary the tone, raising and sinking it by a certain
                    pitch of voice; so that their talking is a sort of music or singing. Attempts
                    have been made to determine the quantity of the rise or fall on each accent by
                    means of musical notes; but this is hard to effect, as being different in
                    different persbns. Hence the great difficulty of the language to foreigners, who
                    are forced to sing most scrupulously; for if they deviate ever so little from
                    the accent, they say quite a different thing from what was intended. Thus,
                    meaning to compliment the person you are talking of with the title <hi
                    rend="italic">Sir,</hi> you call him a beast with the same word, only a little
                    varied in the tone. Magalhon, however, makes the language easier to learn on
                    this account. The Siamese are also observed to sing rather than to talk. Their
                    alphabet begins with six characters, all only equivalent to a K, but differently
                    accented. For though in the pronunciation the accents are naturally on the
                    vowels, yet they have some to diversify such of their consonants as are in other
                    respects the same.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Accent,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Music,</hi> is a certain
                    enforcement of particular sounds, whether by the voice or instruments, generally
                    used at the beginning of bars.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Acceptance,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Commerce,</hi> is the
                    subscribing, signing, and making one’s self debtor for the sum contained in a
                    bill of exchange or other obligation.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
