<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0702-4554-0365-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">AJMEER, or Rajpootana (7th edition, volume 2, page
                    365)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4599z60x">Hindoos</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2cg69">Mahrattas</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gh9bg6t">Mussulmans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k06x81c">Rana</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40p0ww6s">Journeys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9q77g">Desertion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49z90f3q">Deserts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tx35b4z">Wells</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1089716">Rana</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1071040">Poor</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:891230">Deserts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1173723">Wells</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1124682">Soils</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193034554?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">AJMEER, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Rajpootana</hi></label>, a
                    large province situated in the centre of Hindostan, between the 24th and 31st
                    degrees of N. lat. It is bounded on the north by the provinces of Moultan,
                    Lahore, and Delhi; on the south by Gujerat and Malwah; on the east by Delhi and
                    Agra, and on the west by Moultan and the principality of Sinde. From north to
                    south it extends 350 miles, and is 200 in average breadth. The following are the
                    modern divisions of this province :—</p>
                <p>1. The Bhatty country.</p>
                <p>2. Bicanere.</p>
                <p>3. The Great Sandy Desert 4. Jesselmere.</p>
                <p>5. Joudpoor.</p>
                <p>6. Marwar.</p>
                <p>7. Nagore.</p>
                <p>8. Shekawutty.</p>
                <p>9. Jeypoor.</p>
                <p>10. Ajmeer district</p>
                <p>11. Harowty.</p>
                <p>12. Odeypoor.</p>
                <p>13. Mewar.</p>
                <p>14. Sarowy.</p>
                <p>This province is generally of a barren and sandy soil, in many parts a good deal
                    covered by thorny trees and thickets of the cactus. The province of Marwar has a
                    superior soil, and is in a better state of cultivation than the eastern
                    provinces of Jeypoor and Ajmeer, or the southwestern tract of Mewar, including
                    Odeypoor. This part of the country was laid waste to such a degree by the
                    ravages of the Pindarees, that it has yet scarcely recovered. The soil,
                    naturally arid, is in some of the southern provinces rendered productive by
                    streams which descend from the mountains. The Chumbul, Calysina, and Banass are
                    the most considerable streams; and where they afford supplies of moisture, the
                    country presents something like the appearance of verdure. The soil of the whole
                    province is remarkably saline, containing many salt springs and lakes, and
                    producing salt and saltpetre spontaneously. In other parts, in order to procure
                    a supply of water, deep wells are sunk, from which the country being partially
                    irrigated, yields wheat, barley, and other sorts of grain and pulse common in
                    India. In Marwar, where they derive their supplies of water from these deep
                    wells, Bishop Heber mentions that he saw cotton growing of the finest quality,
                    and oxen and sheep which bore evidence, by their size and fatness, of the
                    luxuriance of the pasture. Other parts, again, of the southern provinces are
                    strangely desolate, though the ruins with which they are covered, and the
                    numerous tombs, show that they have been inhabited at no distant period, and
                    that their present desolation has been the work of violence.</p>
                <p>Towards the east, and in the north, there is an extensive tract, which is a
                    continued desert of the most dismal appearance. Towards the south mountainous
                    tracts occur, and between Marwar and Mewar they rise to 2000 feet above the
                    level of the sea. The mountains of Aboo, towards the western boundary, rise, it
                    is supposed, to the height of 6000 feet. Except in the mountains, trees are
                    seldom seen; and the consequence is, that timber for building and other purposes
                    is extremely scarce, and proportionably dear. Such is the scarcity of wooden
                    furniture, that at dinner parties it is the practice among the British residents
                    for ladies and gentlemen to send their own chairs to the house where the
                    entertainment is to take place; and they have nothing better for their doors and
                    windows than pieces of matting. The Shekawultz country on the west is sandy,
                    badly watered and cultivated, scattered over with rocky hills, and sprinkled
                    with tufts of long grass and bushes. Yet it contains several large towns; and it
                    seems to lose its title to be included in the desert, when compared with the
                    tract which extends north-east as far as Bahawulpoor, a distance of 280 miles;
                    and even this tract is only for the last hundred miles absolutely destitute of
                    inhabitants, water, or vegetation. For 180 miles the country presents the
                    appearance of hills and valleys of loose and heavy sand from 20 to 100 feet in
                    height. These hills shift their positions; and the passage of the desert is
                    rendered dangerous in summer by clouds of moving sand. Among these sandy deserts
                    villages are occasionally met with, which consist merely of a few round huts of
                    straw, with low conical roofs like stooks of corn. They are surrounded by hedges
                    of dry thorny branches, stuck in the sand. Around these miserable abodes are to
                    be seen a few fields, which depend for water on the rains and dews, and which
                    bear thin crops of the poorest kinds of pulse, and a species of the <hi
                    rend="italic">holcus</hi><hi rend="italic">spi-</hi><pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193034567?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0702-4567-0366"/><hi
                    rend="italic">catus,</hi> which, though it flourishes in the most sterile
                    countries, grows here with difficulty, each stalk several feet from its
                    neighbour. In this arid waste is found in profusion the most juicy of all
                    fruits, the water-melon. Some of these grow to the size of three or four feet in
                    circumference, from a stalk as slender as that of the common melon. Agriculture
                    depends on supplies of water procured from wells thinly scattered over the
                    country, and sunk to the enormous depth of 300 and 345 feet, while some of them
                    are only three feet in diameter. The water is drawn from these wells by
                    water-wheels worked by bullocks, in small quantities, and is brackish and
                    unwholesome. The wells are lined with masonry, and the natives frequently cover
                    them with boards heaped with sand, which effectually conceals them from an
                    enemy. The rest of the desert for 100 miles, from Poogul toBahawul-poor, is a
                    flat hard clay, which sounds under the horses’ hoofs like a board. In some
                    places small sand-hills are formed over the clay, on which a few plants shoot
                    up. But the clay is destitute of all appearance of vegetation; and, excepting at
                    the fort and pool of Monjgur, and two wells about sixteen miles from
                    Bahawulpoor, the country is wholly destitute both of inhabitants and of water.
                    In approaching the town of Bahawulpoor the desert and the cultivated country are
                    separated as if by a marked line. The edge of the desert is skirted by a long
                    row of trees; and beyond it are to be seen clumps of trees, green fields, and
                    wells of abundant and clear water, with houses and every sign of fertility and
                    cultivation. This great desert is 400 miles in breadth, and extends far beyond
                    the limits of Ajmeer. Several tracts are within the limits of the periodical
                    rains, and might be recovered from desolation by industry; but at present these
                    rains are absorbed by the thirsty soil, without any benefit whatever to the
                    inhabitants.</p>
                <p>The domestic animals are bullocks and camels. The animals of the desert are, the
                    antelope; the wild ass, remarkable for its shyness and for its speed; the fox;
                    and a curious species of rat, which is found in such numbers that the ground is
                    undermined by it in many parts, and is rendered dangerous to horsemen. The lower
                    classes of the people are Jauts. They are of small stature, ill-looking, and
                    have every appearance of poverty and wretchedness. The upper classes are Rhatore
                    Rajpoots. They are a stout and handsome race, with hooked noses and Jewish
                    features; of haughty manners, indolent in their habits, and almost continually
                    drunk with opium. The inhabitants are estimated at 3,000,000, the Mahometans
                    being to the Hindoos as one to eight. The principal towns are Jeypoor, Joudpoor,
                    Odeypoor, Ajmeer, Kotah, Bondee, Rantampoor, Chitore, Shahpoorah, Bicanere, and
                    Jesselmere. The three grand modern divisions of Raj-pootana are, Isí, Odeypoor,
                    named also Mewar and the Rana of Chitore; <hi rend="italic">2d,</hi> Joudpoor,
                    named also Marwar, and its sovereign occasionally described as the Rhatore
                    Rajah, being of that tribe; 3√, Jeypoor, Jynagur, or Ambeer, three names of one
                    state. From the dismemberment of these, the original Rajpoot states, others have
                    been formed, and in later times the rajahs of Jesselmere and Bicanere, and the
                    petty chiefs of Kotah, Boondee, and Banswara.</p>
                <p>The country is governed by numerous chiefs, who owe allegiance and pay tribute to
                    their liege lords; and who occasionally, as opportunities occur, have thrown off
                    their dependence, and have set up as independent sovereigns within their own
                    territories. During the scenes of confusion and trouble which took place in
                    Central India, previously to the last war, and general pacification in 1818,
                    Rajpootana was frequently laid waste by the inroads of the Pindarees and other
                    freebooters, who were in many cases abetted by the native chiefs. At that time
                    no title was secure; power was the only rule of right; and various portions of
                    the province were possessed and held by powerful invaders, such as Scindia and
                    Holkar. Such was the anarchy that prevailed in this province, as well as
                    generally in Central India, that every freebooter who could collect a sufficient
                    force extorted contributions from the peaceable inhabitants. The petty chiefs
                    were also frequently involved in war with each other; and the destruction
                    inseparable from such contests added to the mass of misery which already pressed
                    on the country. When the war undertaken by the British in 1817, against the
                    bands of plunderers who infested the country, and spread confusion and misery
                    wherever they appeared, was brought to a successful termination, Ajmeer was
                    finally rescued from the Mahratta influence, and placed under Sir D. Ochterlony,
                    as resident and commander; and a large body of troops was cantoned near the city
                    of Ajmeer, by whose presence the turbulent were overawed, and the public peace
                    preserved. Since this period tranquillity and good order have arisen out of
                    confusion; and the peaceable inhabitants, delivered from rapine, and from the
                    miseries of continued pillage and oppression, have resumed their former
                    occupations of commerce and agriculture. The different chiefs are allowed to
                    regulate their own internal policy; but they are no longer permitted to go to
                    war with each other, all their differences being now referred to the supreme
                    tribunal of British authority. (p.)</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Ajmeer,</hi> a city of Hindostan, in the province of
                    Aj-meer. It is situated on the slope of a hill, and was nearly ruined in the
                    long period of anarchy and misgovernment which prevailed in Central India prior
                    to 1819. It was acquired by the British from Scindia in 1818, when it was in a
                    state of the utmost desolation and decay. After this period it rapidly improved;
                    and in 1823 commerce had revived, and the population had been more than tripled.
                    Bishop Fieber, who visited it in 1825, mentions, that it is a well-built town,
                    of moderate size. The buildings are chiefly white-washed; and the surrounding
                    rocks have some thorny trees and brush-wood on them, which hide their
                    barrenness, and make a good back-ground to the little ruinous mosques and
                    Mussulman tombs which are scattered round the circuit of this holy city. Above,
                    on the mountain top, is a very remarkable fortress, called Tara-ghur, nearly two
                    miles in circuit, but, from its irregular shape and surface, not capable of
                    containing more than 1200 men. It consists of a plain stone-wall along the edge
                    of a mountain, strengthened with a few round bastions; and it has an abundant
                    supply of good water in all seasons, from cisterns cut in the rock. The works of
                    this fortress are now going fast to decay, as it is not the policy of the
                    British government to rely, for their security, on fortresses. The old palace
                    and garden of Shah Jehan still exist, and the former contains several habitable
                    rooms. Ajmeer is renowned as a place of pilgrimage, the great attraction being
                    the tomb of Khoja Mögen ud Deen, famed as a great Mahometan saint, whose
                    miracles are celebrated all over India. The tomb is of white marble, but
                    remarkable neither for style nor beauty of architecture. To this place the
                    emperor Acbar made a pilgrimage on foot, to implore at the sainted tomb the
                    blessing of male offspring. The emperors of Delhi formed a fine fresh-water lake
                    just above the city, which during the rains is six miles in circumference. It
                    supplies the means of irrigation to a large district on its banks, is full of
                    fish, and affords excellent water to the inhabitants of the town. Ajmeer is 80
                    miles W. S. W. from Jeypoor. Travelling distance from Delhi 230 miles; from
                    Bombay, 650; and from Calcutta, 1030 miles. Long. 74. 28. E. Lat. 26.31. N.
                    (Bishop Heber's <hi rend="italic">Journey through the Upper Provinces of
                    India;</hi> Hamilton<pb break="no" facs="nls:193034580?mode=fullsize"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0702-4580-0367"/>’s <hi rend="italic">Description of
                    Hindostan</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> Elph instone’s <hi rend="italic">Journey
                    into AfylMnistαn.')</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">(f.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
