<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0712-7396-0738-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">KIRMAN, or Kerman</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 12, page 738</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1028366">Mountains</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1179993">Wool</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:798948">Afghans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4qb9v878">Wool</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kh0c">Afghans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:192947396" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">KIRMAN, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Kerman</hi></label>, a
                    province of Persia, is bounded on the east by a part of Seistan and
                    Beloochìstan, west by the province <hi rend="italic">of</hi> Fars, south by
                    Laristan, Mukran, and the Persian Gulf, and north by Irak and Khorassan. It has
                    been in all ages partitioned into the habitable and desert regions; the former
                    extending, in extreme length, from Regan, in Nurmansheer, to Robat, on the
                    boundary of Fars, about 305 miles, and in breadth, from the southern limit of
                    Irak to the town of Gom-baroon or Bunder Abass, en the shore of the Persian
                    Gulf, about 280 miles in a direct line.</p>
                <p>Even the soil of this habitable tract is in many places unprolific, and the face
                    of the country barren and waste. There is not a river in the province, the few
                    streams that occur being merely mountain torrents swelled by the rains, and dry
                    during the remainder of the year; and were it not for a few springs in the
                    mountainous districts, and the karezes or under-ground aqueducts (a singular
                    contrivance, common in Persia, by which water is conducted, by means of pits
                    from thirty to ninety feet deep, and about 100 paces apart, and connected by a
                    common trench, sometimes a distance of thirty or forty miles), the inhabitants
                    could not possibly exist. In this manner water is procured with extraordinary
                    pains and attention, and withal not more than sufficient to cultivate a very
                    trifling portion of the soil. The only exception to this description is the
                    district of Nurmansheer , but, even here, the abundant supplies of water, once
                    so common, have much decreased within the last twenty years; and Lieutenant
                    Pöttinger, in travelling through this country, concluded, from the vast tracts
                    of desolate plains which are encountered in travelling across the country from
                    the east towards Kirman, that^ the desert was fast encroaching on the regions
                    <hi rend="italic">of</hi> cultivation.</p>
                <p>The country is, generally speaking, mountainous. The principal range of mountains
                    is that which divides Nurmansheer from Laristan, and thence, running in a
                    southwesterly direction, approaches within four days of Gombaroon. Here, running
                    along the coast to the west and north-west, it joins the mountains of Fars, in
                    latitude 29. 40. N. and longitude 54. E. In its course it throws out numerous
                    ramifications, both to the northward and southward. So entirely do these hills
                    intersect the country, that the plains which they separate seldom exceed ten or
                    twelve miles in breadth, though often of an indefinite length. The climate of
                    the province varies of course with the inequality of the ground. Snow lies to a
                    great depth on the mountains in winter, and, from their loftiness, it does not
                    melt for the greater part of the year; so that the people in the plains are
                    frequently seen panting from extreme heat, whilst it is freezing in the adjacent
                    mountains. The cold mountain air also is far from salubrious, as it brings along
                    with it agues, fevers, and other diseases; so that the natives prefer the most
                    sultry weather.</p>
                <p>To the southward of the great chain of mountains, and between their base and the
                    sea, lies the Gurmseer, or hot country, which is a narrow strip, varyingfrom
                    thirty to ten leagues in breadth, and extending all along the sea-coast of
                    Persia, from Meenab, the capital of Laristan, to the mouth of the Shatool-Arab
                    or Bussorah River. The portion of this tract that lies within the limits of
                    Kirman is almost solely composed <hi rend="italic">of</hi> saline sand; it
                    produces nothing but dates of a very inferior quality, and the climate is
                    peculiarly unhealthy.</p>
                <p>The desert region of Kirman extends 270 miles in length, from the northern
                    boundary of Nurmansheer, in latitude 29. 30. north, to the mountains of
                    Khorassan, in latitude 34. north; and in breadth 200 miles, from the city of
                    Yezd, in longitude 55. 40. east, to a range of mountains separating it from
                    Seistan, in 60° east. The whole of this tract is a salt desert, and so decidedly
                    barren, that it does not even produce grass, or any other vegetation, for eighty
                    or ninety miles at a stretch; nor is there a drop of water. The Afghan army, on
                    its march to invade Persia in 1719, lost one third of its numbers in this
                    desert. There is a path from Kirman to Herat in Khorassan, by which couriers can
                    travel in eighteen days; but the risk is so great that a high sum is always
                    demanded for such a journey.</p>
                <p>This province is famous for very fine wool, produced by great flocks of sheep and
                    goats, which are fed on the mountains, cold in winter, and hot and arid in
                    summer. Not only is the wool of the sheep of very fine quality, but the goats
                    produce a down that grows in winter at the roots of the hair, in the same manner
                    as that of the Thibet and shawl goats, and nearly as fine. This is spun into
                    various fabrics, which almost vie with the celebrated shawls of Cashmere in
                    fineness and beauty of manufacture. From the wool of the sheep are made shawls,
                    numuds, and felts, which are celebrated all over Asia. The wool is prepared in a
                    peculiar manner, being immersed in a wash, the ingredients of which are known
                    only to the makers. The Kirnianees are also famed for the manufacture of
                    matchlocks. These they send to Khorassan, Cabul, Balkh, Buckharia, and the
                    northern provinces; and in return receive assafoetida, gums, rhubarb, madder,
                    and other drugs; Buckharia skins, furs, silk, steel, copper, and tin (the last
                    three articles are for home consumption; they export the remainder to India,
                    Sinde, Arabia, and the Red Sea); pistachio nuts, rose,leaves and buds for making
                    conserve, gums, cotton, carpets, and buttons. They import from India tin, lead,
                    iron, coppér, steel, pepper, and all other spices; chintz both European and
                    Indian, indigo, muslin, tea, satin, gold, flowered silks, gold-cloth,
                    cocoa-nuts, china and glass-ware, broad cloth, &amp;c. From Sinde they receive
                    white cloth and coloured stuffs for turbans; and from Arabia and the Red Sea
                    coffee, gold-dust, ivory, musk, frankincense, stones, &amp;c.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Kirman,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Kerman,</hi> called also
                    sometimes Sirjian, a large city, and capital of the above province, situated on
                    the western side of a capacious plain, so close to the mountains, that two of
                    them, on which there are ancient forts, completely command it. It was in early
                    times one of the most flourishing cities in Persia, and was inferior to none in
                    size except the capital, Ispahan. It became, by its situation in the direct road
                    from Khorassan, Balkh, Buckharia, the countries beyond the Oxus, and all the
                    northern part of the Persian empire, to the sea-port of Bunder-Abass, a great
                    emporium of eastern commerce, and the centre of wealth, learning, and
                    magnificence. The date of its foundation is not ascertained, but Lieutenant
                    Pöttinger states, on the authority of a manuscript history of the conquest in
                    the 90th year of the hejira, or about the 700th year of the Christian era, that
                    Kirman was then a very extensive city, full of riches, and celebrated for the
                    excellence of the shawls and arms made in it; and he imagines that its
                    foundation is coeval with the renowned city of Ormuz. No city has been subject
                    to greater reverses of fortune, or oftener the scene of severe, destructive
                    wars, both foreign and domestic, than Kirman<pb break="no" facs="nls:192947409"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0712-7409-0739"/>. It has been successively taken and plundered by
                    the caliphs, by Ghengis Khan, Tamerlane, the Afghans, and Nadir Shah: in
                    addition to all that, it has suffered from civil broils, in the course of which
                    it has often been taken by storm. The last event of this kind took place in the
                    year 1794, when it was betrayed into the hands of Agha Mahommed Khan, uncle of
                    the present king, and founder of the Kajjar dynasty,* who had besieged it in
                    vain for several months. Under this eastern barbarian the city was given up for
                    three months to incessant ravages by a licentious soldiery. All its
                    fortifications and elegant structures, which were raised by the Afghans, were
                    razed to the ground; and the cruel conqueror, after sacrificing to his revenge
                    every person of whom he had the slightest suspicion, carried 30,000 of the
                    inhabitants into slavery, or exiled them to the'distant provinces of Mazunderan
                    and Azerbijan. After this dreadful calamity, the city lay desolate for some
                    years after the accession of the present king, who directed the fortifications
                    to be rebuilt on a reduced scale. They are still, however, large, and consist of
                    a high mud wall, with nineteen bastions, and a dry ditch twenty yards wide and
                    ten deep. The works are entirely encompassed by ruins. There are four gates, and
                    the ark or the citadel, in which the governor’s palace is built, and which is on
                    the southern face of the fort, is defended by similar works. The bazar is well
                    supplied with articles of every description, and from every nation: one part of
                    it is covered in with very elegant domes, built of a beautiful blue stone, dug
                    from quarries in the adjacent mountains. There are eight or nine caravanserais
                    within the walls, besides many inferior ones outside. Kirman contains 30,000
                    inhabitants, consisting of Armenians, Hindus, or Jews, resident in the place,
                    and of a small proportion of Guebres or Parsces. The trade of the town, though
                    considerable, has never revived to its former extent; and it is not likely that
                    it will again do so, as the great resort of merchants is now to the sea-port
                    town of Bushire, farther up the Gulf of Persia, to the prejudice of
                    Bunder-Abass, and of course of Kirman, of which Bunder-Abass is the port. Its
                    manufactures of shawls, matchlocks, and numuds or felts, are celebrated all over
                    Asia, and are said to afford employment to upwards of one third of the
                    inhabitants, whether male or female. The former are made from the famous wool
                    already described, and rival those of Cashmere in delicacy of fabric and
                    texture, though they are not equal in downy softness and warmth. The revenues of
                    the city, which in 1810 amounted to L.25,000 per annum, and are said to be
                    rapidly increasing, are employed by the prince in maintaining his court, and a
                    body of troops for the protection of the city and neighbourhood from the
                    incursions of the wild predatory tribes of the mountains. These duties arise
                    from a heavy tax on shawls and matchlocks. Camels, horses, &amp;c. which enter
                    any caravanserai in the city, are charged each one rupee. Long. 56. 6. E. Lat.
                    29. 56. N.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
