<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0712-7682-0760-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">KOSCIUSZKO, Thaddeus</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 12, page 760</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1042815">Objectivity</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:952579">Head</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1069177">Polishes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1068347">Poles</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1080735">Prussians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fastgeo:1206891">Poland</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1227863">Lithuania</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4nc5sn82">Combat</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4mk65f63">Soldiers</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0m53j">Polishing</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4804xp4n">Polishes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4h41jp6g">Cossacks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b46w96878">Diet</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:192947682" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">KOSCIUSZKO, <hi rend="smallcaps">Thaddeus</hi></label>, a
                    Polish general, less celebrated for his exploits than for his attachment to the
                    independence of his country, was descended of a noble but not opulent family, in
                    the province of Lithuania. He was educated in the school of cadets at Warsaw,
                    and made such progress in drawing and in mathematics, that he was named one of
                    four pupils destined to travel at the expense of the state, in order to improve
                    their talents by observation and inquiry. He consequently repaired to France,
                    and having there passed several years devoted to study, returned to his native
                    country enriched with new acquisitions. He obtained the command of a company,
                    and proposed to prosecute the military profession in the Polish array, when the
                    consequences of an unfortunate attachment for the daughter of the Marshal of
                    Lithuania blighted his prospects, and forced him to leave his country. He
                    proceeded to North America, which had just declared itself independent; served
                    as adjutant to General Washington in the war which the revolted colonies had to
                    maintain against the mother country, was decorated with the order of
                    Cincinnatus, and returned to his own country, where he lived in retirement until
                    1789. About this period he was promoted to the rank of general-major by the
                    Diet, which was then making vain efforts to restrain the influence of foreign
                    powers. Kosciuszko was at that time little known; but in 1792 the affair of
                    Dubienka, where with four thousand men he defended for six hours a post attacked
                    by fifteen thousand Russians, gained him much reputation. He served, with equal
                    distinction, during the whole campaign of that year, under the young
                    Poniatowski; but the weakness of Stanislaus rendered fruitless the most generous
                    efforts to maintain the independence of his country. He submitted to the
                    conditions which were imposed upon him by Russia, and, under the appearance of a
                    treaty of peace, signed the ruin of Poland. The bravest officers of the Polish
                    army, unable to support the disgrace thus incurred, gave in their resignation.
                    Kosciuszko was amongst the number; but having become an object of extreme
                    suspicion to the enemies of his country, he found himself obliged to quit
                    Poland; a circumstance which added much to his credit with the patriotic party,
                    and caused him to be declared a French citizen by the Legislative Assembly of
                    France. He afterwards retired to Leipzig, where his friends in Warsaw, having
                    decided to make a new effort against the Russians, apprised him that he had been
                    chosen as their chief. Kosciuszko did not refuse the perilous honour thus
                    conferred on him; but, convinced that the means which his party had at their
                    disposal were still insufficient, he resolved to proceed circumspectly, and, in
                    order to avoid suspicion, undertook a journey to Italy, where he passed several
                    months. At the beginning of 1794, however, having learned that it was no longer
                    possible to restrain the impatience of the Poles, he drew near to the scene of
                    approaching action, and reached Cracow at the moment when Medalinski had raised
                    the standard of insurrection, and when he himself had just been declared
                    generalissimo of the national forces. Finding himself thus invested with
                    dictatorial power, in circumstances of great difficulty, he was careful not to
                    abuse the trust reposed in him; and, by his conduct in every instance, he amply
                    justified the choice of his countrymen. Master <hi rend="italic">of</hi> Cracow,
                    he published a manifesto, and immediately marched against the Russians at the
                    head of a corps of five thousand men. He encountered the enemy, in number about
                    ten thousand, at Wralawice, and, after a combat of four hours, completely
                    defeated them. This first success produced ageneral rising; Warsaw was delivered
                    from the'presence of the Russians; and Kosciuszko soon saw himself at the head
                    of an army of fifty thousand combatants, including about twenty-five thousand
                    regular troops. With this comparatively small force the Polish general-in-chief
                    had to make head at once against the Russians and the Prussians. Frederick
                    William II., who had just failed in his contest with the French, appeared
                    desirous to avenge himself for this affront on the Poles; and, at the beginning
                    of 1794, he marched against Warsaw, at the head of forty thousand men.
                    Kosciuszko, who, upon this point, could not oppose to him more than fifteen
                    thousand men, had, nevertheless, the courage to attack him at Szezekocin, on the
                    8th of June 1794; but, after a murderous combat, in which he had two horses
                    killed under him, he was obliged to retire to the entrenched camp that covered
                    the capital, where, for two months, he resisted the most impetuous attacks and
                    reiterated assaults. At the same time, he contrived to restrain and keep in
                    order a furious populace, prone to give way to the greatest excesses. Scarcely
                    had he been delivered from the Prussians, in consequence of the diversion which
                    the insurrection of Great Poland operated in his favour, when Kosciuszko saw
                    advancing against him the Russian army under Suwarow, and also that commanded by
                    Fersen. It was in vain that he attempted to prevent the junction of these two
                    armies. On the 4th of October, being attacked at Macijowice, by very superior
                    forces, he obstinately disputed the victory during the whole day; but at length
                    he sank down pierced with wounds, exclaiming, as he fell, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Finis Poloniae.</hi> He was about to expire under the sabres of the Cossacks,
                    when being happily recognised, he was immediately surrounded with the respectful
                    attentions of his enemies. Having been sent as a prisoner to St Petersburg, he
                    remained two years confined in a dungeon, whence he was not liberated until
                    after the death of the Empress Catharine. Paul 1. immediately after his
                    accession set him at liberty, and loaded him with marks of esteem and regard.
                    The first use which Kosciuszko made of his liberty was to proceed to England,
                    and thence to America, where he passed several years amongst his old companions
                    in arms. In 1798 he returned to France, where he was received with much
                    distinction, and learned that a great number of his countrymen had enlisted
                    under the banners of the new republic. Those who served in the army of Italy
                    sent him the sabre of John Sobieski, which had been found in the Casa di
                    Loretto. From this time he lived either at Paris or at a country-house which he
                    had purchased near Fontainebleau. When Napoleon was about to invade Poland in
                    1807, he wished to avail himself of the name of Kosciuszko, in the hope of
                    thereby inducing the people of that country to revolt against the Russians. But
                    the Polish general had too much knowledge and experience not to divine the
                    object for which recourse had been had to him, and he answered by
                    positivelyrefusing to comply with the imperial invitation. Nevertheless there
                    was published in the journals a proclamation fabricated in his name, and
                    addressed to the Poles. But although it was not till 1814 that he had an
                    opportunity of denouncing this fraud, yet the truth had long been known in
                    Europe, and the hero of Poland had never ceased to be an object of veneration,
                    even when the government of Bonaparte treated him as a suspected person. When
                    the Russians penetrated into Champagne in 1814, they learned with surprise that
                    their ancient enemy was living peaceably in the immediate vicinity. All those
                    who had an opportunity of visiting his retreat testified their regard for him in
                    the strongest manner; and the Emperor Alexander himself had along interview with
                    the veteran arid patriotic soldier. Nothing could induce Kosciuszko to return to
                    his native country. In 1815 <pb break="no" facs="nls:192947695"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0712-7695-0761"/>he made a tour in Italy, and afterwards
                    established himself at Saleure in Switzerland, where he died on the 16th of
                    October 1817. On the intelligence of his demise, the whole of Europe resounded
                    with his eulogium; amongst all nations, and in every country, justice was
                    equally rendered to the brave soldier and the true patriot, who, without any
                    other object than the independence and welfare of his country, had exposed
                    himself to the greatest perils, and the most painful sacrifices. His mortal
                    remains were interred in the cathedral at Cracow, between those of John Sobieski
                    and of Joseph Poniatowski. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Poland. (a.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
