<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0712-7084-0714-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">KILKENNY</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 12, page 714</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47p8tc5z">Abbeys</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4r20rz2q">Cistercians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4125q963">Dominicans</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vr13">Stone</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4028pc5x">Soils</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1133812">Stone</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1133955">Stoning</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1124682">Soils</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1085637">Queens</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:794216">Abbeys</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:192947084" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">KILKENNY</label>, an inland county, in the province of
                    Leinster, in Ireland, is bounded on the north by the Queen’s county, on the east
                    by the counties of Carlow and Wexford, on the south by the county of Waterford,
                    and on the west by that of Tipperary. It comprehends an area of 513,686 acres,
                    of which 417,117 acres are cultivated land, and 96,569 acres are bog and
                    mountain.</p>
                <p>The parish of Durrow, forming an insulated portion surrounded by the Queen’s
                    county, was made part of the county of Kilkenny by an act of parliament,
                    obtained through the influence of the Duke of Ormond. His object was to repress
                    the outrages committed on his tenantry by the Fitzpatricks, who inhabited that
                    district, and who, when tried in the Queen’s county, which belonged to their own
                    sept, were always acquitted, but when tried in Kilkenny, the duke’s county, were
                    sure to be convicted.</p>
                <p>According to Ptolemy, the county was inhabited by the Brigantes and the Caucoi.
                    It afterwards formed part of the kingdom of Ossory, which was sometimes
                    tributary to Leinster, sometimes to Munster. After the arrival of the English,
                    it formed one of the counties into which King John divided that portion of the
                    island which recognised his supremacy. At the termination of the sixteenth
                    century it was chiefly occupied by the Graces, the O’Brenans, the Butlers, the
                    O’Sheas, the Rooths, the Harpurs, the Walshes of the mountains, the Shortals,
                    and the For-stals. It is now divided into the nine baronies of Cran-nagh,
                    Fassadining, Galmoy, Gowran, Ida, Iverk, Kells, Knocktopher, and Shillelogher;
                    besides which, the county of the city of Kilkenny forms a separate jurisdiction.
                    These baronies are subdivided into 126 parishes, and one part of a parish.</p>
                <p>According to the ecclesiastical arrangements of the country, Kilkenny is chiefly
                    comprehended within the diocese of Ossory, which extends over 120 of its
                    parishes. Of the remainder, six are in the diocese of Leighlin, and part of one
                    in that of Cashel. The see of Ossory was first planted at Seikyran, near Birr,
                    about the year 402. Thence it was removed to Aghaboe, in the Queen’s county,
                    about 1052; and finally to Kilkenny, in the latter end of the reign of Henry II.
                    Like Meath, it derives its name, not from the seat of the episcopal see, but
                    from that of the district over which it extends. Besides nearly the whole part
                    of the county of Kilkenny, the diocese also comprehends the entire barony of
                    Upper Ossory, forming one third of the Queen’s, county, and a small part of the
                    King’s county. The dean of the cathedral exercises a kind of episcopal
                    jurisdiction over the vicars-choral, similar to that of the dean of St
                    Patrick’s, Dublin; and the archdeacon formerly exercised an ordinary
                    prescriptive jurisdiction over the whole diocese. The total number of its
                    parishes is 136, of which 120 are in Kilkenny, fifteen in the Queen’s, and one
                    in the King’s county. The annual value of the see was estimated at L.3859 by the
                    parliamentary return made in 1833. In conformity with the new arrangements for
                    the established church in Ireland, this diocese has been consolidated into that
                    of Leighlin and Ferns.</p>
                <p>The face of the country is mostly level, particularly in the central baronies;
                    but hilly in the northern, and still more so in the south-eastern districts. An
                    argillaceous soil is predominant. Very little ground is unfit for tillage, and
                    that which is not productive of good grain throws up excellent herbage. The soil
                    in the northern parts is chiefly a mossy turf a few inches deep, lying over a
                    bed of stiff yellow or whitish clay. More southerly, the soil is light, covering
                    an argillaceous schistus. To the west there is a hungry clayey loam, over a bed
                    of limestone. In general, the nearer the limestone is to the surface, the poorer
                    the soil. A light soil covers all the vicinity of the city of Kilkenny,
                    exhibiting the appearance of slaty hills and gravelly bottoms. Proceeding
                    southwards, the fertility increases. The angle of the river Suir, which forms
                    the parish of Portnascully, is the richest land in the county. There is. a great
                    extent of mountainous land, much of it unimproved. The quantity of bog is
                    inconsiderable, amounting altogether to 3500 acres; the largest tract is in the
                    north-western extremity. Marl has been found between two strata of black
                    turfpnould; three strata of bog have also been discovered, separated by
                    intervening beds of marl, oak, fir; sallow and birch have been found in the
                    bogs. There arc no loughs of any extent. In the parish of Cloghmanta there are
                    some temporary lakes, produced by the water bursting up from the ground in
                    November, and subsiding in spring. They are here named Longhans; in Connaught
                    they are called Turloughs. The climate is less humid than that of Dublin or
                    Wicklow.</p>
                <p>The principal rivers are the Nore, the Barrow, and the Suir, all of which rise in
                    the range of the Slieve Bloom Mountains, and, taking a southern direction,
                    discharge themselves by a common mouth into the estuary at Waterford. The Nore
                    passes through the middle of the county, and by the city of Kilkenny; it is
                    navigable for boats as far as Thomastown, whence a canal has been for many years
                    proposed to be carried to the last-named city; but it still remains uncut. The
                    salmon-peal, a fish resembling the salmon, is caught in this river. The King’s
                    River joins the Nore at Jerpoint, and the Argula near Innistioge. The Barrow
                    forms the eastern boundary of the county, <pb break="no" facs="nls:192947097"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0712-7097-0715"/>from near New Bridge to its junction with the
                    Suir, which latter river is its boundary to the south. The Barrow is navigable
                    for boats along the whole extent of the borders of the county of Kilkenny, and
                    still farther to Athy in Kildare county. The Suir is navigable for sloops to
                    Carrick, and for barges to Clonmell in Tipperary.</p>
                <p>The substrata of this county are granite, siliceous schistus, siliceous breccia,
                    argillite, sandstone, and limestone. The granite hills form a very small part
                    <hi rend="subscript"> t</hi> being merely the extension of the Wicklow group.
                    The rock is of various shades, but the best is of a light yellow tint, finely
                    grained, and compact; black mica is found in it, together with specks of iron
                    ore, and crystals of schorl. Siliceous breccia forms many of the lower hills. It
                    consists principally of fine quartz sand, united by a siliceous cement, and
                    enveloping rounded pebbles of quartz. This stone is constantly accompanied by a
                    red argillite, which covers the sides of the hills, but scarcely ever the
                    summits. The hills of breccia run southward from the Nore towards Waterford. The
                    great hill of Drumdowney, near the Ross River, forms the extremity of the
                    principal range. The stone is here of a fine grain, and is quarried for
                    millstones, which are exported to Cork, Dublin, and other parts. In the western
                    part of the county there is an extensive slate quarry, highly esteemed. The
                    northern part of the county consists either of ferruginous argillite or of
                    siliceous schistus. The former, from being always found above coal, is called
                    coal-cover.</p>
                <p>The collieries of Castlecomer are situated near the confluence of the small
                    rivers Dinan, Dian, Bruckagh, and Cloghoge, which join the Nore. They were
                    discovered by accident, in working for iron ore. The depth of the beds varies
                    from two feet six inches to three feet one inch. The coal sill, or seat of the
                    coal, which is sometimes raised with it, is a soft, black, brittle stone, full
                    of shining impressions, exhibiting obscure traces of the roots of rushes. It
                    stands fire in a peculiar manner; crucibles made of it resist the strongest
                    heat, as, the more it is exposed to the fire, the harder it becomes. Fire-bricks
                    are made from two parts of it and one part of clay. The excellent qualities of
                    the Kilkenny coal for particular purposes occasion a great demand for it. It is
                    heavy, burning with little flame, like charcoal in an ignited state, and
                    throwing out a steady and violent heat. It dries malt well, and is excellent for
                    the forge. When analyzed, it appears to approach nearly to pure carbon, the
                    proportions being 97∙3 of that element, and the remainder uninflammable ashes.
                    It seems peculiarly calculated for cementing steel, and for potteries; but it
                    has not been applied to either purpose, although materials for earthenware are
                    to be found in the neighbourhood, and iron-mines of the best quality from the
                    upper strata of entire hills. Yellow ochre is found in various places; also
                    pipeclay of good quality. Manganese is seen on the banks of the Barrow, and near
                    Freshford, and lead in small quantities between Innistioge and Ross; a mine of
                    the latter at Floodhall was worked for some time with considerable profit. Iron
                    has also been raised. Jasper, in pieces from ten to twelve inches long, and half
                    as broad, have been found near the extremity of the granite district, between
                    the Nore and Barrow. Limestone is the base of the central part of the county;
                    but the quality varies much in different places, all the species of it
                    containing impressions of shells or corallines. The most important limestone
                    quarry is that which produces the Kilkenny marble; it lies about half a mile
                    from the city. The stone, when polished, presents a black ground, varied with
                    white marks, which appear more strongly when exposed to the air; but that
                    approaching nearest to unmixed black is most esteemed. The analysis gave
                    ninety-eight per cent, soluble in marine acid, and two per cent, of a black
                    powder, which appeared to be carbon. The blocks, when raised, are finished at a
                    marble-mill at some distance, remarkable for the ingenuity and simplicity of its
                    mechanism.</p>
                <p>At Ballyspellan, in Galmoy barony, is a very celebrated mineral spring. It is a
                    chalybeate, and contains carbonic acid gas, which soon evaporates on exposure to
                    the air. Its medicinal qualities have long been highly esteemed in the
                    neighbouring country. Chalybeate springs, but not of much strength, exist in
                    other places. This county is also celebrated for springs of very pure
                    transparent water, most of them dedicated to some saint, whose patron-day is
                    annually celebrated on their verge.</p>
                <p>The population, taken at different periods, presents the foliowing results:</p>
                <p>1760 De Burgo 62,832</p>
                <p>1792 Beaufort 100,000</p>
                <p>1812 Parlimentary census 134,664</p>
                <p>’ 1821 Ditto 158,716</p>
                <p>1831 Ditto 160,283</p>
                <p>• This table exhibits an increase of more than double in seventy years, and gives
                    an average of one inhabitant to every three acres and a quarter, or of a family
                    of six to every nineteen acres.</p>
                <p>The parliamentary returns of the numbers of children receiving education in the
                    public schools, in the years 1821, and 1824-26, give the following results:</p>
                <p>Boys. Girls. Total.</p>
                <p> ascertained.</p>
                <p>1821, 10,191 4,420 — 14,511</p>
                <p>1824-26, 12,398 7,000 274 19,672</p>
                <p>Out of this total of children enjoying the benefits of public instruction,
                    according to the latter of these returns, upwards of 18,000 were Catholics; the
                    Protestants amounting only to 1376, of which number but thirteen were
                    dissenters. The number of schools maintained by public money was nineteen, in
                    which 1515 pupils were instructed; of those maintained by private subscriptions,
                    the number*was the same, the pupils in them being 1281; all the other schools,
                    346 in number, in which 16,876 children were instructed, were maintained wholly
                    by the fees of the pupils. From the same data, it may be inferred that the
                    Catholics in the county of Kilkenny were to the Protestants at that time in the
                    proportion nearly of twenty to one.</p>
                <p>The county returned sixteen members to the Irish parliament, two for the county
                    at large, two for the city of Kilkenny, two for the adjoining borough of
                    Irishtown, and two each for the boroughs of Callan, Gowran, Innistioge,
                    Knocktopher, and Thomastown. All these, except Kilkenny, were close boroughs,
                    the elective franchise being vested in the burgesses, whose number seldom
                    exceeded twenty, and who were elected through the influence of the proprietor of
                    the land. The constituency of the county was as follows, before the Catholic
                    relief act, after that act but previously to the reform act, and subsequently to
                    the reform act :—-</p>
                <p>L.50. L.20. L.10. 40s. Total.</p>
                <p>1829, 689 210 — ‘2353 3261</p>
                <p>1830, 726 234 118 — 1024</p>
                <p>1832, 222 106 918 — 1246</p>
                <p>Very little ground throughout the county is unfit for tillage; the central parts
                    are peculiarly adapted for wheat, to the growth of which the best ground, most
                    of which has a limestone sub-soil, is devoted. The more mountainous tracts are
                    exclusively appropriated to oats or pasture. Wheat is sown either on a fallow or
                    after potatoes. The seed is always steeped for a day and night, in which prccess
                    brine has been found most effectual in guarding against smut. Wheat here suffers
                    also from what is called the red or yellow worm; but as this disease appears
                    only in dry seasons, when <pb break="no" facs="nls:192947110"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0712-7110-0716"/>the crop is better and more abundant, the evil is
                    not much felt. Change of seed is much attended to. Barley is usually sown after
                    wheat. Bear is little cultivated. The same may be said of rye; when raised, it
                    is sown on burned land, and produces fine crops in the mountainous districts.
                    All the manure that can be collected is applied to the potatoes. The street
                    scrapings of Waterford bear a high price in the neighbouring baronies; sea-sand
                    and composts of turf mould are also common. The use of green food for cattle is
                    not so general as might be desired. Many of the cattle graze out during the
                    winter; some are housed from Christmas to April. The only green food used in
                    winter is furze-tops pounded, on which the cattle soon become sleek and fine
                    skinned; for this purpose the large French furze is preferred. Little attention
                    is paid to improve the pasturages. The mountain pastures are left in a state of
                    nature, and the land produces little but heath. These heaths are very liable to
                    take fire in dry summers, by which means the soil is eventually improved. Much
                    land on the borders of the Nore and Suir is embanked and used for meadowing. The
                    most considerable dairies are in the Walsh Mountains; a name supposed to be
                    derived from the family to which a large tract of land formerly belonged. It is
                    now mostly held by a single family, consisting of five branches, who possess
                    upwards of two thousand acres amongst them. Their houses are small and
                    contiguous. They intermarry amongst each other, which renders ecclesiastical
                    dispensations frequently necessary. If a widow marry a stranger, she loses all
                    except what she had brought with her to her first husband. The land is grazed in
                    common, excepting three hundred acres, which are divided equally among the five
                    families. They live principally on potatoes and griddle bread, with occasionally
                    the offal of the pigs killed for sale. Their dairies have earthen floors, and
                    are without ceiling, window, table, or shelf, but they are kept very neat.</p>
                <p>Few horses are bred in the county, most are brought in from Munster to the fair
                    of Callan, the only esteemed fair for this description of stock. The Suffolk
                    sorrel breed is much in request. The common stock of black cattle is a cross of
                    the Irish breed on the long-horned English. The Kerry cow is much in demand in
                    dairies, for its low price and quantity of milk. The breed of sheep has improved
                    very much, in consequence of the great pains taken to improve it. Merinos have
                    been successfully introduced. Pigs are fattened to the weight of five hundred
                    lbs. Goats are kept by small fanners and cottiers, but not in flocks. Rearing
                    fowl is also an object with the small farmers. Large numbers of turkeys are sent
                    to the autumn fair of Callan. Bees were more attended to formerly than now, yet
                    the soil and climate are well suited to them. The dry hills, covered with heath
                    and scented herbs, produce honey celebrated for its flavour, and for the depth
                    of its combs.</p>
                <p>Within the memory of some old persons, many parts of the county were covered with
                    woods. Now there are but few, not covering more than two thousand acres.
                    Attempts to raise plantations from the seed have not been successful, the seeds
                    in this mild climate being liable to destruction from vermin. Orchards are much
                    neglected. There are some ozieries on the banks of the Nore and Suir.</p>
                <p>The woollen manufacture was introduced by the Earl of Ormond in the early part of
                    the fourteenth century. He brought over workmen from Flanders, whose manufacture
                    is still to be seen in the castle of Kilkenny. James duke of Ormond went to
                    great expense to introduce the linen manufacture in the seventeenth century.
                    Latterly an attempt was made to manufacture superfine broad cloths in the
                    neighbourhood of Kilkenny, but it soon failed. Frizes and ratteens are still
                    made; the women spin the wool. The manufacture of woollen cloth was succeeded by
                    that of blankets, which is still carried on. The linen trade, after a
                    continuance of fifty'or sixty years, has so died away that not a vestige of it
                    now remains, beyond the making of coarse linen and sacking tor domestic use.
                    There are salt-houses at Kilkenny, Newbridge, and Kilmurry. Paper is
                    manufactured in several places. Bolting mills are numerous on the great rivers.
                    The principal part of the grain raised in the county is sent to Dublin in the
                    form of flour, malt, and meal, the manufacturing of which is another source of
                    wealth.</p>
                <p>The number of resident gentry is considerable. Amongst the mansions remarkable
                    for splendour or for architectural beauty are, the castle of Kilkenny; Mount
                    Juliet, the seat of the Earl of Carrick; Desart, the seat of the Earl of Desart;
                    Kilfane, that of George Power, Esq.; Flood Hall, the residence of the head of
                    the Flood family; and Besborough, the seat of the Earl of Besborough.
                    Gentlemen’s seats are numerous and elegant. The farm-houses are of stone, more
                    generally cemented with clay than with mortar; the offices usually forming an
                    irregular yard in front of the house. The people in the hilly parts, who hold
                    land at will, live in scattered villages. The usual food of the peasantry is
                    potatoes, to which milk and salt are sometimes added, and occasionally a
                    herring. Turf is the general fuel, except in the neighbourhood of the
                    collieries, where coal is burned, or else culm made up in balls with one third
                    of clay. The clothing is frize, ratteen, and flannel. The w omen wear stuff
                    petticots and strawhats manufactured at home. Spirituous liquors are seldom
                    used, excepting at fairs, patrons, wakes, weddings, and christenings. One person
                    at least from every family in the village is expected to attend at a wake, and
                    the body is often conveyed many miles to the family burial-place. Irish is the
                    language generally spoken, particularly in the hilly districts and in the
                    western parts, where the priests frequently preach alternately in Irish and
                    English.</p>
                <p>Amongst the remains of antiquity may be noticed a circle covered with stones on
                    the summit of Slieve Grian, “the Hill of the Sun,” called also Tory Füll, on one
                    of which is an inscription that has given rise to much controversy. There is
                    another circular mound of stones on the hill of Cloghmanta, which signifies “the
                    Rock of God.” The most remarkable cromleach is at Kilmogue; its upper stone is
                    forty-five feet in circumference. The country people call it Lachan Schal, or
                    “the Great Altar Stone.” Near the spa of Ballyspellin is a large stone, formerly
                    supported by others; it is called Clogh-bannagh, or “the Stone of thessing.”
                    Raths are numerous, particularly in Galmoy and near the Nore. At Earlsrath are
                    the remains of a very large fort enclosed by a fosse. A moat near Rathbeath is
                    pointed out as the place where Heremon, son of Milesius, built his palace and
                    was buried. There are five pillar towers in the county. One is in Kilkenny,
                    close to the cathedral; the others are at Tulloherin, Kilree, Fertagh, and
                    Aghaviller, of which last the lower part only remains. All are in the vicinity
                    of places of worship. Besides the remains of monasteries in the city of
                    Kilkenny, there are vestiges of some others, once of great note, particularly
                    one at Jerpoint, and another at Graige, both of the Cistercian order. The
                    Dominicans had abbeys at Rosbercon and Thomastown, the Carmelites had one at
                    Knocktopher; and there was a nunnery at Kilculliheen.</p>
                <p>The number of castles is very great; most of them consist of a single square tow
                    er, which formed the keep. Graney or Grandison Castle, in Iverk, is among the
                    most celebrated, as being the residence of Margaret Fitzgerald, the great
                    Countess of Ormond, a woman of uncommon energies. King John built a castle at
                    Tybrachny, where there are the remains of a Danish town.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Kilkenny</hi> city is situated on the river Nore, nearly in
                    <pb break="no" facs="nls:192947123" xml:id="kp-eb0712-7123-0717"/>the centre of
                    the county. Its name is generally derived from Kill-kenny, “the church or cell
                    of St Canice,” though by some it is traced from the words Coil-ken-uĩ, “the
                    wooded hill near the river.” It consists of two separate jurisdictions, the city
                    of Kilkenny properly so called, and the borough of Irishtown, separated from
                    each other by the small river Bregagh. An English settlement was formed here
                    shortly after the landing of Strongbow; a castle was also erected, and the seat
                    of the see of Ossory removed thither. William lord marshal, who married
                    Strongbow’s daughter, granted the town a charter of incorporation, which was
                    confirmed by Gilbert earl of Clare. Elizabeth and James I. confirmed and
                    enlarged its privileges. Parliaments were frequently held in it; amongst others,
                    that which passed the celebrated statute of Kilkenny, which first notices the
                    distinction of English by blood and English by birth. During the wars of 1641,
                    it was the place where the assembly of the confederate Catholics held their
                    sittings; the room where they met is still shown. Cromwell afterwards took the
                    city on terms highly honourable to its defenders, and afterwards held his high
                    court of justice in it. The buildings in the city and borough together occupy an
                    area of about 380 acres. On the two most elevated points of the united towns are
                    the castle and the cathedral, the most marked and ornamental structures of both.
                    The city is irregular, but presents a cheerful and busy aspect: the houses,
                    built chiefly of stone,are large and respectable. The Nore, here a river of some
                    breadth, though not navigable, is crossed by two modern bridges. The castle
                    comprehends the remains of the ancient fortress, combined with more modern
                    buildings. It was purchased by James, third earl of Ormond, in 1391, and has
                    ever since been the principal residence of the head of the Butler family. In
                    1399, he entertained Richard II. in it for fourteen days. King William dined
                    there after the battle of the Boyne. The buildings now form the sides of a
                    quadrangle. Its principal apartments were the presence chamber, formed of a
                    suite of rooms opening into one another, in the farthest of which was an
                    elevated seat for the lord of the mansion; and the picture gallery, chiefly
                    furnished with family portraits. Several of the rooms were hung with tapestry;
                    but the whole is now undergoing such alterations as will materially change the
                    state of the interior without altering the feudal character of its exterior. The
                    court-house is a large and elegant modern building, erected on the site of
                    Grace’s old castle, where the assizes used to be held. The tholsel, or city
                    court, is also large, but unornamented; it contains several apartments, one of
                    which is used as a library. The market, well stocked with provisions of every
                    kind, is held in one of the divisions of its inferior area. There are barracks
                    both for cavalry and infantry. The theatre is small, and was for some time kept
                    open by an amateur company, composed of the neighbouring resident gentry. The
                    county jail is at a short distance from the city. The environs of the town are
                    very beautiful. The Duke’s Walk is carried from it upwards of a mile along the
                    banks of the Nore. The corporation consists of a mayor and aidermen, two
                    sheriffs, a recorder, and other subordinate officers, who have the management of
                    an income, arising from rents, of about L.1600 per annum. The cathedral of St
                    Canice is an extensive pile, on a commanding elevation, in Irishtown. It is
                    cruciform, surmounted by a small tower, and of greater dimensions than any
                    similar building in Ireland, except the cathedral in Dublin. In the north
                    transept is a chapel used as the parish church, where also is a stone seat
                    called the chair of St Kevin. The choir and chancel are fitted up in a style of
                    chaste simplicity. The aisle contains several sepulchral monuments; amongst them
                    that of Pierce, eighth earl of Ormond, and Margaret Fitzgerald his wife. The
                    burial-ground of the cathedral is entered by a flight of marble steps, and is
                    planted with trees. The episcopal palace was originally erected in the time of
                    Edward III., and was modernized and enlarged in 1735; it is now a commodious,
                    though not a splendid residence. <hi rend="subscript"> f</hi> The church of St
                    Mary is a spacious but plain structure. Several monastic institutions added much
                    to the beauty and dignity of the city. The most ancient was the preceptory of St
                    John, founded about 1211. The abbey church, remarkable for the singular
                    structure of its windows, which procured it the name of “the Lanthorn of
                    Kilkenny,” has been converted into a parochial church under its old name. The
                    extensive and noble ruins of the Dominican or Black Abbey, founded in 1225, have
                    been repaired, and now form a Roman Catholic place of worship. The origin of the
                    Franciscan Abbey is unknown. Its ruins are much admired. The grammar-school,
                    generally called the college, is situated near the banks of the Nore. It was
                    founded by Pierce earl of Ormond, and re-endowed by the Duke of Ormond in 1684.
                    James II. erected it into a royal college, but on his abdication it reverted to
                    its former state, and is now a respectable place of elementary instruction,
                    capable of accommodating eighty resident pupils. In it Dean Swift, Congreve,
                    Farquhar, and Bishop Berkeley, acquired the rudiments of classical literature.
                    Kilkenny has also a seminary for the education of students intended for the
                    Roman Catholic priesthood. A nunnery provides for the education of twelve boys
                    and as many girls. The charter-school is adapted for seventy children. The
                    infirmary, opened in 1767, is supported partly by grants of public money, partly
                    by benefactions and subscriptions. The house of industry provides for the
                    maintenance of the poor when out of employment; and an hospital for lunatics is
                    attached to it. A neat range of buildings, called St James’ Asylum, in the
                    suburbs, was endowed in 1803, by Mr James Switzer, for the maintenance of twelve
                    protestant and eight catholic widows. The population of the city and borough in
                    1821 amounted to 23,230 souls, and in 1831 to 23,741. The other towns the
                    population of which exceeds one thousand souls each are, Callan,· 6111;
                    Thomastown, 2871; Castlecomer, 2436; Freshford, 2175; Graige, 2130; Ballyragget,
                    1629; Urlingford, <hi rend="subscript"> j1</hi> 1336; Durrow, ∙ 1298; and
                    Gowran, 1109.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
