<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0712-6746-0688-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">KEMAON, or Kumaon</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 12, page 688</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206073">China</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1028366">Mountains</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1065075">Plains</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1050382">Pain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4mc8rm1n">Plains</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0mz9r">Pain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:192946746" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">KEMAON, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Kumaon</hi></label>, a
                    district of Northern Hindustan, which was formerly a Hindu principality,
                    conterminous with that of Dution the east, the boundary line being the Cali
                    River. On the west it was separated from Gurwal by the Ramgunga, and extended a
                    considerable way into the plains of Bareilly. The modern district of Kemaon, as
                    it has been regulated by the British since its conquest in 1815, comprehends the
                    whole tract of country between the Ganges and the Cali, from the plains to the
                    highest pinnacle of the Himalaya, which space includes a large portion of the
                    Gurwal province south-east of Alcananda, whilst the Cali River on the east forms
                    a natural and well-defined boundary towards Nepaul. The other geographical
                    divisions are Kemaon proper, Pain-khandi, and Bhutant, within the limits of
                    which last is the pass of Niti, supposed to have been the earliest and most
                    frequented route into Chinese Tartary. It includes an area of 7000 square
                    miles.</p>
                <p>Kemaon is situated amongst the lower ranges of the Himalaya Mountains. It is
                    separated from the lower districts of Bareilly 'and Morabad by a thick forest of
                    nearly two days’journey, which surrounds the whole and skirts the margin of the
                    mountains. The soil is marshy, and the atmosphere, during two thirds of the
                    year, is more pestilential than that of the Sunderbunds; it is, says Heber,<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Vol. ii. p. 143.</p></note>
                    “a literal belt of death, which even the natives tremble to go near, and which,
                    during the rains more especially, the monkies are forced to abandon. After the
                    middle of November this is dry, practicable, and safe.” Kemaon proper is
                    separated on the north-east from the province of Gurwal by a range of mountains,
                    which, in point of ruggedness, presents a contrast to the hills of Kemaon. These
                    latter appear to rise in a regular gentle acclivity from their bases; and the
                    soil is fertile, consisting of rich earth, which gives nourishment to fine
                    verdure and extensive forests. The hills are also intersected by rather spacious
                    valleys, rendered fertile by tillage; and the cultivation is more extended, and
                    carried farther up the hills, than in Gurwal with a denser population. In these
                    valleys, rice is produced in abundance, and the cultivator is thus in a manner
                    rendered independent of the seasons, as the numerous mountain streams,
                    descending in ever}' direction, enable him to irrigate all the lower lands. The
                    higher lands produce wheat, barley, and various small grains, which being raised
                    in a redundant quantity, form an article of traffic with Bhutant. There are
                    several passes into Kemaon from the districts of Bareilly and Morabad, but those
                    leading through Cossipoor and Roderpoor are considered as the best, and are most
                    frequented. The first leads by Chilkeah, where an annual <hi rend="subscript">
                    k</hi> fair is held, to which the hill people resort in great numbers. Similar
                    meetings also occur at Bhagesur, on the banks of the Cali, each continuing ten
                    days, and are frequented by merchants from Bhote and the low countries. Chilkeah
                    is one of the principal marts of trade in Kemaon, and through that country into
                    Thibet and Tartary. The article which meets with the readiest sale is cloth with
                    distinct colours on each side. European articles, of a coarse quality, are also
                    in demand, such as knives, razors, wine-glasses, tumblers, spying and looking
                    glasses, spectacles, and cheap enamelled watches; and Bishop Heber also saw
                    exposed to sale English cloths, and eastern shawls of good appearance, with many
                    other serviceable and valuable commodities. The greatest staple that is exported
                    from this southern frontier has always been timber, found in the immense forests
                    already mentioned, which skirt the border. Here the saul forests are of great
                    extent, and produce some of the best timber of that species in India. Owing to
                    the difficulty of access, it is necessary to convert the trees into planks on
                    the spot, that they may be the more easily transported to the populous parts of
                    the country. In some parts they have to be carried down a perpendicular height
                    of 500 feet. The fir-tree grows to an immense size, and it is much stronger than
                    the firs of Europe, and as heavy as teak, the grain strong and full of
                    turpentine. Some of the trees have from sixty to seventy feet clear of branches,
                    and the spans are from twenty to twenty-three inches in diameter. Rosin,
                    turpentine, doedwar, oil, and hemp of an excellent quality, are to be found
                    among the Kemaon Hills. The bamboo, though small, grows remarkably tough, and
                    seems to gain consistency and soundness from a certain degree of frost. The same
                    is said to be the case with the plantains. The tea-plant grows wild all through
                    Kemaon, but cannot be made use of, from an emetic quality which it possesses.
                    The upper mountains produce copper, lead, iron, and the Panar River gold, but
                    there is no mine of consequence. The northern parts are cold, and yield pasture
                    for numerous flocks of sheep; and in summer a considerable intercourse is
                    carried on with the country subject to China.</p>
                <p>The towns and villages of Kemaon, when viewed from a distance, present a neat
                    appearance. But a nearer approach does not confirm these favourable
                    prepossessions. They are generally surrounded by dirt and filth; though Bishop
                    Heber mentions, that the town of Almorah is very neat, with a natural pavement
                    of slaty rock, which is kept beautifully clean. He mentions, however, of the
                    peasantry, namely, the Khasyas, that, near Almorah, though they are honest,
                    peaceable, and cheerful, they are dirty to a degree which he never saw amongst
                    the Hindus, and extremely averse to any improvement, using their women ill, and
                    employing them in the most laborious tasks. These people are rigid Hindus. The
                    houses are generally constructed of large masses of stone, roofed with slate,
                    and of two stories in height, the lower story being allotted to cattle. Their
                    poverty is extreme, their food consisting of coarse cakes made from the grain of
                    a kind of holcus, in which the flour, bran, and husk, are mixed together, and
                    baked, or rather scorched, on the fire. In other parts, however, as he advanced
                    farther among the hills, Bishop Heber saw tolerably neat and comfortable
                    cottages, the people better fed and clothed than most of the Khasyas. Polygamy
                    is common among the lower classes.</p>
                <p>Wild animals abound in the mountains and forests of this country. The tiger is
                    found quite, up to the glaciers, of size and ferocity undiminished. There are
                    also lynxes, and bears are common and mischievous throughout the province.
                    Though they do not, except when pressed by hunger, eat flesh, preferring roots,
                    berries, and honey, yet, as if out of capricious cruelty, they often worry and
                    destroy passengers. The chamois is not uncommon in the snowy mountains, but
                    scarce elsewhere; and the hares are much finer and larger than those in
                    Hindustan, and not much inferior to those of Europe. The musk-deer is also found
                    in the highest and coldest parts of the province, and the neighbouring countries
                    of Thibet and Tartary. It cannot, says Heber, even bear the heat at Almorah. In
                    like manner, the yak or mountain ox of Tartary droops as soon as it leaves the
                    neighbourhood of the ice. The shawl-goat will live, but its wool degenerates. On
                    the other hand, <pb break="no" facs="nls:192946759" xml:id="kp-eb0712-6759-0689"
                    />English dogs, impaired by the climate of the plains, improve in strength,
                    size, and sagacity, amongst the mountains; and it is remarkable that, in a
                    winter or two, they acquire the same fine short shawl-wool, mixed with their own
                    hair, which distinguishes the indigenous animal of the country. The same is in
                    some degree the case with horses. Flying squirrels are also common amongst the
                    colder and higher parts of these woods. Some of the marmots, of the alpine kind,
                    also abound in the neighbourhood of the snow. A singular species of wild dog is
                    mentioned as a native of these hills. In form and fur these animals resemble a
                    fox, but they are much larger. They hunt in packs, give tongue like dogs, and
                    possess a very fine scent. They make great havock of the game amongst the hills,
                    and even attack and destroy the tiger, overpowering him by their numbers. Of
                    birds, the condor is to be found of a remarkable strength and size. Eagles are
                    numerous, and very large and formidable; and these birds do much injury to the
                    shepherds and goatherds, and sometimes carry away the poor naked children of the
                    peasants. Their nests being in the remote glaciers, and among inaccessible
                    crags, there is no possibility of destroying these dangerous animals. There are
                    larks in Kemaon, not very different from the English, as well as quails,
                    partridges, pheasants, thrushes, &amp;c. A little bird resembling the robin, and
                    the goldfinch, are found at the foot of the snowy mountains.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Heber, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Narrative of a Journey through the Upper Provincer of India,</hi> vol. ii. p.
                    218, 219.</p></note> This country, though, from its elevation, the climate is
                    colder than in Hindustan, with ice and snow in winter, is remarkably unhealthy,
                    from a certain malaria which prevails in all the lower valleys, especially
                    during and after the rainy season, and which gives rise to ague, intermittents,
                    and fevers which assume the appearance of typhus, and under which the powers of
                    life decline more rapidly, though often not more surely, than under continued
                    fits of the ague. Several of the inhabitants seen by Bishop Heber in this
                    devoted region, he describes as singularly wretched; the fever and the ague
                    destroying all their energy, and preventing them from adopting the simple means
                    of dry and well-raised dwellings, and sufficient clothing, to support life and
                    health. “They are,” says the intelligent traveller already quoted, “a very ugly
                    and miserable race of human beings, with large heads, and particularly prominent
                    ears, flat noses, tumid bellies, slender limbs, and sallow complexions, and have
                    scarcely any garments but a blanket of black wool, though most of them have
                    matchlocks, swords, and shields.” The chief region of insalubrity is at the foot
                    of the lowest hills, where a long, black, and level line of forest extends,
                    though the mountainous country is also more or less unhealthy in all the low
                    valleys. This insalubrity is said to be increasing. The industry of the
                    inhabitants was at one time reclaiming the forest, and the cowmen and woodmen
                    were pushing their incursions farther every year; and the plains, now desolate,
                    being shunned as the abodes of disease, were once populous. But the country was
                    ruined by the invasion of Meer Khan in 1805, and it has never recovered from the
                    devastation to which it was exposed from his licentious soldiery. So terrified
                    are the natives to approach it, that no witnesses can be procured, at certain
                    seasons of the year, to attend the circuit court; and two of them, rather than
                    go to Chilkeah, forfeited a small pension which was due to them.</p>
                <p>This country was acquired by the British government in 1815, when its limits were
                    extended to the westward by the annexation of a portion of Gurwal, east of the
                    Aleananda and the Ganges. Prior to this, it was ruled by military chiefs, who
                    owned a nominal allegiance to Nepaul, though they were nearly independent within
                    their own territories. They were extremely tyrannical, and not only divided the
                    lands amongst themselves, without regard to the rights of the ancient
                    proprietors, but, on any arrears of rent, sold the wives and children of the
                    peasants as slaves, to an amount almost incredible, whilst they quelled every
                    murmur among the people by the most barbarous severity. The court of Nepaul
                    issued repeated edicts against the practice, but without effect, since most of
                    the young persons who were of a marketable age were sold into slavery when the
                    British, to the great joy of the inhabitants, who gave them every possible aid,
                    acquired possession of the country. Since this period uninterrupted tranquillity
                    has prevailed, which may be partly ascribed to the peaceable and orderly habits
                    of the people, and to the general popularity of the British government. The
                    revenue of the country has been fixed at 85,746 rupees for Kemaon proper, and at
                    37,614 for the annexed districts of Gurwal; and, as a proof that the assessment
                    is moderate, it has been punctually realized, and has even been paid in many
                    instances in advance.</p>
                <p>Almorah is the chief town. The population of Kemaon proper is estimated at
                    300,000; that of Gurwal, east of Alcananda, is yet more considerable; and the
                    people generally are in a high state of civilization. (r.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
