<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0712-7292-0730-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">KINROSS-SHIRE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 12, page 730</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49z90g16">Fife</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4736m682">Lakes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94c35">Extents</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4h708258">Surveying</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zd00">Surveys</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1109125">Scots</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1139635">Surveys</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1139579">Surveying</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:923951">Fife</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:990901">Lakes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1094658">Rent</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:192947292" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">KINROSS-SHIRE</label>, a county in Scotland, bounded on the
                    north-east, east, and south by the county of Fife, and on the north and west by
                    Perthshire, is about twelve miles in length from east to west, and ten miles in
                    breadth from south to north; but,according to the latest survey,contains only
                    seventy-eight square miles, or 49,920 English acres, being one of the smallest
                    counties in Scotland. Kinross, the county town, situated nearly in the centre,
                    is in north latitude 56. 15. and west longitude from Greenwich 3. 10.</p>
                <p>Kinross-shire is the highest level ground in the peninsula formed by the Forth
                    and the Tay, which was formerly called Ross, or the promontory, and included the
                    counties of Fife, Kinross, and Clackmannan. From this county the waters flow in
                    every direction. The greater part of the soil is dry, resting on gravel; but
                    part of it is damp, resting on till, with considerable fields of moss and muir.
                    The whole has been very much improved of late. The productive land may extend to
                    30,000 acres, or about three fifths of the whole. The only lake it contains
                    worth noticing is Lochleven, which is in the vicinity of Kinross. This lake was
                    originally about fifteen miles in circumference, and covered an area of 3308
                    acres; but, by a recent drainage, ground to the extent of about 900 acres has
                    been laid dry, and is in the course of being improved. It abounds in trout of
                    excellent quality, pikes, perches, and eels. There are several islands in it,
                    all of which have been enlarged by the drainage. On one of these, about four
                    acres in extent, stands the Castle of Lochleven, in which Queen Mary was
                    confined; and another, called St Serf’s Island, extending to about sixty acres,
                    contains the ruins of a monastery. Several rivulets flow into this lake, of
                    which the principal are the Gairny, the South Queich, and the North Queich; and
                    the river Leven, the only stream of any note in the district, issues from its
                    eastern extremity, and, after passing through a considerable part of the county
                    of Fife, enters the Frith of Forth at the town of Leven. The prevailing rocks
                    are whinstone, sandstone, and limestone. Coal has been found on the estate of
                    Blair-Adam; it is wrought at Kelty, in the parish of Cleish, on the southern
                    boundary of the county.</p>
                <p>Kinross-shire is divided into a number of small estates. Only about ten
                    proprietors hold of the crown; the others hold of these freeholders, the lands
                    having been feued out to them, for the most part, about the end of the
                    seventeenth and beginning of the eighteenth century, for payment of a feu-duty.
                    Hence, over the greater part of the county, every single farm is a separate
                    property, possessed for the most part by its owner. The valued rent is L.20,250.
                    4s. 3d. Scots, and the real rent, according to the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Agricultural Survey,</hi> published in 1814, was L.14,541. 10s. sterling; but
                    it is now much increased, and cannot be taken at less than nearly double that
                    sum. In 1811, the number of freeholders was only fifteen. When the land is let
                    out to tenants, the leases are from fourteen to twenty-one years, except in the
                    neighbourhood of the villages, where they are for a shorter period; and the rent
                    is paid in money, the amount being in some instances regulated by the fiars. The
                    size of the farms is from 100 to 300 acres. A fair proportion of them is in
                    grass, for which both the soil and climate are favourable; and much of the land
                    is enclosed either with stone-walls or hedges. The principal corn crops are oats
                    and barley; wheat, though partially cultivated, does not enter into the regular
                    course of cropping. Potatoes, turnips, and clovers, with rye-grass, are raised
                    in every part of the county. On the banks of the Leven and the Gairny there were
                    formerly meadows of considerable extent; but these have been drained and
                    cultivated, and now form very productive land. The pastures of the Cultivated
                    land are occupied by cattle. Sheep are kept in numbers only on the Cleish Hills,
                    and on that part of the Ochills which belongs to this county. Not much of the
                    district is under wood. The most considerable plantations are on Blair-Adam, the
                    estate of Lord Chief Commissioner Adam, and they are for the most part in a very
                    flourishing state.</p>
                <p>Besides Kinross the county town, and Milnathort, this county contains several
                    villages. In 1831, Kinross contained a population of about 2400, and Milnathort
                    about 1600. At both these places several annual fairs are held; and a weekly
                    market for the sale of grain is held in the latter. Little manufactures are to
                    be found here; the weavers are employed by the manufacturers of Glasgow.
                    Assessments are resorted to for the poor of the villages, but those of the
                    country parishes are relieved by voluntary contributions.</p>
                <p>Kinross-shire sends a member to parliament along with the county of Clackmannan.
                    Both counties are under the jurisdiction of one sheriff, who has a substitute
                    for each. There are only four entire parishes, viz. Cleish, Orwell, Kinross, and
                    Portmoak, with portions of other three; the first three belong to the presbytery
                    of Dunfermline, and the fourth to that of Kirkcaldy, both under the jurisdiction
                    of the synod of Fife. The population in 1811, 1821, and 1831 is given in the
                    annexed abstract. By the returns for the first of these years, there were about
                    ninety-three inhabitants to the square mile.</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>YEARS.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="3" role="data" rows="1"><p>HOUSES.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="3" role="data" rows="1"><p>OCCUPATIONS.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="3" role="data" rows="1"><p>PERSONS.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Inhabited.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>By how many Families
                            occupied.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Uninhabited.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Families chiefly employed in
                            Agriculture.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Families chiefly employed in Trade,
                            Manufactures, or Handicraft.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>All other Families not comprised in
                            the two preceding classes.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Males.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Females.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Total of Persons.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1811</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1364</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1680</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>53</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>428</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>640</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>612</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3466</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3779</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7245</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1821</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1419</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1827</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>34</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>446</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>735</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>646</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3660</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4102</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7762</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1831</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1524</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2019</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>43</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>440</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>819</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>760</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4519</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4553</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>9072</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>See <hi rend="italic">Beauties of Scotland,</hi> vol. iv.; <hi rend="italic"
                    >General Report of Scotland,</hi> vol. i.; Playfair’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Geographical and Statistical Account of Scotland,</hi> vol. i.; Dr Graham’s <hi
                    rend="italic">General</hi><hi rend="italic">Vieιυ of the Agriculture of Kinross
                    and Clackmannan</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and, for its antiquities, Sibbald’s
                    <hi rend="italic">History of Fife and Kinross.</hi></p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:192947305" xml:id="kp-eb0712-7305-0731"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
