<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0712-7708-0762-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">KOTZEBUE, Augustus Frederick Ferdinand Von</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 12, page 762</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1080735">Prussians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1057037">Pens</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:897549">Dramatists</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1002769">Love</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205190">Peru</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ft8dp2t">Sand</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kj57">Caesarism</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zm3g">Pens</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vs7f">Dramatists</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z196">Love</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:192947708" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">KOTZEBUE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Augustus Frederick Ferdinand
                    Von</hi></label>, a prolific German dramatist and miscellaneous writer, was born
                    on the 3d of May 1761, at Weimar, where his father was a counsellor of legation.
                    He early evinced a propensity to poetry, and, whilst yet a boy, the
                    representation of a play which he witnessed inspired in him such a love of the
                    drama as determined his future destiny. lie received the rudiments of his
                    education at his native place, and when he was about sixteen years of age he
                    entered the university of Jena. Here he remained one year; but certain family
                    circumstances occurred which induced him to remove to Duisburg, where he studied
                    for a short time at the university, and returned to Jena in 1779. He was
                    destined for the profession of the law, but the master passion predominated; and
                    in gratifying his love of the drama, as well as literature in general, he
                    consumed no inconsiderable portion of his time. If at this period he did not
                    display great talent, he at least evinced wonderful versatility. Tragedy,
                    comedy, ballads, essays, and other species of literary composition, came rapidly
                    from his prolific pen. Their merits, however, he himself confesses in his
                    autobiography, were exceedingly equivocal, although some of his plays were acted
                    with applause. In his nineteenth year, he closed bis studies at Jena with taking
                    the character of an opponent at a doctor’s degree. Soon afterwards he returned
                    to his native place, where he diligently applied himself to the pandects, and
                    was admitted as an advocate. But his addresses to the muses were still as
                    assiduously paid as ever; and, in the ardour of his desire for distinction, he
                    tried his skill in almost every species of composition, imitating, as caprice or
                    admiration predominated, all the great writers of Germany, Schiller, Goethe,
                    Wieland, Hermes, and others.</p>
                <p>In 1781, on the invitation, it is said, of the Prussian ambassador, Kotzebue went
                    to St Petersburg, where he obtained a situation under Von Bawr, general of
                    engineers. The latter became his warm friend, and recommended him to the
                    empress, who, on the death of Bawr, which occurred about two years afterwards,
                    nominated him a counsellor. His imperial patroness first placed him in a
                    judicial situation at Revel, and finally appointed him president of Esthonia, on
                    which occasion he was ennobled. His literary ambition kept pace with his growing
                    fortunes, and drama succeeded drama from his pen, with great, if not increasing
                    rapidity. In 1790, on a journey to Pyrmont, he published his Doctor Bahrdt with
                    the Iron Forehead, under the name of <hi rend="italic">Knigge</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi><hi rend="italic">a</hi> work which created a considerable
                    sensation at the time of its appearance, but by which he lowered himself not a
                    little in public estimation. Having received his dismission from the imperial
                    service, he retired for a time to an estate which he possessed at some distance
                    from Narva: but, in 1797, he returned to Weimar, with a pension of 1000
                    guilders. Three years afterwards, he was induced to pay a short visit to Russia;
                    but he had scarcely crossed the frontiers of the empire when he was arrested by
                    order of Paul I. and sent to Siberia. This treatment of Kotzebue is said to have
                    originated in a suspicion of the autocrat that he was the author of some
                    political pamphlets, in which the emperor was personally attacked; but the exile
                    was kept entirely ignorant of the cause of his banishment. He was, however,
                    shortly afterwards recalled, and, as he informs us himself, well received by the
                    emperor, who confided to his direction the theatre of St Petersburg.</p>
                <p>After the death of Paul I. Kotzebue returned to Weimar,'and in 1802 was admitted
                    a member of the Academy of Sciences at Berlin. Some disputes which he had with
                    Goethe and the Schlegels induced him to remove to Paris, where the French
                    literati flattered his love of adulation by the attentions which they paid him.
                    It is not much to his credit that he repaid their kindness by the publication of
                    a calumnious work entitled My Recollections of Paris. The Italians were treated
                    in the same spirit of illiberality in his Recollections of Rome and of Naples.
                    About the end of 1803 he commenced, in conjunction with Merakel, a journal
                    entitled Der Freymüthige, The Sincere, in which Napoleon was virulently
                    attacked. In 1806 he went again to Russia, and lived from 1807 on his estate in
                    Esthonia, never ceasing to write against the imperial usurper of France.
                    Literature and politics continued to engage the pen of Kotzebue until 1813,
                    when, as counsellor of state, he followed the Russian head-quarters during the
                    campaign of that year; and, in order more effectually to excite the nations
                    against Napoleon, he published in Berlin the Russian-German National Gazette <hi
                    rend="italic">(</hi><hi rend="italic">Volksblatt).</hi> After the affairs of
                    Europe were decided by the victory of Waterloo, he went to St Petersburg; but
                    was in 1817 commissioned by the Emperor Alexander to return to his own country,
                    and report upon the state of literature and public opinion, for which he was to
                    receive a salary of 15,000 roubles. He who had exerted himself so much in favour
                    of Russia, sometimes, it is affirmed, at the expense of his native country, was
                    not likely to be warmly welcomed on his return home. From the first he was
                    looked upon as a spy; and the zeal which he displayed in his new employment soon
                    confirmed this opinion, and prepared the way for his destruction. He established
                    a literary weekly paper, in which judgment was passed on the publications of the
                    day, and political opinions advanced, at once dishonourable and obnoxious to
                    Germany, then awakening from its torpor, and heated with the expectation of
                    concessions on the part of its rulers, and by delusive anticipations of
                    representative systems. In his journal Kotzebue steadily ridiculed every attempt
                    to form liberal institutions; and not only was every species of political
                    amelioration opposed, but a marked enmity to the liberty of the press was
                    exhibited. A private communication of his to the emperor of Russia, which had
                    been obtained, it matters not how, was published in a German paper, and
                    republished throughout the country; and its appearance excited a strong feeling
                    of hostility and indignation against the author. Shielded as he was by the power
                    of the autocrat, he found it necessary to quit Weimar for Manheim, where his
                    literary and diplomatic labours were resumed with increased activity.
                    Unfortunately for him, he began to point his pen more directly against the
                    enthusiastic anticipations and theoretical notions of liberty which had become
                    the distinguishing characteristic of the great mass of the students at the
                    German universities. A spark of dangerous enthusiasm caught the heated and
                    disordered mind of a young student named Sand, who doomed the versatile
                    dramatist and venal party writer to the death of a Caesar, under the impression
                    that he was only performing an act of heroic virtue in the cause of national
                    liberty. Having obtained admission into the house of his victim, he deliberately
                    murdered him, on the 23d of March 1819, after which he gave himself up to
                    justice, and suffered on the scaffold. Kotzebue was three times married, and
                    left thirteen children. He wrote about a hundred dramas, the best of which are
                    the comedies, and even these are far from being first-rate productions. As a
                    dramatist he is more artificial than natural, and more melodramatic and
                    picturesque than profound in the knowledge of the human heart, or happy in the
                    concoction of incident or illustration of manners. Some of his plays, however,
                    have been translated into English, and adapted to the British stage with great
                    success. His Misanthropy and Repentance, under the title of the Stranger, is a
                    stock piece; and his Spaniards in Peru, or the Death of Rolla, metamorphosed
                    into Pizzaro by Sheridan, was the most . successful play ever produced in this
                    country. Kotzebue wrote a history of the German empire, and the Early History<pb
                    break="no" facs="nls:192947721" xml:id="kp-eb0712-7721-0763"/> of Prussia; but
                    as a historian he is held in little esteem by his countrymen. <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">(r.</hi> R. R∙)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
