<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> <?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0997-0957-12" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bw6x">Spirits</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bg2hh25">Mongols</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48s4jx3p">Shamanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h41jp6g">Cossacks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1130061">Spirits</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130040">Spirit</term>
                    <term ref="fast:936387">Fur</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1043442">Ocean</term>
                    <term ref="fast:946112">Graining</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1025421">Mongols</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1115174">Shamans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1115159">Shamanism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:880643">Cossacks</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=997" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">YAKOUTSK</label>, one of the four districts into which the
                    province of Irkoutsk, in Asiatic Russia, is divided. It extends as far as the
                    Frozen Ocean, north from the boundary of the provinces of Irkoutsk proper and of
                    Nertschinsk. It is bounded on the east by the province of Okhotsk, which
                    intervenes between the eastern extremity of Asia. It is watered by the great
                    river Lena, which traverses its whole extent from south to north. The climate is
                    so severe as to prevent the ripening of grain to advantage; and even a crop of
                    rye is extremely uncertain, as in June the ground in the vicinity of Yakoutsk is
                    frozen three feet deep. The inhabitants subsist chiefly by hunting; but this
                    formerly lucrative branch of trade has considerably fallen off, in consequence
                    of the depredations made on the game by the activity of the hunters. The sables
                    have become extremely scarce; but other animals still abound, and bring
                    considerable gain.</p>
                <p>The tribe that inhabits this dreary region bears the name of the Yacoutes. They
                    formerly occupied the countries on the Angara and Upper Lena, and are supposed
                    to have been originally a Tartar race; but being driven from their original
                    abodes by the Mongols and Burats, they have taken shelter in the frozen
                    solitudes of the Lower Lena. They occupy an extensive territory, extending
                    eighteen degrees from north to south, and nearly fifty from east to west. This
                    desolate country is but thinly peopled. The number of males paying tribute
                    amounts to 34,979, which, it is supposed, may be about the third of the entire
                    number of both sexes. Those who inhabit the southern districts of this province
                    are tolerably rich and industrious, and possess the usual size, activity, and
                    vigour: but those farther to the north live poorly; they are seldom able to
                    procure bread, and feed on onions, garlic, and other roots, with various sorts
                    of berries, both fresh and preserved, which form their chief luxuries. They are
                    remarkably ignorant and superstitious, and live in the continual dread of evil
                    spirits. The Shamans, a set of magical impostors, enjoy unbounded influence
                    among them. They are eager for spirits, and greedily drink brandy when they can
                    procure it, and use as a substitute fermented mare’s milk, which forms the chief
                    luxury of their feasts. They now submit quietly to the Russian yoke, though they
                    long continued to view that nation with hostility. They acknowledge their
                    subjection by an annual tribute, generally paid in furs.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Yakoutsk,</hi> the capital of the above province, is
                    situated on the western bank of the Lena, on a plain surrounded by mountains,
                    which enclose it at the distance of ten or twelve miles. It is a place of some
                    trade, notwithstanding the inhospitable climate in which it is situated, being
                    the emporium of the fur trade; all the furs which are collected in the extensive
                    regions of the north being brought to this place, as are also all the Russian
                    and Asiatic commodities which are imported in exchange. It also forms a species
                    of entrepôt for the Russian trade with Kamtschatka and the western coast of
                    America. The dreary winter is the greatest disadvantage of this place. The cold
                    is excessive; and the inhabitants arc almost entirely confined to their houses,
                    the daylight continuing during the deadness of the season for only a few hours.
                    They consume their time, accordingly, between drinking and sleeping; and they
                    use ice as the most effectual mode of stopping up every chink and crevice, being
                    applied, like double glass, to the outside of the windows. Yakoutsk contains 500
                    or 600 houses, and about 3000 inhabitants, who for the most part are Cossacks or
                    Yakoutes. Long. 140. 8. E. Lat. 60. 2. N.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
