<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0713-6220-0369-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LIPARI (7th edition, volume 13, page 369)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g08p">Groups</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:916316">Etruscans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1169356">Vulcanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="fast:882286">Cratering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028366">Mountains</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193206220?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LIPARI</label>, the collective name of a group of islands in
                    the Mediterranean Sea, forming a part of the kingdom of Naples. They were known
                    in the most remote ages as the Ephestiades, in the subsequent centuries as the
                    AEolian Islands, and latterly have commonly borne the name of the most
                    considerable of their number. According to the mythology of the heathens, they
                    were imagined to be the chimneys of a vast subterraneous cavity, inhabited by
                    Steropes, Brontes, and Argos; and the caverns in which AEolus confined the winds
                    were in this archipelago. Here Diana was said to have been placed by Latona in
                    her infancy, and here also Vulcan forged the thunderbolts of Jupiter.</p>
                <p>It is most probable that, at an early period, Liparus, the son of Auson, having
                    passed from Italy with some of his followers, planted the largest of the
                    islands, and conferred his name upon it. AEolus, the son of Hippotas, arrived
                    afterwards, and marrying Cyane, the daughter of Liparus, succeeded to the
                    throne; and being very attentive to meteorology, and often successfully
                    predicting changes of weather, this may have given rise to the fabulous power
                    attributed to him. This colony had suffered a decline, in spite of an
                    augmentation of the inhabitants by the immigration of some Rhodians and
                    Cnidians, when it was visited by some Etruscan pirates, who built the city of
                    Lipari, and, by means of husbandmen transported from the continent, extended
                    cultivation to the other islands. Since that period, they have been subject to
                    Sicily, forming in Christian times a bishopric, restricted in 1394 to these
                    islands. The whole of these islands exhibit the corrosive effects of gases and
                    spray; but their western coasts, rising abruptly in precipitous masses, and
                    shelving down gradually to the eastward, form an interesting geological feature,
                    in which it agrees with the greater part of the West India and other islands. It
                    is remarkable that, besides the western coasts of all these islands being steep
                    and craggy, they have each of them a high isolated rock on their northern
                    shores. The basis of the whole group is hornstone, with the various alterations
                    and decompositions occasioned by volcanic influence; an influence easily
                    traceable throughout these islands, in its grandest and wildest varieties.</p>
                <p>The climate is highly salubrious, and the weather generally soft and refreshing;
                    but though there are a few trifling springs, a general scarcity of water is
                    experienced, as the soil, consisting almost entirely of scoriae, tuffa, pumice,
                    pozzolana, and ashes, without any intervening stony stratum, except occasional
                    masses of obdurate vitrification, rapidly absorbs the moisture. The natives are
                    consequently obliged to construct capacious cisterns, in which rainwater is
                    preserved in a cool temperature. Most of the cattle are lean, and they are not
                    abundant, as the pasturage is only adapted for the most part to the feeding of
                    goats. The land is well cultivated, and yields grapes, currants, figs, prickly
                    pears, corn, cotton, olives, and pulse, which latter grow under the cane
                    trellises that support the vines. Violent rains sometimes cause great injury to
                    the grounds, owing to their situation, and the friability of the soil; and at
                    other times swarms of locusts greatly injure and diminish the produce. A large
                    quantity of wine and currants is annually exported, and an active trade is
                    carried on in bitumen, pumice, nitre, pozzolana, cinnabar, coral, and fish. At
                    one period alum formed a considerable article of export, but it has decreased,
                    probably owing to the diminished heat of the subterranean fires. Some sulphur is
                    still shipped, but in less quantity than formerly, owing to a prejudice
                    entertained by the inhabitants, that the vapour which arises from purifying it
                    infects the air, and is injurious to vegetation.</p>
                <p>The inhabitants, who amount in all these islands to 22,350, are contented,
                    temperate, and hardy, and are esteemed excellent sailors; but they are commonly
                    considered as impertinent, mean, and immoral. They are by no means rich, but few
                    are in extreme poverty; and, from leading an active life, they are healthy,
                    except that, from their filthy habits, the itch is very prevalent amongst all
                    classes. They are described as very expert slingers and throwers of stones, a
                    valuable talent in an unarmed population, exposed to predatory visits from
                    corsairs. The islands are variously enumerated, some stating them to be eight or
                    nine, and others eleven. This has arisen from those who stated them at the
                    greater numbers including some which are uninhabited, or may be considered as
                    mere rocks belonging to adjacent islands.</p>
                <p>Isí, The island of Lipari is the largest and most populous of the whole group. It
                    is accessible by a bay on the east side of the island, formed on the north by
                    Monte Rosso, an immense mass of volcanic matter, and on the south by Cape
                    Capistello, a rugged rock of lava. It is hilly, but intermixed with peculiarly
                    beautiful and fertile valleys and plains, from which, amongst other produce, is
                    supplied the Malmsey wine, whose flavour is admired in most parts of the world.
                    The extent of the island is 110 square miles, and the population amounts to
                    about 15,000 persons. Lipari has not suffered from volcanic eruptions for many
                    ages, but its subterraneous fires are not yet extinguished; for, on digging in
                    the central parts of the island to a trifling depth, heat, smoke, and a
                    sulphureous smell, immediately arise. The highest mountain, St Angelo, contains
                    a crater 200 feet wide; and on another mountain, Guardia, the course of the lava
                    from an eruption is still visible. Lipari is literally the wreck of a vast
                    conflagration, and affords perhaps the finest field in the world for the study
                    of the geologist. This island contains the capital, the seat of government of
                    the whole group. It is a city of the same name, situated on the south-east side;
                    it has two havens, is the see of a bishop, and has a castle, a cathedral, and
                    several other churches. It is healthy, though crowded, irregular, and filthy. It
                    contains 12,500 inhabitants. Long. 14. 57.50. E. Lat. 38. 27. 56. N.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">2d,</hi> Volcano is a lofty island, fifteen miles in circuit,
                    and possesses two small ports on the northern side. At a small distance from
                    these ports is a hill, having a great crater, with a deep valley encircling, and
                    detaching it from the neighbouring hills. It is about 2400 feet in height, but
                    accessible to the summit with no little fatigue and some danger. The crater is a
                    mile and a quarter in circumference, and nearly a quarter of a mile deep,
                    forming an inverted elliptical cone, with the northern considerably higher and
                    hotter than the southern side. The interior is full of volcanic scoriae, coaŧbd
                    over with sulphur, alum, vitriol, and muriate of ammonia, diverging into every
                    possible shade of brown, red, green, blue, orange, black, yellow, and white.
                    From the numerous apertures in every part, a sulphureous and hydrogenous vapour
                    rushes out in gusts, which, when collected on the sides, where a considerable
                    quantity of sulphur has been deposited by sublimation, forms a species of
                    stalactite, covered with boracic or other light efflorescences. The bottom is
                    about two of three hundred yards in extent. There is a frequent explosion of
                    gases, and a continued roar similar to that of a cataract, or of many
                    anchor-smiths’ forges, which impress on the imagination the horrid feeling of
                    being only separated by a frail crust from some vast abyss of central fire. Fire
                    is only observable at night, when a pale lambent flame is seen to issue from
                    many of the fissures, accompanied<pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193206233?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0713-6233-0370"/> with nauseous
                    fumes and vapours. There are but few inhabitants, and these are mostly employed
                    in the sulphur works. Long. 14. 57. 50. E. Lat. 38. 27. 56. N.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">3ċZ,</hi> Salina. This island is to the north-west of
                    Lĩpari, and is about fourteen miles in circumference, with an industrious
                    population of4000 persons, employedin raisinggrain, fruit, pulse, capers, salt,
                    alum, and soda. Although no mention is made in history of any eruption, it is
                    evidently of volcanic origin, and there are palpable vestiges of its once
                    desolating craters, the fires of which must have ceased before the dawn of
                    history, whilst they have now become the most pleasing and fertile spots of the
                    group of islands. Long. 14. 55. 56. E. Lat. 38. 35. 40. N.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">⅛th,</hi> Felicudi. This island is ten miles to the westward of
                    Salina, is nine miles in circumference, and contains about 1100 inhabitants. The
                    soil consists chiefly of detached masses of ferruginous and argillaceous lava,
                    strongly marked with white felspars and black schorl, intermixed with enamel,
                    cinders, sand, and pozzolana. It is highly fertile, and produces wheat, barley,
                    grapes, olives, pulse, and flax, in abundance. It is an extinct volcano, with
                    three high mountains; but.there are no remains of the fire that produced the
                    island, nor does history give any accounts of eruptions. Long. 14. 29. 37. E.
                    Lat. 38. 34. 5. N.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">oth,</hi> Alicudi. This is the westernmost of the islands, and
                    rises like a cone from the sea, having a crater, the fires of which have been
                    extinct for ages; but the lava is seen in grotesque streams, extending from the
                    summit to the sea. The few spots capable of cultivation are highly fertile, and
                    support 750 inhabitants. Long. 14. 16. 30. E. Lat. 38. 32. 4L N.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Qth,</hi> Panaria, a small island to the north of Lipari, is
                    seven miles in circumference, has a good port, and about two hundred
                    inhabitants, who, from a rich soil, produce corn, wine, soda, and especially
                    excellent raisins. The rocks around it, called the Dattoli, appear to have
                    formed the circumference of an immense crater. It was known by the Romans as <hi
                    rend="italic">Thermissea,</hi> and was celebrated for its warm baths. Long. 15.
                    2. 55. E. Lat. 38. 37. 40. N.</p>
                <p>7t7z, Basiluzzo, a small island to the north of Panaria, is about a mile and
                    three quarters in circumference, and is very thinly inhabited. It produces corn,
                    flax, and culinary vegetables, and is overrun with rabbits, which injure the
                    crops. Like the rest of the group, this island exhibits abundant proofs of its
                    volcanic origin. Long. 15. 7. 54. E. Lat. 38. 39. 50. N.</p>
                <p>8rΛ, Stromboli, the most northern of this group of islands, was known to the
                    ancients by the name of <hi rend="italic">Strongyle.</hi> It is a conical
                    mountain, with an irregular base. It is upwards of 2000 feet high, is
                    bifurcated, and about nine miles in circumference; and, from every indication,
                    seems an evident product of subterranean fire. The crater has been rarely
                    visited, on account of the great difficulty of ascending to it. The best
                    description is that of Captain William Henry Smyůh, who surveyed the whole of
                    these islands, as well as the shores of the Mediterranean. About one third of
                    the way from the summit of the mountain the crater appears. It is continually
                    burning, with frequent explosions, and a constant ejection of fiery matter. It
                    is of a circular form, about one hundred and seventy yards in diameter, with a
                    yellow efflorescence adhering to its sides like that of AEtna. When the smoke
                    clears away, an undulating igneous substance is to be seen, which at short
                    intervals rises and falls with great agitation, and, when swollen to the utmost
                    height, bursts with a violent explosion and a discharge of red-hot stones in a
                    semi-fluid state, accompanied with showers of ashes and sand, and a strong
                    sulphureous smell. The masses are usually thrown up to the height of from sixty
                    or seventy to three hundred feet; but some, the descent of which Captain Smyth
                    found to occupy from nine to twelve seconds, must have ascended above a
                    thousand. In the moderate ejections, the stones in their ascent gra-, dually
                    diverge like a pyrotechnical exhibition, and fall into the abyss again, except
                    on the side next the sea, where they roll down in quick succession, after
                    bounding from the declivity, to a considerable distance in the water. This
                    crater, which is on the north-west side of the mountain, has burned without
                    intermission from the earliest periods. The incessant combustion is supposed to
                    be kept up by oxygen, pyrites, and sulphur; but there are no traces of the
                    presence of bitumen. It appears to be not only the vent of all these islands,
                    but to have a subterraneous communication with Sicily and Italy; for, previous
                    to a severe earthquake taking place in those parts, Stromboli has been observed
                    to be covered with dense clouds of smoke, and to emit, with increased activity,
                    unusually ardent flames. It appears, moreover, from the concurrent relation of
                    the islanders, to be influenced by atmospheric changes, as storms, particularly
                    those from the southward, which are preceded by thick volumes of smoke, so that
                    the native pilots are guided at night by its flame, and gain intimation of the
                    weather by day from the smoke.</p>
                <p>The island contains about 1200 inhabitants, who have neither magistrate nor
                    lawyer, but are governed by two priests. The soil is a fertile black mould,
                    producing wine, wheat, barley, cotton, raisins, currants, and figs. There is an
                    extinct volcano on Mount Schicceola, which burned in the time of Aristotle, and
                    was noticed by him. The church is dedicated to St Bartholomew, and is in long.
                    15. 13. 10. E. and lat. 38. 48. 12. N.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
