<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0891-0826-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ORENBURG (9th edition, volume 17, page 826)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h41jp6g">Cossacks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pg1hv69">Nonconformists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4804xr51">Mohammedans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v698h77">Mohammedanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g03">Cent</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:880643">Cossacks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:850620">Cent</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:890865">Depositions</term>
                    <term ref="fast:979089">Iron</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n891/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ORENBURG</label>, a government of south-eastern Russia,
                    bounded on the N. by Ufa and Perm, on the S. and E. by the steppe of the
                    Orenburg Kirghiz, and on the W. by Samara, has an area of 73,890 square miles.
                    Situated at the southern extremity of the Urals and extending to the north-east
                    on their eastern slope, Orenburg consists of a hilly tract bordered on both
                    sides by steppes. The central ridge occasionally reaches an elevation of about
                    5000 feet; there are several parallel ridges, which, however, nowhere exceed
                    2600 feet, and gradually sink towards the south. A great variety of geological
                    formations are represented within the government. Diorites and granites enter it
                    from the north and appear at many places from under the Silurian and Devonian
                    deposits. The Carboniferous limestones and sandstones, as also softer Permian,
                    Jurassic, and Cretaceous deposits, have a wide extension in the south and east.
                    Magnetic iron, copper, silver, and lead ores, auriferous sands, and salt from
                    the lakes constitute the mineral wealth of Orenburg, along with its very fertile
                    “black earth,” which covers wide areas around the Urals. It is traversed from
                    north to south by the Ural river, which also forms its southern boundary; the
                    chief tributaries are the Sakmara and the Ilek. The upper courses of the Byelaya
                    and the Samara, tributaries of the Kama and the Volga, also lie within the
                    government, as well as the affluents of the Tobol on the eastern slope of the
                    Ural range. Numerous salt lakes occur in the district of Tchelabinsk; but
                    several parts of the flat lands occasionally suffer from want of water. Thirteen
                    per cent, of the surface is under wood. The climate is continental and dry, the
                    average temperature at Orenburg being 37 <hi rend="superscript"> 0-</hi> 4 Fahr.
                    (4° ’ 5 in January, 69 <hi rend="superscript"> 0,</hi> 8 in July). Frosts of -
                    38°, and heats of 98° are not uncommon.</p>
                <p>The population (900,550 in 1870) numbered 1,120,700 in 1881. The increase is
                    largely due to immigration, an extensive tract of uncultivated land which
                    formerly belonged to the Bashkirs having recently been purchased by the
                    Government officials and leased to immigrants from the interior of Russia. The
                    inhabitants are mainly Great Russians, Bashkirs (26 per cent.), and Kirghiz
                    (about 5 per cent.). The majority belong to the Greek Church, or are
                    Nonconformists; 27 per cent, are Mohammedans, The chief occupations are
                    agriculture and cattle-breeding. Although only 3 2 per cent, of the area is
                    under crops, grain is both distilled and exported. In 1881 there were in the
                    province 581,000 horses, 441,000 cattle, 880,000 sheep, and 65,000 pigs.
                    Notwithstanding the abundance of iron and copper ore, mining is but little
                    developed. The industrial establishments (distilleries, tanneries, flourmills,
                    &amp;c. ) are few, and their aggregate production in 1879 was only 5,195,000
                    roubles, employing about 2200 workmen. The export trade in corn, skins, and
                    tallow is of some importance, and the fairs at Orenburg, Troitsk, and
                    Tchelabinsk yield large returns. There are five districts, the chief towns of
                    which are Orenburg (35,600 inhabitants), Orsk (14,350), Tchelabinsk or Tchelaba
                    (9000) Troitsk (8300), and Verkhneuralsk (10,350).</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n892/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0892-0827"/>
                <p>The territory of the Orenburg Cossacks, which extends as a narrow strip up the
                    Ural river, occupies the whole of the government east of the Ural mountains, and
                    joins, by a narrow line of posts, the former line of blockhouses of the Siberian
                    Cossacks, has an area of 35,820 square miles, with a population in 1880 of
                    290,800 Cossacks and 16,460 peasants; 25,000 were Moslem Bashkirs.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Orenburg,</hi> capital of the above government, is situated
                    on the right bank of the Ural river, 933 miles by rail south-east from Moscow.
                    The fortress, which has eleven bastions and a circumference of 6300 yards, has
                    lost its importance since the recent advances of Russia towards the south-east,
                    and is falling into decay. The town, on the other hand, is rapidly increasing,
                    and now includes the former suburbs of Golubinaya and Novaya. The population is
                    35,600. Orenburg has a military cadet school, two lower military schools, a
                    lyceum, and various primary schools,—one of them for Kirghiz children. The
                    inhabitants are chiefly occupied in agriculture and trade. The manufactures are
                    few, but the trade is steadily increasing; the imports include cotton, silk,
                    furs, wool, cattle, and horses, while cotton and woollen stuffs, cotton yarn,
                    leather, colours, sugar, and grain are exported. Orenburg is connected, by rail
                    with Samara on the Volga and with Moscow.</p>
                <p>The government of Orenburg was formerly inhabited by the Kirghiz in the south and
                    the Bashkirs in the north. The latter were brought under the rule of Russia in
                    1557, and the fort of Ufa was erected a few years later in order to protect them
                    against the raids of the Kirghiz. The frequent risings of the Bashkirs and the
                    continuous attacks of the Kirghiz led the Russian Government in the 18th century
                    to erect a line of forts and blockhouses on the Ural and Sakmara rivers, which
                    was afterwards extended south-westwards towards the Caspian, and eastwards
                    towards Omsk. The central point of these military lines was the fort of
                    Orenburg, originally founded at the confluence of the Or with the Ural (now
                    Orsk), and afterwards removed (in 1740) 120 miles lower doλvn the Ural river to
                    its present site. In 1773 it was besieged by Pugatchoff, the leader of the great
                    revolt of the peasantry, supported by the Bashkirs. The government of Orenburg
                    was created in 1774, embracing a wide territory which reached to the Volga, to
                    the Caspian, and to Perm, the limits to the eastward being undefined. In 1865
                    this was divided into two governments,—Ufa in the north and Orenburg in the
                    south. The steppe of the Kirghiz, which extends south of the Ural river towards
                    the Caspian and the Sea of Aral, continued under the jurisdiction of the
                    governor-general of Orenburg. Recently the steppe of the Orenburg Kirghiz has
                    been incorporated with the newly-created provinces of Turgay and Uralsk; and the
                    territory of the Orenburg Cossacks, formerly independent, has been brought
                    within the government of Orenburg, and subdivided into districts.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
