<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0752-0695-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">OASES (9th edition, volume 17, page 695)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zs2kn9v">Tracts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4901zk6v">Springs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tx35b4z">Wells</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pc5x">Soils</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n29p69w">Barley</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jd4pp0f">Air</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1242088">Sahara</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812576">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:799938">Africans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:799932">Africanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:804971">Algerians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1153794">Tracts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130905">Spring</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130935">Springs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1173723">Wells</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1124682">Soils</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n752/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">OASES</label>. Throughout the great belt of desert extending
                    from the west coast of Africa to central Asia, various fertile tracts occur,
                    clothed with vegetation and watered by springs, to which the name oases has been
                    applied. Those which are best known are met with in the central and eastern
                    portions of the Great Sahara and in the Libyan Desert. In that region they
                    consist generally of deep depressions or valleys, locally termed “wâdis,” where
                    the water comes to the surface in natural springs, or where it may be procured
                    by sinking wells. Under the influence of these beneficent springs vegetation
                    bursts forth and covers a more or less extensive area, which becomes a
                    halting-place for travellers in the desert, and frequently supports a
                    considerable population. Many of the oases are situated in the mountainous
                    regions, where the ground is sufficiently elevated to precipitate the moisture
                    in the atmosphere. The rain which falls, however, is rapidly absorbed by the
                    rocks or sandy soil, and much of it collects in depressions at no great depth
                    from the surface. The Arabs have long been in the habit of tapping these
                    subterranean waters by sinking wells, a copious supply being usually obtained at
                    depths varying down to 200 fathoms. Indeed, so rapidly does the water ascend
                    when the aqueous strata are pierced in certain localities that the well-sinkers
                    are sometimes suffocated ere they reach the surface. In the Algerian Sahara a
                    large number of artesian wells have been sunk by the French, resulting in the
                    formation of oases, which have to some extent affected the habits of the native
                    tribes by inducing them to become cultivators of these fertile tracts. It is
                    evident, therefore, that, notwithstanding the arid climate which prevails
                    generally throughout the African deserts, a tolerably plentiful supply of water
                    can be obtained by artificial means at various points. The springs, being
                    essential to the very existence of the oases, are naturally guarded with care so
                    as to prevent the sands encroaching on them. Should they cease to flow, the
                    decay of the vegetation rapidly ensues and the oases disappear. Another
                    characteristic feature of these fertile tracts is the palm-tree forests, which
                    are admirably adapted to such unfavourable conditions. The date and the dûm palm
                    are the commonest species met with in the forests; they are highly prized by
                    reason of the produce which they yield to the cultivators of the soil and the
                    shelter which they afford from the scorching sun. Indeed, so serviceable are
                    they that in some cases the Arabs artificially create an oasis with the aid of a
                    few palm trees by digging holes deep enough to allow the roots to pierce the
                    aqueous strata.</p>
                <p>From the accounts given by various travellers it would appear that, while the
                    larger oases cover extensive tracts, the smaller ones are liable to be effaced
                    by drifting sand. As an example of one of the largest, Air or Asben may be
                    mentioned, which measures 180 miles from north to south. Such extensive fertile
                    tracts are dotted over with villages, whose inhabitants carry on the cultivation
                    of the soil and export various articles of produce. By means of irrigation
                    different cereals are successfully cultivated, such as barley, rice, and
                    millet.</p>
                <p>In the western Sahara the chief oases are :—(1) Tuât, about 1000 miles to the
                    south-west of Tripoli, the principal town being In-sâlah ('Ain Salah); (2)
                    Taudeni, south-west of Tuât; (3) 'Arawân, south of Taudeni and north of
                    Timbuktu; and (4) Wâlata, southwest of 'Arawân. In the eastern portion of the
                    Great Desert the important oases are :—(1) Fezzân, the capital of which is
                    Morzιik, lying to the south-south-east of Tripoli; (2) Ghadâmes, north-west of
                    Fezzân; (3) Tibesti, south of Fezzân; (4) Bilma,west-south-west of Tibesti; and
                    (5) Air or Asben, west from Bilma and north-west from Lake Tchad. The last is
                    perhaps one of the most remarkable oases in the African desert, forming a
                    tableland whose average elevation is 2000 feet, with peaks rising to a height of
                    5000 feet. Heavy tropical rains are precipitated by this lofty plateau, and
                    hence the valleys are clothed with vegetation. This oasis is richly cultivated,
                    producing barley, maize, and millet. The capital is Agades, a town with 7000
                    inhabitants, which is situated on the caravan route between Morzιik and Sokoto,
                    and constitutes one of the important centres of trade in central Africa. _ , , .
                    .</p>
                <p>In the Libyan Desert the chief oases are :—(1) Khargeh or Kharιja (the outer
                    oases), sometimes termed the <hi rend="italic">oasis</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >magna,</hi> about 120 miles to the west of Thebes; (2) Dakhel or Dâkhila (the
                    inner oases), situated to the west of Khargeh; (3) Farafreh (Farafira),
                    north-west of Dakhel; (4) Bahriya (northern), to the north of Farafreh; (5) Siwa
                    (the famous oasis of Jupiter Ammon), at the northern limits of the Libyan
                    Desert; and (6) the Kufra group, smith-west of Siwa. Perhaps the most fertile of
                    these tracts is Dakhel, which was first made known to Europeans in 1819 by Sir
                    A. Edmonstone. The chief produce consists of dates, rice, olives, and apricots,
                    but durra, barley, lemons, citrons, and figs also grow on the rich sou of this
                    oasis. It contains eleven villages, the total population being estimated at
                    6000. . ...</p>
                <p>Similar fertile tracts, though of smaller extent, occur in Arabia and in that
                    part of Persia lying to the west of the Salt Desert. In <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n753/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0753-0696"/> central Asia the great desert of Gobi, ranging
                    from Turkestan to Manchuria, is interspersed with a few oases, the chief one
                    being Kami, which is characterized by a rich growth of vegetation.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
