<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0761-0704-08" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">OBLIGATION (9th edition, volume 17, page 704)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1207035">Louisiana</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:968113">Imperfection</term>
                    <term ref="fast:876969">Contracts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058777">Personals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058667">Personality</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42b8vd88">Contractions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795945">Contracts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sx86">Personality</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4t43j33z">Debt</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n761/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">OBLIGATION</label>, in law, is a term derived from the Roman
                    law, in which <hi rend="italic">obligatio</hi> signified a tie of law <hi
                    rend="italic">(vinculum juris}</hi> whereby one person is bound to perform or
                    forbear some act for another. The <hi rend="italic">obligatio</hi> of Roman law
                    arose either from voluntary acts or from circumstances to which legal
                    consequences were annexed. In the former case it was said to arise <hi
                    rend="italic">ex contractu,</hi> from contract, in the latter <hi rend="italic"
                    >quasi ex contractu, ex delicto,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">quasi ex
                    delicto,—</hi> that is to say, from tort, or from acts or omissions to which the
                    law practically attached the same results as it did to contract or tort. <hi
                    rend="italic">Obligatio</hi> was used to denote either end of the legal chain
                    that bound the parties, the right of the party who could compel fulfilment of
                    the <hi rend="italic">obligatio,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">creditor,</hi> or
                    the duty of the party who could be compelled to fulfilment, the <hi
                    rend="italic">debitor.</hi> In English law obligation has only the latter sense.
                    Creditor and debtor have also lost their Roman law signification; they have been
                    narrowed to mean the parties where the obligation is the payment of a sum of
                    money. In English law obligation is used in at least four senses—(1) any duty
                    imposed by law; (2) the special duty created by a <hi rend="italic">vinculum
                    juris</hi>; (3) not the duty, but the evidence of the duty,—that is to say, an
                    instrument under seal, otherwise called a bond: (4) the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n762/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0762-0705"/> operative part of a bond. The third use of the
                    word is chiefly confined to the older writers. <hi rend="italic">Simplex</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">duplex</hi><hi rend="italic">obligatio</hi> were the old
                    names for what are now more commonly called a single and a double or conditional
                    bond. The party bound is still called the obligor, the party in whose favour the
                    bond is made the obligee. The fourth like the third, is a use scarcely found
                    except in the older writers. The word “bond” is of course a mere translation of
                    <hi rend="italic">obligatio.</hi> Obligations may be either perfect or
                    imperfect. A perfect obligation is one which is directly enforceable by legal
                    proceedings; an imperfect or moral obligation (the <hi rend="italic">naturalis
                    obligatio</hi> of Roman law) is one in which the <hi rend="italic">vinculum
                    juris</hi> is in some respects incomplete, so that it cannot be directly
                    enforced, though it is not entirely destitute of legal effect. A perfect
                    obligation may become imperfect by lapse of time or other means, and,
                    conversely, an imperfect obligation may under certain circumstances become
                    perfect. Thus a debt may be barred by the Statute of Limitations and so cease to
                    be enforceable. The obligation, however, remains, though imperfect, for if there
                    be a subsequent acknowledgment by the debtor, the debt revives, and the
                    imperfect obligation becomes again perfect. At one period there was some doubt
                    among English lawyers whether a moral obligation could be regarded as sufficient
                    consideration for a contract; it has now, however, been long decided that it
                    cannot be so regarded.</p>
                <p>The Scotch law as to obligations closely follows the Roman. As in English law,
                    the term obligation is used to express the instrument itself by which the
                    obligation is imposed. The bond or unilateral obligation of Scotch law is a
                    simple contract to pay the sum borrowed, &amp;c., with interest. The English
                    bond is generally a contract to pay double the sum of the debt, with a condition
                    that the bond is to be void if the debt be paid by a certain day. In Scotch law
                    gratuitous obligations rank in competition with the claims of creditors; in
                    English law a voluntary bond, though effectual against the grantor, cannot be
                    set up against creditors. Bonds in Scotland which are heritable securities still
                    rank as immovables for certain purposes, though they have been made movables as
                    regards the succession of the creditor, unless executors are expressly excluded
                    (31 and 32 Vict. c. 101, s. 117).</p>
                <p>American law is in general agreement with English, except in the case of
                    Louisiana, vdιere the terms obligor and obligee are used in as wide a sense as
                    the <hi rend="italic">debitor</hi> and <hi rend="italic">creditor</hi> of Roman
                    law. By art. 3522 of the Louisiana civil code obligor or debtor means the person
                    who has engaged to perform some obligation, obligee or creditor the person in
                    favour of whom some obligation is contracted, whether such obligation be to pay
                    money or to do or not to do something. The term obligation is important in
                    America from its use in art. i. s. 10 of the constitution of the United States,
                    “No State shall pass any law . . . impairing the obligation of contracts.” This
                    does not affect the power of Congress to pass such a law. Contracts between
                    private individuals are of course within the provision. So are private
                    conveyances, charters of private corporations, and statutory and other grants by
                    a State. On the other hand, marriage and divorce, and arrangements which are
                    political in their nature, such as charters of municipal corporations, licences
                    to carry on particular trades, or regulations of police, are not within the
                    provision. In order to fall within it, the law must act upon the terms of the
                    agreement, and not merely upon the mode of procedure. If it act not upon the
                    terms but upon the remedy, it impairs the obligation if it purport to be
                    retrospective, but it is valid so far as it applies to subsequent contracts.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
