<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0759-0702-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">OBADIAH (9th edition, volume 17, page 702)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1033832">Nationalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:984609">Judgments</term>
                    <term ref="fast:984572">Judgment</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1061214">Phoenicians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812576">Arabs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r50f">Phoenicians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48911q68">Baptists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f45m">Judgments</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v698j66">Prophets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204236">Israel</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205669">Jordan</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n759/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">OBADIAH</label> (∏∏⅛ζ O∕5δ∈ιoυ, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Aβ8ιov,</hi> Abdias) is a name pretty frequent in the Old Testament, meaning
                    “servant” or worshipper “of Jehovah.” It is synonymous with Abdi and Abdeel, and
                    of a type common in Semitic proper names; compare the Arabic 'Abdallâh,
                    Taimallât, 'Abd Manât, &lt;fcc., the Hebrew Obed Edom, and many Phoenician
                    forms. The name of Obadiah is prefixed to the fourth and shortest book of the
                    minor prophets, and as no date or other historical note is added it is not
                    surprising that an early Hebrew tradition recorded by Jerome <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Comm. in Ob.)</hi> identified the prophet with the best-known Obadiah of the
                    historical books, the protector of the prophets in the reign of Ahab (1 Kings
                    xviii.). His tomb was shown in Samaria with those of Elisha and John the
                    Baptist, and the <hi rend="italic">Epitaphium</hi><hi rend="italic">Paulae</hi>
                    describes the wild performances, analogous to those of modern dervishes, that
                    took place before these shrines.</p>
                <p>It is now agreed on all hands thatΓit is vain to connect Obadiah the prophet with
                    any other Obadiah of the Old Testament, and that our only clue to the date and
                    composition of the book lies in internal evidence. The prophecy is directed
                    against Edom. Jehovah has sent a messenger forth among the nations to stir them
                    up to battle against the proud inhabitants of Mount Seir, to bring them down
                    from the rocky fastnesses which they deem impregnable. Edom shall be not only
                    plundered but utterly undone and expelled from his borders, and this he shall
                    suffer (through his own folly) at the hand of trusted allies (vers. 1-9). The
                    cause of this judgment is his cruelty to his brother Jacob. In the day of
                    Jerusalem’s overthrow the Edomites rejoiced over the calamity, grasped at a
                    share of the spoil, lay in wait to cut off the fugitives (vers. 10-14). But now
                    the day of Jehovah is near upon all nations, Esau and all the heathen shall
                    drink full retribution for their banquet of carnage and plunder on Jehovah’s
                    holy mountain. A rescued Israel shall dwell in Mount Zion in restored holiness;
                    the house of Jacob shall regain their old possessions; Edom shall be burned up
                    before them as chaff before the flame; they shall spread over all Canaan, over
                    the mountain of Esau and the south of Judah as well as over Gilead and the
                    Philistine and Phoenician coast. The victorious Israelites shall come up on
                    Mount Zion to rule the mountain of Esau, and the kingdom shall be Jehovah’s
                    (vers. 15-21).</p>
                <p>In vers. 10-14 the expositor finds sure foothold. The calamity of Jerusalem can
                    only be the sack of the city by Nebuchadnezzar; the malevolence and cruelty of
                    Edom on this occasion are characterized in similar terms by several writers of
                    the exile, but by none with the same circumstance and vividness of detail as
                    here (Ezek. xxv. 8, 12 <hi rend="italic">sq.,</hi> XXXV.; Lam. iv. 21; Psalm
                    cxxxvii <hi rend="subscript"> t</hi>). It is impossible to doubt that these
                    verses were written under the lively and recent impression of the events to
                    which they refer; to regard them as predictive (Caspari, Pusey, &amp;c.) is to
                    misunderstand the whole character of prophetic foresight, and to ascribe them
                    with Hitzig to the Persian or Greek period is equally unreasonable. The opening
                    verses of the prophecy, on the other hand, present a real difficulty. Obad. 1-6,
                    8 agree so closely and in part verbally with Jer. xlix. 14-16, 9, 10, 7 that the
                    two passages cannot be independent; nor does it seem possible that Obadiah
                    quotes from Jeremiah, for Obad. 1-8 is a well-connected whole, while the
                    parallel verses in Jeremiah appear in different order, interspersed with other
                    matter, <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n760/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0760-0703"/> and in a much less lucid connexion. In Jeremiah
                    the picture is vague, and Edom’s unwisdom (ver. 7) stands without proof. In
                    Obadiah the conception is quite definite. Edom is attacked by his own allies,
                    and his folly appears in that he exposes himself to such treachery. Again, the
                    probability that the passage in Jeremiah incorporates disjointed fragments of an
                    older oracle is greatly increased by the fact that the prophecy against Moab in
                    the preceding chapter uses, in the same way, Isa. xv., xvi., and the prophecy of
                    Balaam. In spite of the objections of Blau (Z. <hi rend="italic">D. Jtf.
                    G.,</hi> xx. 173 <hi rend="italic">sq.)</hi> there is no good reason to doubt
                    that the prophecy against Edom ascribed to Jeremiah is really from his pen; it
                    is earlier than the fall of Jerusalem,<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Inver. 12 “have assuredly drunken” should be “shall
                    assuredly drink.”</p></note> and is one of a circle of prophecies in which
                    Nebuchadnezzar (the lion ascending from Jordan, ver. 19) appears as the
                    instrument of divine judgment on the nations. This being so, it seems necessary
                    to conclude, with Ewald <hi rend="italic">{Propheten,</hi> i. 489 <hi
                    rend="italic">s(p),</hi> Graf <hi rend="italic">(Jeremia,</hi> p. 558 <hi
                    rend="italic">sq.∖</hi> and others, that Jeremiah and our book of Obadiah alike
                    quote from an older oracle. Ewald supposes that the treacherous allies of Edom
                    are the Aramaeans and the time that of Ahaz (2 Kings xvi. 6); but the tone of
                    the prophecy seems rather to refer it to a later date, when Edom had been for
                    some time independent and powerful; and it is not improbable that in Obad. 1-8
                    we have the first mention of that advance of the Arabs upon the lands east of
                    Palestine which is referred to also in Ezek. xxv. (comp. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Moab,</hi> vol. xvi. p. 535). That the book of Obadiah, short as it is, is a
                    complex document might have been suspected, apart from Jer. xlix., from an
                    apparent change of view between vers. 1-9 and vers. 15 <hi rend="italic"
                    >sq.</hi> In the former verses Esau is destroyed by his allies, and they occupy
                    his territory, but in the latter he perishes with the other heathen in the day
                    of universal retribution, he disappears before the victorious advance of Israel,
                    and the southern Judaeans occupy his land.</p>
                <p>The eschatology of Obadiah contains little that is peculiar. The conceptions of
                    the “rescued ones” (∏D'5δ), of the sanctity of Zion, of the kingship of Jehovah,
                    are the common property of the prophets from the time of Isaiah. The restoration
                    of the old borders of Israel and the conquest of Edom and the Philistines are
                    ideas as old as Amos ix., Isa. xi. 14; but the older prophets more often
                    represent this conquest as a suzerainty of Israel over its neighbours, as in the
                    days of David, while in Obadiah, as in other later books, the intensified
                    antithesis—religious as well as political —between Judah and the surrounding
                    heathen finds its expression in the idea of a consuming judgment on the
                    latter,—the great “day of Jehovah.” This view is not, however, original in
                    Obadiah; it is already expressed in Zephaniah. Between Joel and Obadiah there
                    are points of material and verbal agreement, sqjcTose as to imply that Joel used
                    the earlier book (Joel iii. 19,—Ob. 10, 14; Joeliii, 3, —Ob. 11; Joel ii. 32,
                    iii. 17,—Ob. 17). Another characteristic common to Obadiah with the latest
                    prophets is that, while he uses the words house of Jacob and house of Joseph,
                    the northern tribes have become to him a mere name; the restoration he thinks of
                    is a restoration of the kingdom of Jerusalem, and even Gilead is to be occupied
                    not by Joseph but by Benjamin.</p>
                <p>An indication of the place where Obadiah wrote seems to lie in ver. 20, where he
                    speaks of “the exiles in this S∏.” The word as pointed has been variously
                    explained to mean “bulwark” or “army”; it may also be read as “sand” or
                    “sea-coast” (Ewald), but, as the text of the verse is not sound and cannot be
                    translated without some correction, it is unsafe to build on this obscure
                    allusion. The prominence given to Edom, and the fact that Chaldaea is not
                    mentioned at all, make it probable that the book was not written in Babylonia.
                    The same verse speaks of exiles in Sepharad.</p>
                <p>Sepharad is probably Sardis, the Çparda of Darius in the Behistun inscription.
                    Many of the Jews were doubtless sold as slaves by Nebuchadnezzar. Lydia was a
                    great slave-market, and Asia Minor was a chief seat of the Diaspora at an early
                    date (comp. Gutschmidt, <hi rend="italic">Neue Beiträge,</hi> p. 77), so that
                    this identification does not supply ground for Hitzig’s argument that Obadiah
                    was written in the Greek period, when we read of many Jews being transplanted to
                    Asia Minor (Jos., <hi rend="italic">Ant.,</hi> xii. 3). Schrader, however <hi
                    rend="italic">{K. G. F.,</hi> 116 <hi rend="italic">sq.; K.A. T.,</hi> 446),
                    thinks of a Shaparda mentioned by Sargon,, and lying in south-west Media.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Literature.</hi> —The commentaries on the minor prophets (see
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Hosea)</hi>; Jäger <hi rend="italic">Ueber</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">das Zeitalter</hi><hi rend="italic">Obadia’s,</hi> Tübingen, 1837;
                    Caspari, <hi rend="italic">Der</hi><hi rend="italic">Pr. 0badia</hi> 1842 ·
                    Delitzsch in <hi rend="italic">Z. f Luth. Th.,</hi> 1851. A fuller list is given
                    by Reuss, <hi rend="italic">Gesch des A.T.</hi> (1881), p. 449. (W. R. S.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
