<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0916-0851-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ORLEANS, Charles, Duke of (9th edition, volume 17, page
                    851)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0399k">Towers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qn5z99h">Age</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hn48">Mothers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888134">Daughters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:800130">Age</term>
                    <term ref="fast:800293">Aging</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1138503">Summer</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n916/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ORLEANS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles, Duke of</hi></label>
                    (1391-1465), commonly called Charles d’Orléans, was the eldest son of Louis,
                    duke of Orleans (brother of Charles VI. of France), and of Valentina Visconti,
                    daughter of Galeaso of Milan. He was born on 26th May 1391. Although many minor
                    details are preserved of his youth, nothing except his reception in 1403, from
                    his uncle the king, of a pension of 12,000 livres d’or is worth noticing, until
                    his marriage three years later (29th June 1406) with Isabella, his cousin, widow
                    of Richard II. of England. The bride was two years older than her husband, and
                    is thought to have married him unwillingly, but she brought him a great
                    dowry,—it is said, 500,000 francs. She died three years later, leaving Charles a
                    widower and father of a daughter at the age of eighteen. He was already duke of
                    Orleans, for Louis had been assassinated by the Burgundians two years before
                    (1407). He soon saw himself the most important person in France, except the
                    dukes of Burgundy and Brittany, the king being a cipher. This position his
                    natural temperament by no means qualified him to fill. His mother was eager for
                    vengeance for her husband, and for years Charles did his best to carry out her
                    wishes by filling France with intestine war. Of this, however, he was only
                    nominally one of the leaders, the real guidance of his party resting with the
                    great count of Armagnac, whose daughter, Bonne, he married, or at least formally
                    espoused, in 1410. Five years of confused nego tiations, plots, and fightings
                    passed before the English invasion and the battle of Agincourt, where Charles
                    was joint commander-in-chief. According to one account he was dangerously
                    wounded and narrowly escaped with his life. He was certainly taken prisoner and
                    carried to England, which country was his residence thenceforward for a full
                    quarter of a century. Windsor, Pontefract, Ampthill, Wingfield (Suffolk), and
                    the Tower are named among other places as the scenes of his captivity, which,
                    however, was anything but a rigorous one. He was maintained in the state due not
                    merely to one of the greatest nobles of France but to one who ranked high in the
                    order of succession to the crown. He hunted and hawked and enjoyed society
                    amply, though the very dignities which secured him these privileges made his
                    ransom high, and his release difficult to arrange Above all, he had leisure to
                    devote himself to literary work. But for this he would hardly be remembered as
                    anything better than a more than usually amiable and less than usually able
                    example of the higher feudal nobility, whose political position rather than
                    their personal faults made government difficult or impossible in the later
                    Middle Ages.</p>
                <p>The work which secures a measure of immortality to Charles d’Orléans consists
                    wholly of short poems in the peculiar artificial metres which had become
                    fashionable in France about half a century or more before his birth, and which
                    continued to be fashionable till nearly a century after his death. Besides these
                    a certain number of English poems have been attributed to him. It is certain
                    that he studied the language of his captors, but it is more than doubtful
                    whether the extant English poems which bear his name are genuine, and in any
                    case they are of no value. The ingenuity of a single English critic has striven
                    to attribute to him a curious book in prose, called <hi rend="italic">Le Débat
                    des Hérauts de France et d’Angleterre,</hi> but Μ. Paul Meyer, in his edition of
                    the book in question, has completely disposed of this theory. For all practical
                    purposes, therefore, Charles’s work consists of some hundreds of short poems, a
                    few in various metres, but the majority either ballades or rondels. The
                    chronology of these poems is not always clear, still less the identity of the
                    persons to whom they are addressed, and it is certain that some, perhaps the
                    greater part of them, belong to the later years of the poet’s life. But many are
                    expressly stated in the manuscripts to have been “composed in prison,” others
                    are obviously so composed, and, on the whole, there is in them a remarkable
                    unity of literary flavour. Charles d’Orléans is not distinguished by any
                    extraordinary strength of passion or originality of character; but he is only
                    the more valuable as the last and not the least accomplished representative of
                    the poetry of the middle of the Middle Ages, in which the form was almost
                    everything, and the personality of the poet, save in rare instances, nothing.
                    Yet Charles d’Orléans is not entirely without <hi rend="italic"
                    >differentia.</hi> If he were he would hardly hold the place which at present he
                    justly occupies. He is a capital example of the cultivated and refined—it may
                    almost be called the lettered—chivalry of the last chivalrous age, expert to the
                    utmost degree in carrying out the traditional details of a graceful convention
                    in love and literature. But he is more than this; in a certain easy grace and
                    truth of expression, as well as in a peculiar mixture of melancholy, which is
                    not incompatible with the enjoyment of the pleasures, even the trifling
                    pleasures, of life, with listlessness that is fully able to occupy itself about
                    those trifles, he stands quite alone. He has the urbanity of the 18th century
                    without its vicious and prosaic frivolity, the poetry of the Middle Ages without
                    their tendency to tediousness. His best-known rondels—those on Spring, on the
                    Harbingers of Summer, and others—rank second to nothing of their kind.</p>
                <p>Poetry, however, could hardly be an entire consolation, and it is not surprising
                    to find that Charles, during all the long years of his captivity, was
                    perpetually scheming for liberty. But the English Government had too many
                    reasons for keeping him, and it was not till his hereditary foe Philip the Good
                    of Burgundy interested himself in him that the Government of Henry VI,, which
                    had by that time lost most of its hold on France, released him in return for an
                    immediate payment of 80,000 <hi rend="italic">saluts dor,</hi> and an engagement
                    on his part to pay 140,000 crowns at a future time. The agreement was concluded
                    on 2d July 1440. He was actually released on 3d November following, and almost
                    immediately cemented his friendship with Duke Philip by marrying his niece, Mary
                    of Cleves, who brought him a considerable dowry to assist the payment of his
                    ransom. He had, however, some difficulty in making up the balance, as well as
                    the large sum required for his brother, Jean d’Angoulême, who also was an
                    English prisoner. The last twenty-five years of his life (for, curiously enough,
                    it divides itself into three almost exactly equal periods, each of that length)
                    were spent partly in negotiating, with a little fighting intermixed, for the
                    purpose of gaining the Italian county of Asti, on which he had claims through
                    his mother, partly in travelling about, but chiefly at his principal seat of
                    Blois. Here he kept a miniature court which, from the literary point of view at
                    <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n917/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0917-0852"/> least, was not devoid of brilliancy. At this most
                    of the best-known French men-of-letters at the time—Villon, Olivier de la
                    Marche, Chastelain, Meschinot, and others —were residents or visitors or
                    correspondents. His son, afterwards Louis XII., was not born till 1462, three
                    years before Charles’s own death. He had become, notwithstanding his high
                    position, something of a nullity in politics, and tradition ascribes his death
                    to vexation at the harshness with which Louis XI. rejected his attempt to
                    mediate on behalf of the duke of Brittany. At any rate he died, on 4th January
                    1465, at Amboise. Many of his later poems are small occasional pieces addressed
                    to his courtiers and companions, and in not a few cases answers to them by those
                    to whom they were addressed exist. The best edition of Charles d’Orléans’s
                    poems, with a brief but sufficient account of his life, is that of C.
                    d’Héricault in the <hi rend="italic">Nouvelle</hi><hi rend="italic">Collection
                    J</hi><hi rend="italic">annet</hi>, Paris, 1874. <hi rend="smallcaps">(g.
                    sa.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
