<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0910-0809-0786-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GÖRRES, Joseph Joπann (9th edition, volume 10, page
                    786)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1132936">Steins</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1095066">Republicanism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1144248">Teachers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:864940">Clubs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:966832">Idealism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:817721">Arts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795c7h">Republicanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2th4x">Resultants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sf2md37">Missions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w37kz4v">Teachers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w922">Writers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40z70z6b">Clubs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4639k505">Idealism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n809/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GÖRRES, <hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph Joπann</hi></label>
                    (1776-1848), a distinguished controversialist and writer on religious,
                    political, and scientific subjects, was born January 25, 1776, at Coblentz. His
                    father was a man of moderate means, who sent his son, after he had passed
                    through the usual elementary school, to a Latin college under the direction of
                    the Roman Catholic clergy. The sympathies of the young Görres were from the
                    first strongly with the Revolution, and the dissoluteness and irreligion of the
                    French exiles in the Rhineland confirmed him in his hatred of princes. He
                    harangued the revolutionary clubs, and in his first political tract, called <hi
                    rend="italic">Universal Peace, an Ideal,</hi> he insisted on the unity of
                    interests which should ally all civilized states to one another. He then
                    commenced a republican journal called <hi rend="italic">Das Rothe Blatt,</hi>
                    and afterwards <hi rend="italic">Rübezahl,</hi> in which he strongly condemned
                    the administration of the Rhenish provinces by France.</p>
                <p>After the peace of Campo Formio (1797) there was some hope that the Rhenish
                    provinces would be constituted into an independent republic. In 1799 the
                    provinces sent an embassy, of which Görres was a member, to Paris to put their
                    case before the directory. The embassy reached Paris on the 20th of November
                    1799; two days before this Napoleon had assumed the supreme direction of
                    affairs. After much delay the embassy was received by him; but the only answer
                    they obtained was “that they might rely on perfect justice, and that the French
                    Government would never lose sight of their wants.” Görres on his return
                    published a tract called <hi rend="italic">Results of my Mission to Paris,</hi>
                    in which he reviewed the history of the French Revolution. During the thirteen
                    years of Napoleon’s dominion Görres lived a retired life, devoting himself
                    chiefly to art or science. In 1801 he married Catherine de Lassaulx, and those
                    of Görres’s admirers who claim him as a radical have laid great stress on the
                    fact that this lady was a free-thinker. He published <hi rend="italic"
                    >Aphorisms</hi> on art and physiology—fanciful but suggestive. He was for some
                    years teacher at a secondary school in Coblentz, and in 1806 moved to
                    Heidelberg, where he lectured at the university. He sought, with Brentano,
                    Arnim, and others, to stir up the old national spirit by the republication of
                    some of the old Teutonic ballads, but fruitlessly. He returned to Coblentz in
                    1808, and again found occupation as a teacher in a secondary school, supported
                    by civic funds. He now studied Persian, and in two years produced a really
                    valuable translation of part of the <hi rend="italic">Shahnarnah,</hi> the epic
                    of Firdousi.</p>
                <p>It was in the year 1810 that beseems to have conceived the notion of arousing the
                    people to efforts by means of the press; and after the battle of Leipsic, in the
                    year 1814, he set his paper going. It bore the name of a paper which had been a
                    mere echo of Prussia, the <hi rend="italic">Rheinischer Merkur.</hi> The intense
                    earnestness of the paper, the bold outspokenness of its hostility to Napoleon,
                    and its fiery eloquence secured for it almost instantly a position and influence
                    unique in the history of German newspapers. Blücher read it every day; Gentz,
                    the brothers Grimm, Varnhagen von Ense, were all loud in praise of it; Stein
                    used it as an instrument to move the public in the direction he desired, and
                    continually sent it information of his plans; Napoleon himself called it <hi
                    rend="italic">la cinquième</hi><hi rend="italic">puissance.</hi> The ideal it
                    insisted on was a united Germany, with a representative government, but under an
                    emperor after the fashion of other days,—for Görres now abandoned his early
                    advocacy of republicanism. When Napoleon was at Elba, Görres wrote an imaginary
                    proclamation issued by him to the people, the intense irony of which was so well
                    vei <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> ed that many Frenchmen mistook it for an
                    original utterance of the emperor. He inveighed bitterly against the second
                    peace of Paris (1815), declaring that Alsace and Lorraine should have been
                    demanded back from France.</p>
                <p>Stein was glad enough to use the <hi rend="italic">Merkur</hi> at the time of the
                    meeting of the congress of Vienna as a vehicle for giving expression to his
                    hopes. But Hardenberg, in May 1815, warned Görres to remember that he was not to
                    arouse hostility against France, but only against Bonaparte. There was also in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Merkur</hi> an antipathy to Prussia, a continual
                    expression of the desire that an Austrian prince should assume the imperial
                    title, and also a tendency to pronounced liberalism,—all of which made it most
                    distasteful to Hardenberg, and to his master King Frederick William III. Görres
                    disregarded warnings sent to him by the censorship and continued the paper in
                    all its fierceness. Accordingly it was suppressed early in 1816, at the instance
                    of the Prussian Government; and soon after Görres was dismissed from his post as
                    teacher at Coblentz. From this time his writings were his sole means of support,
                    and he became a most diligent political pamphleteer. He was not himself a member
                    of the <hi rend="italic">Tugendbund,</hi> but he watched that society with deep
                    interest, and believed, as did all the patriots of his time, that the clubs of
                    students, or <hi rend="italic">Burschenschaften,</hi> were calculated to restore
                    the pristine greatness of Germany. The agitation continued, and finally
                    Kotzebue’s denunciation of young Germany led to his assassination. In the wild
                    excitement which followed, the reactionary decrees of Carlsbad were framed, and
                    these were the subject of Görres’s celebrated pamphlet <hi rend="italic"
                    >Deutschland und</hi><hi rend="italic">die Revolution.</hi> In this work he
                    reviewed the circumstances which had led to the murder of Kotzebue, and, while
                    expressing all possible horror at the deed itself, he urged that it was
                    impossible and undesirable to repress the free utterance of public opinion by
                    reactionary measures. The success of the work was very marked, despite its
                    ponderous style. It was suppressed by the Prussian Government, and orders were
                    issued for the arrest of Görres and the seizure of his papers. He escaped to
                    Strasburg, and thence went to Switzerland. Two more political tracts, <hi
                    rend="italic">Europa</hi><hi rend="italic">und</hi><hi rend="italic">die
                    Revolution</hi> (1821), and <hi rend="italic">In</hi><hi rend="italic">Sachen
                    der</hi><hi rend="italic">Rhein</hi><hi rend="italic">Provinzen und</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">in</hi><hi rend="italic">eigener Angelegenheit</hi> (1822), also
                    deserve mention.</p>
                <p>In Görres’s pamphlet <hi rend="italic">Die Heilige Allianz und die Volker auf
                    dem</hi><hi rend="italic">Congress</hi><hi rend="italic">von Verona</hi> he
                    asserted that the princes had met together to crush the liberties of the people,
                    and that the people must look elsewhere for help. The “elsewhere” was to Rome;
                    and from this time Görres became a vehement Ultramontane writer. He was summoned
                    to Munich by King Louis of Bavaria, and there his writings <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n810/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0910-0810-0787"/> enjoyed very great popularity. His <hi
                    rend="italic">Christliche Mystik</hi> gave a series of biographies of the
                    saints, together with an exposition of Roman Catholic mysticism. But his most
                    celebrated Ultramontane work was a polemical one. Its occasion was the
                    deposition and imprisonment by the Prussian Government of the archbishop Clement
                    Wenceslaus, in consequence of the refusal of that prelate to sanction in certain
                    instances the marriages of Protestants and Roman Catholics. Görres in his <hi
                    rend="italic">Athanasius</hi> fiercely upheld the power of the church, although
                    the liberals of later date who have claimed Görres as one of their own school
                    deny that he ever insisted on the absolute supremacy of Rome. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Athanasius</hi> went through several editions, and originated a long and bitter
                    controversy. In the <hi rend="italic">Historisch-politische Blätter,</hi> a
                    Munich journal, Görres and his son Guido continually upheld the claims of the
                    church. Görres received from the king the order of merit for his services. He
                    was terribly disturbed when the king sunk under the dominion of Lola Montez, and
                    he died July 29, 1848.</p>
                <p>See A. Denk, <hi rend="italic">Joseph von G&lt;ims,</hi> 1870; J. J. Sepp, <hi
                    rend="italic">Görres und</hi><hi rend="italic">seine</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Zeitgenossen,</hi> 1877. A complete edition of Görres's works was published at
                    Munich in 1854. (L. A. Μ.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
