<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0910-0605-0588-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GIDEON (9th edition, volume 10, page 588)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204236">Israel</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205669">Jordan</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jq0sv10">Altars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mc8rm1n">Plains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:806095">Altars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1065075">Plains</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198492">Faith</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n605/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GIDEON</label>, liberator, reformer, and “judge” of Israel,
                    was the youngest son of Joash, of the “house” of Abiezer, and tribe of Manasseh,
                    and had his home at Ophrah, the site of which is probably to be sought westward
                    of Jordan, somewhat to the south of the plain of Jezreel. Gideon lived at a time
                    when Israel, grown idolatrous, had been brought very low by periodic incursions
                    of the “Midianites” and “Amalekites,” nomad tribes from the east of Jordan, who
                    in great numbers were wont to overrun the country, destroying all that they
                    could not carry away. In the beginning of the narrative of his public life he is
                    represented as an unambitious man, quietly engaged in agricultural pursuits, who
                    yet had already distinguished himself as a “mighty man of valour,” probably in
                    guerilla warfare against the common foe. According to that narrative, his first
                    exploit worthy of special commemoration was the destruction, by divine command,
                    of the altar of Baal belonging to his father, and of the Ashera beside it, and
                    the substitution of an altar to Jehovah. But immediately before this he had also
                    been summoned by “the angel of the Lord” to undertake, in dependence on
                    supernatural direction and help, the work of liberating his country from its
                    long oppression, and, in token that he accepted the mission, had already erected
                    in Ophrah an altar which he called “Jahveh-Shalom” (Jehovah is prosperity). The
                    great gathering of the Midianites and their allies on the north side of the
                    plain of Jezreel “stretching from the hill of Moreh”; the general muster first
                    of Abiezer, then of all Manasseh, and lastly of the neighbouring tribes of
                    Asher, Zebulun, and Naphtali; the signs by which the wavering faith of Gideon
                    was steadied; the methods by which an unwieldy mob was reduced to a small but
                    trusty band of energetic and determined men; and the stratagem by which the vast
                    army of Midian was surprised and routed by the handful of Israelites descending
                    from “above Endor,” are indicated with sufficient clearness in the Scripture
                    narrative, and need not be detailed minutely here. There is some difficulty in
                    following the account of the subsequent flight of the Midianites, which seems to
                    have taken place in two directions,—Oreb and Zeeb making for the lower fords of
                    Jordan towards the south-east, while Zebah and Zalmunna took the upper passage,
                    a little below the place where the river flows out of the Sea of Galilee.
                    Leaving the Ephraimites (who had now risen in force) to deal with the former,
                    Gideon with his 300 appears to have kept up the pursuit of the latter to Nobah
                    and Jogbehah, points beyond Succoth and Penuel, where a bloody contest resulted
                    in the destruction of that portion of the Midianite army, and in the ultimate
                    capture and execution of Zebah and <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n606/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0910-0606-0589"/> Zalmunna. Almost simultaneously with these
                    occurrences eastward of Jordan, messengers from Ephraim bearing the heads of
                    Oreb (“raven”) and Zeeb (“wolf”), who with their followers had been crushed at
                    “theraven’s rock” and “the wolf’s den” respectively, announced the completeness
                    of Israel’s victory. Having taken unrelenting vengeance on the men of Penuel and
                    Succoth, who had shown a timid neutrality when the patriotic struggle was at its
                    crisis, Gideon returned to his native Ophrah, where he further distinguished
                    himself by his pious magnanimity in refusing the kingship which had been put
                    within his reach—an act of self-denial, however, which, according to the sacred
                    historian, was somewhat neutralized by his subsequent folly in establishing a
                    shrine which proved a snare to all Israel, not excluding his family or even
                    himself. For forty years after the great victory he lived at his own house in
                    Ophrah in considerable wealth and magnificence, yet always in a private
                    station—there being no direct scriptural evidence at least that his judgeship
                    lasted during all that period, or that it ever gave him any position of legally
                    recognized authority. The name of Gideon occurs in Heb. xi. 32, in the list
                    there given of those who became heroes by faith; but, except in Judges
                    vi.-viii,, it is not to be met with anywhere in the Old Testament. In 1 Sam.
                    xii. 11 and 2 Sam. xi. 21 (LXX.) he is called Jerubbaal (the reading
                    Jerubbesheth having been introduced into the latter passage in accordance with
                    the usage explained in the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Baal).</hi> The fact
                    that in Judges ix., which appears to be the oldest part of the narrative, he is
                    invariably called Jerubbaal, has suggested to Kuenen and others that this ought
                    to be regarded as his original and proper name, that of Gideon (l⅛∏2, <hi
                    rend="italic">i.e.</hi> “hewer” or “warrior,” <hi rend="italic">cf</hi> Isa. x,
                    33) having been a later designation. In confirmation of this it is pointed out
                    that the derivation of Sy31' as equivalent to ∕ ’ y3∏ 13 3Ύ (“Let Baal contend
                    against him,” v. 32, or “Let Baal contend for himself,” v. 31) is much less
                    probable than that which interprets it as precisely analogous with such names as
                    Merib-baal, Jehoiarib or Joarib, Seraiah, Israel, and perhaps also Josadec, all
                    meaning “God fights” or “contends.” The nature of the grounds on which it is
                    conjectured that Gideon’s conquest of the Midianites was somewhat slower than
                    the narrative on a first reading would lead one to suppose, and that his
                    religious reforms, far from being confined to a solitary act of his early
                    manhood, were rather the principal employment of his later life, is indicated in
                    the histories of Israel by Ewald, Hitzig, and Kuenen. See also especially
                    Wellhausen, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte,</hi> i. 252 <hi rend="italic"
                    >sq.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
