<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0910-0170-0159-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GENTIAN (9th edition, volume 10, page 159)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3m81r">Swiss</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17ss11">Trees</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40k074">Shrubs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6pc2x">Planting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w37kw6x">Flowers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s24m">Acids</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239717">Alps</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204537">Sweden</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:927866">Flowers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:940284">Gentians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028366">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1140558">Swiss</term>
                    <term ref="fast:967439">Illyrians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:940281">Gentianella</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n170/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GENTIAN</label>, botanically <hi rend="italic">Gentiana,</hi>
                    a large and typical genus of herbaceous plants forming the type of the natural
                    order <hi rend="italic">Gentianaceoe.</hi> The genus comprises about 180
                    species, —most of them perennial plants growing in hilly or mountainous
                    districts, chiefly in the northern hemisphere, some of the blue-flowered species
                    ascending to a height of 16,000 feet in the Himalaya mountains. The leaves are
                    opposite, entire, and smooth, and often strongly ribbed. The flowers are
                    furnished with a persistent calyx and corolla, which is usually 4- or 5-parted,
                    but occasionally 10-parted; the stamens are equal in number to the lobes of the
                    corolla. The ovary is one-celled, with two stigmas, either separate and rolled
                    back or contiguous and funnel-shaped. The fruit when ripe separates into two
                    valves, and contains numerous small seeds. The majority of the genus are
                    remarkable for the deep or brilliant blue colour of their blossoms,
                    comparatively few having yellow, white, or more rarely red flowers; the last are
                    almost exclusively found in the Andes.</p>
                <p>Only a few species occur in Britain. <hi rend="italic">G. Anιαrellα</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">G.</hi><hi rend="italic">campestris</hi> are small annual species
                    growing on chalky or calcareous hills, and bear, in autumn, somewhat tubular
                    pale purple flowers; the latter is most easily distinguished by having two of
                    the lobes of the calyx larger than the other two, while the former has the parts
                    of the calyx in fives, and equal in size. Some intermediate forms between these
                    two species occur, although rarely, in England; one of these, <hi rend="italic"
                    >G.</hi><hi rend="italic">germanica,</hi> Willd., has larger flowers of a more
                    blue tint, spreading branches, and a stouter stem. Some of these forms flower in
                    spring. <hi rend="italic">G. Bneumοnanthe,</hi> the Calathian violet, is a
                    rather rare perennial species, growing in moist heathy places from Cumberland to
                    Dorsetshire. Its average height is from 6 to 9 inches. It has linear leaves, and
                    a bright blue corolla 1⅜ inches long, marked externally with five greenish
                    bands, is without hairs in its throat, and is found in perfection about the end
                    of August. It is the handsomest of the British species; two varieties of it are
                    known in cultivation, one with spotted and the other with white flowers. <hi
                    rend="italic">G. verna</hi> and <hi rend="italic">G. nivalis</hi> are small
                    species with brilliant blue flowers and small leaves. The former is a rare and
                    local perennial, occurring, however, in Teesdale and the county of Clare in
                    Ireland in tolerable abundance. It has a tufted habit of growth, and each stem
                    bears only one flower. It is sometimes cultivated as an edging for flower
                    borders. <hi rend="italic">G. nivalis</hi> in Britain occurs only on a few of
                    the loftiest Scotch mountains. It differs from the last in being an annual, and
                    having a more isolated habit of growth, and in the stem bearing several flowers.
                    On the Swiss mountains these beautiful little plants are very abundant; and the
                    splendid blue colour of masses of gentian in flower is a sight which, when once
                    seen, can never be forgotten. For ornamental purposes several species are
                    cultivated. The great difficulty of growing them successfully renders them,
                    however, less common than would otherwise be the case; although very hardy when
                    once established, they are very impatient of removal, and rarely flower well
                    until. the third year after planting. Of the ornamental species found in British
                    gardens some of the prettiest are <hi rend="italic">G. acaulis,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">G. verna,</hi><hi rend="italic">G.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >pyrenaica,</hi><hi rend="italic">G.</hi><hi rend="italic">bavarica,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">G.</hi><hi rend="italic">scρtemfida,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">G.
                    gelida.</hi> Perhaps the handsomest and most easily grown is the first named,
                    often called <hi rend="italic">Gentianella,</hi> which produces its large
                    intensely blue flowers early in the spring.</p>
                <p>All the species of the genus are remarkable for possessing an intense but pure
                    bitter taste and tonic properties. About forty species are used in medicine in
                    different parts <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n171/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0910-0171-0160"/> of the world. The name of felwort given to <hi
                    rend="italic">G. Amarella,</hi> but occasionally applied to the whole genus, is
                    stated by Dr Prior to be given in allusion to these properties— <hi
                    rend="italic">fel</hi> meaning gall, and <hi rend="italic">τvort</hi> a plant.
                    In the same way the Chinese call the <hi rend="italic">G. asclepiadea,</hi> and
                    the Japanese the <hi rend="italic">G. Bucτgcri,</hi> “dragon’s gall plants,” in
                    common with several other very bitter plants whose roots they use in medicine.
                    <hi rend="italic">G. campestris</hi> is sometimes in Sweden and other northern
                    countries a substitue for hops.</p>
                <p>By far the most important of the species used in medicine is the <hi
                    rend="italic">G. lutea,</hi> a large handsome plant 3 or 4 feet high, growing in
                    open grassy places on the Alps, Apennines, and Pyrenees, as well as on some of
                    the mountainous ranges of France and Germany, extending as far east as Bosnia
                    and thβ Danubian principalities. It has large oval strongly-ribbed leaves and
                    dense whorls of conspicuous yellow flowers. Its use in medicine is of very
                    ancient date. Pliny and Dioscorides mention that the plant was noticed by
                    Gentius, a king of the Illyrians, living 180-167 B.c., from whom the name <hi
                    rend="italic">Gentiana</hi> is supposed to be derived. During the Middle Ages it
                    was much employed in the cure of disease, and as an ingredient in
                    counter-poisons. In 1552 Tragus mentions the use of the root as a means of
                    dilating wounds.</p>
                <p>The root, which is the part used in medicine, is tough and flexible, scarcely
                    branched, and of a brownish colour and spongy texture. It has a pure bitter
                    taste and faint distinctive odour. On account of its porous nature it has been
                    used in modern surgery, as in the time of Tragus, as a substitute for sponge
                    tents. The root has been several times analysed with varying results, but
                    Kromayer in 1862 first obtained the bitter principle in a state of purity. This
                    substance, to which the bitterness of the root is due, he called <hi
                    rend="italic">gentiopicrin</hi> (C <hi rend="subscript"> 20</hi> H <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 30</hi> O <hi rend="subscript"> 12</hi>). It is a neutral
                    glucoside, crystallizing in colourless needles, and is contained in the fresh
                    root in the proportion of about <hi rend="subscript"> τ</hi> ⅛th per cent., but
                    has not been obtained in a crystalline state from the dried root. It is soluble
                    in water and spirit of wine, but it does not dissolve in ether. It is easily
                    decomposed, dilute mineral acids splitting it up into <hi rend="italic"
                    >glucose</hi> and <hi rend="italic">gentiοgenin,</hi> the latter being an
                    amorphous yellowish-brown neutral substance. It is not precipitated by tannin or
                    subacetate of lead. A solution of caustic potash or soda forms with gentiopicrin
                    a yellow solution, and the tincture of the root to which either of theβe
                    alkalies ha3 been added loses its bitterness in a few days. Gentian root also
                    contains <hi rend="italic">gentianic acid</hi> (C <hi rend="subscript"> 14</hi>
                    H <hi rend="subscript"> 10</hi> O <hi rend="subscript"> 5</hi>), which is inert
                    and tasteless. It forms pale yellow silky crystals, very slightly soluble in
                    water or ether, but soluble in hot strong alcohol and in aqueous alkaline
                    solutions. This substance, which is also called <hi rend="italic">gentianin,
                    gentisin,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">gentisic acid,</hi> has been shown by Ville
                    to partake of the nature of tannin, giving the reactions of that substance with
                    ferric chloride, gelatin, and albumen. On this account he proposes to change the
                    name to <hi rend="italic">gentiano-tannic acid.</hi></p>
                <p>The root also contains 12 to 15 per cent, of an uncrystallizable sugar, of which
                    fact advantage has long been taken in Switzerland and Bavaria, for the
                    production of a bitter cordial spirit called <hi rend="italic"
                    >Enzianbranntwein.</hi> The use of this spirit, especially in Switzerland, has
                    sometimes been followed by poisonous symptoms, which have been doubtfully
                    attributed to inherent narcotic properties possessed by some species of gentian,
                    the roots of which may have been indiscriminately collected with it; but it is
                    quite possible that it may be due to the contamination of the root with that of
                    <hi rend="italic">Veratrιιrn album,</hi> a poisonous plant growing at the same
                    altitude, and having leaves extremely similar in appearance and size to those of
                    <hi rend="italic">G. lutea.</hi> Gentian is considered by therapeutists to be
                    one of the most efficient of the simple bitter tonics, that is, of that class of
                    substances which act upon the stomach so as to invigorate digestion and thereby
                    increase the general nutrition, without exerting any direct influence upon any
                    other portion of the body than the alimentary canal. It is used in dyspepsia,
                    chlorosis, anaemia, and various other diseases, in which the tone of the stomach
                    and alimentary canal is deficient, and is sometimes added to purgative medicines
                    to increase and improve their action. In veterinary medicine it is also used as
                    a tonic, and enters into a well-known compound called <hi rend="italic"
                    >diapente</hi> as a chief ingredient.</p>
                <p>See Sowerby, <hi rend="italic">English Botany,</hi> 3d edit., vol. vi. p. 74-81;
                    Hemsley, <hi rend="italic">Handbook of Hardy Trees, Shrubs, and Herbaceous
                    Plants,</hi> p. 303; <hi rend="italic">Journal of Botany,</hi> 1864, p. 65;
                    1872, p. 166; 1878, p. 265; <hi rend="italic">Pharmacographia,</hi> p. 389; <hi
                    rend="italic">Pharmaccιιtical Journal</hi> (1), vol. xii. p. 371; (3) vol. iii.
                    p. 42; (3) vol. vi. p. 90; (3) vol. viii. p. 182; Wood and Bache, <hi
                    rend="italic">United States Dispensatory,</hi> 14th edit., p. 438; Porter Smith,
                    <hi rend="italic">Chinese Materia</hi><hi rend="italic">Medica,</hi> p. 102. (E.
                    Μ. H.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
