<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0910-0025-0016-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GAIUS (9th edition, volume 10, page 16)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1163799">Valentinians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795379">Accounting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2t79r">Digestion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n25/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GAIUS</label>, a celebrated Roman jurist. Of his personal
                    history very little is known. It is impossible to discover even his full name,
                    Gaius or Caius being merely a personal name (praenomen) very common in Rome.
                    From internal evidence in his works it may be gathered that he flourished in the
                    reigns of the emperors Hadrian, Antoninus Pius, Marcus Aurelius, and Commodus.
                    Hie works were thus composed between the years 130 and 180, at the time when the
                    Roman empire was most prosperous, and its government the best. Most probably
                    Gaius lived in some provincial town, and hence we find no contemporary notices
                    of hie life or works. After hie death, however, his writings τere recognized as
                    of great authority, and the emperor Valentinian named him, along with Papinian,
                    Ulpian, Modestin, and Paulus, as one of the five jurists whose opinions were to
                    be followed by judicial officers in deciding cases. The works of these jurists
                    accordingly became most important sources of Roman law.</p>
                <p>Besides the <hi rend="italic">Institutes,</hi> which are a complete exposition of
                    the elements of Roman law, Gaius was the author of a treatise on the <hi
                    rend="italic">Edicts of the Magistrates,</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Commentaries
                    on the Twelve Tables,</hi> and on the important <hi rend="italic">Lex
                    Papiα</hi><hi rend="italic">Poppoea,</hi> and several other works. His interest
                    in the antiquities of Roman law is apparent, and for this reason his work is
                    most valuable to the historian of early institutions. In the disputes between
                    the two schools of Roman jurists he generally attached himself to that of the
                    Sabinians, who were said to be followers of Ateius Capito, of whose life we have
                    some account in the <hi rend="italic">Annals</hi> of Tacitus, and to advocate a
                    strict adherence as far as possible to ancient rules, and to resist innovation.
                    Many quotations from the works of Gaius occur in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Digest</hi> of Justinian, and so acquired a permanent place in the system of
                    Roman law; while a comparison of the <hi rend="italic">Institutes</hi> of
                    Justinian with those of Gaius shows that the whole method and arrangement of the
                    later work were copied from that of the earlier, and very numerous passages are
                    word for word the same. Probably, for the greater part of the period of three
                    centuries which elapsed between Gaius and Justinian, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Institutes</hi> of the former had been the familiar text-book of all students
                    of Roman law.</p>
                <p>Unfortunately the work was lost to modern scholars, until, in 1816, a manuscript
                    was discovered by Niebuhr at Verona, in which certain of the works of St Jerome
                    were written over some earlier writings, which proved to be the lost work of
                    Gaius. The greater part of the palimpsest has, however, been deciphered by
                    various German scholars, and the text is now fairly complete.</p>
                <p>This discovery has thrown a flood of light on portions of the history of Roman
                    law which had previously been most obscure. Much of the historical information
                    given by Gaius is wanting in the compilations of Justinian, and, in particular,
                    the account of the ancient forms of procedure in actions. In these forms can be
                    traced “survivals” from the most primitive times, which provide the science of
                    comparative law with valuable illustrations, which may explain the strange forms
                    of legal procedure found in other early systems. Another circumstance which
                    renders the work of Gaius more interesting to the historical student than that
                    of Justinian, is that Gaius lived at a time when actions were tried by the
                    system of formulae, or formal directions given by the praetor before whom the
                    case first came, to the judex to whom he referred it. Without a knowledge of the
                    terms of these formulae it is impossible to solve the most interesting question
                    in the history of Roman law, and show how the rigid rules peculiar to the
                    ancient law of Rome were modified by what has been called the equitable
                    jurisdiction of the praetors, and made applicable to new conditions, and brought
                    into harmony with the notions and the needs of a more developed society. It is
                    clear from evidence of Gaius that this result was obtained, not by an
                    independent set of courts administering, as in England until recently, a system
                    different from that of the ordinary courts, but by the manipulation of the
                    formulae. In the time of Justinian the work was complete, and the formulary
                    system had disappeared.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Institutes</hi> of Gaius are divided into four books—the
                    first treating of persons and the differences of the status they may occupy in
                    the eye of the law; the second of things, and the modes in which rights over
                    them may be acquired, including the law relating to wills; the third of
                    intestate succession and of obligations; the fourth of actions and their
                    forms.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n26/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0910-0026-0017"/>
                <p>There are several carefully prepared editions of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Institutes</hi>; the first was that of Göschen, published in 1820. During the
                    next fifty years more than twenty new editions appeared. A list of these, and of
                    the various treatises on Gaius, is given in the preface to Booking’s edition.
                    The most complete English edition is that ®f Mr Poste, which includes beside the
                    text an English translation and copious commentary. A comparison of the early
                    forms of actions mentioned by Gaius with those used by other primitive societies
                    will be found in Sir H. Maine’s <hi rend="italic">Early Institutions,</hi> cap.
                    9. For further information see Μ. Glasson, <hi rend="italic">Étude sur</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Gaius</hi><hi rend="italic">et sur le jus</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >respondendi.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
