<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0910-0715-0692-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GLOVE (9th edition, volume 10, page 692)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k55x">Gloves</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p843w5c">Hand</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cv3f">Skins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45d8nd6f">Skin</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0341g">Customs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:943657">Gloves</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950823">Hand</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1075502">Preparedness</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1120047">Skin</term>
                    <term ref="fast:987598">Kindness</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210278">Belgium</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n715/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GLOVE</label> (Saxon <hi rend="italic">flof),</hi> a covering
                    for the hand, with a separate sheath for each finger. Among our ancestors, to
                    throw down the glove or gauntlet was equivalent to a challenge to single combat,
                    and the person thus defied signified his acceptance of the challenge by taking
                    up the glove, and casting down his own,—which ceremony was regarded as a mutual
                    compact to meet at the time and place specified. This custom, according to Favyn
                    <hi rend="italic">(Theatre ιVHonneur</hi><hi rend="italic">et de
                    Chevalerie),</hi> was derived from the Oriental mode of contracting sales of
                    land and the like by giving the purchaser a glove, by way of delivery or
                    investiture; and to this effect he quotes Ruth iv. 7 and Psa. cviii. 9, passages
                    where the word commonly translated “shoe” is by some rendered “glove.” Du Cange
                    quotes from a charter of the 13th century an instance of re-investiture or
                    restitution symbolized by the person depositing his glove on the earth. The use
                    of gloves is of high antiquity. There is reason to believe the ancient Persians
                    wore them, since it is mentioned in the <hi rend="italic">Cyropoedia</hi> of
                    Xenophon that on one occasion Cyrus went without his gloves; and we know that
                    some kind of protecting coverings for the hands were used by the Greeks and
                    Romans in certain kinds of manual labour, although their precise form is
                    unknown.</p>
                <p>The word <hi rend="italic">ganius,</hi> used for a glove in mediaeval Latin, is
                    obviously of Teutonic derivation. In the life of St Columbanus, written by
                    Jonas, abbot of Bobbio, in the 7th century, gloves for protecting the hands in
                    manual labour are spoken of as “tegumenta manuum quae Galli <hi rend="italic"
                    >wantos</hi> vocant.” A pair of gloves are mentioned in the will of Bishop
                    Riculfus, who died 915 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> Gloves did not become
                    articles of ecclesiastical vestment till the 12th century. They do not appear in
                    the Bayeux tapestry, and they did not come into general use in England till the
                    13th century. Matthew Paris, noticing the burial of Henry II. (1189), mentions
                    that he was buried in his coronation robes, with a golden crown on his head and
                    gloves on his hands. Gloves were also found on the hands of King John when his
                    tomb was opened in 1797, and on the hands of Edward I. when his tomb was opened
                    in 1774. In the 14th century they w ere in common use among the better classes.
                    In the 16th century they were frequently embroidered with great elaboration, and
                    in the reign of Charles II. the short sleeves of the ladies’ dresses brought in
                    long gloves reaching almost to the elbow. It is an old custom in England that a
                    pair of gloves are given by the sheriff to the judge who presides at a maiden
                    assize; and in Scotland white gloves are given to the judges on a maiden
                    circuit,—that is, when there are no cases for trial.</p>
                <p>The manufacture of gloves was early introduced into the British Islands, and such
                    was the dignity of the craft that, as early as the reign of King Robert III.,
                    the incorporation of glovers of Perth was chartered—a wealthy guild still
                    existing, although the calling has long ceased to characterize that town. The
                    glovers’ company of London received its armorial bearings as early as 1464, but
                    the body was not chartered till 1638; and in Worcester, which has long been the
                    principal British centre of the trade, a company was incorporated in 1661.</p>
                <p>The glove industry of the present day is both extensive and diversified, seeing
                    that gloves are now almost universally worn, and made of various classes of
                    material and in several different ways. Of yarn, thread, silk, and cloth gloves
                    it is unnecessary to speak, as these varieties are, in comparison with leather
                    gloves, of comparatively little importance. The leather employed by glovers is
                    prepared from the skins of deer, sheep and lambs, goats aud kids— the last being
                    by far the most important. The skins are prepared either by the ordinary
                    processes of shamoying for wash-leather and doe or buck leather gloves, or by a
                    special method of tawing in the case of ordinary dress gloves. The kid-skins are
                    principally collected by hawkers in the South European countries, aud sold in
                    the Leipsic and Naples fairs. The tawing industry is conducted on a great scale
                    at Annonay, Paris, and Milhau in France. The tawing process differs from
                    ordinary tanning in the greater care and cleanliness of all the operations, in
                    the submission of the dressed skins to a brief fermentation by piling them under
                    the influence of heat, which increases the softness and flexibility of the
                    leather, and in tawing with a∙ mixture of flour, the yellow of eggs, and alum.
                    On the completion of this operation, they are stretched by hand and dried as
                    rapidly as possible. Thereafter they are damped, placed in dozens between linen
                    cloths, and worked about to render them soft and pliable, after which they are
                    planed on the flesh side, dried, and again planed. They are then polished by
                    rubbing with a heavy glass disc or other smooth substance, and dyed by brushing
                    liquid dyes over one side. Finally they are stretched on a marble table, and
                    smoothed with a blunt knife. From a kid skin so prepared the materials of three
                    gloves are obtained. The skins are moistened and stretched, and the various
                    parts are cut out by a machine having steel punches the shape and size desired.
                    The thumb piece, the quirks and the fourchettes inserted between the fingers,
                    and the wrist welt—the latter frequently white—are cut out separately. Machine
                    sewing, in which a kind of button stitch is made, is to a small extent utilized
                    in the manufacture of gloves; but the greater part of the sewing is done by
                    hand. The pieces to be sewn together are placed in a machine between a pair of
                    jaws, the holding edge of which is composed of fine saw teeth, between each of
                    which the sewer passes back and forward her needle, and in this way a neat
                    uniform stitch is secured. There are three kinds of hand-sewing in the glove
                    trade— round sewing or ordinary glove stitch, piqué stitch, and prick seam.
                    After sewing, the backs are stitched or tamboured, the button-hole is formed,
                    the wrist attached, and the button sewed on, thus finishing the glove. After
                    damping and stretching to its utmost length, the glove is ready to be stamped
                    and put up for use.</p>
                <p>Paris is, beyond question, the most important centre of glove-making, and for
                    delicacy of material and beauty of workmanship the productions of some Parisian
                    manufacturers are without any rivals; but it is at Grenoble that French gloves
                    are most extensively manufactured. English gloves, of unfailing excellence of
                    material and workmanship, are principally made at Worcester; and in one
                    specialty— “dogskin” gloves made from Cape sheep-skin, having a warm tan
                    colour—English makers have no competitors. A very large quantity of cheap but
                    useful gloves are made at Brusselsand Copenhagen. During the year 1876,1,084,400
                    dozen pairs, of a value of £1,380,884, were imported into <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n716/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0910-0716-0693"/> the United Kingdom from France; from Belgium
                    there were 301,305 dozen pairs, valued at £345,174; and the total imports from
                    all quarters amounted to 1,497,437 dozen pairs, of a value of £1,840,956. In
                    1878 the total imports were 1,060,040 dozen pairs, valued at £1,302,060.</p>
                <p>Buckskin gloves are largely made in the United States, and that branch, together
                    with a limited production of kid and other gloves, is chiefly centred in the
                    village of Gloversville, Fulton co., N.Y. It is estimated that from about 140
                    separate glove factories in that village not less than two-thirds of the gloves
                    made in the United States are sent out. Kid gloves are made to some extent in
                    New York city.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
