<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0910-0654-0637-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GLAS, John (9th edition, volume 10, page 637)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw1m">Martyrs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bw6x">Spirits</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1139094">Suppers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130061">Spirits</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130040">Spirit</term>
                    <term ref="fast:875210">Congregationalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1010918">Martyrs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n654/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GLAS, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi></label> (1695-1773), the
                    founder of the sect generally known as Glassites or Sandemanians, was born at
                    Auchteπnuchty, Fife, where his father was parish minister, on the 5th of October
                    1695. On completion of his education for the. ministry at the universities of St
                    Andrews and Edinburgh, he was licensed as a preacher by the presbytery of Perth,
                    and soon afterwards ordained by that of Dundee as minister of the parish of
                    Tealing (1719). During his ministry there he gradually formed peculiar opinions,
                    which as early as 1725 found expression in the formation of a society “separate
                    from the multitude,” numbering nearly a hundred, and drawn from his own and
                    neighbouring parishes. The members of this <hi rend="italic">ecclesiola
                    in</hi><hi rend="italic">ecclesia</hi> pledged themselves “to join together in
                    the Christian profession, to follow Christ the Lord as the righteousness of His
                    people, to walk together in brotherly love and in the duties of it in subjection
                    to Mr Gias as their overseer in the Lord, to observe the ordinance of the Lord’s
                    Supper once every month, to submit themselves to the Lord’s law for removing
                    offences” (Matth, xviii.), and so on. From the scriptural doctrine of the
                    essentially spiritual and heavenly nature of the kingdom of Christ, Gias in his
                    public teaching drew the conclusions, not only that the church, as being
                    identical with that kingdom, ought to consist of none but truly spiritual
                    Christian men, but also that the civil establishment of the church was unlawful
                    and utterly inconsistent with the spirit of Christianity.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>His argument is most fully exhibited in a
                    treatise entitled The Testimony of the King of Martyrs concerning His Kingdom
                    (John xviii. 36, 37) Explained and Illustrated (1729).</p></note> For the
                    promulgation of these views, which were confessedly at variance with the
                    doctrines of the standards of the national Church of Scotland, he was summoned
                    (1726) before his presbytery, where, in the course of the investigations which
                    followed, he affirmed with still more explicitness than formerly his belief that
                    “every national church established by the laws of earthly kingdoms is
                    antichristian in its constitution and persecuting in its spirit,” and further
                    declared opinions upon the subject of church government which amounted to an
                    entire repudiation of Presbyterianism and an acceptance of Independency. For
                    these opinions he was in 1728 suspended from the discharge of ministerial
                    functions, and finally in 1730 deposed; the members of the society already
                    referred to, however, for the most part continued to adhere to him, thus
                    constituting the first “Glassite” or “Glasite” church. The seat of this
                    congregation was shortly afterwards transferred to Dundee, whence Gias
                    subsequently removed to Edinburgh, where he officiated for some time as an
                    “elder.” He next laboured in Perth for a few years, but ultimately returned to
                    Dundee, where the remainder of his life was spent. In 1739 the General Assembly,
                    without any application either from him or from his friends, removed the
                    sentence of deposition which had been passed against him, and restored him to
                    the character and exercise of a minister of the gospel of Christ, though
                    declaring that he was not to be esteemed a minister of the Established Church of
                    Scotland, or eligible for a charge, until he should have renounced the
                    principles embraced and avowed by him that were inconsistent with the
                    constitution of the church. Besides the <hi rend="italic">Testimony</hi> Gias
                    wrote a number of papers, expository, polemical, or practical, which were
                    published in a collected edition at Edinburgh in 1761 (4 vols. 8vo), and again
                    at Perth in 1782 (5 vols. 8vo). He died in 1773.</p>
                <p>The Glassite denomination, which has never been a numerous one, is distinguished
                    by a number of peculiarities alike in doctrine, discipline, and worship, some of
                    which have already been indicated. One of the most characteristic of its tenets
                    is that which owes its elaboration to Robert Sandeman (1718-1771), the
                    son-in-law of Gias, from whom is derived the name of Sandemanians, by which the
                    sect is principally known in England and America. In a series of letters (1757)
                    to Hervey, the author of Theron and Aspasio, he maintained that justifying faith
                    is a simple assent to the divine testimony concerning Jesus Christ, differing in
                    no way in its character from belief in any ordinary human testimony. No
                    distinctive theological system, however, has as yet been elaborated from this
                    point of view. In their practice the Glassite churches aim at a strict
                    conformity with the primitive type of Christianity as that is understood by
                    them. Each congregation has a plurality of elders, pastors, or bishops, who are
                    chosen according to what are believed to be the instructions of Paul, without
                    regard to previous education or present occupation, and who enjoy a perfect
                    equality in office. To have been married a second time disqualifies for
                    ordination, or for continued tenure of the office of bishop. In all the action
                    of the church unanimity is considered to be necessaiy; and if any member differ
                    in opinion from the rest, he must either surrender his judgment to that of the
                    church or be shut out from its communiori. To join in prayer with any one who is
                    not a member of the denomination is regarded as unlawful, and even to eat or
                    drink with one who has been excommunicated is held to be a heinous sin. The
                    Lord’s Supper is observed weekly; and between forenoon and afternoon service
                    every Sunday a love feast, at which it is incumbent on every member to be
                    present, is held after the manner of the primitive Christians. Mutual
                    exhortation is practised at all the meetings for divine service, it being lawful
                    for any member who possesses the gift to speak. The practice of washing one
                    another's feet was at one time observed; and it is still customary for each
                    brother and sister to receive new members, on admission, with a holy kiss.
                    “Things strangled” and “blood” are rigorously abstained from; the lot is
                    regarded as sacred; the accumulation of wealth is regarded as unscriptural and
                    improper, and each member considers his property as liable to be called for at
                    any time to meet the wants of the poor and the necessities of the church. The
                    number of adherents at present belonging to the denomination is probably a
                    little under 2000.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
