<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0910-0444-0431-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GEORGIA (9th edition, volume 10, page 431)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4f766g40">Sovereigns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86v83">Race</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sf2mc0b">Aryans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xk84r7r">Caucasians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g08p">Groups</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2cj5q">Sassanians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079619">Protectionism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1938968">Aryans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:818281">Aryanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:814767">Armenians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1111954">Seljuks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812571">Arabism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204622">Georgia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208963">Turkey</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1226682">Albania</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204537">Sweden</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n444/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GEORGIA</label>, a kingdom in central Transcaucasia,
                    remarkable for the long list of its sovereigns, the monarchy having extended
                    over a period of upwards of 2000 years, the kings reigning at times
                    independently, or under the rule of Persia, Turkey, or the Eastern empire. The
                    earliest name of the country was Karthli; the ancients knew it as Iberia,
                    bounded on the one side by Colchis and on the other by Albania; and it has for
                    centuries been called Georgia.</p>
                <p>Georgia proper, which includes Karthli and Kakhetia, is bounded on the N. by
                    Ossety and Daghestan, on the E. by Shekynn, on the S. by Shamshadyl and the
                    khanates of Erivan and Kars, and on the W. by Gouria and Imeritia; but the
                    kingdom at times included Gouria, Mingrelia, Abkhasia, Imeritia, and Daghestan,
                    and extended from the great mountain range to the Araxes. It now forms the
                    government of Tiflis, divided into the districts of Doushett, Telav, Sygnah,
                    Gori, and Akhalzikh, having an area of nearly 25,000 square miles, and in 1873 a
                    population of 635,313, made up chiefly of Georgians and Armenians,— there being
                    also Persians, Tatars, and a few Jews and Europeans. The chief city is the
                    ancient capital of Tiflis, the seat of government, under a governor-general, for
                    the whole of Transcaucasia, and the principal centre of com merce. See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Caucasus</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Tiflis.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Vegetable Products.—</hi> The valleys and declivities are fertile,
                    producing maize, millet, barley, oats, rice, beans, lentils, and com (which is
                    best in the plains near Gori), also cotton, flax, and hemp, now exported
                    exclusively to Russia. The vineyards cover 75,400 acres, the average produce of
                    wine being at the rate of 230 gallons per acre; the valley of the Alazan yields
                    the best qualities. It is consumed in the country and adjoining districts, the
                    only wine exported being that produced from vine-canes brought from the Crimea.
                    Grapes are gathered in September, and the wine is fit for use one month after it
                    has been put into a <hi rend="italic">bourdyouk,</hi> “skin,” or <hi
                    rend="italic">kvevry,</hi> a huge earthen jar in which it may be preserved for
                    years. New vines are planted every six, eight, or ten years, according to the
                    nature of the soil, and are cut after the fruit is gathered, and again in March
                    and April when the soil is turned up. The <hi rend="italic">Leeanium</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">vitis</hi> and <hi rend="italic">0idium</hi> have attacked the
                    plants from time to time, though not in severe form, but the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Phylloxera</hi><hi rend="italic">vastatrix</hi> has been hitherto quite
                    unknown. In the vineyards are often seen the apple, pear, and quince trees;
                    other fruits include the pomegranate, peach, apricot, plum, almond, mulberry,
                    pistachio, fig, cherry, walnut, hazel-nut, medlar, melon and water melon,
                    raspberry, &amp;c. In summer the banks of streams are covered with beautiful
                    wild flowers,—the primrose in double form, the crocus of varied colours, and
                    snowdrops appearing early in March in the greatest profusion.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Animals.—</hi> The domestic animals are the camel, ox, mule,
                    ass, and buffalo as beasts of burden, with the goat, and an immense number of
                    pigs, pork being favourite food. The horse—small, hardy, and enduring—is ridden
                    more frequently unshod, except in the hills; no pains are taken to improve the
                    breed. The wild animals of greatest importance are the bear, ibex, wolf, hyaena,
                    fox, wild boar, wild goat, and antelope; while the pheasant, woodcock, quail,
                    and “partridge of the Caucasus” are the principal winged game. The fish taken in
                    the Kour and other rivers are the sturgeon, silurus, carp, perch, trout,
                    gudgeon, and a fish resembling the salmon, called <hi rend="italic"
                    >oragoula</hi> by the Georgians. The great sturgeon, <hi rend="italic"
                    >bélouga</hi> or hansen, is taken at the estuary of the Kour in the Caspian.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Communication.—</hi> A railroad connects Tiflis with Poti on
                    the Black Sea, the line over the Souram pass, 3037 feet above the sea, being
                    laid at gradients of 1 in 22, over a distance of about 8 miles. Lines of rail
                    are projected for connecting Vladykavkaz in the north, and Djoulpha at the
                    Persian frontier, with the capital. Post-roads are excellent, and saddle-horses
                    and comfortable vehicles for post-horses are to be obtained at the principal
                    towns. Locomotion is very inexpensive.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">History.—</hi> The material at the disposal of the historian of
                    Georgia is scanty. An anonymous work of the 12th century gives the history from
                    the earliest times to the year 1124; another, also anonymous, is a continuation
                    to the division of the kingdom in 1445; and a third is the compilation by the
                    Czarevitch Wakhoucht, being the complete annals from the earliest times to the
                    year 1745. These, and a few pamphlets indifferently edited, if we except the
                    memoirs of his family by Stephen Orbeliani, archbishop of Siouny in the 13th
                    century, comprise all that is left to us during an interval of upwards of 2000
                    years.</p>
                <p>The earliest Armenian chroniclers have included facts on Georgia, which it is
                    believed were founded on traditions they received from the Georgians. According
                    to these authorities, the Georgian, Armenian, Kakhetian, Lesghian, Mingrelian,
                    and other races in Transcaucasia are the descendants of Thargamos, who was the
                    great-grandson of Japhet, the son of Noah, though we read in Gen. x. 3 that
                    Togarmah was the son of Gomer, who was the son of Japhet. Those different
                    populations were afterwards included under the ’general name of Thargomosiany.
                    The second son of Thargamos, named Karthlos, having settled in that part where
                    is now the rivulet Karthli, became the patriarch and king of the people in the
                    land around, called Karthli after himself. His son Mtzkhethos founded the city
                    of Mtzkhetha, which became the capital; and a son of Mtzkhethos; named Ouphlis,
                    was the author of the rock-cut town near Gori. At that period the title assumed
                    by the ruler was <hi rend="italic">mamasalclysy,</hi> “lord or head of the
                    house,” the worship being that of the sun, moon, and five planets. The first to
                    revive the title of king was Phamawaz, 302-237 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi>
                    who rid the country of the tyrant Ason, a governor appointed by Alexander the
                    Great. Pharnawaz originated the orthography of the Georgian language, and is
                    said to have invented the military alphabet. In 140 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b.c.</hi> Mirvan became king. His son and successor was dethroned by his own
                    subjects, and the crown offered to Ardaces I., whose son, Arshag, ascended the
                    throne 71 B.α, the dynasty of Arsaces thus commencing its rale. The deeds of
                    Sulla, Lucullus, Pompey, and Mithradates next serve to illustrate the courage
                    and warlike qualities of the people of Iberia. In 265 the Sassanian dynasty
                    commenced in the person of Miriam, son of Shapour I., who was married to a
                    daughter of the late king Asphagor. Miriam and all his subjects were converted
                    to Christianity by Nouna or Nina, a poor captive, who had escaped the
                    persecution of Tiridates, king of Armenia. She prevailed upon the people of
                    Karthli to desist from offering human victims, and to overturn their pagan
                    altars; and the king erected a sanctuary, which was afterwards replaced by a
                    noble edifice, 364-379, on the spot where now stands the cathedral at M’zhett.
                    Miriam applied to Constantine for priests to instruct his people, and many were
                    sent, among them being Eustace of Antioch. In 469 King Vakhtang, surnamed <hi
                    rend="italic">Gourgasal, “</hi> wolf-lion," founded <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n445/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0910-0445-0432"/> a city which he called Tbylysys-Kalaky, now
                    Tiflis, on account of the warm springs there. Vakhtang established a
                    patriarchate at Mtzkhetha, and constructed the fortress of Souram. He conquered
                    Mingrelia, and brought the Ossets and Abkhasians under subjection. He also took
                    possession of a large part of Armenia, and having formed an alliance with
                    Chosroes, king of Persia, even advanced into India. The seat of government was
                    transferred from Mtzkhetha to Tbylysys-Kalaky, when Datchy came to the throne in
                    499. At this epoch the Georgian and Armenian Churches had separated; and a
                    century later, the Georgian and Russian Churches united. On the death of
                    Stephanos, who had ruled under the protection of the Eastern empire, a Bagιatide
                    named Gouram was nominated couropolate by the emperor. Soon after the appearance
                    of Mahomet in the 7th century, the Arabs, having conquered the Persians, entered
                    Armenia and Georgia, and for nearly a century compelled all, under pain of
                    death, to embrace Mahometanism. In 787 the Sassanian dynasty came to an end.
                    Ashod I., <hi rend="italic">Medz,</hi> “the Great,” a Bagratide, succeeded,
                    receiving from the caliph Haroun al Raschid the title of grand prince, and that
                    of couropolate from the emperor; but it was not until about 841 that the
                    sovereign (Bagrat I.) was recognized by the caliph as ruler, the country during
                    the interval having been continually ravaged by the Arabs. Their last
                    expedition, in the reign of Bagrat I., included the occupation of Tiflis. The
                    reign of Bagrat III. marks an epoch, for that monarch, who was king of Abkhasia,
                    succeeded to the crown of Georgia by right of inheritance, his sovereignty
                    extending from the Black Sea to the Caspian. He encouraged the arts and
                    sciences, and was the founder of the noble cathedral at Koutaïs, the first
                    building in the style of architecture thenceforth denominated Georgian. During
                    the reign of Bagrat IV. the Seljuks commenced in 1048 a succession of invasions,
                    until they were effectually repulsed by Liparit Orboulk at the head of a
                    comparatively small force of Georgians, Armenians, and Greeks. Liparit himself
                    was taken prisoner, and Bagrat carried off his wife in his absence; but,
                    regaining his liberty, Liparit took up arms against his sovereign, and drove him
                    out of his capital into Abkhasia. Bagrat appealing to the emperor, it was
                    arranged that he should return to his kingdom of Georgia and Abkhasia, Liparit
                    being suffered, as his dutiful subject, to retain the province of Meskhy.</p>
                <p>In 1064 the Seljuks under Arp-Aslan again overran Georgia, destroying Tiflis and
                    slaughtering the inhabitants. In 1072 George II. ascended the throne, and in his
                    reign Tiflis was again devastated by the Seljuks, the king himself being forced
                    to fly. With his valiant son and successor, David III., the fortunes of Georgia
                    changed, for the enemy was driven out of the plains of Kakhetia, and the land
                    from Tiflis to Ani was freed of hrs presence in 1123 by Ivan Orbeliani, whose
                    signal services were rewarded by elevation to the rank of constable. The next
                    monarchs were Demetrius I. and David IV., the latter, at his death, entrusting
                    his son Demna or Demetrius to the guardianship of Ivan Orbeliani, and the
                    regency to his brother George, who with the assistance of Ivan, greatly extended
                    the Georgian territory, rescuing from the Seljuks a large portion of Armenia.
                    When in 1177 Demna had attained his majority, the nobles desirous of supporting
                    the young prince’s claims called upon Ivan, whose popularity had meanwhile been
                    increasing, to place him on the throne. George fortified himself at Tiflis and
                    awaited events; his rule, however, was too firmly established to be easily
                    shaken, and, many of Ivan’s partisans espousing his cause, he at length set out
                    to besiege Lorhy, which Ivan and his charge had made their headquarters.
                    Numerous desertions reduced the ranks of the besieged, until young Demna fled at
                    last to the encampment of his uncle, and entreated him to spare his life. His
                    prayer was granted, but he was deprived of his eyes, and otherwise mutilated.
                    The prince having surrendered, Ivan declared his readiness to submit on
                    condition that he should be honourably treated. George assented, showed his
                    prisoner all honour until he had got the whole of his relatives into his power,
                    when he ordered that all should be massacred, Ivan himself being blinded and
                    brutally treated. Three only of his kinsmen were saved—a brother named Liparit,
                    and his two sons who had gone to Persia to solicit the aid of the atabek
                    Ildegouz. From them are descended the Orbeliani of the present day. At the time
                    of their extermination, the possessions of the Orboulk comprised more than the
                    half of Georgia. It is related that the ancestors of this powerful family,
                    princes of the family of Djenkapour of the royal race of Djenesdan, first came
                    to Karthli from that part of Asia which lies between China and the Ural; the
                    fortress of Orpeth was given to them for a residence. In return for the friendly
                    reception accorded to them, they united with the Karthlosides in throwing off
                    the Persian yoke, a service which obtained for the chief Orboulk the rank of <hi
                    rend="italic">sbaaealar</hi> or generalissimo. During the reign of Pharnawaz,
                    the Orboulk took precedence next to the sovereign, and matrimonial alliances
                    were formed with the royal house. The first of the family individualized in the
                    annals was the warrior Liparit (875-900). George III. died in 1184, and was
                    succeeded by his only child Thamar, whose kingdom extended from the Caspian to
                    the Black Sea, and from beyond the Caucasus to Armenia, for Trebizond, Erzeroum,
                    Tovin, Kars, and Aui fell to her anus. Her missionaries travelled far and wide,
                    and numerous churches were constructed, and thus it was that lier many virtues
                    and brilliant rule secured to her the title of <hi rend="italic">Mcſihc,</hi>
                    “king.” This great queen was succeeded in 1212-13 by her son George IV.,
                    surnamed <hi rend="italic">Lasha,</hi> “He who enlightens the world,” who,
                    assisted by the powerful noble, Ivan Mkhargrdzelidze, of the family that had
                    replaced the Orbeliani in the royal favour, vanquished the Persians in many
                    battles, conquering Gandja, and permanently occupying Kars. In 1220 and 1222 the
                    Mongols again visited Georgia. The king left an infant son who afterwards
                    reigned as David IV., but his own sister, Roussoudan, seized the crown in 1223,
                    and passed a life not free from reproach. To revenge himself upon the queen, who
                    refused his suit, Jalal-uddin twice occupied her capital, and her kingdom was
                    again overrun by the Mongols, who committed fearful ravages. Next follow the
                    exploits of Timur, who invaded Georgia in 1386, and, having seized upon the
                    capital, carried away the king, Bagrat V., who feigned conversion to Islamism
                    that he might gain the confidence of the conqueror. By this means he succeeded
                    in obtaining from Timur a force of 12,000 men, for the purpose of prevailing
                    upon his people to embrace Mahometanism. Bagrat had preconcerted his plans, and
                    in due course every Tatar in his suite was slaughtered by his own warriors. In
                    an ungovernable passion Timur re-entered Georgia (1393-94), and laid waste the
                    entire country, levelling towns and villages, without sparing a single life.
                    Satiated of bloodshed, he withdrew to the plains of Karabagh, and George VII.,
                    son and successor to Bagrat, returned upon the death of his father (1401) from
                    the mountains where he had remained concealed, and occupied the capital. Timur
                    made war upon him as well, compelling his submission, and in 1403 finally
                    quitted the country. George was succeeded by Constantine II., whose successor,
                    Alexander I., son of George VII., restored the kingdom to prosperity; but
                    towards the close of his days he conceived the unhappy idea of dividing his
                    kingdom among his three sons, an act that was followed by internecine wars,
                    rebellions, massacres, and foreign invasions. From about this period commence
                    the relations of Russia with Georgia and its neighbouring principalities, for in
                    1492, during the war fomented between Turkey aud Persia, Alexander, king of
                    Kakhetia, sought the protection of the czar John III. Again, in 1587, Boris
                    Godounoff was appealed to for succour; and when, in 1618, Shah Abbas invaded
                    Georgia, Teimouraz I. applied for assistance to Michael Feódorovitch (the first
                    of the Romanoffs), as did also, in 1621, George III. king of Imeritia, and Mamia
                    Gouriel the ruler of Gouria. In 1638 Levan, sovereign of Mingrelia, took the
                    oath of allegiance to Alexis Michaelovitch, and in 1650 Alexander of Imeritia
                    acknowledged the sovereignty of Russia. That empire, however, could not render
                    material assistance to those petty sovereigns in distress, and little was done
                    until fresh excesses committed by the Turks and Persians afforded Peter the
                    Great the excuse for sending an expedition, in 1716, under Bekevitch a
                    Circassian chieftain, to survey the Caspian shore and erect defences. Bekevitch
                    was overpowered by the Tatars, and slaughtered with the whole of his force.
                    Peter then occupied the western shore of the Caspian, taking the king of Georgia
                    under his protection. This was Vakhtang VI., the author of a code that was in
                    vogue until 1841, when Russian laws were in great measure introduced. But he was
                    unable to resist Nadir Shah, and abdicating in 1724, retired to Astrakhan, where
                    he died. Peter being at peace with Turkey, and having concluded the treaty of
                    Nystadt with Sweden, left Moscow, May 24, 1722, and embarked at Astrakhan with
                    troops destined for Georgia and the Persian provinces. Derbent, Bakou, Ghylan,
                    and Mazanderan fell into his power, and he constructed a fort on the river
                    Soulak, which he named St Croix. All these places were ceded by treaty, in 1732,
                    after Nadir Shah had delivered Karthli and Kakhetia from Turkish oppression. A
                    few years later, in 1735, Turkey renounced all claim to those countries in
                    favour of Persia. When war broke out with Turkey in 1768, General Todleben was
                    sent to the assistance of Solomon I., king of Imeritia, and the Turks were
                    expelled that kingdom. Then followed the treaty of Kainardschi in 1774, by which
                    Georgia, Imeritia, and Mingrelia were placed under the protection of Russia. In
                    1795 Aga Mahomet Shah laid Tiflis in ruins, a disaster that was succeeded by
                    dissensions in the royal family; and Heraclius II., who in 1783 had declared
                    himself the vassal of Russia, now appealed to that country for protection. The
                    next sovereign, George XIII., renewed this appeal, which would have been granted
                    but for the sudden death of the emperor Paul. Alexander I. hesitated for a time,
                    until George finally renounced his crown in 1799 in favour of Russia, drawing
                    down upon him the hatred and curses of his country. His younger brother,
                    Alexander, made an effort to secure the crown, but the chiefs saw the
                    hopelessness of attempting to throw off the Russian yoke, and, being but poorly
                    supported, the prince was beaten on the banks of the Lora. George died the
                    following year, being the last of the Bagratides to occupy the throne of
                    Georgia, which his ancestors had held for the space of 1029 years. It may be
                    stated that the Bagrations claim descent from David, by his adulterous
                    intercourse with the wife of Uriah! Georgia was now virtually annexed to the
                    empire, and on <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n446/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0910-0446-0433"/> September 12, 1801, Alexander I. issued a
                    proclamation announcing the fact to the people of that country. In 1810 the
                    prince of Imeritia revolted against Russia; but this movement was quickly
                    suppressed, and the principality annexed. MamiaV., the ruler of Gouria,
                    recognized the suzerainty of Russia in the same year, his principality being
                    eventually annexed in 1829.</p>
                <p>See wakhoucht, <hi rend="italic">Histoire delà Géorgie,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >irons.</hi> by Brosset, and additions,5 vois , St Petersburg, 1849; Vladykyn,
                    <hi rend="italic">Sabesyédnyk</hi><hi rend="italic">v</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> ,</hi><hi rend="italic">pouteshestvyry</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >pa</hi><hi rend="italic">Jiackaεou,</hi> Moscow, 1874; Zeidleitz, <hi
                    rend="italic">Otcherk Vynadyelya</hi><hi rend="italic">Kaι∙kaza,</hi> Tiflis,
                    187S; Comm. J. Buchan Teller. R.N., <hi rend="italic">The Crimea and
                    Transcaucasia,</hi> 1877. (J. B. TE.)</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ethnology.—</hi> Of the three main groups into which the
                    Caucasian races are now usually divided, the Georgian is in every respect the
                    most important and interesting. It has accordingly largely occupied the
                    attention of Orientalists almost incessantly from the days of Klaproth to the
                    present time. Yet such are the difficulties connected with the origin and mutual
                    relations of the Caucasian peoples that its affinities are still far from being
                    clearly established. Anton Schiefner and P. V. Uslar, however, who must be
                    accepted as undoubtedly the greatest authorities on the subject, have at least
                    arrived at some negative conclusions valuable as starting points for further
                    research. In their valuable papers, published in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Memoirs</hi> of the St Petersburg Imperial Academy of Sciences and elsewhere,
                    they have finally disposed of the views of Bopp and Brosset, who attempted on
                    linguistic grounds to connect the Georgians with the Aryan family. They also
                    clearly show that Max Müller’s “Turanian” theory is untenable, and they go a
                    long way towards proving that the Georgian, with all the other Caucasian
                    languages except the Ossetian, forms a distinct linguistic family absolutely
                    independent of all others. This had already been suspected by Klaproth, and as
                    the same conclusion has been arrived at by Fr. Müller and Zagarelli, it is not
                    likely to be set aside by further investigation.</p>
                <p>Uslar’s “Caucasian Family” comprises the following three great divisions :—</p>
                <p>1. Western Group. Typical races: Tcherkessians and Abkhasians.</p>
                <p>2. Eastern Group. Typical races: Tchetchenzes and Lesghians. 3. Southern Group.
                    Typical race: Georgians.</p>
                <p>Here the term “family” must be taken in a far more elastic sense than when
                    applied, for instance, to the Aryan, Semitic, or Eastern Polynesian divisions of
                    mankind. Indeed, Uslar would perhaps be the first to admit that the fundamental
                    unity of the three groups has not yet been established, and that they present at
                    least as wide divergencies as are found to exist between the Semitic and Hamitic
                    linguistic families, whose primitive relationship has not yet been definitely
                    determined. Thus, while the Abkhasian of group 1 is still at the agglutinating,
                    the Lesghian of group 2 has fairly reached the inflectingjstäte, and the
                    Georgian seems still to waver between the two. In consequence of these different
                    stages of development, Uslar hesitates finally to fix the position of Geoigian
                    in the family, regarding it as possibly a connecting link between groups 1 and
                    2, but possibly also radically distinct from both.</p>
                <p>Including all its numerous ramifications, the Georgian or southern group occupies
                    the greater part of Transcaucasia, reaching from about the neighbourhood of
                    Batoum on the Euxine eastwards to the Caspian, and merging southwards with the
                    Armenians of Aryan stock. It comprises altogether nine subdivisions, as in the
                    subjoined table :—</p>
                <p>1. The <hi rend="smallcaps">Georgians</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Pjjoper,</hi> who
                    are the <hi rend="italic">Iberians</hi> of the ancients and the <hi
                    rend="italic">Grusya</hi> of the Russians, but who ca;l themselves <hi
                    rend="italic">Karthalinians,</hi> and who in mediaeval times were masters of the
                    Bion and Upper Kur as far as its junction with the Alazan.</p>
                <p>2. The <hi rend="smallcaps">Imekitians,</hi> west of the Suram mountains as far
                    as river Tzchenis-Tzchali.</p>
                <p>3. The <hi rend="smallcaps">Guriλns,</hi> between the Rion and Lazistan,</p>
                <p>4. The <hi rend="smallcaps">Lazes</hi> of Lazistan on the Euxine.</p>
                <p>5. The <hi rend="smallcaps">Swanithians, Shvans,</hi> or <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Swanians,</hi> on the Upper Ingur and Tzchenis-Tzchali rivers.</p>
                <p>6. The <hi rend="smallcaps">Mingrelians,</hi> between rivers Tzchenis-Tzchali,
                    Rion, Ingur and the Black Sea.</p>
                <p>8 The <hi rend="smallcaps">Pshavs</hi> or <hi rend="smallcaps">Ph'tchÀvy</hi>
                    {about the headstreams of the Alazan and</p>
                <p>9.' The <hi rend="smallcaps">Khevscrs</hi> ’"Z j <hi rend="superscript"> jora
                    rivers</hi> ∙</p>
                <p>All these formed jointly the ancient kingdom of Iberia, whose <hi rend="italic"
                    >meſkhè</hi> or “king” resided at Mtzklιet till 469 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >a.d.,</hi> when the seat of government was removed to the neighbouring Tphlissi
                    or Tphilis-kalaki, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> “warm town,” so called from its
                    thermal springs. This place has ever since continued to be the capital of the
                    kingdom, and now bears the abbreviated name of Tiflis. The representative branch
                    of the race have always been the Karthalinians, a name which the native
                    Christian chroniclers profess to trace back to Khartlos, second son of
                    Thargamos, son of Japhet, son of Noah. From Thargamos all their tribes are by
                    their writers called, collectively, Thargamossiani, and from Khartlos their
                    country receives the name of Karthveli or Karthli. But no weight can be attached
                    to these genealogies and etymologies, which would doubtless never have been
                    heard of but for the national desire to connect the race with the Mosaic account
                    of the dispersion. It is now pretty well established that the Georgians are the
                    descendants of the aborigines of the Pambaki highlands, and that they found
                    their way to their present homes from the south-east some four or five thousand
                    years ago, possibly under pressure trom the great waves of Aryan migration
                    flowing from the Eranian table-land westwards to Asia Minor and Europe. The
                    terms Georgian and Grusya are simply corruptions of the Persian <hi
                    rend="italic">Gurj,</hi> as in Gurjistan = Gurjland = Georgia. The Georgians
                    proper are limited on the east by the Alazan, on the north by the Caucasus, on
                    the west by the Meskhian hills, separating them from the Imeritians, and on the
                    south by the Kur river and the Karadagh and the Pambaki mountains. Southwards,
                    however, no hard and fast ethnical line can be drawn, for even immediately south
                    of Tiflis, Georgians, Armenians, and Tatars are found intermingled. confusedly
                    together.</p>
                <p>The Georgian race, which represents the oldest elements of civilization in the
                    Caucasus, is distinguished by some excellent mental qualities, and is especially
                    noted for personal courage and a passionate love of music. The people, however,
                    are described as fierce and cruel, and addicted to the vice of intemperance,
                    though Von Thielmann speaks of them as “rather hard drinkers than drunkards.”
                    Physically they are a fine athletic race of pure Caucasian type; hence during
                    the Moslem ascendency Georgia supplied, next to Circassia, the ]aιgest number of
                    female slaves for the Tui kish harems and of recruits for the Osmanli armies,
                    more especially for the select corps of the famous Mameluks.</p>
                <p>The social organization rested on a highly aristocratic basis, and the lowest
                    classes were separated by several grades of vassalage from the highest. But
                    since their incorporation with the Russian empire, these relations have become
                    greatly modified, and a more sharply defined middle class of merchants, traders,
                    and artisans has been developed. The power of life and death, formerly claimed
                    and freely exercised by the nobles over their serfs, has also been expressly
                    abolished. They are altogether at present in a fairly well-to-do condition, and
                    it cannot be denied that under the Russian administration they have become
                    industrious, aud have made considerable moral and material progress.</p>
                <p>Missionaries sent by Constantine the Great introduced Christianity about the
                    beginning of the 4th century. Their efforts were greatly aided by the exemplary
                    life of a female slave named Nina, who came into Georgia during the reign of
                    King Miriam (265-318), and who occupies a prominent place in the ecclesiastical
                    records of the country. Since that time the people have, under severe pressure
                    from surrounding Mahometan communities, remained faithful to the principles of
                    Christianity, and are still amongst the most devoted adherents of the orthodox
                    Greek Church. Indeed it was their attachment to the national religion that
                    caused them to call in the aid of the Christian Muscovites against the
                    proselytizing attempts of the Shiite Persians—a step which ultimately brought
                    about their political extinction.</p>
                <p>As already stated, the Karthli language is not only fundamentally distinct from
                    the Aryan linguistic family, but cannot be shown to possess any clearly
                    ascertained affinities with either of the two northern Caucasian groups. It
                    resembles them chiefly in its phonetic system, so that according to Rosen <hi
                    rend="italic">(Sprache der</hi><hi rend="italic">Lazen}</hi> all the languages
                    of central and western Caucasus might be adequately rendered by the Georgian
                    alphabet. Though certainly not so harsh as the Avar, Serghian, and other
                    Daghestan languages, it is very far from being euphonious, and the frequent
                    recurrence of such sounds as <hi rend="italic">ts, ds, thz,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">kh,</hi><hi rend="italic">khh.</hi><hi rend="italic">gh</hi>
                    (Arab. £), <hi rend="italic">q</hi> (Arab, ð), for all of which there are
                    distinct characters, renders its articulation rather more energetic and rugged
                    than is agreeable to ears accustomed to the softer tones of the Irenian and
                    western Aryan tongues. It presents great facilities for composition, the laws of
                    which are very regular. Its peculiar morphology, standing midway between
                    agglutination and true inflexion, is well illustrated by its simple declension
                    common to noun, adjective, and pronoun, and its more intricate verbal
                    conjugation, with its personal endings, seven tenses, and incorporation of
                    pronominal subject and object, all showing decided progress towards the
                    inflecting structure of the Aryan and Semitic tongues.</p>
                <p>Georgian is written in a native alphabet obviously based on the Armenian, and
                    like it attributed to St Mesropius (Mesrob), who flourished in the 6th century.
                    Of this alphabet there are two forms, differing so greatly in outline and even
                    in the number of the letters that they might almost be regarded as two distinct
                    alphabetic systems. The first and oldest, used exclusively in the Bible and
                    liturgical works, is the square or monumental <hi rend="italic"
                    >Khutsuri,</hi><hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> “sacerdotal,” consisting of 38
                    letters, approaching the Armenian in appearance. The second is the <hi
                    rend="italic">Mkhcdrñli khë,U,</hi><hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> “soldier’s
                    hand,” used in ordinary writing, and consisting of 40 letters, neatly shaped and
                    full of curves, hence at first sight not unlike the modern Burmese form of the
                    Pali.</p>
                <p>Of the Karthli language there are several varieties; and, besides those comprised
                    in the above table, mention should be made of the Kakhetian current in the
                    historic province of Kakhetia. A distinction is sometimes drawn between the
                    Karthalinians proper and the Kakhetians, but it rests on a purely political
                    basis, having originated with the partition in 1424 of the ancient Iberian
                    estates into the three new kingdoms of Karthalinia, Kakhetia, andlmeritia. On
                    the other hand, both the Laz of Lazistan and the Swanian pre»</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n447/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0910-0447-0434"/>
                <p>sent such serious structural and verbal differences from the common type that
                    they seem to stand rather in the relation of sister tongues than of dialects to
                    the Georgian proper. All derive obviously from a common source, but have been
                    developed independently of. each other. The <hi rend="italic">Tush</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">Mosok</hi> appears to be fundamentally a Kistian or Tchetchenz
                    idiom affected by Georgian influences.</p>
                <p>The Bible is said to have been translated into Georgian as early as the 5th
                    century. The extant version, however, dates only from the 8th century, and is
                    attributed to St Euthymius. But even so, it is far the most ancient work known
                    to exist in the language. Next in importance is, perhaps, the curious poem
                    entitled <hi rend="italic">The Amours oj T</hi><hi rend="italic">uricl</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">and Ncstan Darejan,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">The man clothed in
                    the panther's skin,</hi> attributed to Rustevel, who lived during the prosperous
                    reign of Queen Thamar (11th century). Prince Leonidze of Akhmeti in Kakhetia
                    showed Baron von Thielmann a rare and very old MS. of this poem, written on fine
                    hemp paper in exquisite Mkhedruli characters, and embellished with arabesques
                    and miniatures evidently the work of an eminent artist Other noteworthy
                    compositions are the national epics of the <hi rend="italic">Baramiani</hi> and
                    the <hi rend="italic">Rostomiani,</hi> and the prose romances of <hi
                    rend="italic">Visramiani</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Darcjaniani,</hi> the former
                    by Sarg of Thmogvi, the latter by Mosi of Khoni. Apart from these, the great
                    bulk of Georgian literature consists of ecclesiastical writings, hymns sacred
                    and profane, national codes, and chronicles.</p>
                <p>See Baron Max von Thielmann ’ s <hi rend="italic">Journey in the Caucasus,
                    Persia, and Turkey in Asia,</hi> translated by Dr Charles Hemeage, London 1875;
                    Fr. Müller's <hi rend="italic">Ethnographie</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Reise
                    der</hi><hi rend="italic">Oestr.</hi><hi rend="italic">Fregatte</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Notarra,</hi> Vienna, 1S68; Anton Schiefner and General P. V.
                    Uslar, numerous papers in the Bulletins of the Académie Impériale des Sciences
                    de Saint Petersbou∣g for 1859, &lt;fcc.; Μ. Zagarelli's <hi rend="italic">Examen
                    de la littérature</hi><hi rend="italic">relative</hi><hi rend="italic">à la
                    grammaire Géorgienne,</hi> St Petersburg, 1873; Michel ∖Smirnows paper in <hi
                    rend="italic">Revue</hi><hi rend="italic">d Anthropologie,</hi> April 15,1878.
                    (A H. K.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
