<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0910-0621-0604-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GINGUENÉ, Pierre (9th edition, volume 10, page
                    604)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n621/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GINGUENÉ, <hi rend="smallcaps">Pierre</hi></label> Louis
                    (1748-1815), the author of the <hi rend="italic">Histoire littéraire
                    d'Italie,</hi> was born on 25th April 1748 at Rennes in Brittany. He was
                    educated at a Jesuit college in his native town, but he owed most of his
                    literary tastes and accomplishments to his father, who early imbued him with a
                    love of music and the languages of England and Italy. His first literary effort,
                    a poetical piece entitled <hi rend="italic">Confession</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                    Zulmé,</hi> brought him into notice among the literary coteries of Paris, from
                    the circumstance that, when published at first anonymously, it was claimed by
                    six or seven different authors. Though the value of the piece is not very great,
                    it is Ginguené’s poetical <hi rend="italic">chef</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >d'oeuvre.</hi> The part he took as a defender of Piccini against the partisans
                    of Gluck made him still more widely known; and the reputation he acquired as a
                    promising political writer secured employment for him in the public service in
                    1780. He hailed, however, the first symptoms of the Revolution, joined Rabaut,
                    St Étienne, and Cerutti in producing the <hi rend="italic">Feuille
                    Villageoise,</hi> and celebrated in an indifferent ode the opening of the
                    states-general. A more creditable effort was his <hi rend="italic">Lettres
                    sur</hi><hi rend="italic">les Confessions de J. J. Rousseau,</hi> 1791, in which
                    he defended to the uttermost the life and principles of his author. Refusing to
                    countenance the excesses of the Revolution, he was thrown into prison, whence he
                    only escaped with life by the downfall of Robespierre. Some time after his
                    liberation he assisted, as director-general of the “commission exécutive de
                    l'instruction publique,” in reorganizing the system of public instruction. When
                    the Institute was established in 1796, he was elected a member of the division
                    called the academy of moral and political sciences. In 1798 the directory
                    appointed him minister plenipotentiary to the king of Sardinia, whose ruin,
                    begun by force of arms, they had determined to complete by treachery. A less
                    promising tool could not have been found for carrying out their design. After
                    fulfilling his duties for seven months, very little to the satisfaction of his
                    employers, Ginguené retired to his country house of St Prix, in the valley of
                    Montmorency, and there he prosecuted his literary labours till the Revolution of
                    the 18th Brumaire called him once more before the world. He was appointed a
                    member of the tribunate, which made a show of maintaining democratic opposition
                    to the first consul; but Napoleon, finding that he was not sufficiently
                    tractable, had him expelled at the first “purge,” and Ginguené once more
                    joyfully returned to his favourite pursuits. These were now more than ever a
                    necessity of life to him, as his only other source of income was the small
                    endowment attached to his seat in the Institute. Fortunately he was nominated
                    one of the commission charged to continue the literary history of France, which
                    had been brought down by the Benedictines to about the close of the 12th
                    century; and the three volumes of this series which appeared in 1814, 1817, and
                    1820 are for the most part the result of his labours. But the work by which
                    Ginguené will be longest remembered is his <hi rend="italic">Histoire littéraire
                    T Italie</hi> (9 vols. 8vo, 1811-1819), to which he was putting the finishing
                    touches when he was cut off by a painful disease, November 16, 1815. The first
                    six volumes appeared before their author’s death; the seventh is entirely his
                    except a few pages; and of the eighth and ninth he wrote about a half, the other
                    half being composed by Salfi, and revised by Daunou. The success of the history
                    in Italy was astonishing: editions were published in various parts of the
                    peninsula, with notes and comments by the best scholars, and three translations
                    appeared respectively at Milan, Naples, and Venice.</p>
                <p>Ginguené was originally led to make Italian literature his special study by
                    finding how ill that subject was understood, and how little it was appreciated,
                    by his countrymen. In the composition of his history he was guided for the most
                    part by the great work of the Jesuit Tiraboschi, but he avoids the prejudices
                    and party views of his model. His own style, though occasionally forcible and
                    eloquent, is noi unfrequently too tame for the subject, and he often trespasses
                    on his reader’s patience by over-minuteness of detail; but these faults are more
                    than atoned for by fine critical discernment, impartiality, and freedom. On the
                    score of accuracy, indeed, Ginguené sometimes offends, but seldom in matters of
                    great moment; and his slips are such as are almost inevitable to a foreigner,
                    who could hardly be said to have even seen the country whose literary history he
                    relates. The Italians felt grateful to him for having placed their literature in
                    its proper light, and readily forgave the excessive eulogies which he passed on
                    many of their writers, whose very names had been forgotten in their own
                    country.</p>
                <p>During the latter years of his life Ginguené wrote extensively for the press, and
                    he edited the Décade philοsοphupue, politique, et littéraire, till it was
                    suppressed by Napoleon in 1807. He contributed largely to the Biographic
                    universelle, the Mercure de France, and the Encyclopédie méthodique; and he
                    edited the works of Chamfort and of Lebrun. Among his minor productions are an
                    opera, Pomponin ou le Tuteur mystifié, 1777; La Satire des Satires, 1778; De
                    l’autorité de Rabelais dans la révolution qrrésente, 1791; De Μ. Neckar, 1795;
                    Fables inédites, 1814. See “Éloge de Ginguené,” by Dacier, in the Mémoires de ΐ
                    Institut, tom. vii.; “Discours” by Μ. Daunou, prefixed to the 2d edit, of the
                    Hist. litt. d'Italie·, D. J. Garat, Notice sur la vie et les ouvrages de P. L.
                    Guingené, Paris, 1817 <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n622/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0910-0622-0605"/></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
