<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0910-0797-0774-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GOOD FRIDAY (9th edition, volume 10, page 774)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43j3985w">Danes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r48v">Passions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mh6r">Fasting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m6284z">Sunday</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208757">Syria</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921717">Fasting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1037913">Nisan</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1138620">Sunday</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1090626">Reading</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:887617">Danes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n797/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GOOD FRIDAY</label>, the usual English name for the day
                    observed throughout a great part of Christendom as the anniversary of the
                    passion and death of Christ. In the Greek Church it has been or is known as <hi
                    rend="italic">πάσχα</hi> [σταυ- <hi rend="italic">ρώσιμον],</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">παρασκευή, παρασκευή μεγάλη</hi> or άγια, <hi rend="italic"
                    >σωτηρία</hi> or τά <hi rend="italic">σωτήρια, ήμερα του σταυρόν,</hi> while
                    among the Latins the names of moet frequent occurrence are Pascha Crucis, Dies
                    Dominic® Passionis, Parasceve, Feria Sexta Paschae, Feria Sexta Major in
                    Hierusalem, Dies Absolutionis. It was called Long Friday by the
                    Anglo-Saxons<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See
                    Johnson’s <hi rend="italic">Collection of Ecclesiastical Laws</hi> (vol. i.,
                    anno 957): “Housel ought not to be hallowed on Long Friday, because Christ
                    suffered for us on that day.”</p></note> and Danes; in Germany it is sometimes
                    designated Stiller Freitag (compare Greek, <hi rend="italic">εβ8oμaς</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">άπρακτος</hi><hi rend="italic">∙,</hi> Latin, hebdomas
                    inofficiosa, non laboriosa), but more commonly Charfreitag. The etymology of
                    this last name has been much disputed, but there seems now to be little doubt
                    that it is derived from the Old High German <hi rend="italic">chara,</hi>
                    meaning suffering or mourning.</p>
                <p>The origin of the custom of a yearly commemoration of the crucifixion is involved
                    in some obscurity. It may be regarded as certain, indeed, that among Jewish
                    Christians it almost imperceptibly grew out of the old habit of annually
                    celebrating the Passover on the 14th of Nisan, and of observing the “days of
                    unleavened bread,” from the 15th to the 21st of that month. In the Gentile
                    churches, on the other hand, it seems to be well established that originally no
                    yearly cycle of festivals was known at all. The weekly observance of the dies
                    dominica, however, became universal at a very early date; and the practice of
                    giving special prominence to Easter Sunday (the first Sunday after the 14th of
                    Nisan), as well as that of keeping a previous fast of considerable rigour,
                    though of indeterminate duration, had established itself in Egypt and in the
                    Western churches at least by the middle of the 2d century. The accounts which
                    have been transmitted by Eusebius, Socrates, and Epiphanius of the paschal
                    controversies, which began to be agitated about 160 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >a.d.,</hi> are obscure on many points—so obscure, indeed, as to suggest doubts
                    whether these historians had altogether comprehended the questions under
                    discussion. So much, however, is clear, that Occidental feeling had even then
                    begun to take great offence at the prevailing Eastern practice. In Asia Minor,
                    Syria, and Mesopotamia, the 14th and 16th of Nisan were specially observed,
                    altogether irrespective of the day of the week, and for this apostolic sanction
                    was urged by Polycarp; but Anicetus of Rome, with great earnestness, though
                    still with deference, pleaded immemorial usage for the custom of observing a</p>
                <p>Friday and Saturday fast followed by an Easter Sunday feast. As the Western
                    churches gained in influence, the practice of tolerance became increasingly
                    difficult; already in 190 <hi rend="smallcaps">λ.d.</hi> we find Victor of Rome
                    insisting on the conformity of Polycrates of Ephesus, and proclaiming the
                    contumacious Asiatics to be out of communion (ακοινώνητους). To secure
                    uniformity in this matter was one of the objects for which the council of Nice
                    was convened in 325; no canon, however, was framed by the fathers there
                    assembled, but it was recommended in a circular letter that Easter <hi
                    rend="italic">(πάσχα)</hi> should invariably be observed on a Sunday, and that
                    the passion should, with equal regularity, be commemorated on Friday.
                    Considerable progress towards the compulsory establishment of a uniform paschal
                    usage was made in the years immediately following; thus, by a canon of the
                    council of Antioch (341), the followers of the Oriental use were laid under
                    severe ecclesiastical censures; in the decrees of that of Laodicea (361) the
                    ominous word αi'peσις is heard (αipεσις <hi rend="italic">των
                    τεσσαρεςκαι.8εκατι.των)</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> while in the Theodosian
                    Code (xvi. 5, 9; 6, 6; 10, 24), the Quartodecimans are formally ranked among the
                    other heretics whose error is to be visited with civil pains and penalties.</p>
                <p>From the earliest period of its observance, the day was marked by a specially
                    rigorous fast, and also, on the whole, by a tendency to greater simplicity in
                    the public services of the church. Prior to the 4th century there is no evidence
                    of non-celebration of the eucharist on Good Friday; but after that date the
                    prohibition of communion became common. In Spain, indeed, it became customary to
                    close the churches altogether as a sign of mourning; but this practice was
                    condemned by the council of Toledo (633). In the Romish Church the Good Friday
                    ritual at present observed is marked by many special features, most of which c⅛n
                    bo traced back to a date at least prior to the close of the 8th century (see the
                    Ordo Romanus in Muratori’s <hi rend="italic">Liturg. Pom. Vet.).</hi> The altar
                    and officiating clergy are draped in black, this being the only day on which
                    that colour is permitted. Instead of the epistle, sundry passages from Hosea,
                    Habakkuk, Exodus, and the Psalms are read. The gospel for the day consists of
                    the history of the passion as recorded by St John. The reading of this is
                    followed by bidding prayers for the peace and unity of the church, for the pope,
                    the clergy, all ranks and conditions of men, the sovereign, for catechumens, the
                    sick and afflicted, heretics and schismatics, Jews and heathen. Then follows the
                    “adoration of the cross” (a ceremony said to date back to near the time of
                    Helena’s “invention of the cross”); the hymns <hi rend="italic">Pange</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Lingua</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Vexilla Pegis</hi> are sung, and
                    the reserved host brought out and partaken of by the priest. In many Roman
                    Catholic countries, as, for example, in Spain, it is usual with the faithful to
                    spend much time in the churches in meditation on the “seven last words” of the
                    Saviour; no carriages are driven through the streets; the bells and organs are
                    silent; and in every possible way it is sought to deepen the impression of a
                    profound and universal grief. In the Greek Church also the Good Friday fast is
                    excessively strict; as in the Roman Church, the passion history is read and the
                    cross adored; towards evening a dramatic representation of the entombment takes
                    place, amid open demonstrations of contempt for Judas and the Jews. In Lutheran
                    churches the organ is silent on this day; and altar, font, and pulpit are draped
                    in black, as indeed throughout Holy Week. In the Church of England the history
                    of the passion from the gospel according to John is also read; the collects for
                    the day are based upon the bidding prayers which are found in the Ordo
                    Romanus.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
