<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0910-0573-0556-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GEULINCX, Arnold (9th edition, volume 10, page
                    556)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:915833">Ethics</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944037">God</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1091272">Reason</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1091282">Reasoning</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z31nq7b">Ethics</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zg6gc5h">Reason</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46688j6x">Reasoning</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n573/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GEULINCX, <hi rend="smallcaps">Arnold</hi></label>
                    (1625-1669), one of the most distinguished of the earlier Cartesians, was born
                    at Antwerp in 1625. Few details are known with regard to his life, and his more
                    important works are extremely rare. He studied philosophy and medicine at the
                    university of Louvain, and took there the degree of doctor. For twelve years he
                    continued at the same university as lecturer, and was noted as one of the most
                    successful teachera. For what reason he left is quite uncertain, but he seems to
                    have been obliged to fly from Louvain and to take refuge in Leyden, where he
                    appears to have been in the utmost distress. Only the generous assistance of a
                    friend, by name Heidanus, prevented his death from absolute want of means. At
                    Leyden he entered the Protestant Church, having been previously a Catholic, and
                    it has been supposed that his flight from Louvain was due to doubts excited
                    there as to his orthodoxy. This, however, is merely conjecture. In 1663, through
                    his friend Heidanus, he obtained leave to lecture at Leyden, and devoted himself
                    with the utmost zeal to hi3 new duties. He died in 1669. His most important
                    works were published posthumously. During his lifetime there seem to have been
                    made public only the theses which he defended on graduating at Louvain <hi
                    rend="italic">(Saturnalia, sen</hi><hi rend="italic">quoestiones</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">quod-</hi><hi rend="italic">libeticoein</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >utrαmque partem</hi><hi rend="italic">disputata;,</hi> 2d ed. 1665). The <hi
                    rend="italic">Metaphysica vera,</hi> 1691, and the Γvω0ι <hi rend="italic"
                    >σεαυτόν,</hi><hi rend="italic">sive Ethica,</hi><hi rend="italic">post</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">tristia auctoris</hi><hi rend="italic">fata,</hi> 1696 (first
                    part, 1665), are the works by which he is known in the history of philosophy. In
                    addition to these were published <hi rend="italic">Physica</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Vera,</hi><hi rend="italic">Logica restituta,</hi> and J <hi rend="italic"
                    >nnotata in</hi><hi rend="italic">Principia</hi><hi rend="italic">Phüosophioe
                    P.</hi><hi rend="italic">Cartesii.</hi> Geulincx takes up principally the
                    doctrine, left in an obscure and unsatisfactory state by Descartes, of the
                    relation between soul and body. Extension and thought, the essences of spiritual
                    and corporeal natures, are absolutely distinct, and cannot act upon one another.
                    External facts are not the causes of mental states, nor are mental states the
                    causes of physical facts. So far as the physical universe is concerned, we are
                    merely spectators. The influence we seem by will to exercise over bodies is only
                    apparent; volition and action only accompany one another. I cannot be the author
                    of any state of which I am unconscious, for my very nature is consciousness; but
                    I am not conscious of the mechanism by which bodily motion is produced, hence I
                    am not the author of bodily motion. Body and mind are like two clocks which act
                    together, because at each instant they are adjusted by God. A physical
                    occurrence is but the occasion on which God excites in me a corresponding mental
                    state. Geulincx is thus definitely the originator of the theory called
                    Occasionalism. But the principles on which that theory was founded compelled a
                    further advance. God, who is the cause of the concomitance of bodily and mental
                    facts, is in truth the sole cause in the universe. No fact contains in itself
                    the ground of any other; the existence of the facts is due to God, their
                    sequence and co-existence are also due to him. He is the ground of all that is.
                    My desire3 or volitions and my thoughts are thus the desires, volitions, or
                    thoughts of God. Apart from God, the finite being has no reality. Geulincx is
                    thus the precursor of Spinoza, and, like Spinoza, he gave out his final results
                    under the title of Ethics. Descartes had left untouched, or nearly so, the
                    difficult problem of the relation between the universal element or thought and
                    the particular desires or inclinations. All these are regarded by Geulincx as
                    modes of the divine thought and action, and accordingly the end of human
                    endeavour is the end of divine will, or the realization of reason. The love of
                    right reason is the supreme virtue, whence flow the cardinal virtues, diligence,
                    obedience, justice, and humility. Liberty is obedience to reason; <hi
                    rend="italic">nemo</hi><hi rend="italic">servit</hi><hi rend="italic">qui
                    rationi</hi><hi rend="italic">servit.</hi></p>
                <p>Geulincx has not directly touched the problem which evidently must have caused
                    the greatest difficulty to the Cartesians,—how we perceive extended
                    reality,—though he plainly indicates the opinion that we do not perceive it, but
                    have the idea of it from God. He thus carried out to their extreme consequences
                    the irreconcilable elements in the Cartesian metaphysics, and his works have the
                    peculiar value attaching to the vigorous development of a one-sided principle.
                    The abrupt contradictions to which such development leads of necessity compels
                    revision of the principle itself.</p>
                <p>See Damiron, Phil. en France au 17 <hi rend="superscript"> me</hi> siede, 1846;
                    Bouillier, His. de la Bhil. Cartésienne, i. ch. 14; Erdmann, Versuch einer
                    Gesch. d. neu. ΡhU., i., ό., sec. 2; Ritter, Gesch. d. Phil., xi. pp. 97-169
                    (Ritter’s account of Geulincx is the fullest in any history of philosophy); K.
                    Fischer, Gesch. d. neu. Phil., i. 2, 11-27.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
