<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0910-0454-0439-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GERANIUM (9th edition, volume 10, page 439)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:941205">Geraniums</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1056643">Pelargoniums</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1131021">Spurs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:927866">Flowers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:955373">Herbs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hd7nx00">Geranium</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42f7jz4f">Pelargonium</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x63bd91">Spurs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w37kw6x">Flowers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n454/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GERANIUM</label> is the name of a genus of poly petalous
                    exogenous plants, which is taken by botanists as the type of the natural order
                    <hi rend="italic">Geraniaceae.</hi> The name, as a scientific appellation, has a
                    much more restricted application than when taken in its popular sense. Formerly
                    the genus <hi rend="italic">Geranium</hi> was almost conterminous with the order
                    <hi rend="italic">Geraniaceae,</hi> which latter had then a more limited meaning
                    than is given to it by those of our leading botanists of the present day who
                    include in it the <hi rend="italic">Tropaeolaceae,</hi> the <hi rend="italic"
                    >0xali-</hi><hi rend="italic">daceae,</hi> and the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Balsaminaceae.</hi> Then as now the geranium was very popular as a garden
                    plant, and the species included in the original genus became widely known under
                    that name, which has more or less clung to them ever since, in spite of
                    scientific changes which have removed the larger number of them to the genus <hi
                    rend="italic">Pelargonium.</hi> This result has been probably brought about in
                    some degree by an error of the nurserymen, who seem in many cases to have acted
                    on the conclusion that the group commonly known as <hi rend="italic">Scarlet
                    Geraniums</hi> were really geraniums and not pelargoniums, and have in
                    consequence inserted them under the former name in their trade catalogues. In
                    fact it may be said that, from a popular point of view, the pelargoniums of the
                    botanist are better known as geraniums than are the geraniums themselves.</p>
                <p>The species of <hi rend="italic">Geranium</hi> bear the English name of
                    Cranesbill, and consist mostly of herbs, of annual or perennial duration,
                    dispersed throughout the temperate regions of the world. They number nearly a
                    hundred, and bear a considerable family resemblance. The leaves are for the most
                    part palmately-lobed, and the flowers are regular, consisting of five sepals,
                    five imbricating petals, alternating with five glandules at their base, ten
                    stamens, and a beaked ovary. Some dozen or more species are natives of the
                    British Isles; and many of those of exotic origin form handsome border plants in
                    our gardens of hardy perennials. Amongst these <hi rend="italic">G. ibericum, G.
                    platypetalum,</hi><hi rend="italic">G. sanguineum,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >G.</hi><hi rend="italic">Backhousianum,</hi> and the double-flowered varieties
                    of <hi rend="italic">G.</hi><hi rend="italic">pratense</hi> are conspicuous. The
                    genus is not without its virtues, <hi rend="italic">G. maculatum</hi> being the
                    alum-root of North America, used there as an astringent in diarrhoea, dysentery,
                    and such like complaints, while the native Herb Robert of English hedgesides,
                    <hi rend="italic">G. Robertianum,</hi> which is both astringent and aromatic, is
                    used as a remedy in nephritic disorders.</p>
                <p>From these regular-flowered herbs, with which they had been mixed up by the
                    earlier botanists, L’Heritier in 1787 separated those plants which have since
                    borne the name of <hi rend="italic">Pelargonium,</hi> and which, though agreeing
                    with them in certain points of structure, differ in others which are admitted to
                    be of generic value. One obvious distinction of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Pelargonium</hi> is that the flowers are irregular, the two petals which stand
                    uppermost being different—larger, smaller, or differently marked—from the other
                    three, which latter are occasionally wanting. This difference of irregularity
                    the modern florist has done very much to annul, for the increased size given to
                    the flowers by high breeding has usually been accompanied by the enlargement of
                    the smaller petals, so that a very near approach to regularity has been in some
                    cases attained. Another well-marked difference however remains in <hi
                    rend="italic">Pelargonium:</hi> the back or dorsal sepal is furnished with a
                    hollow spur, which spur is adnate, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> joined for its
                    whole length with the flower-stalk; while in <hi rend="italic">Geranium</hi>
                    there is no spur. This peculiarity is best seen by cutting clean through the
                    flower-stalk just behind the flower, when in <hi rend="italic">Pelargonium</hi>
                    there will be seen the hollow tube of the spur, which in the case of <hi
                    rend="italic">Geranium</hi> will not be found as it does not exist, but the
                    stalk will appear as a solid mass. There are other characters which support
                    those already pointed out, such as the absence of the glandules, and the
                    declination of the stamens; but the features already described offer the most
                    ready and obvious distinctions.</p>
                <p>To recapitulate, the geraniums properly so-called are regular-flowered herbs with
                    the flower stalks solid, while many geraniums falsely so-called in popular
                    language are really pelargoniums, and may be distinguished by their irregular
                    flowers and hollow flower stalks. In a great majority of cases too, the
                    pelargoniums so commonly met with in greenhouses and summer parterres are of
                    shrubby or sub-shrubby habit.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
