<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0910-0761-0738-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GOGOL, Nikolai Vasilievich (9th edition, volume 10,
                    page 738)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1137041">Success</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1432098">Soul</term>
                    <term ref="fast:998642">Lighting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:998476">Light</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1131648">Stars</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9785q">Success</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sx64900">Soul</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zh9p">Stage</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rn1g">Light</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4086357g">Stars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40r9m438">Brigands</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4639k84f">Farms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qp5f">Farming</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n761/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GOGOL, <hi rend="smallcaps">Nikolai Vasilievich</hi></label>
                    (1809-1852), was born in the province of Poltava, in South Russia, March 31,
                    1809. Educated at the Niejin gymnasium, he there started a manuscript
                    periodical, “The Star,” and wrote several pieces including a tragedy, <hi
                    rend="italic">The Brigands.</hi> Having completed his course at Niejin, he went
                    in 1829 to St Petersburg, where he tried the stage but failed. Next year he
                    obtained a clerkship in the department of appanages, but he soon gave it up. Tn
                    literature, however, he found his true vocation. In 1829 he published
                    anonymously a poem called <hi rend="italic">Italy,</hi> and, under the pseudonym
                    of V. Alof, an idyll, <hi rend="italic">Hans Kuchel Garten,</hi> which he had
                    written while still at Niejin. The idyll was so ridiculed by a reviewer that its
                    author bought up all the copies he could secure, and burnt them in a room which
                    he hired for the purpose at an iun. Gogol then fell back upon South Russian
                    popular literature, and especially the tales of Cossackdom on which his boyish
                    fancy had been nursed, his father having occupied the post of “regimental
                    secretary,” one of the honorary officials in the Zaporogian Cossack forces. In
                    1830 he published in a periodical the first of the stories which appeared next
                    year under the title of <hi rend="italic">Evenings in a Farm near Dikanka: by
                    Rudy Ranko.</hi> This work, containing a series of attractive pictures of that
                    Little-Russian life which lends itself to romance more readily than does the
                    monotony of “Great-Russian” existence, immediately obtained a great success,—
                    its light and colour, its freshness and originality, being hailed with
                    enthusiasm by the principal writers of the day in Russia. Whereupon Gogol
                    planned, not only a history of Little-Russia, but also one of the Middle Ages,
                    to be completed in eight or nine volumes. This plan he did not carry out, though
                    it led to his being appointed to a professorship in the university of St
                    Petersburg, a post in which he met with small success, and which he resigned in
                    1835. Meanwhile he had published his <hi rend="italic">Arabesques,</hi> a
                    collection of essays and stories; his <hi rend="italic">Taras Bulba,</hi> the
                    chief of the <hi rend="italic">Cossack Tales</hi> translated into English by
                    George Tolstoy ∙, and a number of novelettes, which mark his transition from the
                    romantic to the realistic school of fiction, such as the admirable sketch of the
                    tranquil life led iu a quiet country house by two kindly specimens of <hi
                    rend="italic">Old-world Gentlefolks,</hi> or the description of the petty
                    miseries endured by an ill-paid clerk in a Government office, the great object
                    of whose life is to secure the “cloak” from which his story takes its name. To
                    the same period belongs his celebrated comedy, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Revizor,</hi> or Government Inspector. His aim in writing it was to drag into
                    light “all that was bad in Russia,” and to hold it up to contempt. And he
                    succeeded in rendering contemptible and ludicrous the official life of Russia,
                    the corruption universally prevailing throughout the civil service, the
                    alternate arrogance and servility of men in office. The plot of the comedy is
                    very simple. A traveller who arrives with an empty purse at a provincial town is
                    taken for an <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n762/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0910-0762-0739"/> inspector whose arrival is awaited with fear, and
                    he receives all the attentions and bribes which are meant to propitiate the
                    dreaded investigator of abuses. The play appeared on the stage in the spring of
                    1836, and achieved a full success, in spite of the opposition attempted by the
                    official classes whose malpractices it exposed. The aim which Gogol had in view
                    when writing the <hi rend="italic">Revizor</hi> he afterwards fully attained in
                    his great novel, <hi rend="italic">Mertvuiya Dushi,</hi> or Dead Souls, the
                    first part of which appeared in 1842. The hero of the story is an adventurer who
                    goes about Russia making fictitious purchases of “dead souls,” <hi rend="italic"
                    >i.e.,</hi> of serfs who have died since the last census, with the view of
                    pledging his imaginary property to Government. But his adventures are merely an
                    excuse for drawing a series of pictures, of an unfavourable kind, of Russian
                    provincial life, and of introducing on the scene a number of types of Russian
                    society. Of the force and truth with which these delineations are executed the
                    universal consent of Russian critics in their favour may be taken as a measure.
                    From the French version of the story a general idea of its merits may be formed,
                    and some knowledge of its plot and its principal characters may be gathered from
                    the English adaptation published in 1854, as an original work, under the title
                    of <hi rend="italic">Home Life in Russia.</hi> But no one seems to be able fully
                    to appreciate Gogol’s merits as a humorist, who is not intimate with the
                    language in which he wrote as well as with the society which he depicted. In
                    1836 Gogol for the first time went abroad. Subsequently he spent a considerable
                    amount of time out of Russia, chiefly in Italy, where much of his <hi
                    rend="italic">Dead Souls</hi> was written. His residence there, especially at
                    Rome, made a deep impression on his mind, which, during his later years, turned
                    towards mysticism. The last works which he published, his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Confession</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Correspondence ιvith Friends,</hi> offer
                    a painful contrast to the light, bright, vigorous, realistic, humorous writings
                    which had gained and have retained for him his immense popularity in his native
                    land. Asceticism and mystical exaltation had told upon his nervous system, and
                    its feeble condition showed itself in his literary compositions. In 1848 he made
                    a pilgrimage to Jerusalem, and on his return settled down at Moscow, where he
                    died, March 3, 1852, not having quite completed his forty-third year.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
