<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0706-6116-0701-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CIPHER, or Cypher</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 6, page 701</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47659h24">Ciphers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4g44hq0f">Cipher</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:861549">Ciphers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1128747">Spartanism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1072064">Portas</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:815177">Art</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:996779">Letters</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193356116" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CIPHER, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Cypher</hi></label>, one of
                    the Arabic characters or figures used in computation.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Cipher</hi> is also a kind of enigmatic character composed
                    of several letters interwoven, which are generally the initial letters of the
                    person’s names for whom the ciphers are intended. These are frequently used on
                    seals, coaches, and other movables. Anciently, merchants and tradesmen were not
                    allowed to bear arms; but in lieu thereof, they bore their ciphers, or the
                    initial letters of their names, artfully interwoven about a cross, of which we
                    find divers instances on tombs, and other monuments.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Cipher</hi> likewise denotes certain secret characters,
                    disguised and varied, used in writing letters containing some secret, and not to
                    be understood except by those between whom the cipher is agreed on.</p>
                <p>De la Guilletière, in his <hi rend="italic">Lacedaemon Ancient and Modern,</hi>
                    endeavours to make the ancient Spartans the inventors of the art of writing in
                    cipher. Their scytala, according to him, was the first sketch of this mysterious
                    art. The scytalae were two rollers of wood, of equal length and thickness; one
                    of which was kept by the ephori, the other by the general of the army sent on
                    any expedition against the enemy. Whenever those magistrates meant to send any
                    secret orders to the general, they took a slip of parchment and rolled it close
                    round the scytala which they had reserved, and in this state wrote their
                    instructions, which appeared perfect and consistent while the parchment
                    continued on the roll; but when taken off, the writing was maimed, and without
                    connection, though it was easily retrieved by the general upon his applying it
                    to the scytala in his possession. Polybius says that Aeneas Tacitus had
                    collected together twenty different manners of writing, so as not to be
                    understood by any but those in the secret; and that part were invented by
                    himself, and part used before his time. Trithemius, Baptista Porta, Vigenère,
                    and P. Niceron, have written expressly on the subject of ciphers.</p>
                <p>As the writing in cipher has become an art, so the reading or unravelling thereof
                    is called deciphering. The rules of deciphering are different in different
                    languages. By observing the following, any one may read a common cipher written
                    in English.</p>
                <p>1. Observe the letters or characters that most frequently occur, and set them
                    down for the six vowels, including <hi rend="italic">y;</hi> and of these the
                    most frequent will generally be <hi rend="italic">e,</hi> and the least frequent
                    <hi rend="italic">u.</hi></p>
                <p>2. The vowels that most frequently come together are <hi rend="italic">ea</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">ou.</hi></p>
                <p>3. The consonant most common at the end of words is <hi rend="italic">s,</hi> and
                    the next frequent is <hi rend="italic">r</hi> or <hi rend="italic">t.</hi></p>
                <p>4. When two similar characters come together, they are most likely to be the
                    consonants <hi rend="italic">f, l,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">s,</hi> or the
                    vowels <hi rend="italic">e</hi> or <hi rend="italic">o.</hi></p>
                <p>5. The letter that precedes or follows two similar characters is either a vowel,
                    or <hi rend="italic">l, m, n,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">r.</hi></p>
                <p>6. In deciphering, begin with the words that consist, of a single letter, which
                    will be either, <hi rend="italic">a, I, o,</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >&amp;p</hi></p>
                <p>7. Then take the words of two letters, one of which will be a vowel. Of these
                    words the most frequent are, <hi rend="italic">an, to, be, by, of, on, or, no,
                    so, as, at, if, in, is, it, he, me, my, us, we, am.</hi></p>
                <p>8. In words of three letters there are most commonly two consonants. Of these
                    words the most frequent are, <hi rend="italic">the, and, not, but, yet, for,
                    thd, how, why, all, you, she, his, her, our, who, may, can, did, was, are, has,
                    had, let, one, two, six, ten,</hi> &amp;c. Some of these, and words of two
                    letters, will be found in every sentence.</p>
                <p>9. The most common words of four letters are, <hi rend="italic">this, that, then,
                    thus, with, when, from, here, some, most, none, they, them, whom., mine, your,
                    self, must, will, have, been, were, four, five, nine,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                <p>10. The most usual words of five letters are, <hi rend="italic">their, these,
                    those, which, where, while, since, there, shall, might, could, would, ought,
                    three, seven, eight,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                <p>11. Words of two or more syllables frequently begin with double consonants, or
                    with a preposition; that is, a vowel joined with one or more consonants. The
                    most common double consonants are, <hi rend="italic">bl, br, dr,fl,fr, gh, gr,
                    ph, pl, pr, sh, sb, sp, st, th, tr, wh, wr,</hi> &amp;c.; and the most common
                    prepositions are, <hi rend="italic">com, con, de, dis, ex, im, in, int, mis,
                    per, pre, pro, re, sub, sup,</hi><hi rend="italic">un,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                <p>12. The double consonants most frequent at the end of long words are, <hi
                    rend="italic">ch, ld, lf, mn, nd, ng, rl, rm, rn, rp, rt, sm, st, xt,</hi>
                    &amp;c.; and the most common terminations are, <hi rend="italic">ed,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">en,</hi><hi rend="italic">er,</hi><hi rend="italic">es,
                    et,</hi><hi rend="italic">ing, ly, son, sion, tion, able, ence, ent,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">ment,</hi><hi rend="italic">full, less, ness,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                <p>By applying these rules, any common cipher written in English maybe deciphered;
                    and, <hi rend="italic">mutatis</hi><hi rend="italic">mutandis,</hi> a cipher
                    written in any language may be evolved by an application of the principle on
                    which these rules are constructed.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
