<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0706-0474-0267-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CAYLUS, Anne-Claude, Philippe</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 6, page 267</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r48v">Passions</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94k2c">Painters</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hn48">Mothers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bk43">Levant</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1050530">Painters</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1026940">Mothers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193350474" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CAYLUS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Anne-Claude,
                    Philippe</hi></label><hi rend="smallcaps">de Tubieres, de Grimoard, de Pestels,
                    de Levi, Count de,</hi> Marquis d’Esternay, Baron de Bransac, was born at Paris
                    in October 1692. He was the eldest of the two sons of John Count de Caylus,
                    lieutenant-general of the armies of the king of France, and of the marchioness
                    de Villette. His father and mother were very careful of the education of their
                    son. The former instructed him in the profession of arms and in bodily
                    exercises; the latter watched over and fostered the virtues of his mind, and
                    this delicate task she discharged with singular success. The countess was the
                    aunt of Madame de Maintenon, and remarkable alike for the solidity of her
                    understanding and the charms of her wit. She was the author of the agreeable
                    book entitled, The Recollections of Madame de Caylus, of which Voltaire
                    published an elegant edition. The amiable qualities of the mother appeared in
                    the son, but they appeared with a bold and military air. In his natural temper
                    he was gay and sprightly, having a taste for pleasure, a strong passion for
                    independence, and an invincible aversion to the servitude of a court. Count de
                    Caylus was only twelve years of age when his father died at Brussels in 1704.
                    After finishing his exercises, he entered into the corps of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Mousquetaires;</hi> and in his first campaign, in the year 1709,
                    he distinguished himself so much by his valour, that Louis XIV. commended him
                    before all the court, and rewarded him with an ensigncy in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >gens-d’armerie.</hi> In 1711 he commanded a regiment of dragoons, which was
                    called by his own name, and signalized himself at the head of it in Catalonia.
                    In 1713 he was present at the siege of Fribourg, where he was exposed to
                    imminent danger in the bloody attack of the covered way. The peace of Rastadt
                    having left him in a state of inactivity ill suited to his natural temper, his
                    vivacity soon led him to travel into Italy; and his curiosity was greatly
                    excited by the wonders of that country, where antiquity is still fruitful, and
                    produces so many objects to improve the taste and to excite the admiration.
                    After a year’s absence, he returned to Paris with so strong a passion for
                    travelling and for antiquities, that he resolved to quit the army, and to devote
                    himself entirely to these pursuits.</p>
                <p>He had no sooner left the service of Louis than he set out for the Levant; and,
                    having arrived at Smyrna, proceeded to Constantinople, where he made some stay.
                    He next visited Greece, and other countries of the East rich in historical
                    recollections or in ancient monuments; exposed himself to fatigue, the
                    inclemency of the weather, contagion, and even the cupidity of brigands, in
                    order to gratify his desire of knowledge; visited the ruins of Ephesus,
                    including those of Colophon and the temple of Diana, under the escort of robbers
                    belonging to a troop or band called Caracayali; returned to Byzantium by the
                    Dardanelles; and lastly repaired to Adrianople, where the sultan, Mustapha II.,
                    then resided. But in February 1717 he was recalled from the East by the
                    tenderness of his mother. From that time he only left France to make two
                    excursions to London. The Academy of Painting and Sculpture admitted him as an
                    honorary member in the year 1731; and the count, whose ambition it was to
                    deserve such a distinction, spared neither his labour, his credit, nor his
                    fortune, to instruct, assist, and animate the artists. He wrote the lives of the
                    most celebrated painters and engravers who had done honour to this illustrious
                    academy; and, in order to extend the limits of the art, he collected, in three
                    different works, new subjects for painting which he had met with in the works of
                    the ancients.</p>
                <p>Such was his passion for antiquity, that he wished to have had it in his power to
                    bring the whole of it to life again. He saw with regret that the works of the
                    ancient painters were effaced and destroyed almost as soon as they were drawn
                    from the subterranean mansions where they had been buried. But a fortunate
                    accident furnished him with the means of showing the composition and the
                    colouring of the pictures of ancient Rome. The coloured drawings which Pietro S.
                    Bartoli had taken there from antique pictures happening to fall into his hands,
                    he had-them engraved; and, before he enriched the king of France’s cabinet with
                    this production, he published an edition of it at his own expense. It is perhaps
                    the most extraordinary book of antiquities that ever will appear, the whole
                    being painted with a purity and precision which are altogether inimitable. There
                    were only thirty copies published, and there is no reason to expect that there
                    will hereafter be any more.</p>
                <p>Count de Caylus was at the same time engaged in an enterprise not less
                    illustrative of Roman greatness, and still more interesting to the French
                    nation. Colbert had formed the design of engraving the Roman antiquities which
                    are still to be seen in the southern provinces of France; and by his orders
                    Mignard the architect had made drawings of them, which Count de Caylus had the
                    good fortune to recover. He therefore resolved to finish the work begun by
                    Colbert, and to dedicate it to that great minister; and so much had he this
                    enterprise at heart, that he was employed in it during his last illness, and
                    warmly recommended it to Μ. Mariette.</p>
                <p>In 1742 Count Caylus was admitted as an honorary member of the Academy of Belles
                    Lettres; and then it was that he seemed to have found the place for which nature
                    designed him. The study of literature now became his ruling passion; he
                    consecrated to it his time and his fortune; he even renounced his pleasures to
                    give himself wholly up to the object of making some discovery in the field of
                    antiquity. But amidst the fruits of his research and invention nothing afforded
                    him so much gratification as his discovery of encaustic painting. A description
                    of Pliny, too concise to give a clear view of the matter to an ordinary reader,
                    suggested the idea of this art to Μ. de Caylus. He availed himself of the
                    friendship and skill of Μ. Magault, a physician in Paris, and an excellent
                    chemist; and by repeated experiments discovered the secret of incorporating wax
                    with various tints and colours, and of rendering it manageable with the pencil.
                    Pliny has made mention of two kinds of encaustic painting practised by the
                    ancients, one of which was executed with wax on various substances, and the
                    other upon ivory with hot punches of iron. It was the former kind, however, that
                    Count de Caylus had <pb break="no" facs="nls:193350487"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0706-0487-0268"/>the merit of reviving; and Μ. Muntz afterwards
                    made many experiments in order to carry it to perfection.</p>
                <p>In the hands of Count Caylus, literature and the arts lent each other mutual aid.
                    But it would be endless to give an account of all his works. He published above
                    forty dissertations in the Memoirs of the Academy of Belles-Lettres. To the
                    artists he was particularly attentive; and in order to prevent their falling
                    into mistakes from ignorance of costume, which the ablest of them have sometimes
                    done, he founded a prize of five hundred livres, the object of which was to
                    explain, by means of authors and monuments, the usages of ancient nations. In
                    order that he might enjoy with the whole world the treasures which he had
                    collected, he caused them to be engraved, and gave a learned description of them
                    in a work which he embellished with eight hundred copperplates.</p>
                <p>The strength of his constitution seemed to give him hopes of a long life; but a
                    humour settling in one of his legs, entirely destroyed his health, and he
                    expired on the 5th of September 1765. His character is thus drawn by a French
                    biographer:—“A severe probity, a rooted aversion to flattery, great indifference
                    about honours, a singular simplicity, perhaps sometimes a little despotism in
                    his opinions, formed the basis of his character. In him young artists found both
                    a guide and a friend; and with a discernment and a delicacy still more rare than
                    generosity, he anticipated the wants of those whose progress would have been
                    otherwise retarded by the narrowness of their means. Naturally beneficent, he
                    sometimes amused himself when he met a pauper whose appearance indicated
                    probity, by giving him a louis to get changed, and then concealing himself where
                    he could enjoy the poor creature’s embarrassment when the person from whom he
                    received the gold was not to be found. Caylus, indeed, never knew any other
                    luxury than that of liberality. His dress, in particular, was so plain that,
                    having one day stopped before a shop on which a sign-painter was painting a
                    figure of St Francis, the latter, taking him for one of his comrades, asked his
                    opinion respecting the work, which Caylus instantly gave him, and which
                    delighted the painter so much, that he put the pallet and pencil into the hand
                    of his new acquaintance, and begged him to retouch the picture. Caylus mounted
                    the ladder, and having succeeded to the entire satisfaction of the painter, the
                    latter wished to take him to a neighbouring tavern, when the carriage of the
                    Count arrived, and his footman opened the door for his master. The painter of
                    saints and signs was stupefied with astonishment; but Caylus, taking him by the
                    hand, said, <hi rend="italic">Au revoir, camarade, ce sera pour la première fois
                    que nous nous rencontrerons.</hi><sic>"</sic></p>
                <p>The numerous literary works of Count Caylus may be divided into three classes;
                    humorous pieces and romances; productions relative to the fine arts; and those
                    which treat exclusively of antiquities. I. The first class consists of, 1. <hi
                    rend="italic">Les Eccosseuses, ou les Oeufs de Pâques,</hi> Troyes, 1739 et
                    1745, 12mo; 2. <hi rend="italic">Histoire</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                    Guillaume,</hi><hi rend="italic">cocher,</hi> 12mo; 3. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Féeries</hi><hi rend="italic">Nozwdles,</hi> Paris, 1742, 2 vols. 12mo; 4. <hi
                    rend="italic">Soirées du Bois de Boulogne,</hi> Paris, 1742, 12mo; 5. <hi
                    rend="italic">Etrennes de la St Jean,</hi> in conjunction with Moncrieff,
                    Crebillon the younger, Duelos, La Chaussé, Voisenon, and others; 6. <hi
                    rend="italic">Contes Orientaux,</hi> 1743,12mo; 7. <hi rend="italic">Histoire de
                    Mlle. Cronel, dite Frxtillon {Mlle. Clairon),</hi> Paris 1743, 12mo; 8. <hi
                    rend="italic">Histoires Nouvelles et Mémoires ramassés,</hi> Paris, 1743; 9. <hi
                    rend="italic">Quelques Aventures des Bals de Bois,</hi> 1745, 12mo; 10. <hi
                    rend="italic">Cinq Contes des</hi><hi rend="italic">Fees,</hi> 1745, İ2mo; 11.
                    <hi rend="italic">Recueil de ces Messieurs,</hi> 1745, 12mo; 12. <hi
                    rend="italic">Les Manteaux,</hi> Paris, 1746, 12mo; 13. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Les</hi><hi rend="italic">Fetes</hi><hi rend="italic">roulantes et les Regrets
                    des petites mies,</hi> 1747, 12mo; 14. <hi rend="italic">Mémoires de</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">l’</hi><hi rend="italic">Academie des Colporteurs,</hi> 1748, 8vo;
                    15. <hi rend="italic">Le Calsandre fidèle,</hi> translated from the Italian of
                    Marini, Paris, 1740, 3 vols. 12mo; 16. <hi rend="italic">Histoire du
                    Vaillant</hi><hi rend="italic">Chevalier Tyran-le-Blanc,</hi> translated from
                    the Spanish, London, 1775, 3 vols. 12mo; with some other pieces which are
                    attributed to him. II. His works relating to the fine arts are, 1. <hi
                    rend="italic">Nouveaux Sujets de Peintre et</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                    Sculpture,</hi> Paris, 1755, 12mo; 2. <hi rend="italic">Tableaux tires de
                    l’Iliade, de l’</hi><hi rend="italic">Odyssée et</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                    l’Enéide,</hi><hi rend="italic">avec des Observations generales sur le
                    Costume,</hi> Paris, 1757, 8vo; 3. <hi rend="italic">Histoire d’Hercule
                    le</hi><hi rend="italic">Thebain,</hi> Paris, 1758, 8vo; 4. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Les Vies de Mignard et de</hi><hi rend="italic">Lemoyne</hi> in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Recueil des premiers Peintres du Roi,</hi> Paris, 1752, 8vo; 5.
                    <hi rend="italic">Mémoire sur la Peinture a</hi><hi rend="italic">l’</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Encaustique,</hi> 1755, 8vo; 6. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Descriptiori</hi><hi rend="italic">d’un tableau représentant la sacrifice
                    d’Iphigénie,</hi> 1757, 12mo; 7. <hi rend="italic">Vie</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >d’Edme</hi><hi rend="italic">Bozichardon,</hi> Paris, 1762, 12mo. III. Ilis
                    works relative to antiquities are, 1. <hi rend="italic">Recueil</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">d’Antiquités Egyptiennes,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Etrzisques,</hi><hi rend="italic">Grecques, Romaines, et Gauloises,</hi> Paris,
                    1752, and the years following, 7 vols. 4to; 2. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Numismata</hi><hi rend="italic">Azirea</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Imperatorum</hi><hi rend="italic">Romanorzιm,</hi> without date, 4to, very
                    rare; <hi rend="italic">Recueil de Médailles du Cabinet du Roi,</hi> no date,
                    4to, also very rare; 4. <hi rend="italic">Dissertation sur le Papyrus,</hi>
                    Paris, 1758, 4to, in the <hi rend="italic">Mémoires de</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >l’Academie des Inscriptions;</hi></p>
                <p>5. <hi rend="italic">Recueil de Peintures antiqzies,</hi> Paris, 1757, fol.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
