<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0706-9837-0218-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CASSINI, Johannes</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 6, page 218</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:925697">Fires</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:925173">Fire</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4df6k36b">Earth</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6j598">Charts</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4m32nc36">Fires</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b40k26c70">Fire</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k877">Research</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48s4jt2v">Heights</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kn24">Glass</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193349837" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CASSINI, <hi rend="smallcaps">Johannes</hi></label><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Dominicus,</hi> an excellent astronomer, was born at Piedmont
                    in 1635. His early proficiency in astronomy procured him an invitation to become
                    mathematical professor at Bologna when he was only fifteen years of age; and a
                    comet having appeared in 1652, he discovered that bodies of this kind are not
                    accidental meteors, but of the same nature, and probably governed by the same
                    laws, as the planets. In the same year he solved a problem abandoned by Kepler
                    and Bullialdus as insolvable; which was to determine geometrically the apogee
                    and eccentricity of a planet from its true and mean place. In 1663 he was
                    appointed inspector-general of the fortifications of the castle of Urbino, and
                    had afterwards the care of all the rivers in the ecclesiastical states. He
                    still, however, prosecuted his astronomical studies, in the course of which he
                    discovered the revolution of Mars round his own axis; and in 1666 he published
                    his theory of Jupiter’s satellites. Cassini was invited by Louis XIV. in 1669 to
                    visit France, where he settled as the first professor in the royal observatory.
                    In 1677 he demonstrated the line of Jupiter’s diurnal rotation; and in 1684
                    discovered four more satellites belonging to Saturn, Huygens having observed
                    one. Cassini was principally instrumental in causing the French government
                    undertake the expedition to Cayenne, which served to correct many errors
                    relative to the figure of the earth, at the same time that it demonstrated the
                    decrease of the intensity of terrestrial gravity from the equator to the poles;
                    a phenomenon which exhibits a striking confirmation of the theory of
                    gravitation. In 1693 he published new tables of the satellites of Jupiter, more
                    exact than those which he had given to the world in 1668. In 1693 he went to
                    revisit his meridian of St Pétrone, which he regarded with honest pride; but he
                    was now occupied with another and much longer meridian, commenced in 1669 by
                    Picard,, continued to the north of Paris in 1683 by De Lahirc, and lastly, in
                    1700, carried by Cassini himself to the extremity of Roussillon; being the same
                    line which, forty years after, was measured anew by François Cassini and La
                    Caille, and, at the same distance of a century, measured a third time by Méchain
                    and Delambre, with a precision which left little more to be desired. In the last
                    years of his life he lost his sight, a misfortune which befel him in common with
                    Galileo, and which probably proceeded from the same cause, namely, excessive
                    application to the delicate observations of astronomy. Cassini inhabited the
                    royal observatory at Paris more than forty years, and died on the 14th September
                    1712, “sans maladie, sans douleur, uniquement par la nécessite de mourir.” In
                    Lalande’s <hi rend="italic">Ei-bliograj)hie</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Astronomique</hi> will be found a complete enumeration of the various works of
                    Cassini; we need only cite here, I. <hi rend="italic">Observationes</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Cometoe Ann.</hi> 1655 ct 1653, Modena, 1653, fol.; 2. <hi
                    rend="italic">Opera</hi><hi rend="italic">Astronomica,</hi> Rome, 166G,' 3. <hi
                    rend="italic">Nuntii</hi><hi rend="italic">Syderei</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Interpres</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> 4. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cosmographie.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Cassini,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >James,</hi> another celebrated astronomer, the only son of the former. He was
                    born at Paris on the 18th February 1677. His early studies were conducted in his
                    father’s house, where, from the pursuits and studies of his father, mathematics,
                    and their application to astronomy, were probably not neglected. He afterwards
                    became a student at the Mazarin College, at the time that the celebrated
                    Varignon was professor of mathematics. With the assistance of this eminent man,
                    young Cassini made such progress, that at fifteen years of age he supported a
                    mathematical thesis with great honour. At the age of seventeen he was admitted
                    as a member of the Academy of Sciences; and the same year he accompanied his
                    father in a journey to Italy, where he assisted him in the verification of the
                    meridian at Bologna and in other measurements. After his return he performed
                    similar operations in Holland, and discovered some errors in the measurement of
                    the earth by Snell, the result of which was communicated to the academy in 1702.
                    In 1696 he also made a visit to England, where he was elected a member of the
                    Royal Society. In 1712 he succeeded his father as astronomer-royal at the
                    observatory of Paris. In 1717 he gave to the academy his researches on the
                    distance of the fixed stars, in which he showed that the whole annual orbit, of
                    near two hundred millions of miles diameter, is but as a point in comparison of
                    their distance. The same year he also communicated his discoveries concerning
                    the inclination of the orbits of the satellites in general, and especially of
                    those of Saturn’s satellites and ring. In 1725 he undertook to determine the
                    cause of the moon’s libration, by which she shows sometimes a little on the one
                    side, and sometimes a little on the other, of that half which is commonly
                    behind, or hid from our view.</p>
                <p>In 1732 an important question in astronomy engaged the ingenuity of our author.
                    His father had determined, by his observations, that the planet Venus revolved
                    about her axis in the space of twenty-three hours; and Μ. Bain-chini had
                    published a work in 1729, in which he settled the period of the same revolution
                    in twenty-four days eight hours. From an examination of Bianchini’s
                    observations, which were upon the spots in Venus, he discovered that he had
                    intermitted his observations for the space of three hours, from which cause he
                    had probably mistaken new spots for the old ones, and so had been led into the
                    mistake. He also determined the nature and quantity of the acceleration of the
                    motion of Jupiter at half a second per year, and of that of the retardation of
                    Saturn at two minutes per year; also that these quantities would go on
                    increasing for two thousand years, and then would decrease again. In 1740 he
                    published his Astronomical Tables, and his Elements of Astronomy; both very
                    extensive and accurate works.</p>
                <p>Although astronomy was the principal object of our author’s pursuit, he did not
                    confine himself absolutely to that science, but made occasional excursions into
                    other fields. We owe to him Experiments on Electricity; Experiments on the
                    Recoil of Fire-arms; Researches on the Rise of the Mercury in the Barometer at
                    different Heights; Reflections on the perfecting of Burning-glasses; and other
                    interesting memoirs.</p>
                <p>One of the most important objects of the French academy was the measurement of
                    the earth. In 1669 Picard measured a little more than a degree of latitude to
                    the north of Paris; but as that extent appeared too small from which to deduce
                    the whole circumference with sufficient accuracy, it was resolved to continue
                    the measurement on the meridian of Paris to the north and the south, throughout
                    the whole extent of the country. Accordingly, <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193349850" xml:id="kp-eb0706-9850-0219"/>in 1683, M. de Lahire
                    continued that on the north side of Paris, and the older Cassini that on the
                    south side, while, in the continuation of this operation, the latter was, in
                    1700, assisted by his son. The same work was further continued by the same
                    academicians; and finally, the part left unfinished by Dc Lahire in the north
                    was finished in 1718 by our author, Maraldi, and De Lahire the younger.</p>
                <p>These operations produced a very considerable degree of precision. From this
                    measured extent of six degrees, it appeared also that the degrees were of
                    different lengths in different parts of the meridian; and our author concluded,
                    in the volume published for 1718, that they decreased more and more towards the
                    pole, and that therefore the figure of the earth was that of an oblong spheroid,
                    or having its axis longer than the equatorial diameter. He also measured a
                    perpendicular to the same meridian, and compared the measured distance with the
                    differences of longitude as before determined by the eclipses of Jupiter’s
                    satellites; from which he concluded that the length of the degrees of longitude
                    was smaller than it would be on a sphere, and that therefore again the figure of
                    the earth was that of an oblong spheroid, contrary to the determination of
                    Newton by the theory of gravity. Newton was indeed of all men the most averse
                    from controversy; but the other mathematicians in Britain did not tamely submit
                    to conclusions in direct opposition to the fundamental doctrine of this great
                    philosopher. The consequence was, that the French government sent two different
                    sets of mathematicians, the one to measure a degree at the equator, the other at
                    the polar circle; and the comparison of the whole determined the figure to be
                    that of an oblate spheroid, contrary to the conclusion of Cassini.</p>
                <p>After a long and laborious life, James Cassini died in April 1756, and was
                    succeeded in the academy and observatory by his second son. He published, 1. <hi
                    rend="italic">Expanse d la Dissertation de Μ. Celsius</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >sur</hi><hi rend="italic">les Observations</hi><hi rend="italic">faites</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">pour</hi><hi rend="italic">pouvoir</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >determiner la figure de la Terre,</hi> 1738, 8vo; 2. <hi rend="italic">Εlemens
                    d</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">Astronomie,</hi> Paris, 1740, 4to; 3. <hi
                    rend="italic">Tables</hi><hi rend="italic">Astronomiques du Soleil,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">de la Tune, des</hi><hi rend="italic">Planetes,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">des Etoiles,</hi><hi rend="italic">ei</hi><hi rend="italic">des
                    Satellites,</hi> Paris, 1740, 4to.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Cassini</hi><hi rend="italic">de Thury, Coesar
                    François,</hi> a celebrated French astronomer, director of the observatory, and
                    member of most of the learned societies of Europe, was born at Paris on the 17th
                    June 1714. He was .the second son of James Cassini, whose occupations and
                    talents he inherited and supported with great honour. He received his first
                    lessons in astronomy and mathematics from MM. Maraldi and Camus; and made such
                    rapid progress, that when he was not more than ten years of age he calculated
                    the phases of a total eclipse of the sun. At the age of eighteen he accompanied
                    his father in his two journeys undertaken to draw a perpendicular to the
                    meridian of the observatory, from Strasburg to Brest. A general chart of France
                    was then projected; and for this purpose it was necessary to traverse the
                    country by several lines parallel and perpendicular to the meridian of Paris.
                    Our author was charged with the conduct of this work, in the execution of which
                    he was so scrupulous as to measure again what had been previously measured by
                    his father. This great work was published in 1740, with a chart showing the new
                    meridian of Paris, by two different series of triangles, passing along the
                    sea-coasts to Bayonne, traversing the frontiers of Spain tothe Mediterranean and
                    Antibes, and thence passingalong the eastern limits of France to Dunkirk, with
                    par√lel and perpendicular lines drawn at the distances respectively of 6000
                    toises from side to side of the country.</p>
                <p>In 1741 he made a tour in Flanders, in the train of the king; and this gave rise,
                    at his majesty’s instance, to the chart of France; in relation to which Cassini
                    published different works, as well as a great number of the sheets of the chart
                    itself. In 1761 he undertook an expedition into Germany, for the purpose of
                    continuing to Vienna the perpendicular of the Parisian meridian, in order to
                    unite the triangles of the chart of France with the points taken in Germany, to
                    prepare the means of extending into that country the plan adopted in France, and
                    thus to establish successively for all Europe a most useful uniformity. He was
                    at Vienna the 6th of June 1761, the day of the transit of the planet Venus over
                    the sun’s disc, a phenomena which he observed as accurately as the state of the
                    weather would permit him to do, and of which he published an account in his <hi
                    rend="italic">Voyage en Allemagne.</hi></p>
                <p>Cassini, always meditating the perfection of his grand design, profited by the
                    peace of 1783 to propose the joining of certain points taken upon the English
                    coast with those which had been determined on the coast of France, and thus
                    connecting the general chart of the latter with that of the British isles, as he
                    had before united it with those of Flanders and Germany. The proposal was
                    favourably received by the English government, and carried into effect by <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi> General Roy, under the direction of the Royal
                    Society'.</p>
                <p>Between the years 1735 and 1770, Μ. Cassini published, in the memoirs of the
                    French Academy, a great number of pieces, consisting chiefly of astronomical
                    observations and questions, among which maybe mentioned researches concerning
                    the parallax of the sun, the moon, Mars, and Venus; remarks on astronomical
                    refractions, and the effect caused in their quantity and laws by the weather;
                    numerous observations on the obliquity of the ecliptic, and on the law of its
                    variations. He cultivated astronomy during half a century, the most important
                    for that science that ever elapsed, on account of the magnitude and variety of
                    the objects that had been investigated, in all which Cassini commonly sustained
                    a principal share.</p>
                <p>Μ. Cassini was of a very strong and vigorous constitution, which carried him
                    through the many laborious operations in geography and astronomy which he had
                    conducted. An habitual retention of urine, however, rendered the last twelve
                    years of his life very painful and distressing, till at length it was terminated
                    by the small-pox, on the 4th of September 1784, in the seventy-first year of his
                    age. He was succeeded in the academy, and as director of the observatory, by his
                    only son John Dominic Cassini, the fourth in order of direct descent who filled
                    that honourable station. The following is a pretty correct list of his works,
                    viz. 1. <hi rend="italic">La Méridienne</hi><hi rend="italic">del'</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Observatoire</hi><hi rend="italic">Royal de Paris,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">vérifiée dans toute</hi><hi rend="italic">l’</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >étendue du Royaume, avec</hi><hi rend="italic">des Observations cľ</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Histoire Naturelle</hi><hi rend="italic">par Lemonnier,</hi> 1744,
                    4to; 2. <hi rend="italic">Cartes</hi><hi rend="italic">des</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Triangles</hi><hi rend="italic">de la France</hi> (avec Maraldi), 1744, 4to; 3.
                    <hi rend="italic">Additions aux Tables</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Astronomiques</hi><hi rend="italic">de Cassini,</hi> 1756, 4to; 4. <hi
                    rend="italic">Relation de deux Voyages faits</hi><hi rend="italic">en</hi> 1761
                    <hi rend="italic">et</hi> 1762 <hi rend="italic">en Allemagne, pour</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">determiner</hi><hi rend="italic">la grandeur des degrés de
                    longitude, par rapport a la géographie et a</hi><hi rend="italic">l’</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">astronomie,</hi> 1763, 4to; 5. <hi rend="italic">Opuscules
                    Divers,</hi> 1771, 8vo; 6. <hi rend="italic">Description</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >d</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">un instrument pour prendre hauteur, et pour trouver
                    l’heure vraie sans aucun calcul,</hi> 1770, 4to; 7. <hi rend="italic">Relation
                    d’un Voyage en Allemagne, qui comprend les opérations relatives a la figure de
                    la terre et à la géographie particulière du Palatinat,</hi> etc. 1775, 4to; 8.
                    <hi rend="italic">Description Géométrique de la Terre,</hi> 1775, 4to; 9. <hi
                    rend="italic">Description Geometrique de la France,</hi> 1784, 4to. He also
                    edited <hi rend="italic">Observations sur la Comète de</hi> 1531, <hi
                    rend="italic">pendant le temps de son retour en</hi> 1652, faites par J. D.
                    Cassini, 1759, 12mo.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
