<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0706-1332-0333-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CHASE, or Chace</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 6, page 333</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s53t">Normans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4x63b58d">Kindness</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4707wx1r">Ships</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n5c">Shipping</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4pg1hs5x">Gun</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:987598">Kindness</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:932562">Foresters</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1150446">Thrones</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1042815">Objectivity</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1039127">Normans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193351332" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CHASE, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Chace</hi></label>, is a place
                    of retreat for deer and wild beasts, of a middle kind between a forest and a
                    park, being usually less than a forest, and not possessed of so many privileges.
                    The following history of the English chase is given by Mr Pennant <hi
                    rend="italic">(British Zool.</hi> i. 42): “At first the beasts of chase had this
                    whole island for their range; they knew no other limits than the ocean, nor
                    confessed any particular master. When the Saxons had established themselves in
                    the heptarchy, they vyere reserved by each sovereign for his own particular
                    diversion. Hunting and war in those uncivilized ages were the only employ of the
                    great; their active but uncultivated minds being susceptible of no pleasures but
                    those of a violent kind, such as gave exercise to their bodies, and prevented
                    the pain of thinking.</p>
                <p>“But as the Saxon kings only appropriated those lands to the use of forests which
                    were unoccupied, so no individuals received any injury; but when the conquest
                    had settled the Norman line on the throne, this passion for the chase was
                    carried to an excess which involved every civil right in a general ruin: it
                    superseded the consideration of religion even in a superstitious age; the
                    village communities, nay, even the most sacred edifices, were turned into one
                    vast waste, to make room for animals, the objects of a lawless tyrant’s
                    pleasure. The New Forest in Hampshire is too trite an instance to be dwelt on;
                    sanguinary laws w ere enacted to preserve the game; and in the reigns of William
                    Rufus and Henry I. it was less criminal to destroy one of the human species than
                    a beast of chase. Thus it continued while the Norman line filled the throne; but
                    when the Saxon line was restored under Henry II. the rigour of the forest laws
                    was immediately softened.</p>
                <p>“When our barons began to form a power, they claimed a vast but more limited
                    tract for a diversion that the English were always fond of. They were very
                    jealous of any encroachments on their respective bounds, which were often the
                    cause of deadly feuds. Such a one gave cause to the fatal battle of <hi
                    rend="italic">Chevy-chase,</hi> a fact which, though recorded only in a ballad,
                    may, from what we know of the manners of the times, be founded on truth; not
                    that it was attended with all the circumstances which the author of that natural
                    but heroic composition has given it; for on that day neither a <hi rend="italic"
                    >Percy</hi> nor a <hi rend="italic">Douglas</hi> fell. Here the poet seems to
                    have claimed his privilege, and mixed with this fray some of the events of the
                    battle of <hi rend="italic">Otterbourne.</hi></p>
                <p>“When property became happily more divided by the relaxation of the féodal
                    tenures, those extensive hunting grounds became more limited; and as tillage and
                    husbandry increased, the beasts of chase were obliged to give way to others more
                    useful to the community. The vast tracts of land before dedicated to hunting w
                    ere then contracted, and, in proportion as the useful arts gained ground, either
                    lost their original destination, or gave rise to the invention of <hi
                    rend="italic">parks.</hi> Liberty and the arts seem coeval; for when once the
                    latter got footing, the former protected the labours of the industrious from
                    being ruined by the licentious sportsman, or being devoured by the objects of
                    his diversion. For this reason the subjects of a despotic government still
                    experience the inconveniences of vast wastes and forests, the terrors of the
                    neighbouring husbandmen, while in our well-regulated monarchy very few chases
                    remain. The English still indulge themselves in the pleasures of hunting, but
                    confine the deer kind to parks, of which England boasts of more than any other
                    kingdom in Europe. The laws allow every man his pleasure, but confine them in
                    such bounds as to prevent them from being injurious to the meanest of the
                    community. Before the reformation the prelates seem to have guarded sufficiently
                    against this want of amusement, the see of Norwich in particular being possessed
                    about that time of thirteen parks.”</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Chase,</hi> in the sea language, is to pursue a ship, which
                    is also called <hi rend="italic">giving chase.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Chase-Guns</hi> are guns which are either in the head, when they are used in
                    chasing others, or in the stern, where they are only useful in the event of
                    pursuit by any other ship.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193351345" xml:id="kp-eb0706-1345-0334"/>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Wild-goose</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Chase,</hi> a term
                    used to express a sort of racing on horseback formerly practised, resembling the
                    flying of wild geese; those birds generally going in a train one after another,
                    not in confused flocks as other birds do. In this sort of race the two horses,
                    after running twelve score yards, had liberty, which horse soever could get the
                    lead, to take what ground the jockey pleased, the hindmost horse being bound to
                    follow him within a certain distance agreed on by the articles, or else to be
                    whipped in by the triers and judges who rode by; and whichever horse could
                    distance the other won the race. This sort of racing was not long in common use;
                    for it was found inhuman, and destructive of good horses, when two such were
                    matched together. For in this case neither was able to distance the other till
                    they were both ready to sink under their riders; and often two very good horses
                    were both spoiled, and the wagers forced to be drawn at last. The mischief of
                    this sort of racing soon brought in the method now in use, of only running over
                    a certain quantity of ground, and determining the plate or wager by coming in
                    first at the winning-post.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
