<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0706-6610-0739-01" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">CLERGY</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 6, page 739</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4445hc9k">Indexes</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4000049q">Indexing</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tw3f">Hawking</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qj2t">Hawks</term><term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b4p843w5c">Hand</term><term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term><term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term><term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s347">Trials</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="11" ref="fasttopic:950823">Hand</term><term n="9" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term><term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1047359">Order</term><term n="7" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1156290">Trials</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:968979">Indexing</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:968971">Indexers</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:968973">Indexes</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193356610" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">CLERGY</label>, a general name given to the body of
                    ecclesiastics belonging to the Christian church, in contradistinction to the
                    laity.</p><p>The distinction of Christians into clergy and laity was derived from the Jewish,
                    and adopted into the Christian church, by the apostles themselves. Whenever any
                    number of converts was made, as soon as they were capable of being formed into a
                    congregation or church, a bishop or presbyter, with a deacon, was ordained to
                    minister to them. The clergy originally consisted of the bishops, priests, and
                    deacons; but in the third century many inferior orders were appointed, as
                    subservient to the office of deacon, such as Acoluthists, Readers, &amp;c.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Benefit of</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Clergy</hi> is an
                    ancient privilege, by which one in orders claimed to be delivered to his
                    ordinary, to purge himself of felony.</p><p>After trial and conviction of a criminal, the judgment of the court regularly
                    follows, unless suspended or arrested by some intervening circumstances, of
                    which the principal is <hi rend="italic">benefit of clergy.</hi> As this is a
                    title of no small importance, it may not, therefore, be improper to inquire, <hi rend="italic">first,</hi> into its origin, and the various mutations which this
                    privilege of the clergy has sustained; <hi rend="italic">secondly,</hi> to what
                    persons it is to be allowed; <hi rend="italic">thirdly,</hi> in what cases; and,
                    <hi rend="italic">fourthly,</hi> the consequences of allowing it.</p><p>I. Clergy, <hi rend="italic">doc.</hi><hi rend="italic">privilegium</hi><hi rend="italic">clericale,</hi> or, in common speech, the benefit of clergy, had
                    its origin from the pious regard paid by Christian princes to the church in its
                    infant state, and the ill use which the Romish ecclesiastics soon made of that
                    regard. The exemptions which they granted to the church were principally of two
                    kinds: <hi rend="italic">first,</hi> exemptions of places consecrated to
                    religious duties from criminal arrests, which was the foundation of sanctuaries;
                    and, <hi rend="italic">secondly,</hi> exemption of the persons of clergymen from
                    criminal process before the secular judge in a few particular cases, which was
                    the true origin and meaning of the <hi rend="italic">privilegium</hi><hi rend="italic">clericale.</hi></p><p>But the clergy increasing in wealth, power, honour, number, and interest, soon
                    began to set up for themselves; and that which they had obtained by the favour
                    of the civil government, they now claimed as their inherent right, and as a
                    right of the highest nature, or indefeasible. By their canons and constitutions,
                    therefore, they aspired to and obtained a vast extension of those exemptions, as
                    well in regard to the crimes themselves, as to the persons exempted; and among
                    these were at length comprehended, not only every little subordinate officer
                    belonging to the church or clergy, but even many who were totally laymen.</p><p>In England, however, although the usurpations of the pope were very manifold,
                    till Henry VIII. totally exterminated his supremacy, yet a complete exemption of
                    the clergy from secular jurisdiction could never be thoroughly effected, though
                    often aimed at by the clergy; and therefore, though the ancient <hi rend="italic">privilegium</hi><hi rend="italic">clericale</hi> was allowed in
                    some capital cases, yet it was not universally so. And in those particular
                    cases, the usage was for the bishop or ordinary to demand his clerks to be
                    remitted out of the king’s courts as soon as they were indicted; but the
                    allowance of this demand was for many years a matter of great uncertainty, until
                    at length it was finally settled in the reign of Henry VI. that the prisoner
                    should first be arraigned, and might then either claim his benefit of clergy by
                    way of declinatory plea, or, after conviction, by way of arrest of judgment.
                    This latter way was most usually practised, as it was satisfactory to the court
                    to have the crime previously ascertained by confession or the verdict of a jury;
                    and it was also more advantageous to the prisoner himself, who might possibly be
                    acquitted, and so might not need the benefit of his clergy at all.</p><p>Originally the law held that no man could be admitted to the benefit of clergy,
                    unless he had the <hi rend="italic">habitum et tonsuram clericalem.</hi> But, in
                    process of time, a much wider and more comprehensive criterion was established;
                    every one that could read, a great mark of learning in those days of ignorance,
                    being accounted a clerk, or <hi rend="italic">clericus,</hi> and allowed the
                    benefit of clerkship, though neither initiated in clerkship, nor trimmed with
                    the holy tonsure. When learning, however, by means of the invention of printing,
                    and other concurrent causes, began to be more generally disseminated than
                    formerly, and reading was no longer a competent proof of clerkship, or of being
                    in holy orders, it was found that as many laymen as divines were admitted to the
                    <hi rend="italic">privilegium</hi><hi rend="italic">clericale,</hi> and
                    therefore, by the statute 4 Henry VII. cap. 13, a distinction was drawn between
                    mere lay scholars, and clerks who were really in orders. And although it was
                    thought reasonable still to mitigate the severity of the law with regard to the
                    former, yet they were not put upon the same footing with actual clergy; being
                    subjected to a slight degree of punishment, and not allowed to claim more than
                    once the clerical privilege. Accordingly the statute directs, that no person,
                    once admitted to the benefit of clergy, shall be admitted thereto a second time,
                    until he produce his orders; and to distinguish their persons, all laymen who
                    were allowed this privilege were burned with a hot iron in the brawn of the left
                    thumb. This distinction between learned laymen and real clerks in orders was
                    abolished for a time by the statutes 28 Henry VIII. c. 1, and 32 Henry VIII. c.
                    3; but it is held to have been virtually restored by the statute 1 Edward VI. c.
                    12, which enacts, that lords of parliament and peers of the realm may have the
                    benefit of their peerage, equivalent to that of clergy, for the first offence,
                    although they cannot read, and without being burnt in the hand, for all offences
                    then clergyable to commoners, and also for the crimes of housebreaking, highway
                    robbery, horse-stealing, and robbing of churches.</p><p>After this burning, the laity, and before it the real clergy, were discharged
                    from the sentence of the law in the king’s courts, and delivered over to the
                    ordinary, to be dealt with according to the ecclesiastical canons; whereupon the
                    ordinary, not satisfied with the proofs adduced in the profane secular court,
                    set himself formally to make a purgation of the offender by a new canonical
                    trial, although he had been previously convicted by his country, or perhaps by
                    his own confession. This trial was held before the bishop in person, or his
                    deputy, and by a jury <pb break="no" facs="nls:193356623" xml:id="kp-eb0706-6623-0740"/>of twelve clerks: and there the party himself was
                    first of all ordained to make oath to his own innocence; next there was required
                    the oath of twelve compurgators, who should swear that they believed he spoke
                    the truth; then witnesses were to be examined upon oath, but on behalf of the
                    prisoner only; and, lastly, the jury were to bring in their verdict upon oath,
                    which usually acquitted the prisoner; or if otherwise, the accused, if a clerk,
                    was degraded or put to penance. A learned judge, upwards of a century ago,
                    remarks with much indignation on the vast complication of perjury and
                    subornation of perjury, in this solemn farce of a mock trial; the witnesses, the
                    compurgators, and the jury, being all of them partakers of the guilt. The
                    delinquent party also, though convicted in the clearest manner, and conscious of
                    his own offence, was yet permitted, and almost compelled, ∙ to swear that he was
                    not guilty; nor was the good bishop himself, under whose countenance this scene
                    was transacted, by any means exempt from a share in it. And yet, by this
                    purgation, the party was restored to his credit, his liberty, his lands, and his
                    capacity of purchasing afresh, and was declared an entirely innocent man.</p><p>This scandalous prostitution of oaths and the forms of justice, in the almost
                    constant acquittal of felonious clerks by purgation, was the reason that, in
                    heinous and notorious circumstances of guilt, temporal courts would not trust
                    the ordinary with the trial of the offender, but delivered over to him the
                    convicted clerk, <hi rend="italic">absque</hi><hi rend="italic">purgatione
                    facienda;</hi> in which situation the clerk convict could not make purgation,
                    but was doomed to continue in prison during life, and rendered incapable of
                    acquiring any personal property, or of receiving the profits of lands, unless
                    the king pleased to pardon him. Both these courses were in some degree
                    exceptionable; the latter perhaps being too rigid, while the former was
                    productive of the most abandoned perjury. As these mock trials therefore took
                    their rise from mischievous tenets, tending to exempt one part of the nation
                    from the general municipal law, when the reformation became thoroughly
                    established, it was found necessary to abolish so vain and impious a
                    ceremony.</p><p>Accordingly the statute 18 Elizabeth, c. 7, enacts, that, for the avoiding such
                    perjuries and abuses, after the offender has been allowed his clergy, he shall
                    not be delivered to the ordinary as formerly, but, upon such allowance and
                    burning of the hand, he shall forthwith be enlarged and delivered out of prison,
                    with this proviso, that the judge may, if he thinks fit, continue the offender
                    in jail for any time not exceeding a year. And thus the law continued unaltered
                    for above a century, excepting only that the statute 21 Jac. I. c. 6, allowed,
                    that women convicted of simple larcenies under the value of ten shillings should
                    be burned in the hand,, whipped, put in the stocks, or imprisoned for any time
                    not exceeding a year. And a similar indulgence was, by the statutes 3 and 4
                    William and Mary, c. 9, and 4 and 5 William and Mary, c. 24, extended to women
                    guilty of any clergyable felony whatsoever; they were allowed once to claim the
                    benefit of the statute, in like manner as men might claim the benefit of clergy,
                    and to be discharged upon being burned in the hand, and imprisoned for any time
                    not exceeding a year. All women, all peers, and all male commoners who could
                    read, were therefore discharged absolutely in such felonies, if clerks in
                    orders; and if lay, for the first offence upon burning in the hand: yet all,
                    except peers, were liable, if the judge saw occasion, to imprisonment not
                    exceeding a year; whilst those who could not read, if under the degree of
                    peerage, were hanged.</p><p>Afterwards, indeed, it was considered, that education and learning were not
                    extenuations of guilt, but quite the reverse; and that if the punishment of
                    death for simple felony was too severe for those who had been liberally in- '
                    structed, it was, <hi rend="italic">a fortiori,</hi> too severe for the ignorant
                    and untutored. Hence, by the statute 5 Anne, c∙. 6, it was enacted that the
                    benefit of clergy should be granted to all those who were entitled to ask it,
                    without requiring them to read by way of conditional merit. Experience having
                    shown that so universal a lenity was frequently inconvenient, and proved an
                    encouragement to commit the lower degrees of felony, and that, though capital
                    punishments were too rigorous for these inferior offences, yet no punishment at
                    all, or next to none, as branding or whipping, was as much too slight; it was
                    enacted by the same statute, the 5 Anne, c. 6, that any person convicted of any
                    theft or larceny, and burnt in the hand for the same, shall, at the discretion
                    of the judge, be committed to the house of correction, or public work-house, to
                    be there kept to hard labour for any time not less than six months, and not
                    exceeding two years, with a power of inflicting a double confinement in case of
                    the party’s escape from the first. And it was further enacted, by the statutes 4
                    George I. c. 11, and 6 George I. c. 23, that when any person shall be convicted
                    of any larceny, either grand or petit, or any felonious stealing or taking of
                    money or goods and chattels, either from the person or the house of any other
                    person, or in any other manner, and who by the law shall be entitled to the
                    benefit of clergy, and liable only to the penalties of burning in the hand or
                    whipping, the court in their discretion, instead of such burning in the hand or
                    whipping, may direct such offenders to be transported to America for seven
                    years; and if they return, or are seen at large in this kingdom within that
                    time, it shall be felony without benefit of clergy.</p><p>From the whole of this detail we may collect, that however, in times of ignorance
                    and superstition, so great an anomaly in true policy may for a while exist, as a
                    body of men residing in a state, and independent of its laws, yet when learning
                    and rational religion have a little enlightened men’s minds, society can no
                    longer endure so gross and pernicious an absurdity. For, by the original
                    contract of government, the price of protection by the united force of
                    individuals is obedience to the united will of the community. This united will
                    is declared in the laws of the land; and that united force is exerted in their
                    due and universal execution.</p><p>We are next to inquire to what persons the benefit of clergy is allowable under
                    the foregoing enactments; and this must chiefly be collected from what has been
                    observed in the preceding part of this article. For, upon the whole, we may
                    pronounce that all clerks in orders were, without any branding, and of course
                    without any transportation, to be admitted to this privilege, and immediately
                    discharged, or at most only confined for one year, and this as often as they
                    offended. Again, all lords of parliament and peers of the realm must, by the
                    statute 1 Edward VI. c. 12, be discharged in all clergyable and other felonies
                    provided for by the act, without any burning in the hand, in the same manner as
                    real clerks convict; but this is only for the first offence. Lastly, all the
                    commons of the realm, not in orders, whether male or female, must, for the first
                    offence, be discharged of the punishment of felonies within the benefit of
                    clergy, upon being burnt in the hand, and suffering discretionary imprisonment;
                    or, in case of larceny, upon being transported for seven years, if the court
                    shall think proper.</p><p>The third point to be considered is, for what crimes the <hi rend="italic">privilegium</hi><hi rend="italic">clericale,</hi> or benefit of clergy, is to
                    be allowed. And it is to be observed, that neither in high treason, nor in petty
                    larceny, nor in any mere misdemeanours, was it indulged at the common law; and
                    therefore we may lay it <pb break="no" facs="nls:193356636" xml:id="kp-eb0706-6636-0741"/>down as a rule, that it was allowable only in
                    petty treason and capital felonies, which for the most part became legally
                    entitled to this indulgence by the statute <hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic">clero,</hi> 25 Edward III. stat. 3, e. 4, where it is provided
                    that clerks convict for treason or felonies, touching other persons than the
                    king himself or his royal majesty, shall have the privilege of holy church. But
                    still it was not allowed in all eases whatsoever; for in some it was denied even
                    in common law, namely, <hi rend="italic">insidiatio viarum,</hi> or lying in
                    wait for one on the highway; <hi rend="italic">depopulatio agrorum,</hi> or
                    destroying and ravaging a country; <hi rend="italic">combustio</hi><hi rend="italic">domorum,</hi> or arson, that is, burning of houses; all which are
                    a kind of hostile acts, and in some degree border upon treason. And further, all
                    these crimes, together with petty treason, and many other acts of felony, are
                    ousted of clergy by particular acts of parliament.</p><p>Upon the whole, then, we may observe, that in all felonies, whether newly
                    created, or constituted by common law, clergy was allowable, unless taken away
                    by act of parliament; that where clergy was taken away from the principal, it
                    was not of course taken away from the accessory, unless he was also particularly
                    included in the words of the statute; that when the benefit of clergy was taken
                    away from the offence, as in ease of murder, robbery, rape, burglary, and
                    unnatural crimes, a principal in the second degree, being present, aiding and
                    abetting the crime, was as well excluded from his clergy, as he that was a
                    principal in the first degree; but that where it was only taken away from the
                    person committing the offence, as in the case of stabbing or committing larceny
                    in a dwelling-house, his aiders and abettors were not excluded, through the
                    tenderness of the law, which has determined that such statutes shall not be
                    taken literally.</p><p>The last point for consideration was, the consequences to the party, of allowing
                    him this benefit of clergy. We speak not of the branding, imprisonment, or
                    transportation, which were rather concomitant conditions, than consequences of
                    receiving this indulgence. The consequences were such as affected his present
                    interest, and his future credit and capacity; as, having been once a felon, but
                    afterwards purged from that guilt by the privilege of clergy, this operated as a
                    kind of statute pardon. And we may observe, that by his conviction he forfeited
                    to the king all his goods, which being once vested in the crown, cannot
                    afterwards be restored to the offender; that, after conviction, and till he
                    received the judgment of the law by branding or the like, or else was pardoned
                    by the king, he was to all intents and purposes a felon, and subject to all the
                    disabilities and other incidents of a felon; that, after burning or pardon, he
                    was discharged for ever of that, and all other felonies before committed within
                    the benefit of clergy, but not of felonies from which such benefit was excluded,
                    as appears by the statutes 8 Eliza, e. 4, and 18 Eliza, e. 7; that by the
                    burning or pardon, he was restored to every capacity anderedit, and to the
                    possession of his lands, as if he had never been convicted; and that what has
                    been said with regard to the advantages of commoners and laymen, subsequently to
                    the burning in the hand, was equally applicable to all peers and clergymen,
                    although never branded at all. They had the same privileges without any burning,
                    to which others were entitled after it.</p><p>It is held, that after a man is admitted to his <hi rend="italic">clergy,</hi> it
                    is actionable to call him a felon; because, his offence being pardoned by the
                    statute, all the infamy and other consequences are discharged. As to what
                    felonies are <hi rend="italic">within,</hi> and what <hi rend="italic">without</hi> clergy, see Tomlin’s <hi rend="italic">Law Dictionary,</hi> title
                    <hi rend="italic">Felons</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and the Index to 1 <hi rend="italic">Hawk.</hi> P. C. As to the time of pleading, see titles <hi rend="italic">Pleading</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Judgment,</hi> of the same
                    dictionary.</p><p>The benefit of clergy, which was formerly a declinatory plea, is now very rarely
                    pleaded; first, because the prisoner, upon a trial, has a chance to be acquitted
                    and discharged; and, secondly, because, if convicted of a clergy-able felony, he
                    is equally entitled to his clergy after as before conviction; but if found
                    requisite, it is prayed by the convict before judgment is passed upon him.</p></div></body></text></TEI>