<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0706-8004-0077-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CANDLE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 6, page 77</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="14" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4ft4w">Wax</term>
                    <term n="14" ref="lcsh1910:b40v89s7n">Waxes</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vx1b">Neck</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="14" ref="fasttopic:1172931">Waxes</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:1142351">Tallow</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:926972">Flame</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1035341">Neck</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193348004" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CANDLE</label>, a small taper of tallow, wax, or spermaceti,
                    the wick of which is commonly of several threads of cotton, spun and twisted
                    together.</p>
                <p>A tallow-candle, to be good, must be half sheep’s and half bullock’s tallow; for
                    hog’s tallow makes the candle gutter, and always gives an offensive smell, with
                    a thick black smoke. The wick ought to be pure, sufficiently dry, and properly
                    twisted, otherwise the candle will emit an inconstant, vibratory flame, which is
                    both prejudicial to the eyes and insufficient for the distinct illumination of
                    objects.</p>
                <p>There are two sorts of tallow-candles; the one dipped, and the other moulded. The
                    former are the common candles; the latter are the invention of the Sieur le
                    Brege at Paris.</p>
                <p>As to the method of making candles in general, after the tallow has been weighed,
                    and mixed in the due proportions, it is cut into very small pieces, that it may
                    melt the sooner; for the tallow in lumps, as it comes from the butchers, would
                    be in danger of burning or turning black if it were left too long over the fire.
                    Being perfectly melted and skimmed, a certain quantity of water, proportionable
                    to the quantity of tallow, is poured into it. This serves to precipitate to the
                    bottom of the vessel the impurities of the tallow which may have escaped the
                    skimmer. No water, however, must be thrown into the tallow designed for the
                    three first dips, because the wick, being still quite dry, would imbibe the
                    water, which makes the candles crackle in burning, and renders them bad in use.
                    The tallow, thus melted, is poured into a tub, through a coarse sieve of horse
                    hair, to purify it still more, and may be used after having stood three hours.
                    It will continue fit for use twenty-four hours in summer and fifteen in winter.
                    The wicks are made of spun cotton, which the tallow-chandlers buy in skains, and
                    which they wind up into bottoms or clues; whence they are cut out, with an
                    instrument contrived on purpose, into pieces of the length of the candle
                    required; then put on the sticks or broaches, or else placed in the moulds, as
                    the candles are intended to be either dipped or moulded.</p>
                <p>Wax-candles are made of a cotton or flaxen wick, slightly twisted, and covered
                    with white or yellow wax. Of these there are several kinds; some of a conical
                    figure, used to illuminate churches, and in processions, funeral ceremonies,
                    &amp;c. (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Taper)</hi>; others of a cylindrical form,
                    used on ordinary occasions. The first are either made with a ladle or the hand.
                    1. To make wax-candles with the ladle: the wicks being prepared, a dozen of them
                    are tied by the neck, at equal distances, round an iron circle, suspended over a
                    large basin of copper tinned, and full of melted wax. A large ladle full of this
                    wax is poured gently on the tops of the wicks one after another, and the
                    operation is continued till the candle arrives at its destined size; with this
                    precaution, that the three first ladles are poured on at the top of the wick,
                    the fourth at the height of three fourths, the fifth at one half, and the sixth
                    at one fourth, in order to give the candle its pyramidal form. Then the candles
                    are taken down, kept warm, and rolled and smoothed upon a walnut-tree table,
                    with a long square instrument of box, smooth at the bottom. 2. As to the manner
                    of making wax-candles by the hand, candle-makers begin to soften the wax by
                    working it several times in hot water contained in a narrow but deep caldron. A
                    piece of the wax is then taken out, and disposed by little and little around the
                    wick, which is hung on a hook in the wall, by the extremity opposite to the
                    neck; so that they begin with the big end, diminishing still as they descend
                    towards the neck. In other respects the method is nearly the same as in the
                    former case. However, it must be observed that, in the former case, water is
                    always used to <pb break="no" facs="nls:193348017" xml:id="kp-eb0706-8017-0078"
                    />moisten the several instruments, to prevent the wax from sticking; and in the
                    latter, oil of olives, or lard, is used for the hands, &amp;c. The cylindrical
                    wax-candlcs are either made as the former, with a ladle, or they are drawn.
                    Waxcandles drawn are so called because they are actually drawn in the manner of
                    wire, by means of two large rollers of wood, turned by a handle, which turning
                    backwards and forwards several times, pass the wick through melted wax contained
                    in a brass basin, and at the same time through the holes of an instrument like
                    that used for drawing wire fastened at one side of the basin.</p>
                <p>The Roman candles were at first little strings dipt in pitch, or surrounded with
                    wax, though afterwards they were made of the papyrus, covered likewise with wax;
                    and sometimes also of rushes, by stripping off the outer rind, and only
                    retaining the pith. For religious offices wax-candles were used; for vulgar
                    uses, those of tallow.</p>
                <p>A few years ago Dr Ure of Glasgow made a set of experiments of the relative
                    intensities of light and duration of different candles, the result of which is
                    contained in the following table.</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Number in a Pound.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>Duration of a a Candle· ð</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Weight in</p><p>1
                            grains.</p><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Consumption per hour,
                            grains.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Proportion of Light.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Economy of 1</p><p>Light.
                            1</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Call dice equal one
                            Argand.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>10 Mould</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5h</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>9m.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>682</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>132</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi>
                            ¾</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>68</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5∙7</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>10 Dipped</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>36</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>672</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>150</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>13</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>65⅜</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5 25</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>8 Mould</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>31</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>856</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>132</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>10⅜</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>59’-</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6∙6</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6 Do</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2-⅛</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1160</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>163</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>14-⅛</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>66</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5∙0</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4 Do</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>9</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>36^</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1787</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>186</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>20∣</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>80</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3∙5</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Argandoil</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>flame...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>512</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>69∙4</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>100</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>A Scotch mutchkin, or one eighth of a gallon, of good seal oil, weighs 6010
                    grains, or thirteen and one tenth ounces, avoirdupois, and lasts in a bright
                    argand lamp eleven hours and forty-four minutes. The weight of oil it consumes
                    per hour is equal to four times the weight of tallow in candles eight to the
                    pound, and three and one seventh times the weight of tallow in candles six to
                    the pound. But its light being equal to that of five of the latter candles, it
                    appears from the above table, that two pounds weight of oil, value ninepence, in
                    an argand, are equivalent in illuminating power to three pounds of tallow
                    candles, which cost about two shillings. The larger the flame in the above
                    candles, the greater the economy of light.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Candle.</hi> Sale or auction by inch of candle, is when a
                    small piece of candle is lighted, and the byestanders are allowed to bid for the
                    merchandise that is selling as long as it lasts; but the moment the candle is
                    out the commodity is adjudged to the last bidder.</p>
                <p>There is also an excommunication by inch of candle, when the sinner is allowed to
                    come to repentance while a ćandle continues burning; but. after it is consumed,
                    he remains excommunicated to all intents and purposes.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Candle</hi> is also a term of medicine, and is reckoned
                    among the instruments of surgery. Thus the <hi rend="italic">candela
                    fu-malis,</hi> or the <hi rend="italic">candela pro</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >suffitu odorata,</hi> is a mass of an oblong form, consisting of odoriferous
                    powders, mixed up with a third or more of the charcoal of willow or lime-tree,
                    and reduced to a proper consistence with a mucilage of gum tragacanth, labdanum,
                    or turpentine. It is intended to excite a grateful smell without any flame, to
                    correct the air, to fortify the brain, and to excite the spirits.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Candle-2?otmZ»5,</hi> a name given to small glass bubbles,
                    having a neck about an inch long, with a very slender bore, by means of which a
                    small quantity of water is introduced into them, and the orifice afterwards
                    closed up. This stalk being put through the wick of a burning candle, <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 1</hi> the vicinity of the flame soon rarefies the water
                    into steam, by the elasticity of which the glass is broken with a loud
                    crack.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Medicated</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Candle</hi> is the same with
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Bougie.</hi><hi rend="italic">Push</hi><hi rend="italic
                    smallcaps"> Candles,</hi> used in different parts of England, arc made of the
                    pith of a sort of rushes, peeled or stripped of the skin, except on one side,
                    and dipped in melted grease.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
