<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0706-6415-0724-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CLARE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 6, page 724</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="10" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vr13">Stone</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4r785w31">Paper</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5cs84">Mercerization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4736m682">Lakes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:998850">Limericks</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1018703">Methodists</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1052348">Paper</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:796146">Acting</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193356415" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CLARE</label>, the most northern of the six counties which
                    form the province of Munster in Ireland, is bounded on the north by the bay and
                    county of Galway; on the east by Lough Dearg and the river Shannon, which
                    separate it from the county of Tipperary; on the south by the estuary of the
                    Shannon, which flows between it and the counties of Limerick and Kerry; and on
                    the west by the Atlantic Ocean. Its greatest length, measured in a northeastern
                    direction from Loophead to Scariff Point in Lough Dearg, is seventy miles; and
                    its breadth, from Blackhead in Galway Bay to Limerick city, forty-five miles.
                    Its surface comprehends 802,352 acres, of which 524,113 are cultivated, 259,584
                    are mountain and bog, and 18,655 are covered with water.</p>
                <p>According to Ptolemy, this county was anciently the residence of the tribe of the
                    Gangani; afterwards it was called Tuadmuin or Thomond, which signifies North
                    Munster, and was also known by the appellation of O’Brien’s Country, from the
                    family of that name which then possessed, and still continues to retain,
                    considerable influence there. In 1565 it was made shire ground, by the name it
                    still retains, at which time it was annexed to Connaught, but was restored to
                    Munster in 1602. The county is now divided into nine baronies, viz. 1. Bunratty;
                    2. Burren; 3. Clonderalaw; 4. Corcomroe; 5. Ibrickan; 6. Inchiquin; 7. Islands;
                    8. Moyarta; and 9. Tullagh. These baronies are subdivided into seventy-six
                    parishes, besides two parts of parishes, the remainders of which are in the
                    adjacent counties of Galway and Limerick.</p>
                <p>In the ecclesiastical arrangements of Ireland, Clare is considered as forming
                    part of the diocese of Killaloe, which also extends over the greater part of the
                    county of Tipperary, and some small portions of the King’s County and of those
                    of Galway and Limerick. Killaloe, near the western bank of the Shannon, is the
                    episcopal seat, at a small distance from which stands Clarisford House, the
                    bishop’s residence, built in the middle of a very beautiful demesne. The diocese
                    of Kilfenora, anciently called Fenabore, and which has long been united with the
                    preceding, comprehends the baronies of Burren and Corcomroe, and is the smallest
                    see in Ireland. The town ofKil-fenora is remarkable only for its cathedral, the
                    nave of which is full of old family memorials. A figure of St Feighan, the
                    founder, is to be seen at full length in the choir. In the same cathedral are
                    seven crosses, each formed of a single stone, and carved with antique devices.
                    The yearly value of the united dioceses, including mensal lands, according to a
                    return made to parliament in 1831, amounts to L.4600.</p>
                <p>The surface of the country is hilly, and in some parts mountainous, but nowhere
                    rising to heights of very great elevation. A considerable portion is covered
                    with bog, particularly in the western baronies of Moyarta and Ibrickan. Bogs are
                    frequent also in the mountainous districts in other parts, except in the
                    limestone barony of Burren. It has been remarked that the large tracts of rocky
                    country, which must always be used for grazing, and therefore require but a very
                    small population, enjoy but a scanty supply of this valuable material for fuel.
                    The inhabitants of several parts of Burren import it from the opposite shores of
                    Connemara. Generally speaking, the eastern parts of the county are mountainous,
                    with tracts of rich pasture lands interspersed; the west abounds with bog, and
                    the north is rocky, and best adapted for grazing sheep. In the southern part,
                    along the banks of the Fergus and Shannon, are bands of rich low grounds, called
                    carcasses, of various breadth, and indenting the land in a great variety<pb
                    break="no" facs="nls:193356428" xml:id="kp-eb0706-6428-0725"/> of shapes. That
                    part called Tradree, properly Tradruihe, or the King’s Land, a name supposed to
                    be attached to it in consequence of its being the patrimony of the celebrated
                    Brian Boroimhe, is proverbially rich. These carcasses are distinguished, from
                    the nature of their respective substrata, into black and blue; the former is
                    more esteemed for tillage, the latter for meadow. Indeed this county seems to be
                    distinguished from most others in Ireland, by the peculiarity of containing such
                    a variety of soils, from the rich lowland carcass to the light mountain gravel,
                    as to include a gradation fitted to produce all the necessaries and many of the
                    luxuries of civilized life. Every quality of ground exhibits itself, from the
                    shores of the Atlantic, in regular progressive chains of varied productive
                    fertility, from the luxuriant lowlands of Tradree to the rocky pasturages of
                    Burren. The traveller cannot but be struck with the wonderful contrast between
                    the cliff that frowns over the vale of Glanagarud, where the eye looks in vain
                    for the scanty herbage that maintains the goats on its summit, and the banks of
                    the Shannon, whose fertility cannot be exhausted by the most numerous herds of
                    cattle, or by the uninterrupted tillage of many years. .</p>
                <p>The climate is remarkably healthy. The strong gales from the Atlantic, though
                    unfriendly to planting, insomuch that trees sixty miles inland, if not
                    sheltered, incline towards the east, seem to produce no injurious effects on the
                    human constitution. Yet low fevers are common, and often pass through whole
                    parishes, cutting off numbers; but their frequency and malignity are attributed
                    more to the slovenly habits and want of cleanliness too prevalent among the
                    peasantry, than to any insalubrity in the climate. The frequent use of ardent
                    spirits also contributes its baleful agency to increase the extent and virulence
                    of this awful visitation.</p>
                <p>Besides the Shannon, a portion of which forms the eastern and southern boundaries
                    of the county, the most considerable river is the Fergus, which rises in the
                    barony of Corcomroe, and after flowing through Lough Inchiquin and several other
                    smaller sheets of water, passes through Ennis, where it is joined by the
                    Clareen; then, expanding into a large and beautiful estuary, studded with
                    picturesque islands, it unites itself with that of the Shannon. The Fergus is
                    navigable for vessels of two hundred tons, ten miles up to Clare, and for small
                    craft to Ennis. In consequence of the many mountain streams with which it is
                    fed, it is subject to floods, by which the low carcass lands on its borders are
                    frequently overflowed, and much injury is done to the stocks of hay and cattle.
                    The Ougarnee joins the Shannon near Bunratty Castle, as does the Blackwater near
                    Limerick. The former of these rivers presents peculiar advantages for extensive
                    manufactures. The supply of water is equal to any expenditure, and in some parts
                    the fall is so rapid that a mill could be erected at every hundred yards. The
                    Ardsallas and Clarcen are branches of the Fergus. The Innistymon river divides
                    the baronies of Ibrickan and Islands, and falls into Lisea-nor Bay. The Boagh or
                    Bow forms part of the boundary between this county and Galway. A large stream
                    rising in Mount Callan forms Lough Dulogh, and disembogues itself into the
                    Atlantic.</p>
                <p>The lakes are very numerous, amounting to upwards of an hundred, to which names
                    have been given. The principal are Lough Graney, Lough Tedane, and Lough
                    Inchiquin. They are, however, more celebrated for their picturesque beauties
                    than their extent. Lough Terroig rests on the summit of the Slieveboghta
                    mountain, in Tullagh barony; a stream from it feeds the beautiful Lough Graney,
                    or Lake of the Sun, and, after a serpentine course of several miles, flows into
                    the Shannon at the bay of Scariff. Besides the perennial lakes, large
                    accumulations of water occur, either forced upwards from under ground of a
                    higher level, or produced by collections of surface water draining down from
                    more elevated spots. These dry up in summer, and are called turloghs or loghans.
                    On the subsiding of the water, its place is supplied by a copious growth of fine
                    grass, that affords pasturage to numerous herds and flocks. Many of these
                    turloghs admit of easy drainage.</p>
                <p>Although mineral and metallic substances have been found in many places
                    throughout the county, they do not show themselves in sufficient abundance at
                    any one spot to induce the application of capital for their extraction. The
                    principal are lead, iron, and manganese.' Copper pyrites occurs in several parts
                    of Burren. Coal has been discovered, but the seams are too thin to warrant the
                    expectation of profit from their working on a large scale. Limestone is very
                    general. Flags, easily quarried, and raised in blocks or slabs of considerable
                    size, are procured near Kilrush; they are curiously connected by serpentine
                    insertions between the layers. Thin flags, used for covering houses, are raised
                    near Innistymon, as are slates for the same purpose in several places. A species
                    of very fine black marble has been discovered near Ennis. It takes a high
                    polish, and is free from the white spots with which the black Kilkenny marble is
                    marked.</p>
                <p>The mineral springs, which are found in many places, are chiefly chalybeate. That
                    of Lisdownvarna has long been celebrated for its medicinal qualities,
                    particularly in biliary obstructions: it is ferruginous, with an astringent
                    taste and strong smell, yet not fetid. It possesses the additional advantage of
                    being contiguous to the sea, thus affording the valetudinarian the option of
                    sea-bathing, if deemed advisable. There are chalybeate springs of less note at
                    Scool, Cloneen, Kilkishen, and Cassino, near Miltoun Malbay. Springs called by
                    the people holy or blessed wells, are common; but their efficacy in performing
                    cures in inveterate maladies is every day less valued. One of these, near
                    Tomgraney, called St Cullen’s, is remarkable for the purity of its water: it was
                    formerly overshadowed by a magnificent oak, the stump of which, measuring
                    sixteen feet in circumference at four feet from the ground, still exists. At St
                    Giaran’s Well, near Ennis, are the relics of a very large ash-tree.</p>
                <p>This county, in common with most other parts of Ireland, is deficient in timber.
                    Many miles square present themselves to the view, with scarcely the vestige of a
                    tree to vary the monotony of the scene. This is the more to be deplored, because
                    even the most rocky tracts admit of being planted, as the fissures of the
                    limestone generally have a perpendicular direction, and are usually filled with
                    a rich black earth. It is also well known that many tracts now bare of trees,
                    and affording but a scanty herbage for sheep, were once covered with woods; and
                    in spots where the soil is protected from the invasion of sheep and goats,
                    plants of oak, quicken, hazel, and other species of useful timber, shoot up
                    spontaneously, which, if properly protected and nurtured, would in a few years
                    clothe these naked cliffs with an abundant and profitable foliage. Several
                    proprietors have latterly been active in remedying this defect. The most
                    extensive modern plantations are at Cratilow, near Limerick, where several
                    hundred acres have been judiciously planted.</p>
                <p>The results of inquiries respecting the population, at different periods, partly
                    by private individuals, partly by order of government, give the number of houses
                    as follows, whence, as the number of souls in each is now universally estimated
                    at <hi rend="italic">5ļ,</hi> or 6 at the utmost, the total number of
                    individuals in the county can easily be calculated.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193356441" xml:id="kp-eb0706-6441-0726"/>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1712</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Houses.</p><p>8,602</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1791</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Houses.</p><p>18,050</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1732</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6,313</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1812</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>29,050</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1754</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>10,014</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1821</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>35,373</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1777</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>12,564</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1831</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The enumeration of the population, taken by authority of parliament, exhibits the
                    following results:</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Souls.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Souls.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Souls.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1812... 162,402</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1821...208,089</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1831...258,262</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The county was represented in the imperial parliament by three members; two for
                    the county at large, and one for Ennis. The new arrangements under the reform
                    act have made no change in this particular. The number of electors, previously
                    to the disfranchisement of the fortyshilling freeholders, was 8557; subsequently
                    to that period it was reduced to 1604; under the provisions of the reform act it
                    amounts to 2515.</p>
                <p>The peasantry possess most of the qualities, habits, and prejudices, usual among
                    the agricultural classes throughout the south and west of Ireland. Under the
                    ordinary circumstances of society, when not exposed to the influence of some
                    unusual excitation, they are kindly and well-mannered towards each other, and
                    hospitable to strangers, their intercourse with whom is marked, from the lowest
                    ranks to the highest, with an almost undeviating civility and readiness to
                    oblige. The cottages of the labouring classes are usually built of stone without
                    cement, sometimes with sods, and thatched with straw, or, in lieu of it, with
                    fern rushes, sedge, or even potato stocks. Their fuel is exclusively turf, drawn
                    from their own extensive bogs, or from the neighbouring shores of Galway. Their
                    usual food is potatoes, with milk in summer. On the sea coast their fare is
                    occasionally improved by the addition of fish. Almost every cottar has a small
                    garden planted with cabbage, varied, perhaps, with a small patch of onions or
                    parsnips.</p>
                <p>Their usual clothing is frieze wrought at home by the women of the family, whose
                    industry generally enables them to produce an additional quantity for sale. The
                    women used to wear pettieoats of home-dyed red flannel; but the introduction of
                    cotton cloths is rapidly excluding all other kinds of manufactures for female
                    dress here as well as elsewhere.</p>
                <p>The state of education, as far as it has been ascertained from the returns of the
                    census of 1821, and the reports of the parliamentary commissioners in 1824-6,
                    gives the following numbers of pupils :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Males.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Females.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Sex not <hi rend="subscript"> τ</hi>,
                            ascertained. <hi rend="superscript"> 0 a</hi> ’</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1821...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>....8,159..</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>....3,794..</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>11,953</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1824...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>..13,382..</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>....6,463..</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>206 20,051</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Of the number specified in the latter of these statements, 695 were of the
                    established church, and 19,366 Roman Catholics. The total number of schools was
                    315, of which 249 were supported wholly by the fees of the pupils, whose number
                    amounted to 15,070; the remaining 66 schools, containing 6320 pupils, were
                    supported either by grants of public money, or by voluntary contributions of
                    societies or individuals of various religious persuasions.</p>
                <p>Though, from the general description already given of the soil and surface of the
                    country, it would appear to be better adapted to grazing than tillage, yet in
                    the richer lands the latter is carried on extensively, and the modern
                    improvements in agriculture are rapidly gaining ground. Dairies are numerous.
                    Spade culture is still practised in the mountainous and rocky parts: some of the
                    best corn is raised in this expensive and laborious manner. At Ralahine, an
                    establishment combining agriculture and manufactures, on a plan somewhat similar
                    to that proposed by Mr R. Owen, late of Lanark, is successfully carrying on
                    under the superintendence of the proprietor, J. S. Vandeleur, Esq. If the county
                    be remarkable for the raising of any produce not in general cultivation
                    elsewhere, it is for that of onions. Around Ennis this vegetable is raised in
                    great quantities, and the very superior attention it requires gives employment
                    to numerous labourers.</p>
                <p>The usual rate of wages for field work is from 8d. to lθd. per day. But
                    employment is not abundant, except in spring and autumn, at which seasons the
                    number of hands is insuflicient for the demand. Near the sea good land is let to
                    the peasantry to raise potatoes, at L.3. 10s. to L.4 per aere. This land they
                    manure with sea-weed and sea-sand. In the interior potato ground is let without
                    manure at from L.5 to L.7, and with manure at from L.10 to L.12 per aere. After
                    paying for his cabin and potato garden, the labourer has very little remaining
                    to purchase necessary apparel for himself and his family.</p>
                <p>The general term for leases is three lives, or thirty-one years. Bishops’ land is
                    let for twenty-one years, with liberty to renew annually, or at other periods,
                    on payment of a proportionate fine. Much property is held by this uncertain and
                    discouraging tenure. Some landlords retain a right of planting on the tenant’s
                    land, allowing him the value of the part so planted. From a return very lately
                    made as to the residence of the landed proprietors, it appears, that of
                    sixty-three, the number stated in the return, forty-eight are resident on their
                    respective estates, nine reside in other parts of Ireland, and six only are
                    absentees. Yet this county has been as much disturbed of late years, and the
                    peasantry are in as great a state of destitution, as in those in which
                    absenteeism is prevalent. The names of the absentees are the Marquis of
                    Lansdowne, the Earl of Egremont, the London Mercers’ company, Morrugh O’Brien,
                    William Casey, and Crosdaile Morony, Esqrs.</p>
                <p>Besides the manufactures for home consumption already mentioned, flannels and
                    friezes are largely made for sale. In the western parts coarse yarn stockings
                    are manufactured by hand, in such quantities as to be the common medium of
                    barter. Coarse linens for sacks and packing are also fabricated. A species of
                    coarse hat is manufactured near Scariff. Kelp is made in large quantities along
                    the sea-shore; but in consequence of the negligent manner in which it is
                    prepared, and of the fraudulent practice of mixing with it a particular kind of
                    stone, hence called kelp-stone, its value in the general market is considerably
                    less than that made in Scotland or other parts of Ireland.</p>
                <p>The fisheries ought to be a source of much wealth and comfort to the inhabitants
                    of a district so contiguous to the sea; yet such is by no means the case.
                    Kilrush is the only harbour which engages largely in them. Here the
                    herringfishcry is carried on, yet not to a great extent. Fishing piers have
                    within these few years been built in several suitable situations. Shell-fish,
                    especially oysters, crabs, and lobsters, abound. The salmon-fishery of the
                    Shannon is very productive. Eels form a material article of consumption and
                    traffie. They are found in every stream; yet the weirs constructed for their
                    capture are thought to produce more injury, by the floodings arising from the
                    water thrown back from them on the cultivated land, than benefit from the fish
                    caught by them.</p>
                <p>The amusements in which the country people chiefly indulge are hurling matches,
                    here called goals, in which feats of surprising strength and activity are
                    performed. Chairs are nothing more than night-meetings at public houses, where
                    they give themselves up to conversation, dancing, and drinking. A curious custom
                    prevails in some parts: <pb break="no" facs="nls:193356454"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0706-6454-0727"/>the head of every beast that is slaughtered is
                    given to the blacksmith, a usage probably originating in a remuneration for the
                    use of his sledge and arm in knocking down the animal. In many places it is
                    customary among the lower classes to call the gentry by their abbreviated
                    Christian names, without any addition of family name or title, and this is done
                    with no intention of insult or degradation.</p>
                <p>The county abounds with remains of antiquities, both military and religious. Of
                    the former there are still visible 119 fortified castles, seven of which are
                    inhabited. Raths are to be found in every part; they arc generally round,
                    composed either of large stones without mortar, or of earth thrown up and
                    surrounded by one or more ditches, on which was formerly placed a staked hedge.
                    The list of abbeys and other' religious houses formerly existing here, some of
                    which are now only known by name, comprehends upwards of twenty. The most
                    remarkable are, Quin, said to be the finest and most perfect specimen of ancient
                    monastic architecture in Ireland; Corcomroe, Ennis, in which a very fine window
                    of uncommonlyelegant work-manship is still to be seen; and Inniscattery,
                    situated on an island in the Shannon, said to be founded by St Senanus, and
                    particularly noted for the total exclusion of females from its precincts. In the
                    island is a round tower. Four others are to be found in various stages of
                    preservation, at Drumelieve, Dysert O’Dea, Kilnabay, and Inniscal-tra. Cromlechs
                    are found chiefly in Burren, though there are some in other baronies. That at
                    Ballygannor is formed of a stone forty feet long and ten broad. The celebrated
                    tomb of Conan, on Mount Callan, is still extant. Near the same place is a
                    monument, called Darby’s and Graney’s Bed, to which the very singular custom is
                    attached, that if a young woman goes thither with a stranger, she is bound to
                    grant him any favour he asks.</p>
                <p>There are no towns of considerable size or importance in the county. Ennis, the
                    assize town, contains a population not much exceeding 7000 souls. It is situated
                    at the junction of the Fergus and Clareen, about ten miles from the entrance of
                    the joint stream into the Shannon. It is a post, market, fair, and borough town,
                    and the only one which sends-a representative to parliament. The electors, under
                    the new arrangement, amount to 237. The public buildings are, the parish-church,
                    adorned with a handsome steeple; a Roman Catholic chapel, and a Methodist
                    meeting-house. The market-house is a very fine building, as is the new jail,
                    which is constructed according to the modern ideas of prison discipline. The
                    latest reports to parliament describe it as holding a distinguished place among
                    the best regulated establishments of this class. The town is a mart for flannels
                    and linen; it is also the seat of an extensive corntrade. A school, on the
                    foundation of Erasmus Smith, has been established here, besides which there are
                    several private seminaries of education. The navigation of the river is
                    obstructed by a bar which prevents the ingress of large vessels; but this
                    defect, it is said, could be remedied at an expense of about L.10,000. Kilrush,
                    on the estuary of the Shannon, is the next town of importance. Its population is
                    about 4000, and from its situation and good harbour, aided by the exertions of a
                    resident and improving landlord, it is yearly increasing in wealth and
                    importance.</p>
                <p>Dutton’s <hi rend="italic">Statistical Survey of Clare</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >;</hi> Shaw Mason’s <hi rend="italic">Parochial Account of Ireland</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi><hi rend="italic">Bog Reports</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi>
                    Erck’s <hi rend="italic">Ecclesiastical Register; Parliamentary Papers; Reports
                    of the Commissioners of Education</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Returns under the Population Act</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Reports of the Society for the Improvement of Prison Discipline.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
