<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0706-9239-0172-02" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">CARPET</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 6, page 172</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:899678">Dutch</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1002458">Looms</term><term n="16" ref="fasttopic:1182520">Yarn</term><term n="7" ref="fasttopic:885683">Cutting</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:847868">Carpets</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1142046">Tail</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43r0pw3g">Looms</term><term n="16" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16z5c">Yarn</term><term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mj7p">Beams</term><term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r47q">Cuttings</term><term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4mg7fz12">Cutting</term><term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6j916">Passes</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1208963">Turkey</term><term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term><term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193349239" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">CARPET</label>, a well-known species of covering, chiefly
                    employed for the floors of rooms, but also used for a variety of other purposes.
                    Carpets are of oriental origin, and are made of different sorts of stuffs; some
                    of them of silk ornamented with gold, dthers of cotton, but by far the greater
                    part of wool. They are woven in a variety of ways.</p><p>Persia and Turkey carpets are the most esteemed. They are woven in a piece, in
                    looms of a very simple construction, being only composed of two beams placed the
                    one above the other, about eight feet separate, in parallel lines; the warp of
                    the web being put on the uppermost, and brought down the undermost beam, through
                    heddles. The pattern to be wrought is drawn and painted on design paper, and
                    placed before the weaver, who works the figure into the warp with dyed worsted
                    yarn, cut into proper lengths. He then passes a woof shot through the web, to
                    bind the worsted yarn. When the carpet is made to the dimensions required, it is
                    then taken out of the loom and dressed with shears made for the purpose. Till of
                    late years the manufacture of these carpets was confined to Persia and Turkey;
                    but they are now successfully imitated at Axminster in the south of England, and
                    at Kilmarnock in the west of Scotland.</p><p>Brussels, Wilton, imperial Brussels, and royal Wilton carpets, are all woven in
                    looms of the same construction, and derive their names from the places where
                    they were invented. The difference of their fabric consists as follows, viz. in
                    the Brussels, the worsted yarn raised to form the pile and show the figure is
                    not cut; in the Wilton the pile is cut, and has the appearance of velvet; in the
                    imperial Brussels the figure is raised above the ground, and the pile cut, the
                    ground uncut; and in the royal Wilton the pile is raised higher than in the
                    Wilton, and cut, which makes it a more massy carpet. The cloth of these carpets
                    is composed of linen and worsted, and the loom for weaving them is very
                    ingeniously constructed. The linen is put on a beam, and brought through heddles
                    and a reed; it is only used to bind the worsted yarn, and should not appear on
                    the right side. The better it is covered, the more complete and perfect is the
                    carpet.</p><p>The worsted yarn is put on small bobbins, with a weight attached to each to keep
                    the yarn of a uniform tightness. There are in some of the looms 1300, and in
                    others 1800 of these bobbins (according to the width of the web, which is
                    generally twenty-seven inches, although some are thirty-six inches), placed in
                    frames behind the loom, and planted of different coloured yarn, to answer the
                    figure. The yarn is then passed through the harness, heddles, and reed, to
                    combine with the linen yarn, and form the cloth. The harness is tied to
                    tail-cords, which are passed through a frame filled with small pulleys; a simple
                    is then attached to the tail cords, and brought down by the side of the loom,
                    upon which the pattern of the carpet intended to be wrought is put with lashes
                    and drawn by boys. Machines have been introduced in place of boys, but they have
                    <pb break="no" facs="nls:193349252" xml:id="kp-eb0706-9252-0173"/>
                    not been found to answer the purpose so well as in the other sorts of carpeting.
                    When the boy draws the lash, he has in one hand a piece of thin board, three
                    feet long and six inches broad, which is called a sword. This sword he passes
                    through under the yarn so drawn with the lash, and keeps it on its edge until
                    the weaver passes a wire through in front of the reed. This wire keeps up the
                    worsted, and the weaver throws two shots of linen woof through the web, and
                    forms the pile. It is necessary to have sixty of these wires for raising the
                    pile, and at all times to have at least six of them in the web next to the reed,
                    or else the worsted would sink, and the linen appear on the right side of the
                    carpet, which is a great defect. When it is intended to make Wilton and royal
                    Wilton, the wires that are used have a groove in them; and a small knife with a
                    guide to it, called a travat, is drawn across the web into the groove, and cuts
                    the pile: and for making imperial Brussels both a round wire and a grooved wire
                    are used at the same time.</p><p>Double or Kidderminster carpeting is composed of two plies of cloth, and having
                    what is called a right and a wrong side, the colours being reversed. Suppose a
                    carpet of scarlet and black, what is scarlet on one side will be black on the
                    other. They are, however, made in a variety of colours; and when done so, the
                    warp of the web is made of small yarn, so that when it happens to be of a
                    different colour from the woof, it may appear as little as possible; for in this
                    sort of carpeting there cannot be put more than two colours in a line without
                    mixing, whereas in Brussels five can be thus put.</p><p>The warp of the web is put all on one beam, and passed through the harness and
                    reed; the figure intended to be wrought is raised by a machine placed on the top
                    of the loom above the harness. A machine was in use for this purpose, which was
                    invented in Kilmarnock about eighteen years ago, and was wrought on the
                    principle of the organ barrel; but it is now superseded by another, where the
                    figure is cut on paper, and is consequently called a paper machine. It is of
                    French invention, and was originally used in the silk trade, but is now in
                    common use in the carpet trade. One great advantage which the paper machine has
                    over that of the barrel, is, that when once a pattern is cut, it can be woven at
                    any time (for an indefinite number of patterns may be wrought in one machine),
                    and it is only necessary to take out one pattern and lay it past for future use,
                    and put in another, which can be done in ten minutes; whereas on the barrel
                    machine, the figure, which is put on with small wire pins, when it is required
                    to be changed, must all be taken out and put on anew, or else have a number of
                    barrels for each machine, which adds greatly to the expense.</p><p>This sort of carpeting differs from Brussels, inasmuch as that both warp and woof
                    appear on the surface of the cloth, whereas in Brussels it is the warp only.</p><p>With regard to three-ply imperial or Scotch carpeting, although it is only
                    recently that this sort of carpeting has been made, it is getting very much into
                    repute, and is considered very little inferior to Brussels. Some years ago an
                    attempt was made in England to make three-ply carpeting, but it did not succeed;
                    they could not make the figure distinct on both sides, and it was abandoned.
                    Kilmarnock has the merit of obviating this defect, by bringing them to their
                    present state, and of fairly establishing the trade, which has now become very
                    considerable, and is still increasing.</p><p>They are woven in the same way, and in looms of the same construction, as the
                    two-ply carpeting, having three plies of cloth in place of two plies, which
                    makes them much more durable and comfortable, being nearly one half heavier in
                    the fabric, and every way superior in appearance.</p><p>In this sort of carpeting, as well as in the two-ply Kidderminster, it is the
                    woof which predominates, and shows the figure.</p><p>French or tapestry carpeting differs from Kidderminster and three-ply imperial
                    Scotch carpeting, inasmuch as it is the warp of the web, which is made of
                    worsted, that shows the figure. In other respects they are much the same, and
                    are woven in looms of the same construction, with a machine and the other
                    appendages.</p><p>Venetian carpeting is made both plain and figured, and is used mostly for stairs,
                    passages, and lobbies.</p><p>Plain Venetian carpets are woven in looms of a very simple construction, having
                    only heddles and reed. The warp is a very heavy body of worsted yarn, and should
                    cover the woof so completely that it cannot be seen. The pattern is generally in
                    stripes, and shaded like the rainbow; and the great object of the manufacturer
                    is to bring off the shade of colour from dark to light imperceptibly. They are
                    likewise made checked, and in squares like a draughtboard. The figured Venetian
                    are woven in looms of the same construction as the two-ply or Kidderminster
                    carpeting, having a machine to raise the pattern wanted, which is entirely of
                    the warp of the web, and is all worsted yarn, the woof being completely covered
                    by it, which is composed of a thick shot of woollen and a small shot of linen
                    yarn alternately.</p><p>Besides these described above, there is also Dutch carpeting, which is woven much
                    in the same way as plain Venetian, but a great deal coarser, some of them being
                    made of cow hair.</p><p>There are other branches of the arts and sciences upon which the successful
                    manufacturing of carpeting very much depends, such as spinning, dyeing, and
                    drawing. In Scotland it is matter of regret that so few artists have turned
                    their attention to the designing and drawing of patterns for Persian, Turkey,
                    Brussels, and double or three-ply carpeting. In England there are some who make
                    it a very lucrative branch of trade, and we have no doubt but it may become
                    equally so in this country.</p><p>The carpet trade in Scotland is much indebted to the Board of Trustees for the
                    Encouragement of domestic Manufactures, for the very liberal premiums given by
                    them to the successful competitors in carpet weaving. They have, by their
                    patriotic exertions, introduced into this country several sorts of carpeting,
                    which are likely to become a very considerable branch of trade, and consequently
                    employ a number of men, and likewise to consume a great portion of wool, a
                    staple article of the country. The premiums sometimes amount to between six and
                    seven hundred pounds.</p><p>The following is a description of the machines employed in the manufacture.</p><p>Plate CLIII. fig. 1, <hi rend="italic">description of Brussels,</hi> ⅛∙c. <hi rend="italic">Carpet Loom.</hi> A A A A, the frame of the loom, consists of six
                    posts, with caps and cross rails to bind them together. The posts arc seven feet
                    high, of an oblong square, six inches broad and five inches thick, and the caps
                    and cross rails five inches broad and two inches thick; the extreme length of
                    the frame eight feet, and width five feet. B B, the cloth beam, is made of a
                    circular piece of wood, six inches diameter, sufficiently long to reach the
                    width of the loom, with gudgeons in the end. which run into sockets in the frame
                    of the loom; on the one end of the beam is a cast-iron ratchet-wheel, with a
                    latch to keep the cloth when wound up on the· beam from coming back, and so keep
                    the web, when weaving, of a proper tightness. C, the lay, has an under and upper
                    shell, two swords, and rocking-tree; there are grooves in the upper and under
                    shell, to admit the reed which the yarn passes through, which is made of iron
                    splits. D, the heddles, of which there are <pb break="no" facs="nls:193349265" xml:id="kp-eb0706-9265-0174"/>three leaves,
                    arc made of brass wire; two of the leaves, where the linen yarn passes through,
                    have <hi rend="italic">eyes</hi> about one inch long; the other leaf, where the
                    woollen yarn passes through, has eyes four inches long, on purpose to allow the
                    worsted yarn to be raised that is required to form the pattern. The heddles are
                    connected and worked with the treadles, E E, with cords, by coupers placed on
                    the top of the loom at E, as well as under the heddles. The treadles are about
                    three inches square and six feet long, and are pressed down on the point by the
                    weaver’s foot. F is the linen yarn. G G, the linen yarn beam, is made of the
                    same materials, and in the same way, as the cloth beam, only it has no gudgeons
                    in the end of it, but moves in an aperture the thickness of the beam, which is
                    generally eight inches diameter. H H H, the harness, has a brass mail (with
                    three eyes) for every woollen thread in the web, of which thereare thirteen
                    hundred. Through the middle eye, which is the largest, the worsted yarn is
                    passed. From the undermost of the other two eyes is suspended with twine a small
                    lead weight, sufficient to keep the worsted yarn down in its proper place.
                    Through the upper eye is put the harness twine, and the twine is afterwards
                    passed through a board perforated with holes, and is called a harness board; it
                    is then attached to the tail-cords at 1, by means of fine small twine spun for
                    the purpose. By the proper arranging and tying of the harness to the tail-cords
                    depends in a great measure the correctness of the figure to be put to work. I,
                    the horal box, which is about twenty inches by thirty, has five rows of pulleys,
                    fifty-two in each row; and every pulley is divided by sheet-iron divisions. Over
                    each of these pulleys a tail-cord K K passes, which is tyed to the harness II.
                    To this tail-cord is connected the simple L L; and on this simple, which is made
                    of fine twine, the figure is lashed on with fine cotton thread, as at MM. N N N
                    N is the bobbin-frame. There are four full frames and two half ones; a full
                    frame is eight feet long and four feet broad, divided into eight rows, having
                    thirty-two bobbins in each row, with a small lead weight attached to each
                    bobbin. The frames arc supported at one end by two posts 0000, having holes in
                    them to heighten and lower them at pleasure. The other end of the frame is
                    supported by two posts of the frame of the loom.</p><p>Fig. 2, <hi rend="italic">description of Three-ply Imperial Scotch, and Two-ply
                    Kidderminster Carpet Loom.</hi> The frame treadles, beams, and lay of this loom
                    are so like fig. 1, that it will require no farther description. The only
                    difference is, that fig. 1 has six posts, whereas fig. 2 has only four; and that
                    fig. 1 is for making cloth three fourths wide, and fig. 2 four fourths wide.</p><p>The harness E, however, differs so far from fig. 1, that it has what is called a
                    double neck attached to each of the machines F F. These machines are the same as
                    the French machines used for raising the figures on silk. They are worked by the
                    treadle B, by means of the connecting iron rods at their point.</p><p><hi rend="italic">C</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">κιwι-Kmghts,</hi> a denomination given to gown-men and others of peaceable
                    professions, who, on account of their birth, office, or merits in regard to the
                    public, or the like, have been raised by the prince to the dignity of
                    knighthood. They take the appellation of <hi rend="italic">carpet,</hi> because
                    they usually receive their honours from the king’s hands in the court, kneeling
                    on a carpet; and by this they are distinguished from knights created in the
                    camp, or field of battle, on account of their military prowess.</p></div></body></text></TEI>