<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0706-0604-0277-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CEMENT</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 6, page 277</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1172931">Waxes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1024112">Mixing</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1011580">Mastication</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1750267">Mastic</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:850432">Cement</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4g15tk2p">Resins</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4ft4w">Wax</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b40v89s7n">Waxes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4000031d">Mastication</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4c24qm8t">Cement</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208963">Turkey</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193350604" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CEMENT</label>. Any substance which is employed in uniting
                    together things of the same or of different kinds may be termed a cement. The
                    following are some of the principal of those used for various purposes.</p>
                <p>To unite pieces of Derbyshire spar, or other stone, take seven or eight parts of
                    resin and one of wax; then melt them together, and mix them with a small
                    quantity of plaster of Paris. The stone should be made sufficiently hot to melt
                    the cement, and the pieces should be pressed so closely together, that the
                    smallest quantity possible of <pb break="no" facs="nls:193350617"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0706-0617-0278"/>the cement may remain between them. It is a rule
                    of general application, that the thinner the stratum interposed, the firmer the
                    hold will be.</p>
                <p>Jewellers unite precious stones which have been accidentally broken, by means of
                    gum-mastic. The parts of the gem must be previously heated to a degree
                    sufficient to melt the cement. Cameos of white enamel or coloured glass are also
                    in this way joined to a real stone as a ground. Mastic is likewise employed by
                    jewellers in various ways as a cement. The jewellers in Turkey ornament trinkets
                    and weapons with gems, by uniting them together with the following composition
                    :—Isinglass soaked in water till it swells up and becomes soft is dissolved in
                    Frcnch brandy or rum, so as to form a strong glue; then two small bits of gum
                    galbanum, or gum ammoniacum, are dissolved in two ounces of this by trituration;
                    and five or six pieces of mastic about the size of peas, being dissolved in as
                    much alcohol as will render them fluid, are to be mixed with the compound by
                    means of a gentle heat. This cement must be kept in a phial closely stopped; and
                    when used it must be liquefied by immersing the phial in warm water. It will be
                    found to resist moisture.</p>
                <p>If clay and oxide of iron be mixed with oil, they will form a cement which
                    hardens under water. A cement insoluble in water is prepared from skimmed milk
                    cheese. The cheese is cut into slices, the rind being thrown away, and boiled
                    till it becomes a strong glue, which, however, does not dissolve in the water.
                    It is to be afterwards washed in cold, and then kneaded in warm water. This
                    process must be several times repeated. The glue is then to be put warm on a
                    levigating stone, and kneaded with quicklime. Though this cement may be used
                    cold, it is best to warm it ;,and it will unite marble, stone, or earthenware,
                    so as to render the joining scarcely discernible.</p>
                <p>Boiled linseed oil, litharge, red lead, and white lead, mixed together and laid
                    on both sides of a piece of flannel, or even linen or paper, and then put
                    between two pieces of metal before they are brought home or close together, will
                    make a durable joint, capable of resisting boiling water, or even a considerable
                    pressure of steam. The proportions of the ingredients are not material; but the
                    more the red lead predominates the sooner the cement will dry, and the more of
                    the white lead the contrary. This cement joins stones of any dimensions.</p>
                <p>The following is an excellent cement for iron, as it ultimately unites with it
                    into one mass :—Take two ounces of muriate of ammonia, one of flowers of
                    sulphur, and sixteen of cast-iron filings; mix them well in a mortar, and keep
                    the powder dry. When the cement is to be used, take one part of this mixture,
                    twenty parts of clear iron borings or filings, pound them together in a mortar,
                    mix them with water to a proper consistence, and apply the compound between the
                    joints.</p>
                <p>A cement often used by coppersmiths to lay over the rivets and edges of the
                    sheets of copper in large boilers, in order to serve as an additional security
                    to the joinings, and to secure eocks and the like from leaking, is made by
                    mixing powdered quicklime with ox’s blood. This cement dries soon, and
                    accordingly must be used fresh.</p>
                <p>Temporary cements are required in cutting, polishing, or grinding optical
                    glasses, and various articles of jewellery, as these must be fixed to blocks or
                    handles for the purpose. Four ounces of resin, a quarter of an ounce of wax, and
                    four ounces of whitning, made previously red hot, forms a good cement of this
                    kind, as the articles may be united or separated by heat, though they adhere
                    with great tenacity when cold.</p>
                <p>The following composition is recommended as a good cement for electrical
                    apparatus:—Five pounds of resin, one of bees’ wax, one of red ochre, and two
                    table-spoonfuls of plaster of Paris, all melted together. The following is an
                    analysis by Sir Humphry Davy, of Parker’s patent water cement.</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>One hundred grains
                            contain</p><p>Silex</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>...22</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Alumina í</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>... 9</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Oxide of iron and
                            manganese...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>...13</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Carbonate of lime</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>...55</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>99</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>One hundred grains lost by
                            heating..</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3∙25</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>102∙25</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>An excellent artificial water cement is obtained by heating for some hours to
                    redness a mixture of three parts clay and one part slaked lime, by measure. As a
                    cement for broken china, take quicklime and white of eggs, or old thick varnish;
                    pound and temper them well together, and the composition is ready for use.
                    Broken glass may be cemented in the following manner: Let glass which is more
                    easy of fusion than the parts to be united, be ground up like a pigment, and
                    interposed between the pieces; then let these be subjected to a heat which will
                    melt the cementing medium, and make the parts agglutinate without being
                    themselves fused. Any thing thus united will be found as strong as ever. (Ure’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of Chemistry</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Philosophical ĩdagaziner</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Cement</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">for Building.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Lime.</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Cement</hi><hi rend="italic">Pots</hi> are those earthen pots
                    used in the cementation of metals.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
