<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0706-7627-0048-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CAMPER, Peter</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 6, page 48</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ww7759r">Moors</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k877">Research</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4qr4nq4d">Fishing</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mw0m">Fish</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1095153">Research</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:964151">Hunters</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193347627" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CAMPER, <hi rend="smallcaps">Peter</hi></label>, eminent for
                    his extensive knowledge in the various branches of medicine, zoology, and
                    comparative anatomy, and for his taste in the fine arts, was born at Leyden on
                    the 11th May 1722. His family had long held distinguished situations in the
                    magistracy of that city, where his grandfather had exercised the profession of
                    medicine. His father, Florent Camper, was a Protestant clergyman, and had
                    officiated in that capacity for some years at Batavia; but had returned to his
                    native country in 1718, after marrying Sarah Ketting, who was born of Dutch
                    parents, at Surat. Florent Camper was an enthusiastic admirer of painting, and
                    took great delight in the society of artists, whom he treated with the greatest
                    liberality, his purse being ever open to such as needed his assistance. He was
                    much connected with the learned men who adorned the university of Leyden at the
                    beginning of the last century, and was on terms of intimate friendship with the
                    great Boerhaave. Young Camper has, no doubt, been greatly indebted for his
                    success to the fortunate circumstances in which he was placed in early life;
                    being thus surrounded by men of enlarged and cultivated understandings, eminent
                    for their taste and learning, and having, at the same time, every incentive that
                    a wise education could supply to emulate those excellent models«; but nature had
                    besides endowed him with that inherent desire of knowledge, that capacity, and
                    that vigour and activity of mind, which, united as they were with a robust
                    constitution of body, enabled him to reap the full benefit of these advantages.
                    He gave very early proofs of his possessing those mental qualities which lay the
                    foundation of future eminence; and his father, discerning with delight the
                    auspicious dawn of his genius, judiciously removed whatever might cramp its
                    growth, and avoided imposing on him as a task those instructions and attainments
                    which he seemed so well inclined to acquire and pursue as an amusement.</p>
                <p>He applied himself at an early age to drawing and painting, under the tuition of
                    Moor and of his son, both of whom were celebrated artists, and soon became
                    remarkably proficient in these accomplishments. He derived, in the course of his
                    life, immense advantage from the skill with which he used his pencil in
                    delineating any object in which he was interested, whether among the works of
                    art or the productions of nature, or whether they were the offsprings of his own
                    conception in the course of his philosophical researches. The value of this
                    acquirement, as an object of early education, is not perhaps in general
                    sufficiently appreciated. The power of conceiving readily, and with correctness,
                    mechanical forms, is one of the most useful results that practice in the
                    delineation of objects can confer, and is of incalculable advantage in a variety
                    of pursuits, with which such a talent might not at first sight seem to be
                    immediately concerned. There is no doubt, for instance, that it must remove many
                    difficulties in the study of geometry, by facilitating the conception of figured
                    space, the properties of which are the subjects of that science. An accurate
                    knowledge of anatomy is still more directly dependent upon the same power of
                    apprehending the relations of form. The progress which Camper made in this
                    branch of science, and the range of inquiries to which he afterwards made his
                    knowledge subservient, are striking illustrations of this position.</p>
                <p>He was indebted to Laborde for his first lessons in geometry, and was instructed
                    in natural philosophy by Muschenbroeck and Gravesande, who were the intimate
                    friends of his father, and whose names will be ever illustrious in the annals of
                    science. From these studies he was naturally led to the pursuit of medicine, of
                    which the elementary branches have so close an alliance with the physical
                    sciences; and having entered the university of Leyden, became the pupil of
                    Gaubius, Van Rooyen, and the elder Albinus; for Boerhaave was by this time
                    incapacitated, by the infirmities of age, from continuing his exertions as
                    public teacher in the university. Camper earned the first fruits of his
                    academical labours by receiving, in 1746, the degree of doctor in philosophy and
                    medicine, on which occasion he published two dissertations, the one <hi
                    rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Visu,</hi> the other <hi rend="italic"
                    >De</hi><hi rend="italic">Oculi quibusdam Partibus,</hi> which are mentioned
                    with commendation by Baldinger in his <hi rend="italic">Diography of Living
                    Physicians,</hi> and which have been preserved by Haller. In the former he
                    illustrates and defends Smith’s <hi rend="italic">Theory of Vision,</hi> and in
                    the latter describes and gives plates of Petit’s <hi rend="italic">Canal in the
                    Eyes of different Animals.</hi></p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193347640" xml:id="kp-eb0706-7640-0049"/>
                <p>The acquaintance lie had formed at college with several foreigners of merit had
                    long inspired him with a desire of travelling, and of gratifying his thirst for
                    knowledge, by visiting different countries, and conversing with men
                    distinguished for their acquirements in the several branches of science. But the
                    declining health of his parents, who were now advanced in years, and required
                    the continual presence and kindest attentions of their son, long prevented him
                    from accomplishing his wishes. Their death, however, which happened in 1748,
                    released him from duties which he had the consolation of reflecting had been so
                    piously discharged; and he soon after, at the age of twenty-six, embarked for
                    England. In London he met with the celebrated physicians Mead, Pringle, and
                    Pitcairn, with whom he became acquainted. He pursued his medical studies under
                    Hunter, Sharp, Smellie, and Winchester; and indulged his taste for natural
                    history, by examining diligently the cabinets of Hans Sloane and Collinson, and
                    the collections of Hill and Catesby. He studied botany under Elliot, and
                    astronomy under Short, and was instructed in the use of the microscope by Baker,
                    who was at that time applying this instrument with so much success to objects of
                    natural history. He seemed determined to suffer no opportunity of amassing a
                    store of useful knowledge to escape him; and although his views embraced a wide
                    range of subjects, he was never satisfied with a superficial glance, nor trusted
                    to the reports of others, when there was a possibility of seeing with his own
                    eyes the objects of his curiosity. His attention was particularly directed to
                    the mechanical arts; he visited the principal manufactories, and was
                    indefatigable in collecting instructions from artists of eminence in every
                    department; and his eager curiosity even extended to the details of naval
                    architecture, to the study of which he devoted a considerable portion of time.
                    He was in the habit, during all his travels, of making minutes of every thing he
                    saw and learned; and his happy facility in the employment of the pencil enabled
                    him to take sketches on the spot of every object of which a delineation could be
                    useful. Knowledge thus derived from personal observation is the more valuable,
                    as it is more strongly impressed on the memory, and as it is less liable to
                    inaccuracy, and less likely to be tinctured with prejudice, or distorted by the
                    medium through which it is received. He still cultivated his taste for painting,
                    and acquired much practical skill in the art of engraving. After remaining about
                    a year in London, and visiting the universities of Oxford and Cambridge, he
                    proceeded to Paris, and devoted two months to the inspection of the principal
                    public establishments in that capital. He then travelled onwards to Lyons and
                    Geneva; but the prosecution of his journey in the direction of Italy was stopped
                    by the intelligence he received of his being appointed professor in philosophy,
                    medicine, and surgery, at Franeker, in Friesland; and he returned to Holland by
                    Switzerland and the banks of the Rhine, visiting, as he passed through Basel,
                    the great Bernoulli, and examining, in the library of that city, the writings of
                    Erasmus and the paintings of Holbein. The itinerary which he kept of his journey
                    contains a great number of valuable remarks on agriculture and geology, and
                    showed how well he was gifted with the talent for observation.</p>
                <p>In consequence of a severe illness, with which he was attacked in 1749, he was
                    obliged to defer entering upon the duties of his new professorship till the
                    autumn of the following year, when, in conformity with the custom on these
                    occasions, he pronounced apublic inaugural discourse,choosing as his subject <hi
                    rend="italic">De Mundo Optimo.</hi> About the same period he was elected a
                    fellow of the Royal Society of London.</p>
                <p>He had reaped so much advantage by his residence in</p>
                <p>England, and was so much attached to its inhabitants, and full of admiration for
                    the great public establishments of that country, that he returned there during
                    the vacation of 1752, and resumed his various pursuits, both medical and
                    scientific, with unabated ardour. Among other objects, his attention was much
                    directed to the method of inoculating for the small-pox, the practice of which
                    was as yet confined to England. On his return to Franeker he resumed his
                    lectures, which were every year more numerously attended, and gained him such
                    increasing celebrity, that he was soon ranked as one of the ablest men of
                    science in Holland. In 1755 he was appointed professor of anatomy and surgery at
                    the Athenaeum of Amsterdam, and came in consequence to settle in that city,
                    which was then the seat of opulence and learning. According to custom, he
                    pronounced two inaugural discourses, the first, <hi rend="italic">De Anatomes in
                    omnibus</hi><hi rend="italic">Scientiis usu</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and the
                    second, <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Certo</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >in</hi><hi rend="italic">Medicina.</hi> In 1756 he married the widow of the
                    burgomaster of Harlingen.</p>
                <p>After continuing six years in Amsterdam, his avocations were so multiplied and
                    fatiguing, that he yielded to the strong desire which Mrs Camper had long
                    entertained of retiring to Friesland, and once more took up his abode at his
                    country house at Franeker. He of course resigned his professorship at Amsterdam,
                    but was allowed to retain the title of honorary professor of that academy. His
                    principal work, during the time he had held that chair, was the first volume of
                    his <hi rend="italic">Demonstrationes</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >AnatomicoPatho-logicae.</hi> But the leisure he now enjoyed in his retirement
                    in Friesland allowed him to devote his whole time to science; and the second
                    volume of the same work made its appearance in 1762, together with several other
                    publications, of which notice will be taken in the sequel.</p>
                <p>Two years thus glided by rapidly in the country, when he was again called to the
                    active duties of an academical life, by the appointment which was conferred upon
                    him of professor of medicine, surgery, and anatomy, in the university of
                    Groningen. The proximity of this city to his present habitation, the natural
                    activity of his mind, and a conscientious desire of being useful to the
                    community, concurred with the love of fame, which retirement had not
                    extinguished, in inducing him to undertake the office which he was now so
                    honourably called upon to discharge. He accordingly established himself and his
                    family at Groningen, and, at his inauguration as professor, delivered a
                    discourse, <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">admirabili
                    analogia</hi><hi rend="italic">inter Stirpes</hi><hi rend="italic">et
                    Animalia.</hi> The great interest which he took in the improvement of
                    agriculture led to the establishment, under his auspices, of a society for the
                    purpose of conducting experiments in this important art. To this society Camper
                    was nominated secretary. He bestowed much pains in investigating the nature of
                    an epidemic disorder which prevailed extensively among the cattle of Holland,
                    and in devising the best means of diminishing its ravages. He made these the
                    subject of several lectures, which he read in 1796, to the academy of Groningen;
                    and his proposed method of inoculating the disorder, with a view of disarming it
                    of its virulence, appears to have effectually succeeded in those districts where
                    it was adopted. He was also much occupied, at this period, with researches in
                    natural history; and made a variety of important discoveries in comparative
                    anatomy, of which we shall afterwards give a brief account.</p>
                <p>The ten years that he spent at Groningen were esteemed by Camper the happiest, at
                    the same time that they were the most laborious, of his life; and he probably
                    would never have quitted a situation in every respect so congenial to his taste,
                    or the circle of friends he had formed there, by whom his talents were well
                    appreciated, and in whose approbation he found the reward of his exertions, if
                    the wishes of his wife, and his own anxiety to superintend<pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193347653" xml:id="kp-eb0706-7653-0050"/> the education of his family,
                    had not induced him to make the sacrifice of all these enjoyments, and once more
                    remove to Franeker Academy, at which his sons were to be placed. He continued,
                    nevertheless, steadily to prosecute his various philosophical and medical
                    researches until the year 1776, when he sustained a heavy stroke of affliction
                    in the death of his wife, in whom his affections had been centred during a union
                    of twenty years, and whose domestic virtues, and exemplary attention to her
                    children, had secured her the esteem and respect of all who knew her. As the
                    most efficacious mode of soothing his grief, he determined upon varying the
                    scene, and making occasional excursions to the neighbouring parts of the
                    Continent. He accordingly visited all the cities that offered objects of
                    attraction in the sciences or the fine arts; and, after gratifying his taste for
                    painting by the sight of the masterpieces of Rubens, Vandyke, and other painters
                    of the Flemish school, proceeded, in search of amusement and instruction, to pay
                    another visit to Paris. Here he enjoyed the society of Franklin, Marmontel,
                    Diderot, Daubenton, Portal, and other distinguished characters in the literary
                    and scientific world. Returning to his own country with recruited spirits, he
                    applied himself with fresh ardour to his favourite pursuits, and, aiming at more
                    comprehensive views of the animal kingdom, occupied himself in pursuing the
                    analogies which connect its several departments, and in tracing the successive
                    links of that extended chain, by which the different orders of beings are united
                    in one continued series of gradation. A tour through Germany, at a later period
                    of his life, brought him acquainted with many treasures in natural history, with
                    which that country abounds. The anatomical preparations of Kerkringius, and the
                    observatory of Tycho Brahe at Hamburg; the collections of natural history of
                    Taube and Dcsrogues at Zell, and the superb cabinet of antiquities of the Count
                    Walmoden at Hanover, particularly attracted his attention; and he explored with
                    the eye of a geologist the volcanic district of Cassel. He formed also the
                    acquaintance of Zimmerman, Soemmcr-ring, and other eminent physicians. The
                    following year he visited Prussia, and was presented to the great Frederick, who
                    received him at Potsdam with much affability and respect, conversing with him
                    for a long time on the subject of the fine arts; and, on his return, he had the
                    honour of spending two days with the brother of the king, Prince Henry of
                    Prussia, at Rhynsberg.</p>
                <p>In 1785 Camper was chosen member of the Royal Academy of Sciences at Paris, an
                    honour which was the more highly prized, as the number of foreigners on whom it
                    was conferred was limited to eight. In the same year he paid a fourth visit to
                    England, a country for which he had always shown a strong partiality, and was
                    again gratified with the society of the numerous friends he had left there, and
                    of others whose acquaintance he then for the first time made.</p>
                <p>His literary and philosophical occupations, numerous and important as they were,
                    did not preclude him from taking an active part in the political concerns of his
                    country. In 1762 he was returned as deputy in the assembly of the province of
                    Friesland; and in 1776 he appeared there as deputy for Idaarderadeel. He
                    persuaded the assembly to reject a proposal for the restoration of the maritime
                    dikes of that province. In 1783, on the recommendation of the stadtholdcr, he
                    was nominated one of the council of state of the United Provinces, and was of
                    course obliged to reside at the Hague. During the revolution which soon
                    afterwards occurred in Holland, he remained faithfully attached to the party of
                    the stadtholdcr; without, however, yielding his unqualified approbation to all
                    their measures. The triumph of his own party was even accompanied with
                    circumstances which gave him much con cern, and embittered the latter period of
                    his life. He died of a violent pleurisy, on the 7th of April 1789; and his
                    remains were deposited in the tomb of his ancestors, in the church of St Peter
                    at Leyden.</p>
                <p>To a mind enriched with vast stores of knowledge, and adorned with a taste at
                    once elegant and refined, Camper united the most benevolent affections, and
                    possessed all the virtues of domestic and social life. His conduct in the
                    several relations of son, of husband, and of father, was in all respects
                    exemplary. His manners were remarkably placid, and bespoke that habitual
                    equanimity which formed the characteristic quality of his temper, and which,
                    amidst strong sensibility to the affections of humanity, he constantly studied
                    to preserve. Nature had bestowed upon him a dignified and graceful form, and a
                    remarkably animated and expressive countenance. His voice, which was sonorous
                    and flexible, was excellently adapted for public speaking. He had a singular
                    facility in acquiring languages; and spoke fluently Latin, English, French, and
                    German; and had, besides, attained a competent knowledge of Greek and of
                    Italian.</p>
                <p>Few men have received during their lives so many honourable marks of literary
                    distinction as Camper. Besides those which have been already mentioned, he was
                    chosen member of the academics of Petersburg, Berlin, Edinburgh, Manchester,
                    Toulouse, Gottingen, Haarlem, Rotterdam, and Flushing; and was foreign associate
                    of the Royal Society of Medicine at Paris. He obtained the prize of the academy
                    of Haarlem, for his <hi rend="italic">Memoir on the Physical Education of
                    Children.</hi> His <hi rend="italic">Researches on Specific Remedies</hi> gained
                    him the prize of the Academy of Sciences of Dijon; his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Observations on Inoculation</hi> that of the Academy of Toulouse; and his <hi
                    rend="italic">Memoir on Chrrnic Diseases of the Chest</hi> that of the Academy
                    of Lyons. The Royal Academy of Surgery voted him three prizes for his <hi
                    rend="italic">Memoirs on the Influence of Different Circumstances in Regimen on
                    the Treatment of Siirgical Diseases.</hi> To specify in detail the several
                    subjects on which he has written would be to extend this article to too great a
                    length. We shall therefore content ourselves with enumerating those works which
                    are of most importance; and, instead of reciting them in the order of their
                    publication, shall arrange , them according to the subjects to which they
                    relate. His principal labours were bestowed on comparative anatomy and
                    physiology, and his discoveries in this wide field of research are numerous and
                    important. A posthumous collection of his works on these subjects appeared at
                    Paris in 1803, in 3 vols. 8vo, with a folio atlas of plates, under the title of
                    <hi rend="italic">Oeuvres</hi><hi rend="italic">de Pierre Camper,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">qui ont pour objet l Histoire Naturelle, la Physiologie,
                    et</hi><hi rend="italic">l'</hi><hi rend="italic">Anatomie Comparée;</hi> to
                    which is prefixed an Essay on his Life and Writings by his son, and two
                    eulogiums, one by Vicq d’Azyr, and the other by Condorcet. They contain his <hi
                    rend="italic">Dissection and Natural History of the Orang-outang, and other
                    Species of Apes.</hi> He examines especially the peculiarities in the structure
                    of the organ of voice of those animals, which deprive them of the power of
                    uttering articulate sounds, and which alone would place an immense interval
                    between them and the human species. His anatomical description of the two-horned
                    rhinoceros, of the rein-deer, and of the elephant, are the subjects of separate
                    dissertations; as also his researches on the structure of the great bones of
                    birds, and the manner in which atmospherical air is introduced into them (of
                    which the discovery was made by Camper prior to the time at which Hunter
                    published his observations on the same fact); on the structure of the porpoise
                    and the whale; on the classification of fishes according to the system of
                    Linnaeus; on the anatomical structure of the organs of hearing in fishes, and of
                    the blowing-holes of the <hi rend="italic">cetacea</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi>
                    on the <hi rend="italic">dugon</hi> of Buffon, and <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193347666" xml:id="kp-eb0706-7666-0051"/>the <hi rend="italic">sirena
                    lacertina</hi> of Linnaeus, both of which he pronounces to belong to the class
                    of fishes; on the generation of the <hi rend="italic">pipa</hi> or American
                    toad; on the croaking of the male frog; on the petrifactions found in the
                    mountain of St Peter, near Maestricht, and the fossil bones of fish and other
                    animals; on the analogies that may be traced between the several parts of the
                    animal kingdom, especially in the structure of the human species, compared with
                    those of quadrupeds, birds, and fishes; on the alteration of form in the human
                    species produced by age; on the diversity of features which characterize
                    different nations, and the mode of expressing these differences in delineating
                    the human figure; on the mode in which the passions are indicated by the
                    countenance; on the <hi rend="italic">beau physique,</hi> or the beauty of
                    forms; and on the analogy between plants and animals. In the practical branches
                    of medicine he has written observations on the inoculation of the small pox,
                    founded on experiment; on the theory and treatment of chronic diseases of the
                    lungs, and a historical inquiry into the principal methods of cure employed by
                    the ancients and moderns in these disorders; on the nature, employment, and mode
                    of operation of remedies termed specifics; on the nature, causes, and treatment
                    of dropsy, and the different indications of cure derived from the symptoms; on
                    the nature of cancer, and on the signs denoting those of the breast that do not
                    admit of cure; on the herniae incident to new-born children, &amp;c.; on ulcers
                    in the urethra and prolapsus ani; on the fracture of the patella; on the callus
                    of fractured bones; on lithotomy, and especially on the method of performing
                    that operation at two different times, according to the plan of the celebrated
                    Franco; on the construction of bandages for herniae; on bandages in general; on
                    the abuse of ointments and plasters in the treatment of ulcers, and on improved
                    methods of managing them; on the noxious effects attending the admission of air
                    into the body, and the influence of this principle on the treatment of surgical
                    diseases. In the department of midwifery he has written a letter to Dr Van
                    Gescher on the utility of the section of the <hi rend="italic">symphysis
                    pubis</hi> in severe labours, and observations on the use of the lever of
                    Roonhuysen in difficult parturition. Several memoirs on the subject of
                    infanticide, and the juridical questions connected with that subject, were
                    published by him at Leenwarden. (γ.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
