<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0706-9304-0177-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CARRON</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 6, page 177</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0329f">Britons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tv2w">Canals</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20h7x">Valleys</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4rb6w237">Running</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:839101">Britons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1109125">Scots</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1163841">Valleys</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:980104">Islands</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193349304" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CARRON</label>, a small but remarkable river in Scotland,
                    rising about the middle of the isthmus between the Friths of Forth and Clyde.
                    Both its source, and the place where it empties itself into the sea, are within
                    the shire of Stirling, which it divides into two nearly equal parts. The whole
                    length of its course, which is from west to east, is not above fourteen miles.
                    It falls into the Frith of Forth about three miles to the north-east of Falkirk.
                    The stream is small, and scarcely deserves the notice of a traveller; yet there
                    is no river in Scotland, and few in the whole island of Britain, whose banks
                    have been the scene of so many memorable transactions. When the Roman empire was
                    in all its glory, and had its eastern frontiers upon the Euphrates, the banks of
                    the Carron were its boundaries upon the north-west; for the wall of Antoninus,
                    which was raised to mark the limits of that mighty empire, stood in the
                    neighbourhood of this river, and ran parallel to it for several miles.</p>
                <p>Near the middle of its course, in a pleasant valley, stand two beautiful mounts,
                    called the <hi rend="italic">Hills of Dunipace,</hi> which are taken notice of
                    by most of the Scottish historians as monuments of great antiquity. The whole
                    structure of these mounts is of earth, but they are not both of the same form
                    and dimensions. The more easterly one is perfectly round, resembling an oven,
                    and about fifty feet in height; and that it is an artificial work does not admit
                    of the least doubt; but we cannot affirm the same with equal certainty of the
                    other, though it has been generally supposed to be so too. It bears no
                    resemblance to the eastern one either in shape or size. At the foundation it is
                    nearly of a triangular form; but the superstructure is quite irregular, nor does
                    the height of it bear any proportion to the extent of its base. These mounts are
                    now planted with firs, which, with the parish-church of Dumpace standing in the
                    middle between them, and the river running close by, give this valley a very
                    romantic appearance. The common account given of these mounts is, that they were
                    erected as monuments of a peace concluded in that place between the Romans and
                    the Caledonians, and that their name partakes of the language of both people;
                    <hi rend="italic">dun</hi> signifying a hill in the old language of this island,
                    and <hi rend="italic">pax,</hi> peace, in the language of Rome; so that the
                    compound word, <hi rend="italic">Dunipace,</hi> signifies “the hills of peace.”
                    And we find in history, that no less than three treaties of peace were at
                    different periods entered into between the Romans and the Caledonians; the first
                    by Severus about the year 210; the second soon afterwards, by his son Caraealla;
                    and the third by the usurper Carausius about the year 280; but which of these
                    treaties Dunipace is a monument of it is impossible to determine. If the
                    concurring testimony of historians and antiquaries did not agree in giving this
                    original to these mounts, we should be tempted to conjecture that they are
                    sepulchral monuments. Human bones and urns have been discovered in earthen
                    fabrics of this kind in many parts of the island; and the little mounts or
                    barrows which are scattered in great numbers about Stonehenge, in Salisbury
                    Plain, are generally supposed to have been the sepulchres of the ancient
                    Britons.</p>
                <p>From the valley of Dunipace the river runs for some time in a deep and hollow
                    channel, with steep banks on both sides. Here it passes by the foundations of
                    the ancient Roman bridge, not far from which, as is generally thought, was the
                    scene of the memorable conference betwixt the Scottish patriot William Wallace,
                    and Robert Bruce, father to the king of that name, which first opened the eyes
                    of the latter to a just view both of his own true interest and that of his
                    country.</p>
                <p>After the river has left the village and bridge of Larbert, it soon enters
                    another smaller valley, through the midst of which it has now worn out to itself
                    a straight channel; but, in former ages, it had taken a considerable sweep
                    round, as appears by the track of the old bed, which is still visible. The high
                    and circling banks upon the south side give to this valley the appearance of a
                    spacious bay; and, according to the tradition of the country, there was once a
                    harbour here. Nor does the tradition seem altogether groundless, pieces of
                    broken anchors having been found here, and some of them at no distant period.
                    The stream-tides would still flow near the place, if they were not kept back by
                    the dam-head built across the river at Stenhouse; and there is reason to believe
                    that the frith flowed considerably higher in former ages than it does at
                    present. In the near neighbourhood of this valley, upon the south, stand the
                    ruins of ancient Camelon, which, after it was abandoned by the Romans, was
                    probably inhabited for some ages by the natives of the country.</p>
                <p>Another ancient monument, called <hi rend="italic">Arthurs Oven,</hi> once stood
                    upon the banks of the Carron; but it has been entirely demolished. The corner of
                    a small inclosure between Stenhouse and the Carron Iron-works is pointed out as
                    the place where it stood. This is generally supposed to have been a Roman work;
                    though it is not easy to conceive what could be their motive for erecting such a
                    fabric, at so great a distance from any other of their works, and in a spot
                    which at that time must have been very remote and unfrequented.</p>
                <p>As the Carron extends over the half of the isthmus, and runs so near the ancient
                    boundaries of the Roman empire, the adjacent country fell naturally to be the
                    scene of many battles and rencounters. Historians mention a bloody battle fought
                    near the river between the Romans and the confederate army of the Scots and
                    Picts in the beginning of the fifth century. The scenes of some of Ossian’s
                    poems were, in the opinion of the translator <pb break="no" facs="nls:193349317"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0706-9317-0178"/>(though that perhaps is not worth much), upon the
                    banks of this river. About the distance of half a mile from the river, and near
                    the town of Falkirk, is the field of battle where the English defeated Wallace
                    in the year 1298. It goes by the name of <hi rend="italic">Grahams muir,</hi>
                    from the valiant John Graham, who fell there, and whose grave-stone is still to
                    be seen in the church-yard of Falkirk.</p>
                <p>The river Carron, though it has long since ceased to roll its stream amidst the
                    din of arms, still preserves its fame, by lending its aid to trade and
                    manufactures.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Carron,</hi> a small village of Scotland, at which the
                    celebrated iron-works are situated, lies in the parish of Lambert, on the
                    northern bank of the river Carron, about two miles from Falkirk. These works
                    belong to a chartered company, established in 1760, with a capital of L.150,000.
                    They are employed in the smelting of iron ores, and the manufacture of every
                    description of cast-iron goods, whether for the arts of war or peace. Cannon,
                    mortars, howitzers, carronades, shots and shells of all kinds, are cast here in
                    the highest perfection, not only for the use of the British, but for that of
                    foreign powers. Hence the Carron Foundery rivals those of Germany and Russia.
                    For the conveyance of their goods, the company have cut a canal, on which
                    lighters ply from the warehouses at the work to their harbour at Grangemouth,
                    where the goods are shipped for London. A railway runs from the works to the
                    Forth and Clyde Canal, where vessels are loaded for Glasgow, Liverpool, and
                    places on the west coast. The works consist of seven blast or smelting furnaces,
                    twenty air-furnaces, four cupola furnaces, mills for grinding fire-clay, and for
                    grinding and glazing smoothing irons, stove metal, &amp;c. The machinery of the
                    furnaces is moved by a large water-wheel. In the drought of summer an engine is
                    employed in lifting water to supply these wheels. An engine for the production
                    of blast works incessantly both day and night. Another is in the course of
                    erection, which will in every respect excel any in the kingdom. There are mills
                    for boring cylinders, &amp;c. the machinery of which is allowed to be the finest
                    in Europe. Two forges are employed in the manufacture of malleable iron
                    utensils. Water is supplied from dams or reservoirs which cover between two and
                    three hundred acres of ground. The resources of the surrounding country afford
                    ample facilities for carrying on such an extensive establishment. The stores of
                    iron-stone and coal are inexhaustible; and the ground is so flat, that railways
                    can be laid down at a trifling expense. These works employ in one way or other
                    between 2000 and 3000 individuals.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
