<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0706-8784-0137-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CARDIGANSHIRE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 6, page 137</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205150">Florida</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1173757">Welsh</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:849843">Causeways</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:891974">Devil</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1025507">Monks</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:829042">Bays</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1071040">Poor</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1099409">Rocks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="12" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4cz32806">Fall</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bd1d">Poor</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4f18sn8w">Pool</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b46q1sn3j">Pools</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vx06c7f">Welsh</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fk98">Devil</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4222rc53">Monachism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193348784" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CARDIGANSHIRE</label>, a county of Wales, is divided from
                    Caermarthenshire and Pembrokeshire, along the greatest part of its southern
                    side, by the Tivey; on the north it is divided from Merionethshire by the river
                    Dory, and from Montgomeryshire by an artificial boundary. The boundaries on the
                    east, between it and Radnorshire and Breconshire, are also artificial. On the
                    west it stretches along the sea-coast in a bending line, from north-east to
                    south-west, forming part of the shore of Cardigan Bay. Its extent, measured
                    along the shore, is nearly forty miles; its breadth does not average twenty. It
                    contains 726 square miles, or 464,640 acres, and is divided into five hundreds.
                    The market-towns are Aberystwith, Cardigan, Llanbodarnvawr, Llanbeder or
                    Lampeter, and Tregaron. The number of parishes, according to the last
                    parliamentary returns respecting the poor’s rates, is ninety-seven. It sends one
                    member to parliament, lies in the province of Canterbury and diocese of St
                    David’s, and is in the North Wales circuit. The coasts of Cardigan Bay (which is
                    formed by the projecting counties of Caernarvon on the north and Pembroke on the
                    south, with the coasts of Merioneth and Cardigan in the centre) have, according
                    to tradition and appearance, suffered greatly from the depredations of the sea,
                    especially on the Cardigan shore. The tradition of the country is, that there
                    was formerly a sixth hundred, which is now covered by the sea; and there are
                    still to be seen at low water several ridges of rocks, called causeways, which
                    seem to confirm the truth of this tradition. Of these the most remarkable is St
                    Patrick’s Causeway, which extends from within a mile of the point of Mochras,
                    south of Harlech, twenty-two miles into the sea, in a serpentine line. It is
                    formed of rough stones, twenty-four feet broad; and at the extremity there is a
                    round head, formed of sixteen great stones, one of which is four yards in
                    diameter. Trunks and roots of trees are also found at a considerable distance
                    from the shore.</p>
                <p>The principal rivers are the Tivey, the Rydiol, the Ystwith, and the Aeron. The
                    Tivey rises in Llyn Teefy, or Tivey Pool, in a mountain in the north-east of the
                    county. On the top of this mountain there are five lakes, of which Tivey Pool is
                    the principal. It is about one mile and a half in circumference, is surrounded
                    by high and perpendicular rocks, and is said never to have been fathomed. The
                    Tivey at first flows through a rocky district; afterwards, forming a regular
                    channel, it passes Tregaron; and at Llanbeder it becomes the boundary between
                    Caermarthenshire and Cardiganshirc. It falls into the sea about two miles below
                    Cardigan. The Rydiol rises on the south-west side of Plinlimmon; its course is
                    about south-west; and it falls into the sea near Aberystwith. About twelve miles
                    above this town is the Devil’s Bridge, called by the Welsh Pont y Monach, or the
                    Monks’ Bridge, and Pont ar Fynach, from the confluence here of the Fynaeh with
                    the Rydiol. There are two arches, one above the other. The uppermost is between
                    twenty and thirty feet in the chord, and the other less than twenty. The upper
                    one was built in 1753; the date of the building of the lower one is not known.
                    Near this bridge are the falls of the Fynach. The first fall takes place where
                    the river is much confined by the rocks. The water is carried about six feet
                    over them, into a basin eighteen feet below. The next fall is sixty feet, the
                    third fall is twenty, and the last is 110 feet. Near this is the fall of the
                    Rydiol, the scenery around which is considered as very striking and grand. The
                    Ystwith rises among the hills on the eastern side of the county, and falls into
                    the sea at Aberystwith. The Aeron is between six and seven miles in extent,
                    receives six tributary streams, and forms, during the whole of its course,
                    nearly the are of a circle. It falls into the sea at Aberaeron.</p>
                <p>That part of the country which lies along the sea is level, especially the
                    south-western extremity; but the'northern and eastern parts are very rugged and
                    mountainous. The soil of the low lands is either a light or a strong loam, lying
                    on slate. The soil of the mountainous division is in general thin and poor,
                    except in the narrow valleys, where it consists of clay or peat. The tract along
                    the sea-coast produces good crops of wheat, barley, turnips, potatoes, and oats.
                    The quality as well as the produce of the barley grown in some parts of this
                    tract is very remarkable. Between Aberaeron and Llanrysted is an extensive flat,
                    extending from the sea to the east mountains, which produces from sixty to
                    eighty bushels of fine barley per acre. This land is constantly under this
                    .crop, and has been so for at least half a century. It is manured every three
                    years with sea-weed. Potatoes arc grown on the peat mosses in such a manner as
                    at once to secure good crops and to drain the land. The potato sets are laid on
                    the surface of the bog, a little manure is spread over them, and they are
                    afterwards covered with earth dug out of the trenches.</p>
                <p>Very few sheep are kept on the low land, but on the mountains they are numerous.
                    They are in general the native breed, and very inferior both for wool and
                    carcass. Cattle are kept in all parts of the county; in the low lands, and in
                    the vales of the mountainous district, principally for butter and cheese; in the
                    other parts they are bred for the English drovers. Of the 464,640 acres which
                    this county contains, it is calculated that 100,000 are in tillage, 145,000 in
                    pasture, and the rest waste land.</p>
                <p>Cardiganshire was formerly famous for its mines of lead, but at present they are
                    not very productive; the principal are two in the vicinity of Cwmystwith. Near
                    Tal-y-bont are some that used to be very productive, but are now almost
                    exhausted; the matrix of the ore is carbonate of lime. There are also veins of
                    copper, but these are not wrought. The want of coal, of which there is none in
                    the whole county, the rugged nature of the country, and the badness of the
                    roads, are probably the chief causes why the mines arc not worked. Near
                    Aberystwith are large slate quarries; the slates lie in alternate strata with
                    shale, and are in compact masses, of a coarse texture; the inclination of the
                    strata varies very much, following the general irregularity of shale. The slate
                    that is found near the seacoast, not being mixed with shale, lies in
                    perpendicular strata. There are some very extensive tracts of peat, especially
                    on the coast beyond Aberystwith, bordering on the river Dovy; and from Strata
                    Florida, near the Tivey, to Llyn y Maes, or the Lake of the Flood; the latter
                    tract is one continued marshy bog, abounding in turbaries as far as Tregaron.
                    According to tradition, a town once stood in this marsh. As connected with the
                    natural history of this county, it may be remarked, that Mr Aikin observed, near
                    the banks of the Rydiol, a moor-buzzard, and the horse-ant, the largest species
                    of ants that are natives of Britain. The angel-fish is found in the bay of
                    Cardigan,.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193348797" xml:id="kp-eb0706-8797-0138"/>
                <p>There are few manufactures in this county; but at Llech-wydol, near Cardigan, are
                    iron and tin works. Black cattle, pigs, butter, barley, oats, flannels, Welsh
                    webs, bark, iron, tin, slates, and ale, are exported from Aberystwith and
                    Cardigan. There is a great fair for cattle and sheep at Rhos, near the source of
                    the Tivey.</p>
                <p>Cardiganshire is celebrated in the literary history of Wales for having given
                    birth to David ap Gwylim, who flourished between 1330 and 1370. From the poems
                    of this author, the modern literary dialect of Wales has been chiefly formed,
                    and this dialect is spoken with greater purity in the county of Cardigan than in
                    any other part of the principality.</p>
                <p>In Cardiganshire a custom prevails resembling the penny-weddings among the
                    peasantry of Scotland. Before marriage a <hi rend="italic">bidder</hi> goes from
                    house to house inviting the inhabitants to come to the wedding, and to bring
                    money and cheese and butter. The marriage always takes place on the Saturday,
                    and the guests assemble on the Friday with their presents. All these are set
                    down on paper, that, if demanded, they may be repaid; but this seldom happens.
                    The furnishing of the woman is also brought home on this day. On Saturday, ten
                    or twenty of the man’s friends who are best mounted, go to demand the bride, who
                    is placed on a horse behind her father, and rides off as fast as she can. She is
                    soon, however, overtaken. Presents continue to be received on the Saturday and
                    Sunday; on Monday they are sold, frequently making, with the money presented,
                    the sum of L.50 or L.60. </p>
                <p>In 1803 the poor’s rates amounted to L.10,167; in 1815 there was collected from
                    92 parishes L.15,409 8s. 6d.</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >’years.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="3" role="data" rows="1"><p>HOUSES.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="3" role="data" rows="1"><p>OCCUPATIONS.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="3" role="data" rows="1"><p>PERSONS.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>&lt;D</p><p>L2</p><p><hi
                            rend="superscript"> r</hi> 9 h-ł</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>By how many Families
                            occupied.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>ħθ</p><p>.5</p><p>.∙≡ ≡</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Families chiefly employed in
                            Agriculture.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Families chiefly employed in Trade,
                            Manufactures, or Handicraft.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>All other Families not comprised in
                            the two preceding classes.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Males.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Females.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Total of Persons.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1 1811</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>9639</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>11,296</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>129</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5864</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1913</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3519</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>23,759</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>26,501</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>50,260</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>i <hi rend="superscript">
                            1821</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>11,304</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>12,071</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>77</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6312</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2501</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3258</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>27,898</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>29,886</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>57,784</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1 1831</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>30,868</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>43,912</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>64,780</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
