<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0706-6558-0735-02" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">CLEMENCY</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 6, page 735</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kj57">Caesarism</term><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs1k">Manners</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1128153">Spaniards</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:843856">Caesarism</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:908898">Emperors</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1043068">Occasionalism</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193356558" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">CLEMENCY</label> denotes nearly the same thingwith mercy, and
                    implies a remission of severity towards offenders. The term is most generally
                    used in speaking of the forgiveness exercised by princes or persons of high
                    authority. It is the result, indeed, of a disposition which ought to be
                    cultivated by all ranks, though its effects cannot be equally conspicuous or
                    extensive. In praise of clemency joined with power, it is observed, that it is
                    not only the privilege, the honour, and the duty of a prince, but it is also his
                    se-&lt; curity, and better than all his garrisons, forts, and guards, to
                    preserve himself and his dominions in safety; that that prince is truly royal
                    who masters himself, looks upon all injuries as below him, and governs by equity
                    and reason, not by passion or caprice. In illustration of this subject, the
                    following examples arc selected out of many recorded in history.</p><p>Two patricians having conspired against Titus the Roman emperor, were discovered,
                    convicted, and sentenced to death by the senate; but the good-natured prince
                    sent for them, and in private admonished them, that they aspired in vain to the
                    empire, which was given by destiny; exhorting them to be satisfied with the rank
                    in which providence had placed them, and offering them any thing else which
                    might be in his power to grant. At the same time he dispatched a messenger to
                    the mother of one of them, who was then at a great distance, and under deep
                    concern about tb.e fate of her son, to assure her that her son was not only
                    alive, but forgiven.</p><p>Licinius having raised a numerous army, Zosimus says 130,000 men, endeavoured to
                    wrest the government out of the hands of his brother-in-law Constantine the
                    emperor. But his army being defeated, Licinius fled with what forces he could
                    rally to Nicocdia, whither Constantine pursued him, and immediately invested the
                    place; but on the second day of the siege, the emperor’s sister having entreated
                    him, with a flood of tears, by the tenderness he had ever shown for her, to
                    forgive her husband, and grant him at least his life,*he was prevailed upon to
                    comply with her request; and the next day, Licinius, finding no means of making
                    his escape, presented himself before the conqueror, and throwing himself at his
                    feet, yielded to him the purple and the other ensigns of sovereignty.
                    Constantine received him in a very friendly manner, entertained him at his
                    table, and afterwards sent him to Thessalonica, assuring him that he should live
                    unmolested so long as he raised no new disturbances.</p><p>The council of thirty, established at Athens by Lysander, committed the most
                    execrable cruelties. Upon pretence of restraining the multitude within their
                    duty, and to prevent seditions, they caused guards to be assigned them, armed
                    3000 of the citizens for that purpose, and at the same time disarmed all the
                    rest. The whole city was thrown into the utmost terror and dismay. Whoever
                    opposed their injustice and violence fell a victim to their resentment. Riches
                    were a crime which never failed to draw a sentence upon their owners, always
                    followed with death and the confiscation of estates, which the thirty tyrants
                    divided amongst themselves. They put more people to death, says Xenophon, in
                    eight months of a peace, than their enemies had done in a war of thirty years.
                    All the citizens of any consideration in Athens, who retained a love of liberty,
                    quitted a place reduced to so merciless and shameful a state of slavery, and
                    sought elsewhere an asylum, where they might live in safety. At the head of
                    these was Thrasybulus, a person of extraordinary merit, who beheld with the most
                    lively affliction the miseries of 11 is country.</p><p>But the Lacedaemonians had the inhumanity to endeavour to deprive those unhappy
                    fugitives of this last resource. They published an edict prohibiting the cities
                    of Greece from giving them refuge; decreed that they should be delivered up to
                    the thirty tyrants; and condemned all such as should contravene the execution of
                    this edict to pay a fine of five talents. Only two cities rejected with disdain
                    so unjust an ordinance, Megara and Thebes; the latter of which passed a decree
                    to punish all persons whatsoever that should see an Athenian attacked by his
                    enemies without doing their utmost to assist him. Lysias, an orator <pb break="no" facs="nls:193356571" xml:id="kp-eb0706-6571-0736"/> of
                    Syracuse, who had been banished by the thirty, raised 500 soldiers at his own
                    expense, and sent them to the aid of the common country of eloquence.
                    Thrasybulus lost no time in making the necessary preparations. After having
                    taken Phyla, a small fort in Attica, he marched to the Piraeus, of which he made
                    himself master. The thirty flew thither with their troops, and a battle ensued;
                    but the tyrants were completely overthrown. Critias, the most savage of their
                    number, was killed on the spot; and as the army was taking to flight,
                    Thrasybulus cried out, “Wherefore do you fly from me as from a victor, rather
                    than assist me as the avenger of your liberty? We are not enemies, but
                    fellow-citizens; nor have we declared war against the city, but against the
                    thirty tyrants.” He continued to remind them that they had the same origin,
                    country, laws, and religion. He exhorted them to compassionate their exiled
                    brethren, to restore their country to the latter, and resume their own liberty.
                    This discourse had the desired effect. The army, upon their return to Athens,
                    expelled the thirty, and substituted ten persons to govern in their room, whose
                    conduct proved no better than theirs; but King Pausanias, moved with compassion
                    for the deplorable condition to which a city, once so flourishing, was reduced,
                    had the generosity to favour the Athenians in secret, and at length obtained a
                    peace for them. It was sealed with the blood of the tyrants, who having taken
                    arms to reinstate themselves in the government, were all put to the sword; and
                    this left Athens in the full possession of its liberty. All the exiles were
                    recalled. Thrasybulus at that time proposed the celebrated amnesty, by which the
                    citizens engaged upon oath that all past transactions should be buried in
                    oblivion. The government was re-established upon its ancient footing, the laws
                    were restored to their pristine vigour, and magistrates were elected with the
                    usual forms.</p><p>This, says Rollin, is one of the finest events in ancient history, worthy the
                    Athenian clemency and benevolence, and has served as a model to succeeding ages
                    in all good governments. Never had tyranny been more cruel and bloody than that
                    which the Athenians had lately thrown off. Every house was in mourning, every
                    family bewailed the loss of some relation; it had been a series of public
                    robbery and rapine, in which license and impunity had authorized all manner of
                    crimes. The people seemed to have a right to demand the blood of all accomplices
                    in such notorious malversations, and even the interest of the state appeared to
                    authorize such a claim, that by exemplary severities such enormous crimes might
                    be prevented for the future. But Thrasybulus rising above these sentiments, from
                    the superiority of his more extensive genius, and the views of a more discerning
                    and profound policy, foresaw, that by acquiescing in the punishment of the
                    guilty, eternal seeds of discord and enmity would remain, to weaken the public
                    by domestic divisions, when it was necessary to unite against the common enemy,
                    and would also occasion the loss to the state of a great number of citizens, who
                    might render it important services in. the view of making amends for past
                    misbehaviour.</p><p>Such conduct, after great troubles in a state, has always appeared to the ablest
                    politicians the most certain and ready means to restore the public peace and
                    tranquillity. Cicero, when Rome was divided into two factions upon the occasion
                    of Caesar’s death, who had been killed by the conspirators, calling to mind this
                    celebrated amnesty, proposed, after the example of the Athenians, to bury all
                    that had passed in eternal oblivion.</p><p>Cardinal Mazarin observed to Don Lewis de Haro, prime minister of Spain, that his
                    gentle and humane conduct in France had prevented the troubles and revolts <hi rend="italic">ct</hi> that kingdom from having any fatal consequences, and “that
                    the king had not lost a foot of land by them to that day ;” whereas “the
                    inflexible severity of the Spaniards was the occasion that the subjects of that
                    monarchy, wherever they threw off the mask, never returned to their obedience
                    but by the force of arms; which sufficiently appears,” says he, “in the example
                    of the Hollanders, who are in the peaceable possession of so many provinces that
                    not an age ago were the patrimony of the king of Spain.”</p><p>Leonidas the Lacedaemonian having, with 300 men only, disputed .the Pass of
                    Thermopylae against the whole army of Xerxes, and being killed in that
                    engagement, Xerxes, by the advice of Mardonius, one of his generals, caused his
                    dead body to be hung upon a gallows, thereby making the intended dishonour of
                    his enemy his own immortal shame. But some time afterwards, Xerxes being
                    defeated, and Mardonius slain, one of the principal citizens of Aegina came and
                    addressed himself to Pausanius, desiring him to avenge the indignity which
                    Mardonius and Xerxes had shown to Leonidas, by treating Mardonius’s body after
                    the same manner; and as a farther motive for doing so, he added, that by thus
                    satisfying the manes of those who were killed at Thermopylae, he would be sure
                    to immortalize his own name throughout all Greece, and render his memory
                    precious to the latest posterity. “Carry thy base counsels elsewhere,” replied
                    Pausanias; “thou must have a very wrong notion of true glory, to imagine that
                    the way for me to acquire it is to resemble the barbarians. If the esteem of the
                    people of Aegina is not to be purchased but by such a proceeding, I shall be
                    content with preserving that of the Lacedaemonians only, amongst whom the base
                    and ungenerous pleasure of revenge is never put in competition with that of
                    showing clemency and moderation to their enemies, especially after their death.
                    As for the souls of my departed countrymen, they are sufficiently avenged by the
                    death of the many thousand Persians slain upon the spot in the last
                    engagement.”</p></div></body></text></TEI>