<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0706-9759-0212-10" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">CASHMERE</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 6, page 212</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1028334">Mountaineering</term><term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1028364">Mountaineers</term><term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1028366">Mountains</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:990901">Lakes</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1098312">Rivers</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:957175">Hindus</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:798948">Afghans</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1126120">Songs</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1008726">Maps</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1205406">Afghanistan</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4qn5zh77">Mahommedanism</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kh0c">Afghans</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68967">Songs</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term><term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term><term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term><term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4736m682">Lakes</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193349759" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">CASHMERE</label>, formerly a province of Northern Hindustan,
                    but in later times an appendage of Afghanistan. It is an extensive valley,
                    nearly of an oval form, and surrounded by lofty mountains, and is estimated to
                    extend ninety miles in a winding direction from the south-east to the
                    north-west, and is from forty to sixty-nine miles in breadth. Its situation is
                    between the 34th and 35th degrees of north latitude, and between the 73d and
                    76th degrees of east longitude. It is divided by its mountainous barrier from
                    Little Thibet on the north, from Ladauk on the east, from the Punjab on the
                    south, and from Pukhlee on the west. This country is universally celebrated in
                    the east for its romantic beauties, its fertile soil, and its temperate climate.
                    According to ancient tradition, this valley, inclosed by mountains rising above
                    the limit of perpetual snow, was the bed of a great lake, into which flowed all
                    the streams from the adjacent hills, carrying with them large quantities of
                    soil. The lake at last opening itself a passage through the mountains, left the
                    valley <pb break="no" facs="nls:193349772" xml:id="kp-eb0706-9772-0213"/>covered with a rich alluvial deposit, an admirable
                    field for human industry. The valley of Cashmere is not exposed to the
                    periodical rains which deluge the rest of India, the clouds being shut out by
                    the height of the mountains; and it has only light showers. These, however, are
                    in sufficient abundance to feed some thousands of cascades, which roll down into
                    the valley from every part of the lofty barrier that encircles it. The Behut or
                    Jhelum, the Hydaspes of Alexander, is the chief river: it runs through the whole
                    length of the valley with a remarkably smooth current from east to west, and
                    receives numerous tributary streams from every quarter. The plains of Cashmere
                    being abundantly supplied with moisture, yield rich crops of rice, which form
                    the common food of the inhabitants. On the higher grounds, among the hills, all
                    the European grains, namely, wheat, barley, and other species, arrive at
                    maturity. In this elevated region are also found most of the plants, fruit and
                    forest trees, and flowers, common to Europe, such as violets, roses,
                    narcis-susses, and other flowers, which grow wild, and perfume the air; and of
                    fruits, the apple, the pear, the plum, the aprico, and the nut, with abundance
                    of grapes; and many kitchen herbs peculiar to cold countries. A species of nut
                    which grows in the lakes affords an article of food to the lower classes. A
                    superior sort of saffron is also produced in some parts; and iron of an
                    excellent quality is found in the high lands.</p><p>The mountains which surround Cashmere are some of them of great elevation; and,
                    ascending from the plains, we find various climates and the productions of
                    distant regions concentrated within a short space. The lower ridges of these
                    mountains, which are of a moderate height, are covered with trees and verdure,
                    and afford excellent pasturage for cattle of various species, as well as for
                    wild beasts; while they are entirely unfrequented by the ferocious animals, such
                    as lions and tigers. Above these fertile and romantic regions, the increasing
                    cold gradually stunts the vegetation; and the traveller reaches that highest
                    range of mountains which tower above the clouds into the regions of perpetual
                    snow. Among these mountains are interspersed many fruitful and well-watered
                    valleys; and they afford shelter to a rude and bold class of inhabitants, who,
                    in these deep recesses, bid defiance to conquering ' armies, and who have little
                    intercourse with the inhabitants of the plains, their poverty offering as little
                    inducement to the visits of merchants as of warriors.</p><p>Cashmere has been long famed for the manufacture of shawls, which are distributed
                    all over northern and western Asia, and are exported in great quantities to
                    Europe. These shawls owe their peculiar beauty and fine texture to the wool
                    which is brought from Thibet, lying at a distance of a month’s journey to the
                    north-east. The wool forms the inner coat with which the goat is covered, and
                    the breed is peculiar to Thibet, all attempts to introduce it into India or
                    Persia having invariably failed. The wool, which is originally of a dark gray
                    colour, is bleached in Cashmere by the help of a preparation of rice-flour. The
                    process of manufacture is very slow; not more than one inch being added to the
                    finest shawls in the course of a day. It is estimated that about 16,000 looms
                    were at one time employed in this manufacture; but of late years the demand has
                    declined, owing to the decay of the Persian and Hindustance empires, and the
                    desolation and poverty of the eastern countries. When Cashmere was tributary to
                    Afghanistan, a great portion of the public revenue was exacted in shawls. The
                    yarn into which the wool is spun is dyed with various colours, and after being
                    woven, the piece is once washed, and the border, in which is displayed a variety
                    of figures and colours, is attached to the shawls in so dexterous a manner that
                    it is hardly possible to discover the junction. The price varies, in proportion
                    to the quality, from ten or twelve, to fifty shillings; and where the shawl is
                    of flowered work, the price sometimes rises as high as L.5 or L.6. A species of
                    writing paper is also made in Cashmere, which is highly praised throughout the
                    East, and was formerly a great article of traffic; as were also its lacquered
                    ware, cutlery, and sugar. A wine resembling Madeira is manufactured; and a
                    spirituous liquor is distilled from the grape. But very little trade is now
                    carried on. The internal intercourse of the country is chiefly maintained by
                    means of the numerous streams by which it is intersected, and which are
                    navigated in long and narrow boats moved with paddles. Owing to the disorderly
                    state of the country, commerce is insecure; and the course of the river is beset
                    by robbers, who frequently set upon and plunder the unwary traveller.</p><p>The people of Cashmere are a distinct nation of the Hindu stock, and differ in
                    appearance, language, and manners, from all their Tartar neighbours, who are an
                    ugly race. The men are remarkably stout, active, and industrious; while the
                    females have been celebrated for their beauty and complexions, which approach to
                    the brunette. They have been on this account much sought after for wives by the
                    Mogul nobility of Delhi. They are naturally a gay and lively people; excessively
                    addicted to pleasure, and notorious for falsehood and cunning all over the East.
                    They are eager in the pursuit of wealth; and are considered as much more acute
                    and intriguing than the natives of Hindustan generally are. They are said to be
                    addicted to literature and poetry, which is probably limited to a few popular
                    Songs. The country, although fertile, has but a scanty population; both industry
                    and agriculture being retarded by the disorderly habits of the people, and by
                    the want of any efficient police to maintain order and peace. The total number
                    of inhabitants is not estimated to exceed half a million, a great proportion of
                    whom are Hindus. There are also Mahommedans, partly Soonies, and partly also of
                    the sect of Ali. All Cashmere is reckoned holy land; and miraculous fountains
                    abound in all parts. There are numerous temples dedicated to the various objects
                    of Hindu superstition, as Siva, Vishnu, Brahma, &amp;c.; though many of these
                    monuments of Brah- * minical superstition have been destroyed by Mahommc-dan
                    invaders. The country is subject to the dreadful evil of earthquakes; and, to
                    guard against their effects, all the houses are built of wood, which is
                    abundant. The author of the Ayeen Acbery dwells with rapture on the romantic
                    beauty of the valley of Cashmere, which was said to be the favourite retreat of
                    the Mogul emperors when they relaxed from the cares of government; and this
                    description is so far confirmed by Bernier, who in 1663 visited this country in
                    the suite of Aurungzebe.</p><p>As far as the history of Cashmere can be collected from imperfect traditions, the
                    people appear originally to have been Hindus. The period of its subjugation to
                    its Mahommedan conquerors is uncertain. About the year 1012 Mahmoud of Ghizni
                    invaded and plundered the country, but does not appear to have taken permanent
                    possession of it. In the year 1323 it was invaded by an army of about seventy
                    thousand Tartars, whose commander established himself as sovereign of the
                    country, and was soon after converted to Mahommedanism by a priest, who in
                    return was made his prime minister. His descendants reigned in Cashmere till the
                    year 1541, when it was conquered by Mirza Hyder, on the part of the Emperor
                    Humayon, and was annexed by Acbar to his empire in 1588. It was ruled by the
                    house of Timour for a hundred and sixty years, after which it was betrayed by
                    the Mogul governor, about 1754, to Ahmed Shah Duranny, and constituted a
                    province of the Afghan sovereignty.</p><pb break="no" facs="nls:193349785" xml:id="kp-eb0706-9785-0214"/><p>During the revolutions in that kingdom in 1809, the governor, Mohammed Khan,
                    revolted, and still continues to maintain his independence. The principal towns
                    are Cashmere, called also Serinagur; and Islamabad.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Cashmere,</hi> the capital of the above province, is a large
                    city, which extends three miles on each side of the river Jhelum, over which
                    there are five wooden bridges. It is of unequal breadth; but in some places it
                    is nearly two miles. It has a small citadel called Shore Ghur, in the south-east
                    quarter, where the governor resides. The houses are mostly built*of wood, with
                    partition walls of brick and mortar. They are high, being many of them three
                    stories, having sloping wooden roofs covered with a bed of fine earth, which in
                    summer is sown with flowers, and exhibits a lively appearance. The town, like
                    most of those in the East, is dirty in the extreme, its narrow streets being
                    covered with the filth of the inhabitants, who, even in the East, are
                    proverbially unclean. The river is, notwithstanding, covered with baths. The
                    public buildings in the city are not of any consequence; but in the environs
                    there are the remains of palaces built by the emperors of Hindustan. There is a
                    beautiful lake near the town, which extends from the north-east quarter in an
                    oval circumference of five or six miles, and communicates, with the Jhelum by a
                    narrow channel near the suburbs. On the east side of the lake is a detached hill
                    called Tukhti Solomon. On this eminence stands a mosque dedicated to Solomon, to
                    whose miraculous interposition the Mahommedans ascribe the draining off of the
                    waters from the valley; whilst the Hindus claim this river for their divinities.
                    Near this lake stands another hill, which is covered with orchards and gardens,
                    and has on its summit a mosque dedicated to a Mahommedan saint held in high
                    estimation; and in the centre of the lake is an island, on which the Emperor
                    Jehangire built a palace, which he adorned with gardens and water-works at an
                    immense expense, and to which he frequently retired from the heat of India and
                    the noise of a court. A heavy fall of rain, accompanied by a tremendous flood,
                    which took place in 1635, greatly injured the city and all the buildings in the
                    vicinity. Bernier, who visited Cashmere in 1663, gives a romantic and
                    interesting description of it. But since it has come under the dominion of the
                    Afghans, it has fallen into decay, and its buildings are many of them crumbling
                    into ruin. The travelling distance from Lahore is 587 miles, from Agra 724, from
                    Lucknow 866, from Bombay 1277, from Calcutta 1564, and from Madras 1882.
                    (Rennell’s <hi rend="italic">Memoir of a Map of Hindustan</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> Elphinstone’s <hi rend="italic">Account of the Kingdom of Caubul</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> Foster’s <hi rend="italic">Journey from Bengal to
                    England</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> Bernier, Hamilton, &amp;c.)</p></div></body></text></TEI>