<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0706-0318-0255-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CAVAN</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 6, page 255</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4h708258">Surveying</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zd00">Surveys</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4125q963">Dominicans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4028pc5x">Soils</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204597">Virginia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1139635">Surveys</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1139579">Surveying</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:805532">Allene</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1028366">Mountains</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1124682">Soils</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193350318" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CAVAN</label>, the most southern county of the province of
                    Ulster, in Irelend, is bounded by the counties of Leitrim, Fermanagh, Monaghan,
                    Louth, Meath, Westmeath, and Longford. Its form is nearly circular, with the
                    exception of the barony of Tullaghagh, which projects in a northwestern
                    direction between the two first named of the surrounding counties. It lies
                    nearly in the centre of Ireland, midway between the Atlantic Ocean and the Irish
                    Sea, its extremities being less than eighteen miles from either of these waters.
                    According to the latest and most accurate calculation, its contents are
                    estimated at 473,450 acres, or 740 square miles.</p>
                <p>The most ancient geographers speak of it as being inhabited by the tribe of the
                    Erdini. At the period of the arrival of the English, and for some centuries
                    afterwards, it was known by the name of the Brennie, Brennie O’Reylie, or
                    O’Reylie’s country. Under a commission issued by James I. for the subdivision of
                    the county, it was portioned out into seven baronies, two of which were assigned
                    to Sir John O’Reylie, three to his brother, uncle, and the representatives of
                    another of the family, while the two remaining baronies, possessed by the septs
                    of M‘Rernon and M‘Gaurol, being remote, and bordering on O’Rorke’s country, now
                    the county of Leitrim, were allowed to continue subject to the exactions of the
                    Irish lords, the crown reserving two hundred beeves upon the whole county for
                    the lord-deputy’s provision. There was also an ancient subdivision of the county
                    into small portions called polls, each containing twenty-four acres. It is now
                    divided into the baronies of Castleraghan, Clonkee, Clonmaghon, Upper and Lower
                    Loughtee, Tullaghgarvey, Tullaghagh, and Tullaghonoho. At present the county
                    rates are levied according to a peculiar measurement. A certain number of town
                    lands are united under the name of a <hi rend="italic">carvagli,</hi> of which
                    each barony contains a thousand, making eight thousand carvaghs for the whole
                    county. Hence, if these were all of an equal size, which is not the case, as
                    they vary with the superficial contents of their respective baronies, each would
                    contain something less than sixty acres.</p>
                <p>The county, according to its civil arrangements, under which the local taxes are
                    levied, contains twenty-nine parishes, besides four parts of parishes, the
                    remaining parts of which are in the adjoining counties, three in Meath, and one
                    in Fermanagh; but, according to its ecclesiastical arrangement, into
                    thirty-three, of which twenty-nine are in the diocese of Kilmore, three in that
                    of Ardagh, and one in that of Meath. The bishopric of Kilmore extends over the
                    whole of the county. The seat of the see is at Kilmore, a small town nearly in
                    the centre of Cavan. According to the latest return made to parliament, the see
                    lands amounted to 47,361 acres, but no statement was then sent in as to the
                    pecuniary value of the see.</p>
                <p>The population was estimated by Beaufort in 1792 at 81,570 souls; in 1813,
                    according to the imperfect census then taken, it was supposed to be 164,000; in
                    1821, by the census of that year, it amounted to 195,076; and, according to the
                    late but imperfect census of 1831, it was 228,050, giving an increase, in forty
                    years, of 146,480 souls, or nearly double of its amount at the earliest of these
                    dates.</p>
                <p>The county sends two representatives to the imperial parliament. Before the union
                    it sent six, two for the county, and two each for the towns of Cavan and Bel
                    turbet.</p>
                <p>The surface of the country is very uneven, consisting altogether of hills and
                    valleys, without any level ground. The hills rise to a considerable elevation in
                    the interior. The highest land in the county is the mountain of Slieve Russel,
                    in the barony of Tullaghagh, on the confines of Fermanagh. In the same barony is
                    Quilca Mountain, which is held in great veneration by the inhabitants, who
                    relate many traditionary fables connected with the ancient superstitions of the
                    country. It was also the place for installing the M‘Guires, the chieftains of
                    Fermanagh.</p>
                <p>The valleys arc, in many parts, the receptacles of lakes, which, though not of
                    very extended dimensions, arc objects of much interest, from the picturesque
                    beauties of their scenery. Lough Ramor, one of the largest, is in the southern
                    extremity of the county, near Virginia. It contains several islands, once well
                    wooded, but now mostly bare. Lough Gawnagh, in the south-west, may be considered
                    rather as a boundary between Cavan and Fermanagh, than as exclusively belonging
                    to either county. The same observation applies to Lough Shillin. Lough Ough-ter
                    lies between the towns of Cavan and Killeshandra. Though not of very imposing
                    dimensions, the irregularity of its form, the large and beautiful islands
                    imbedded in its waters, and the many deep recesses studded with overhanging
                    woods that wind among its high banks, produce a rich variety of prospect. The
                    interest excited by its natural beauties is augmented by a circumstance of
                    historical notoriety. Bishop Bedel, when taken prisoner during the civil wars of
                    1641, was confined in Cloghoughter, one of its islands. The castle, which was
                    used as the prison of this venerable prelate, is still pointed out to strangers.
                    Beclel’s remains were deposited in Kihnore church. 'The most remarkable of the
                    smaller lakes, which are to be met with in most parts of the county, is Lough
                    Swillan, in the neighbourhood of Shercock, it being considered by many as the
                    principal source of the river Erne. According to others, this river, the largest
                    in the county, derives its origin from the Lake of Scrabo, one of the minor
                    sheets of water that form Lough Gawnagh. The river itself takes a northerly
                    direction by Killcshandra and Belturbet, being enlarged during its course by the
                    Croghan, Ballyhayes, Annalee, and other streams. It enters Lough <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193350331" xml:id="kp-eb0706-0331-0256"/>Erne at its most southern
                    extremity, passes through it, and discharges itself into the Atlantic at
                    Ballyshannon, in the county of Donegal. Woodside River, which skirts the county
                    on the side of Fermanagh, falls into Lough Erne at the same place. The Shannon
                    is said by some topographers to take its rise in Quilca Mountain, under the name
                    of the Owenmore, which it changes for its more celebrated appellation on its
                    junction with the Doubally, at the point where it enters the county of Leitrim,
                    a few miles before it discharges its united streams into Lough Allen.</p>
                <p>The climate of this county is chilly, and the weather often boisterous,
                    particularly in the mountainous districts. The soil is a stiff wet clay, cold
                    and spongy, producing a coarse rushy pasturage, beneath which is usually a thick
                    stratum of brown clay, resting upon a heavy yellow argillaceous substratum. The
                    soil is much improved by draining, for which its undulating surface affords
                    great facilities, and by gravelling or liming. Limestone is scarce in some
                    districts, yet much sought after; so that it is at times drawn from distances of
                    ten or twelve miles. In other parts, particularly throughout the baronies of
                    Castleraghan, Clonkee, and Clonmoghan, marl, which is met with very generally,
                    is preferred to lime, as the latter forms hard lumps when mixed with the clay
                    soil, while the former renders the soil loose and friable. A very fine kind of
                    manure, formed of decayed limestone, is found in the mountainous parts of
                    Tullaghagh. In the banks of rivers it is in great plenty; and about a mile from
                    Swadlingbar there is a large pile of it, which, when used judiciously, produces
                    most luxuriant crops.</p>
                <p>Bog of the best quality, the red ashes of which form an excellent manure, is
                    abundant. The upper part next the surface is dense and close, and makes the best
                    fuel; that immediately under is friable, and therefore less valued as fuel. The
                    bottom is solid and serviceable. In the moorish bogs, in which argillaceous
                    strata are met with throughout the peat, marl abounds, and is very easily
                    raised.</p>
                <p>A rich iron ore was raised from Quilca Mountain, and long wrought with
                    considerable profit. The ore was smelted at Swadlingbar, where mills were
                    erected for the purpose; but the works were ultimately relinquished, in
                    con-quence of the failure of timber for fuel. At Ortnacullagh, near Ballyconnel,
                    fragments of lead and silver ore are carried down the stream. Pure sulphur is
                    also found there. In this and in other parts of Tullaghagh barony, fullers’
                    earth, pipe-clay, potters’ clay, and brick-clay, are frequently met with. Fine
                    white and red transparent spars have also been occasionally picked up near
                    Fermanagh. There are indications of coal in Lugnaguilla, the most north-western
                    point of the county. It is also said that this mineral has been found in the
                    mountain of Slieve Russel, where it has been dug out of the side of the hill in
                    blocks near the surface. Another vein is said to exist at Glasleek, near
                    Shercock, of a very sulphureous quality, burning well, and emitting a bright
                    blue flame.</p>
                <p>These indications of minerals are accompanied with their usual concomitants,
                    mineral springs. The most remarkable is that of Swadlingbar, which has long
                    maintained a high character for its efficacy in restoring debilitated
                    constitutions. Its predominant ingredient is sulphur. Near the same village
                    there is a chalybeate spring. The small lake of Lough Leighs, or
                    Lough-an-Leighaghs, which signifies the healing lake, on the summit of a
                    mountain between Bailieborough and Kingscourt, is celebrated for its
                    antiscorbutic qualities. Its waters are used for drinking and bathing; but the
                    most beneficial effects are said to be produced by the mud raised from the
                    bottom of it being rubbed on the diseased part. The level of the lake never
                    varies. It has no visible supply nor vent for its discharge; neither is it ever
                    frozen or changed in temperature during the severest winters. The water at the
                    surface is clear; but within a foot downwards it becomes clogged with mud, which
                    thickens as the lake descends, to a depth hitherto unascertained. The mud is
                    drawn up for medical purposes from a depth of thirty feet, by means of a pole
                    with a hay-rope twisted round it, to which it adheres, exhibiting, when exposed
                    to the atmosphere, a greasy shining surface like tar. The water is slightly
                    chalybeate. The best season for its use is from June to August. It is said to
                    have been effectual in the cure of leprosy. Other mineral springs of inferior
                    note are those of Derrylester, containing sulphur and natron; Owen Bruen,
                    containing sulphur and calcareous nitre; and Carrickmore, containing calcareous
                    nitre, alkali, and some sulphur. The water of the last named is extremely
                    cold.</p>
                <p>The general character of the people is highly favourable. They are much inclined
                    to acts of kindliness towards each other; their hospitality to strangers is
                    proverbial, and they testify the most laudable anxiety for the education of
                    their children. Crimes of atrocity are uncommon. According to a parliamentary
                    return in 1830, the total number of individuals committed for offences during
                    that year was 171, of whom only 61 were convicted; of these thirty were for
                    illicit distillation, seventeen for larceny, and the rest for assaults,
                    cattle-stealing, and vagrancy. Domestic manufactures are generally combined with
                    agricultural occupations. The culture of flax and the fabric of linens of
                    coarser qualities formerly employed much of the time not required for the
                    external labours of the farm; but this source of profitable employment has
                    gradually declined with the general depression of the linen manufacture in
                    Ireland. The farms are small, from thirty to seven acres, the smallest being the
                    more numerous, in the proportion of ten to one. In the mountainous parts, where
                    the land is chiefly under grazing, the farms are more extensive. Wheat and
                    barley are but little cultivated. The hilly grounds are chiefly under oats, of
                    which the more elevated parts produce a very hardy species, quite black. They
                    are sown after one or two crops of potatoes; and these two vegetables form the
                    principal part of the food of the peasantry. In the mountainous parts the plough
                    is never used, in consequence of the rocky nature of the ground. The loy, a kind
                    of spade long in the blade, with a peculiar curve to prevent the adhesion of the
                    soil, is used in its stead. With this instrument the grain is trenched in high
                    ridges. Twelve men can dig an acre in a day. The undulating nature of the
                    ground, and the copious supply of water from the numerous small lakes and
                    rivers, render the land well suited for draining; but this and other modes of
                    improvement are in many instances checked, in consequence of the short and
                    unsatisfactory tenure by which much of the land in this country is held under
                    church and school land leases. The general character of the farming may be
                    summed up in the expression, that the people are by no means wanting in
                    exertion, but their modes of culture are defective. Most farmers prefer the old
                    Irish breed of black cattle, because, though less inclined to fatten, they give
                    a larger quantity of milk. The oxen of Lough tee barony arc an exception to this
                    remark.</p>
                <p>Illicit distillation was carried on here to a great extent. The lakes afforded
                    great facilities to its practice. The grain was steeped in them, and the
                    portable and cheap apparatus employed in the process was set up close to their
                    borders; so that, in case of alarm, the whole could be flung into the water at a
                    moment’s notice, and remain concealed till raised again for future service. The
                    practice, so injurious to industry and moral improvement, is considerably on the
                    decline.</p>
                <p>The soil, in those districts not well adapted for tillage, <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193350344" xml:id="kp-eb0706-0344-0257"/>is peculiarly favourable for
                    trees. Shrubs, which flourish vigorously in spi&lt;e of the inclemency of the
                    climate, spring out of the fissures of the rock on the mountainous districts.
                    Throughout the barony of Loughtee, and more particularly along the rich tract
                    watered by the Erne, timber trees are to be seen in great numbers. They are
                    chiefly to be found in demesnes, where the gentry seem to vie with one another
                    in their cultivation; so that the bareness of the landscape, too long a glaring
                    drawback upon the natural beauties of the county, is every day less observable.
                    The seats of the resident gentry are numerous and elegant. Lord Farnham has a
                    noble mansion at Cavan. A fine see-house, now building by the Bishop of Kilmore,
                    is nearly completed. Villas of much architectural and rural elegance are to be
                    seen in various parts of the county.</p>
                <p>According to the returns made under the population act in 1821, and by the
                    commissioners of education in 1824-5, the state of education was as follows:</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Boys.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Girls.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Sex not ascertained.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Total.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1821</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>....6080</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2726....</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>...8806</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1824-5...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>..11001....</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6492...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>245</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>..17738</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The religious persuasions of the pupils in the latter of these two statements
                    were as follows :—Of the established church, 4004; dissenters, 922; Roman
                    Catholics, 12,648; religion not ascertained 164. The number of schools was 346:
                    of these, 280, containing 12,700 pupils, were wholly maintained by the fees of
                    the pupils; and the remaining 66, containing 5039 pupils, were supported by the
                    contributions of the higher classes, or by grants or endowments of public money.
                    ∙</p>
                <p>The population of the county is chiefly rural. None of its towns contains 3000
                    inhabitants, and but five contain more than 1000 each.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Cavan,</hi> the capital of the above county, has little to
                    recommend it to special notice. It is situated near the centre of the county, in
                    the parish of Urney, and barony of Upper Loughtee, on one of the tributary
                    streams of the Erne. Its situation is pleasant and healthful, being a large
                    valley, surrounded on every side by elevated grounds. A hill immediately above
                    the town, on the Dublin side, commands a very extended prospect. The town was
                    burnt down in 1791. The consequence has been that it has risen from its ashes in
                    an improved form, excepting some of the suburbs, which consist of a succession
                    of mud-built hovels, the seats of squalor and destitution too often to be seen
                    in similar situations in other country towns of Ireland. The court-house is
                    elegant in its proportions, and convenient in its internal arrangements. The
                    church, built on an elevated site, at one extremity of the town, is also an
                    elegant erection. Not far from the church is a large Roman Catholic chapel,
                    which, together with a dissenting house, was erected at the expense of Lord
                    Farnham, the proprietor of the town. In another quarter is the county infirmary,
                    to the support of which the surrounding gentry contribute liberally. Six
                    alms-houses for destitute widows have been founded by a bequest of a member of
                    the Lanesborough family. The most conspicuous building is the grammar-school,
                    one of the royal foundations of Charles I. It was rebuilt about thirty years
                    ago, at an expense of L.7500, on an eminence overlooking one of the main
                    entrances into the town. It is large and handsome, though by no means highly
                    ornamented, and is capable of accommodating upwards of one hundred resident
                    pupils. The master enjoys a salary of L.300 per annum, besides the fees from
                    pupils, with an additional allowance of L.100 for an assistant; he has also the
                    produce of ten acres of land adjoining the house. Notwithstanding these
                    advantages, the residents of the town and neighbourhood have for some years
                    reaped little benefit from this noble endowment, in consequence of the very
                    advanced age of the head master; nor have their remonstrances to the board of
                    education under whose superintendence it is, and which consists of the four
                    archbishops, and several of the bishops, nor their application to the lord
                    lieutenant, in whose gift is the disposal of the mastership, as yet been
                    effectual in procuring for them the benefits of liberal education for their
                    children contemplated by its royal founder. The sons of the neighbouring gentry,
                    and of the respectable resident inhabitants, are therefore sent, at much expense
                    and inconvenience, to distant places for their literary improvement. The county
                    jail is a substantial building, but rather small for the average number of its
                    inmates. A monastery of Dominican friars, founded by O’Reilly, chieftain of the
                    Brennie, existed here; and it was the place of burial of the celebrated Irish
                    general Owen Roe O’Neal, who died by poison at Cloghoughter in 1649. The town
                    was incorporated by a royal charter of James I., dated 15th November, in the
                    eighth year of that monarch’s reign. The population in 1821 amounted to 2320,
                    and in 1831 to 2322. (Coote’s <hi rend="italic">Statistical Survey of
                    Cavan</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> Shaw Mason’s <hi rend="italic">Parochial
                    Survey of Ireland</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> Rutty’s <hi rend="italic">Mineral
                    Waters</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> Lynch’s <hi rend="italic">Geography of
                    Ireland</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi><hi rend="italic">Reports of Commissioners
                    of Educations</hi>.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
