<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0706-6350-0719-08" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CLACKMANNANSHIRE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 6, page 719</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1109125">Scots</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term n="14" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:865087">Coal</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:865671">Coaling</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1150792">Tides</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fk98">Devil</term>
                    <term n="14" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4fb4wm7s">Coal</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4js9h942">Coaling</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4qr4nq8b">Tides</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193356350" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CLACKMANNANSHIRE</label>, one of the counties of Scotland,
                    situated between 56° 5' and 56° 14' north latitude, and between 3° 33' and 3°
                    56'west longitude from Greenwich, is bounded on the south and south-west by the
                    river Forth, which separates it from Stirlingshire, by Fifeshire on the
                    south-east, and in every other quarter by Perthshire. It is the smallest county
                    in Scotland, being littje more than eight miles in length, and, at a medium, six
                    miles and <hi rend="italic">a</hi> half in breadth; thus extending over
                    fifty-two square miles, or 33,280 acres. But its value is much greater than in
                    the ratio of its extent. About three fourths of its surface are under
                    cultivation, a greater proportion, with the <pb break="no" facs="nls:193356363"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0706-6363-0720"/>exception of East Lothian, than that of any other
                    county of Scotland; and it abounds in the useful minerals, which have long been
                    wrought upon a very extensive scale.</p>
                <p>Between the Ochil Hills, which form the northern boundary of this district, <hi
                    rend="subscript"> ι</hi> and the rich alluvial tracts on the banks of the Forth,
                    which winds along in a very irregular line on its opposite extremity, there is a
                    considerable variety of surface. An elevated ridge rises on the west, and,
                    running through the middle of the county, spreads itself gradually till it
                    reaches the eastern boundary, skirting the alluvial or carse lands on the south,
                    and the vale of Dovan on the north. And still farther to the north, the Oehil
                    Hills, the highest of which, Beneloch, in the parish of Tillicoultry, rises
                    nearly 2500 feet above the level of the sea, form a very picturesque landscape,
                    having their generally verdant surface broken by bold projecting rocks, and
                    deeply indented ravines, the beds of many a pellucid stream, with coppice and
                    thriving plantations occasionally interspersed. These hills protect the lower
                    grounds from the piercing winds which blow from the north and north-east, and
                    give Clackmannanshire some advantage, in regard to climate, over the adjoining
                    counties.</p>
                <p>The only streams worthy of notice which traverse this county are the Dovan and
                    the Black Dovan, or, as they are often called, the North Devon and South Devon.
                    The Dovan rises in the county of Perth, and, descending with impetuosity from
                    the Ochils, where its course is to the east, makes a very sharp turn towards the
                    west, and, proceeding placidly in that direction through the pleasant vale
                    already mentioned, falls into the Forth at the village of Cambus. Exclusive of
                    its windings, the course of this river is more than twenty-six miles, though the
                    distance in a direct line from its source to its embouchure does not exceed six
                    miles. It has long been remarkable for the deep and dark chasms which it has
                    worn in the rocks, and through which it flows in the earlier part of its course,
                    being in some places hardly visible. The <hi rend="italic">Devil’s Mill,</hi> so
                    called from the supposed resemblance of the sound of the water to that of
                    machinery; the <hi rend="italic">Rumbling 13 ridge,</hi> a very narrow and
                    unguarded pass across a chasm ninety feet deep; and the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cauldron Lynn,</hi> where the water is perpetually agitated in the immense
                    cauldron-like excavations which it has formed in the rock, have been frequently
                    visited by the lovers of natural scenery. Though this river is liable to be
                    suddenly swelled by rains, and frequently descends in torrents overflowing its
                    banks, it is in general of no great depth, but might be rendered navigable for
                    small vessels at a moderate expense, to the effect of bringing 10,000 acres of
                    coal within reach of water-carriage.</p>
                <p>The Black Dovan has its source in the county of Fife, flows westward in a
                    direction nearly parallel to the Dovan, and falls into the Forth near
                    Clackmannan. This river is extensively employed in turning mills and coal
                    engines, its whole course being over coal strata. In a dry season it is an
                    inconsiderable stream, the greater part of its waters being then collected into
                    reservoirs for the supply of machinery.</p>
                <p>The Forth is navigable as far as it forms the boundary of this county. Ships of
                    500 tons burden run up as far as Alloa. Its windings, or <hi rend="italic"
                    >links</hi> as they are called, are very remarkable. The distance from the quay
                    of Alloa to that of Stirling, measured in the middle of the stream, is seventeen
                    miles, and to the bridge of Stirling it is nineteen and a half, whereas the
                    distance by land from the latter place to Alloa does not exceed seven miles. A
                    little above Alloa there are three islets in the river, the largest containing
                    more than seventy acres. A remarkable ledge of rock stretches across the Forth
                    below the two smaller islets, which obstructs the passage of vessels of more
                    than sixty tons burden, and where it is fordable at low water of spring tides.
                    The breadth at this place being only about 500 yards, it was long since proposed
                    to throw a bridge over it, the expense of which was estimated at L.70,000. Mr
                    Rennie, the celebrated engineer, made a survey with a view to a bridge at the
                    Alloa ferry, which he declared to be practicable at an expense of L. 150,000; a
                    work which has never been attempted. The passage, however, has of late been
                    improved by means of new piers and a steam boat. The estuary of the Forth, for
                    several miles above and below Clackmannan, exhibits a singular phenomenon in its
                    tides, which rise there from sixteen to twenty-two feet. During neap tides in
                    good weather, and sometimes also during spring tides, if the weather be
                    uncommonly fine, after the water has flowed for three hours, it retires in an
                    hour and a half, nearly as far as the line from which it had begun t□ flow, but
                    returns immediately, and, in an hour and a half more, reaches the same height it
                    had attained before. This flux and reflux takes place both in the flood and ebb
                    tides, so that double the usual number of tides occur in this part of the river.
                    In very boisterous weather, however, these <hi rend="italic">lecky tides,</hi>
                    as they are called by sailors, are not regular, the water then only rising
                    without any perceptible current, as if two tides were acting against each
                    other.</p>
                <p>The soils of the arable land of Clackmannanshire arc in general productive and
                    well cultivated; though the greater part of the elevated range which is
                    interposed between the earse lands on the Forth, and the vale of Dovan at the
                    base of the Oehils on the north, consists of inferior soils, often incumbent on
                    an impervious clay. All the crops commonly raised in Scotland grow luxuriantly
                    on either side of this tract, which also contains within itself a considerable
                    proportion of valuable soil. From the rental of the abbacy of Cambuskenneth,
                    founded in 1147, it appears, that wheat was cultivated on the <hi rend="italic"
                    >links</hi> of the Forth at a very early period; yet it is certain that fifty
                    years ago fields of this grain were only occasionally to be met with in the
                    county. As a proof how early and well the earse lands near Alloa had been
                    cultivated, it may be mentioned, that more than a century ago some farms in that
                    quarter paid as much grain and 6ther kinds of produce, in name of rent, as the
                    present money-rent of similar soils would purchase at the average prices of the
                    last twenty-five years. The farms would be thought small in other counties; few
                    of the arable ones exceeding 200 Scotch or 250 English acres, and the far
                    greater number being below 100 acres. The rent of the county was returned to the
                    collector of the property-tax for the year ending in April 1811, at L.32,047.
                    12s., so that, after making allowance for that part of the surface which is
                    covered by water, or otherwise altogether unproductive, every acre must have
                    paid at least 20s. upon an average of all soils and situations. At the same
                    time, the rent of the houses was stated at L.2827. 5s. The old valuation, by
                    which the land-tax and county-rates are apportioned, is L.26,482.10s. 10d.
                    Scots, or L.2206. 17s. 7d. sterling, of which somewhat more than a third belongs
                    to estates held under entail. The richest earse land under current leases now
                    (1832) lets for three bolls a Scotch acre, half wheat and half barley, payable
                    by the fiars, and in the measure of the county. Good carse land commonly rents
                    at three bolls an acre, one of which is wheat, one barley, and one oats. The
                    first effective thrashing machine in Scotland was constructed at Kilbagie, in
                    the parish of Clackmannan, in 1787, by Mr George Meikle, the son of its
                    celebrated inventor; and the last one, it is believed, at which old Meikle
                    himself worked, is on the estate of the Earl of Mar, near Alloa. One of the
                    greatest disadvantages which the agriculture of this district labours under is
                    the want of limestone, of which, however, very large quantities are <pb
                    break="no" facs="nls:193356376" xml:id="kp-eb0706-6376-0721"/> brought from
                    Dunbar and other places on the Forth, and afterwards calcined in the county,
                    where coal is always plentiful and cheap. Limeshells are also imported to a
                    considerable extent from the Earl of Elgin’s works in Fife.</p>
                <p>This small county is rich in minerals. Silver, copper, lead, iron-ore <hi
                    rend="italic">(Jiaematites),</hi> cobalt, and arsenic, have all been discovered
                    in the Ochil Mountains, between Airthry and Dollar; but, after having been
                    wrought for a time with little success, the labour was discontinued. The
                    operations, however, were not conducted upon an extensive scale; in no instance
                    did the miners penetrate below the level of the plain from which the Ochils
                    rise; and it is still believed that these hills abound in valuable metallic
                    veins, ready to reward more skilful and enterprising adventurers. The hazard
                    would be in working for silver, as it is found chiefly in detached nodules.
                    Ironstone is wrought to a considerable extent for the Devon iron-works, in the
                    parish of Clackmannan. It is found either in strata, or in detached oblate
                    balls, imbedded in the schist, and yields from 25 to 30 per cent, of iron. That
                    obtained from the mine now opened at Vicar’s Bridge, near Dollar, affords, it is
                    said, above 40 per cent. The quantity of ironstone extracted in 1830 was 14,500
                    tons.</p>
                <p>The Abbey Craig, near Stirling, a great mass of greenstone rock, crystallized in
                    the internal structure, and rudely columnar in its external appearance, deserves
                    to be particularly noticed, in this view of Clackmannanshire, from its having
                    afforded a very useful substitute, in the manufacture of flour, for the French
                    bur-stones, which it was so difficult to procure during the late war. This
                    discovery was made by a miller of the name of James Brownhill, then employed at
                    the Alloa mills. Several hundreds of these millstones are now working both in
                    England and Scotland, and are found to be in some respects superior to the burs.
                    The Society for the Encouragement of Arts in London presented this ingenious
                    person with a hundred guineas for his discovery, after they had received the
                    most satisfactory proofs of its great importance.</p>
                <p>Coal has been wrought for two hundred years in this county. The quantity at
                    present annually obtained may be estimated at 160,000 tons, of which a great
                    part is shipped for Leith, Dunbar, Tay water, and foreign ports. In the scale of
                    working, the collieries stand thus: 1. Alloa; 2. Sauchy; 3. Clackmannan; 4.
                    Dollar; 5. Tillicoultry; 6. Kennet. It is all either cubical or slate coal, both
                    being often found in the same bed, of an open burning quality; and no smithy or
                    caking coal has yet been discovered. The thinnest seam which has been wrought is
                    twenty-seven inches thick; and in a depth of 105 fathoms there are nine scams of
                    more than this thickness. The pit opened this year (1832) at Hill End, near
                    Clackmannan, contains a seam six feet eight inches in thickness. The strata
                    which compose the coal-field are varieties of sandstone, argillaceous schistus,
                    fire-clay, and argillaceous ironstone. Limestone is found among the lowest veins
                    of the coal strata. Organic remains of shell-fish and plants abound in them; and
                    of the latter, many are of a kind now found only in the equatorial regions.
                    Carbonic acid gas, termed choke-damp, is the most abundant of the noxious
                    vapours found in the coal mines of this field. Hydrogen gas, or inflammable air,
                    was never known here till lately, and it is still in small quantity. The great
                    coal-field of Scotland, which passes in a diagonal line from the mouths of the
                    Forth and Tay to the Irish Sea, is bounded by the Ochils. No coal has been found
                    to the north of them, excepting at Brora, in the county of Sutherland.</p>
                <p>Machinery for drawing water from the mines was constructed and much improved in
                    this county, before the invention of the steam-engine. The Alloa colliery is
                    drain ed by an overshot water-wheel, 30 feet diameter, which lifts the water
                    from the depth of 300 feet. The Sauchy collieries are drained by powerful
                    steam-engines; that employed by the Devon Company is capable of raising
                    10,000,000 gallons of water in twenty-four hours, from the depth of 280 feet. At
                    the Alloa colliery there is an improved cast-iron railway, of about two and a
                    half miles in length, upon which a horse takes down eight waggons with as many
                    tons of coals. The general price paid for working great coal is from 2s. to 3s.
                    per ton; and the selling price on the hill 6s. 8d., which is said to yield but a
                    very small return to the coal-master.</p>
                <p>At the Alloa colliery the workmen have for a great number of years had a court,
                    composed of five of their own number, appointed annually by the proprietor of
                    the works. By this court all differences amongst themselves are settled. The
                    highest fine exacted is half a guinea, and all the fines are put into a general
                    fund for the support of the poor.</p>
                <p>Under the head of manufactures, the distilleries of this county form by far the
                    most prominent and considerable branch. In this small district there were,
                    twenty years ago, no fewer than six large distilleries. Of these, Kilbagie and
                    Kennetpans paid to government an excise-duty greater than the land-tax of
                    Scotland; the former alone ξ&gt;aying no less at one time than about half a
                    million sterling. <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> reviously to 1788, the quantity
                    of grain annually consumed at Kilbagie exceeded 60,000 bolls (45,000 quarters);
                    while 7000 cattle and 2000 swine were fattened upon the grains and dreg. The
                    saving in the stock of food for man, effected by the stoppage of the
                    distilleries, is therefore much less considerable than has been imagined; an
                    acre of barley used in distillation yielding nearly as much animal food as an
                    acre of middling pasture. It is understood that cattle may be fattened in a
                    complete manner, in the proportion of two, of 50 stones avoirdupois each, for
                    every gallon of a still, when working from grain; affording the means, at the
                    same time, of enriching the soil for future crops, by the abundance and good
                    quality of the manure they produce. The effects which distilleries produce on
                    the morals of the neighbourhood is another question.</p>
                <p>The other manufactures of Clackmannanshire, though numerous, are not conducted
                    upon so very extensive a scale. At the Devon iron-works, already noticed, about
                    sixty tons of pig iron are prepared weekly, only a small part of which is used
                    by the foundery at these works. In the parish of Dollar, on the banks of the
                    Dovan, a bleachfield was established in 1787, of which the water and the
                    machinery are excellent. The cloth bleached here consists chiefly of the fine
                    table linen manufactured at Dunfermline. There is a very complete set of
                    corn-mills at Alloa, and there are mills for various purposes in several parts
                    of the county. In the same town, and in the neighbourhood, there are five
                    breweries, a glass work, a copper work, a rope and sail manufactory, a tannery,
                    a tile and brick work; and this year (1832) a steam-engine manufactory has been
                    commenced.</p>
                <p>The port of Alloa is well situated for commerce, and has a substantial well-built
                    quay, and, a little above the harbour, a dry dock capable of receiving vessels
                    of large burden; the depth of the water at spring-tides being sixteen feet, and
                    the width of the gates thirty-four and a half. There is a custom-house here,
                    which comprehends the ports of Stirling and Kincardine, and Clackmannan Pow, and
                    at which 155 vessels were registered in 1831, carrying 19,000 tons, and
                    navigated by 1020 men. There are cleared outwards annually, on an average, from
                    1100 to 1200 vessels, carrying 55,000 tons, and employing about 3300 seamen; and
                    inwards, about 700 vessels, carrying 32,000 tons, and 1800 men. The principal
                    exports are <pb break="no" facs="nls:193356389" xml:id="kp-eb0706-6389-0722"
                    />coals, about 65,000 tons, pig and cast iron, alcs for London, and British
                    spirits. In 1830, 430,000 gallons of spirits were shipped for the English
                    market; and in the same year, the excise duties, customs, and taxes received in
                    Alloa, and paid into the exchequer, amounted to L.244,097. The annual imports
                    consist, for the most part, of grain for the distilleries and breweries, of
                    which a great proportion is barley from the county of Norfolk, and goods from
                    Leith, Glasgow, Greenock, and London. Timber, iron, and other commodities, arc
                    occasionally imported from the Baltic. The establishment of packets betwixt
                    Alloa and Leith is likely to prove of much benefit to this district, from the
                    low rates at which goods are transported. A most convenient and expeditious
                    conveyance for passengers, by means of steam-boats, has been recently
                    introduced, with great success, between Newhaven and Alloa, and other places on
                    the Forth.</p>
                <p>Among the antiquities of this county may be mentioned the ruins of Castle
                    Campbell, originally called Castlc Gloom, in a singularly wild and almost
                    inaccessible situation, within a recess of the mountains, above the village of
                    Dollar. The period of its erection and its early history are unknown. It became
                    the property of the Argyll family in 1465, from whom it derived its present
                    name, and was the ordinary residence of Archibald earl of Argyll at the time of
                    the Reformation. In this stronghold John Knox found a temporary retreat. In 1644
                    it was burned by Montrose, and since that time it has been suffered to remain in
                    ruins. The tower of Alloa, built prior to the year 1300, the residence of the
                    Erskines, earls of Mar, and now belonging to the representative of that noble
                    family, is in good preservation. -The walls are eleven feet in thickness, and
                    the highest turret is eighty-nine feet above the ground. The tower of
                    Clackmannan was long the scat of the chief of the Bruces after the failure of
                    the male line. There is a charter, dated the 9th of December 1359, quoted by
                    Douglas, in which Dgvid II. grants to Sir Robert Bruce, whom he there styles his
                    dearly beloved re-∣ lation, the castle and manor of Clackmannan, with divers
                    other lands within the county. Since the death of Henry Bruce of Clackmannan, in
                    1772, leaving no male representative, it has been made a question whether the
                    Earl of Elgin or Bruce of Kennet be now the chief of that royal race.</p>
                <p>Clackmannanshire sends a member to parliament, conjunctly with the county of
                    Kinross. By the reform bill, there are annexed to Clackmannanshire, for the
                    purposes of election, the parishes of Culross and Tullyallan, formerly
                    comprehended in the county of Perth; Alva, formerly belonging to Stirling; and
                    the Perthshire portion of Logie. This arrangement will increase the population
                    to 21,392 souls. Clackmannanshire thus comprehends eleven parishes, the
                    constituency of which, as determined by the sheriff, is as follows :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Alloa parish</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>172</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Clackmannan</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>60</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Dollar</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>36</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Logie, part of</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>51</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Tillicoultry</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>27</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Alva</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>27</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Culross</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>31</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Tullyallan</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>87</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>491</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>There is no royal burgh in this county. Clackmannan, which gives its name to the
                    county, is the only town in it besides Alloa deserving of notice.</p>
                <p>There is no legal assessment here for the poor. The total number of poor in 1812
                    was 193, who received L.677, or nearly L.3. 10s. each, from interest of money,
                    collections at the church doors, and voluntary contributions by the heritors and
                    inhabitants. The population of Clackmannanshire in 1811, 1821, and 1831, is
                    exhibited in the following abstracts:—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >years'.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="3" role="data" rows="1"><p>HOUSES.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="3" role="data" rows="1"><p>OCCUPATIONS.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="3" role="data" rows="1"><p>PERSONS.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="superscript"> r</hi>
                            0</p><p>0»</p><p>’JS</p><p>G5</p><p>AE</p><p>Ö</p><p>HH</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>By how many Families
                            occupied.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="superscript"> r</hi>
                            c3</p><p>α&gt;</p><p>⅛ +3</p><p>S</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Families chiefly employed in
                            Agriculture.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Families chiefly employed in Trade,
                            Manufactures, or Handicraft.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>All other Families not comprised in
                            the two preceding classes.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Males.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Females.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Total of Persons.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1811</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1995</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2781</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>99</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>280</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>893</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1608</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5715</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6295</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>12,010</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1821</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2145</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2881</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>62</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>434</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1418</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1029</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6356</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6907</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>13,263</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1831</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2391</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3354</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>85</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>385</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1302</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1665</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7095</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7634</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>14,729</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
