<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0706-8238-0095-08" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CANOVA, Antonio</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 6, page 95</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term n="14" ref="fasttopic:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term n="14" ref="fasttopic:815177">Art</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:817559">Artists</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="14" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4154dp40">Artists</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4p843w5c">Hand</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42b8vd69">Medusae</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="10" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239717">Alps</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204901">Austria</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193348238" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CANOVA, <hi rend="smallcaps">Antonio</hi></label>, one of the
                    greatest sculptors of modern times, was born on the 1st of November 1757, at
                    Passagno, an obscure village situated amid the recesses of the hills of Asolano,
                    where these form the last undulations of the Venetian Alps, as they subside into
                    the plains of Treviso. At three years of age Canova was deprived of both
                    parents. Their loss, however, was compensated by the tender solicitude and care
                    of his grandfather and grandmother, the latter of whom lived to experience in
                    her turn the kindest personal attention from her grandson, who, when the efforts
                    of successful genius had afforded him the means, gave her an asylum in his house
                    at Rome. The father and grandfather of our artist followed the occupation of
                    stone-cutters; and it is said that their family had for several ages supplied
                    Passagno with members of that profession. As soon as Canova’s hand could hold a
                    pencil, he was initiated into the principles of drawing by his affectionate
                    grandfather Pasino, who was acquainted with the subject. He also possessed some
                    knowledge of architecture, designed well, and showed considerable taste in the
                    execution of ornamental works. To his art he was attached with fond partiality;
                    and upon his young charge he looked as one who was designed not only to
                    perpetuate the family name, but also the family profession. The object of his
                    hopes and instructions may be said to have done so; but his works were destined
                    to be known far beyond the period of his life, or the circle of his native
                    hills.</p>
                <p>The early years of Canova were· passed in study. The <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193348251" xml:id="kp-eb0706-8251-0096"/>bias of his mind was to
                    sculpture, and the facilities afforded for the gratification of this
                    predilection in the workshop of his grandfather were eagerly improved. In his
                    ninth year he executed two small shrines of Carrara marble, which are still
                    extant. Soon after this period he appears to have been constantly employed under
                    his grandfather. Amongst those who patronized the old man was the patrician
                    family Faliero of Venice, and by this means young Canova was first introduced to
                    the senator of that name, who afterwards became his most zealous patron. Between
                    the younger son, Giuseppe Faliero, and the artist, a friendship commenced, which
                    terminated only with life. From the interest which was excited in this family
                    for Canova, Signor Faliero was induced to receive him under his immediate
                    protection. It has been related by an Italian writer, and since repeated by
                    several biographers, that Canova was indebted to a fortuitous circumstance, the
                    moulding of a lion in butter, for the warm interest which the senator took in
                    his welfare. The anecdote may be true; but it does not appear to rest on
                    authority sufficiently strong to warrant our stating it as authentic. By his
                    kind patron Canova was placed under Bernardi, or, as he is generally called by
                    filiation, Toretto, a sculptor of considerable eminence, who had taken up a
                    temporary residence at Pagnano, a village in the vicinity of the senator’s
                    mansion. This took place whilst he was in his thirteenth year; and with Toretto
                    he continued about two years, making in many respects considerable progress.
                    This master returned to Venice, where he soon afterwards died; but by the high
                    terms in which he spoke of his pupil to Faliero, the latter was induced to bring
                    the young artist to Venice, where he accordingly went, and was placed under a
                    nephew of Toretto. With this master he continued about a year, studying with the
                    utmost assiduity. After the termination of this engagement he began to work on
                    his own account, and received from his patron an order for a group on the
                    subject of Orpheus and Eurydice. The first figure, which represents Eurydice in
                    flames and smoke in the act of leaving the infernal realms, was completed
                    towards the close of his sixteenth year. It was highly esteemed by his patron
                    and friends, and the artist was now considered as qualified to appear before a
                    public tribunal. The kindness of some monks supplied him with his first
                    work-shop, which was the vacant cell of a monastery. Here for nearly four years
                    he laboured with the greatest perseverance and industry. He was also regular in
                    his attendance at the academy, where he carried off several prizes. But he did
                    not confine himself to these exercises alone. He resolved to begin where the art
                    itself began, in the study and imitation of nature. From his contemporaries he
                    could learn nothing, for their style was vicious. From their works, therefore,
                    he reverted to living models, as exhibited in every variety of situation. A
                    large portion of his time was also devoted to anatomy, which science was
                    regarded by him as “the secret of the art.” He also frequented places of public
                    amusement, where he carefully studied the expressions and attitudes of the
                    performers. Not a day was allowed to pass without his making some visible
                    advances in his profession. He formed a resolution, which was faithfully adhered
                    to for several years, never to close his eyes without producing some design.
                    Whatever was likely to forward his advancement in sculpture, he studied with
                    ardour. On archaiological pursuits he bestowed considerable attention. With
                    ancient and modern history he rendered himself well acquainted, and he also
                    began to acquire several of the continental languages. When we view such
                    industry, inspired and directed by such a genius as that of Canova, it scarcely
                    appears matter of wonder that the result should be a new era in the art.</p>
                <p>Three years had now elapsed without any production coming from his chisel. He
                    began, therefore, to complete the group for his patron, and the Orpheus which
                    followed evinced the great advances he had made in his profession. The work was
                    universally applauded, and laid the foundation of his fame. Several groups
                    succeeded this performance, amongst which was that of Daedalus and Icarus, the
                    most celebrated work of his noviciate. The simplicity of style and the faithful
                    imitation of nature which characterized them called forth the warmest
                    admiration. But there was still wanting in his productions that elevation and
                    ideal beauty which he afterwards attained to, and which rather carried nature to
                    its highest perfection than w ent beyond it. His merits and reputation being now
                    generally recognised, he began to turn his attention from the shores of the
                    Adriatic to the more classic banks of the Tiber, for which he set out at the
                    commencement of his twenty-third year.</p>
                <p>Previous to his departure for Rome, his friends had applied to the Venetian
                    senate for a pension, to enable him without embarrassment to pursue his studies.
                    The application was ultimately successful. It amounted to three hundred ducats,
                    about sixty pounds per annum, and was limited to three years. Our artist had
                    obtained letters of introduction to the Venetian ambassador, the Cavaliere
                    Zuliani, an enlightened and generous protector of the arts, and was received in
                    the most gracious and hospitable manner. Canova’s arrival in the “eternal city”
                    marks a new era in his life. It was here he was to perfect himself, by a study
                    of the most splendid relics of antiquity, and to put his talents to the severest
                    test by a competition with the greatest living masters of the art. The result
                    was equal to the highest hopes cherished either by himself or by his friends.
                    The work which first established his fame at Rome was Theseus vanquishing the
                    Minotaur. The figures are of the heroic size, that is, larger than life. The
                    victorious Theseus is represented as seated on the lifeless body of the monster.
                    The exhaustion which visibly pervades his whole frame proves the terrible nature
                    of the conflict in which he had been engaged, while at the same time it evinces
                    the genius of the sculptor. Simplicity and purity of natural expression had
                    hitherto characterized his style; but with these were now united more exalted
                    conceptions of grandeur and of truth. By those w+o were capable of appreciating
                    the beauties of the Theseus, it was regarded with rapturous enthusiasm, as
                    worthy of the best days of sculpture in a land where sculpture was unrivalled;
                    and it formed a noble presage of future glory and yet more splendid
                    achievements.</p>
                <p>FIis next undertaking was a monument in honour of Clement XIV.; but before he
                    proceeded with it, he deemed it necessary to request permission from the
                    Venetian senate, whose servant he considered himself to be, in consideration of
                    the pension. This he solicited in person, and it was granted in the most
                    handsome manner. He returned immediately to Rome, and opened that studio in the
                    Stracla Babbuino, which was soon to be one of the proudest boasts of Italy, and
                    to which the ardent devotees of the art from every nation of Europe were to
                    perform pilgrimage. He spent about two years of unremitting toil in arranging
                    the design and composing the models for the tomb of the pontiff. After these
                    were completed, other two years were employed in finishing the monument, and it
                    was finally opened to public inspection in 1787. Expectation had been highly
                    excited, and never was it more amply gratified. The work, in the opinion of the
                    best judges, stamped the author as the first artist of modern times. After five
                    years of incessant labour, he completed another cenotaph to the memory of
                    Clement X11I. of which it is sufficient praise to say, that it raised still
                    higher the fame of <pb break="no" facs="nls:193348264"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0706-8264-0097"/>the author. Works came now so rapidly from his
                    chisel, that it will be impossible to enumerate any but the most conspicuous.
                    Amongst those which belong to the period in question is Psychc with a butterfly,
                    which is placed on the left hand, and held by the wings with the right. This
                    beautiful figure, which is intended as a personification of man’s immaterial
                    part, is considered as in almost every respect the most faultless and classical
                    of Canova’s works. In two different groups, and with opposite expression, the
                    sculptor has represented Cupid with his bride; in the one they are standing, in
                    the other recumbent, and both are of superlative excellence. These and other
                    proofs of lofty genius raised his reputation so high, that the most flattering
                    offers were sent him from the Russian court to induce him to remove to St
                    Petersburg; but these were declined. “Italy,” says he, in writing of the
                    occurrence to a friend, “Italy is my country—is the country and native soil of
                    the arts. I cannot leave it; my infancy was nurtured here, and if my poor
                    talents can be useful in any other, they must be of some utility to this; and
                    ought not hers to be preferred to all others ?” Genius never appears so truly
                    great as when it is united with a disinterested love of country. In this respect
                    Canova will ever command admiration. The powers of his mind scarcely surpassed
                    the virtues of his heart.</p>
                <p>Numerous works were produced during the years 1795- 6-7, of which several were
                    repetitions of previous productions. It is only necessary to notice the
                    celebrated group representing the parting of Venus and Adonis. The youth is
                    gazing tenderly upon the goddess. With his left arm he encircles her waist,
                    while his right grasps a hunting spear. She, on the other hand, by the most
                    endearing yet chaste caresses, endeavours to avert his resolution of departing.
                    This famous production was sent to Naples; and, out of respect to the artist,
                    the king ordered every tax which attended its importation to be remitted. As a
                    more substantial mark of approbation, he decorated the sculptor with the
                    insignia of the order of the Two Sicilies. The French revolution was now
                    extending its ravages over Italy; and the pure and peaceful spirit of Canova,
                    shrinking from scenes of contention and blood, sought obscurity and repose in
                    the bosom of his native Passagno. Thither he retired in 1798, and continued
                    about a year, principally employed in the sister art of painting, in which also
                    he was no ordinary proficient. One of his productions in this department of art
                    is a picture representing the dead body of the Saviour just removed from the
                    cross, surrounded by the three Marys, the beloved disciple, Joseph of Arimathea,
                    and, somewhat in the back ground, Nicoemus. Above appears the personification of
                    the Father, with the mystic dove in the centre of a glory, and surrounded by a
                    circle of cherubs. This admirable composition, which was greatly applauded, he
                    presented to the parochial church of his native place. Events in the political
                    world having come to a temporary crisis, he returned to Rome; but his health,
                    from arduous application, having been impaired, he took a journey through a part
                    of Germany, in company with his friend Prince Rezzonica. He returned from his
                    travels much improved, and again commenced his labours with renewed vigour and
                    enthusiasm.</p>
                <p>Canova’s sculptures have been distributed under three heads: 1. Heroic
                    compositions; 2. Compositions of grace and elegance; and 3. Sepulchral monuments
                    and relievos. In noticing the works which fall under each of these divisions, it
                    will be impossible to maintain a strict chronological order, but perhaps a
                    better idea of his productions may thus be obtained. Their vast number, however,
                    prevents their being all enumerated.</p>
                <p>Soon after his return appeared his Perseus with the head of Medusa. The moment of
                    representation is when the hero, flushed with conquest, displays the head of the
                    “snaky Gorgon,” whilst the right hand grasps a sword of singular device. By a
                    public decree, this great triumph of art was placed in one of the <hi
                    rend="italic">stanze</hi> of the Vatican, hitherto reserved only for the most
                    precious works of antiquity. In 1802, at the personal request of Napoleon,
                    Canova repaired to Paris to model a bust of the first consul. The artist was
                    entertained with munificence, and various honours were conferred upon him. The
                    statue, which is colossal, was not finished till six years after. On the fall of
                    the living original, the French king presented this statue to the British
                    government, by whom it was afterwards given to the Duke of Wellington.
                    Palamedes, Creugas, and Damoxenus, the combat of Theseus and the Centaur, and
                    Hercules and Lydias, all displaying great and varied excellence, may close the
                    class of heroic compositions, although the catalogue might be swelled by the
                    enumeration of various others, such as Hector and Ajax, the statues of
                    Washington, Ferdinand, and others. The group of Hercules and Lydias is
                    considered as the most terrible conception of Canova’s mind, and in its peculiar
                    style as scarcely to be excelled.</p>
                <p>Under the second head, namely, compositions of grace and elegance, the statue of
                    Hebe takes the first place in point of time. Four times has the artist embodied
                    in stone the goddess of youth, and each time with some variation. The only
                    material improvement, however, is the substitution of a support more suitable to
                    the simplicity of the art. The invention merits the title of originality, and
                    the figure in each of the statues is, in all its details, in expression,
                    attitude, elegance, and delicacy of finish, perfect in beauty. The Dancing
                    Nymphs maintain a character similar to that of the Hebe. The Graces and the
                    Venus are more elevated, as combining dignity with elegance. The Awakened Nymph
                    is another work of extraordinary beauty, a term indeed which may be applied to
                    all his productions indiscriminately. The mother of Napoleon, Maria Louisa, to
                    model wlκ&gt;m the author made a second journey to Paris in 1810, the Princess
                    Esterhazy, and the muse Polyhymnia, take their place in this class; as do the
                    ideal heads, comprising Corinna, Sappho, Laura, and Beatrice. In these the
                    artist combined reality with fancy; all are representations of celebrated
                    females, and he has endeavoured to realize the glowing descriptions of poesy, or
                    the more veracious traits of history, according to his own refined conceptions
                    of character. Living models supplied the contour and the features, but these
                    were kindled up with the soul of passion and expression by the sculptor’s hand.
                    Belonging to this class of composition the most glowing portraiture of female
                    loveliness is the Helen of Troy.</p>
                <p>The cenotaphs and funeral monuments fall next to be noticed. Of these the most
                    splendid is the monument to the Arch-Duchess Maria Christina of Austria,
                    consisting of nine figures. It is considered as a <hi rend="italic"
                    >chef-d’</hi><hi rend="italic">oeuvrera</hi> this department of art. Besides the
                    two for the Roman pontiffs, already mentioned, there is one for Alfieri, another
                    for Emo, a Venetian admiral, and a small model of a cenotaph for Nelson, besides
                    a great variety of monumental relievos.</p>
                <p>The events which marked the life of the artist during the first fifteen years of
                    the period in which he was engaged on the above-mentioned works, arc of so
                    little importance as scarcely to merit notice. His mind was entirely absorbed in
                    the labours of his studio, and, with the exception of his two journeys to Paris,
                    one to Vienna, and a few short intervals of absence in Florence and other parts
                    of Italy, he never quitted Rome. In his own words, “his statues were the sole
                    proofs of his civil existence.” There was, however, another proof, which modesty
                    forbade him <pb break="no" facs="nls:193348277" xml:id="kp-eb0706-8277-0098"/>to
                    mention, an ever active benevolence, especially towards artists. In 1815 he was
                    commissioned by the Pope to superintend the transmission from Paris, of those
                    works of art which had formerly been conveyed there under the direction of
                    Napoleon. By his zeal and exertions, for there were many conflicting interests
                    to reconcile, he adjusted the affair in a manner at once creditable to his
                    judgment and fortunate for his country. In the autumn of this year he gratified
                    a wish he had long entertained, of visiting the British metropolis, where he was
                    graciously received by the prince regent, and honoured with the highest tokens
                    of esteem. He returned to Rome in the beginning of 1816, with the ransomed
                    spoils of his country’s genius. Immediately after, he received several marks of
                    distinction: by the hand of the pope himself his name was inscribed in “the
                    golden volume of the capitol,” and he received the title of Marquis of Ischia,
                    with an annual pension of 3000 crowns, about L.625.</p>
                <p>He now contemplated a great work, a colossal statue of Religion. The model filled
                    Italy with admiration: the marble was procured, and the chisel of the sculptor
                    ready to be applied to it, when the jealousy of churchmen as to the site, or
                    some other cause, deprived the world of the projected work. The mind of Canova
                    was inspired with the warmest sense of devotion, and though foiled in this
                    instance, he resolved to consecrate a shrine to the cause, at once worthy of
                    himself and of the religion to which he was devoted. In his native village he
                    began to make preparations for erecting a temple, which was to contain not only
                    the above statue, but other works of his own; and within its precincts also were
                    to repose the ashes of the founder. Accordingly, in prosecution of this design,
                    he repaired to Passagno in 1819. At a sumptuous entertainment which he gave to
                    his workmen, there occurred an incident which it is impossible to overlook in
                    any life of Canova, however circumscribed. When the festivities of the day had
                    terminated, he requested the shepherdesses and peasant girls of the adjacent
                    hamlets to pass in review before him, and to each he made a present, expending
                    on the occasion about L.400. We need not therefore be surprised, that, a few
                    years afterwards, when the remains of the donor came to be deposited in their
                    last asylum, the grief which the surrounding peasantry evinced was in natural
                    expression so intense and irrepressible, as totally to eclipse all the studied
                    solemnity of more pompous mourning.</p>
                <p>After the foundation stone of this edifice had been laid, Canova returned to
                    Rome; but every succeeding autumn he continued to visit Passagno, in order to
                    direct the workmen, and encourage them with pecuniary rewards and medals. In the
                    mean time the vast expenditure exhausted his resources, and compelled him to
                    labour with unceasing assiduity, when age and disease had set their seal upon
                    his frame. During the period which intervened between commencing operations at
                    Passagno, and his decease, he executed or finished some of his most splendid
                    works. Amongst these were the group Mars and Venus, the colossal figure of Pius
                    VI., the Pietà, the St John, the recumbent Magdalen, and others of scarcely
                    inferior excellence. The last performance which issued from his hand was a
                    colossal bust of his friend the Count Ciconava. In May 1822 he paid a visit to
                    Naples, to superintend the construction of waxmoulds for an equestrian statue of
                    Ferdinand. This journey materially injured his health, but he rallied again on
                    his return to Rome. Towards the latter end of the year he paid his annual visit
                    to the place of his birth, when he experienced a relapse. He proceeded to
                    Venice, and expired there on the 13th of October 1822, at the age of sixty-five.
                    The most distinguished funeral honours were paid to his remains, which were
                    deposited in the temple at Passagno on the 25th of the same month.</p>
                <p>Canova is allowed to rank above every other master, from the age of Nicholas of
                    Pisa. He renovated the art in Italy, and brought it back to the standard from
                    which it had declined. His style in youth displayed the utmost simplicity; but
                    as he proceeded in his career, he evinced the true poetic feeling which
                    spiritualizes and exalts nature into ideal beauty and grandeur—that power which
                    give^ to marble features an expression apparently resulting from the workings of
                    an inherent and active intelligence; in a word, he stamped them with the impress
                    of the soul. His finishing was excessively refined, and he had a method of
                    giving a mellow and soft appearance to' the marble, hitherto unattempted. He
                    formed his models of the same size as the work he designed was intended to be,
                    which was, undoubtedly, a great improvement in the art. Of his moral character,
                    a generous and unwearied benevolence formed the most prominent feature. Of the
                    vast fortune realized by his works, the greater part was distributed in acts of
                    this description. To artists in particular, his hand was “open as day to melting
                    charity.” He established prizes for them, and endowed all the academies of Rome.
                    The aged and unfortunate were also objects of his peculiar solicitude. His
                    titles were numerous. He was enrolled amongst the nobility of several states,
                    decorated with various orders of knighthood, and associated in the highest
                    professional honours. (See the <hi rend="italic">Life of Canova</hi> by Memes,
                    one vol.; by Missinini, four vols.; also the <hi rend="italic">Eiografia,</hi>
                    by the Count Ciconava.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
