<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0706-7367-0028-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CALVIN, John</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 6, page 28</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b44b2x59s">Calvinism</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4348gn83">Mind</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bw6x">Spirits</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4gb1xr6p">Spirit</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4z892p9k">Spiritism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rj14">Anabaptists</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206891">Poland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:844591">Calvinism</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1130061">Spirits</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1130040">Spirit</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:808176">Anabaptists</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193347367" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CALVIN, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi></label>, the mos't
                    eminent of the reformers from Popery after Luther, and, from the large body of
                    Christians distinguished by his name, deemed entitled to equality with him, was
                    born at Noyou, in Picardy, in 1509. His father was a cooper in that place, and
                    bore the name of Chauvin or Cauvin, which his son afterwards latinized into
                    Calvinus, whence originated the usual appellation of Calvin, by which he has
                    ever since been distinguished. Some traits of early piety evincing themselves in
                    Calvin, he was, like Samuel, from his infancy designed by his family for the
                    church. The first benefice presented to him was in the cathedral of his native
                    place, to which was afterwards added the rectory of Pont l’Eveque. He had not as
                    yet received priest’s orders, but only the tonsure, when his father changed his
                    mind, and requested him to study the civil law. This was the more readily
                    assented to by the young divine, as he had already become disgusted with some of
                    the practices of his own church. Accordingly he repaired first to Orleans, and
                    afterwards to Bourges, to pursue his new professional career. Divinity, however,
                    was not neglected, for he still continued to cultivate it in private with
                    unslackened assiduity. His father dying, he returned to Noyou; and resigning his
                    benefice, set out for Paris, where he wrote his commentary on Seneca’s treatise
                    <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Clementia,</hi> upon the title-page
                    of which he first assumed the name of Calvinus. He now began to be identified
                    with the reformers; but a storm having burst on them in Paris, he was compelled
                    to fly from that city. He repaired to Angoulême, where he subsisted some time by
                    teaching Greek; and receiving shelter in the house of a converted canon, he
                    composed the greater portion of his <hi rend="italic">Institutes.</hi> The Queen
                    of Navarre favoured his doctrines; and, under cover of her protection, he once
                    more ventured to return to Paris in 1534; buta further persecution being again
                    threatened, he finally quitted France, and retired to Basel, in Switzerland,
                    where he published his famous <hi rend="italic">Christian Institutes.</hi> This
                    work was dedicated to Francis I. in an elegant Latin epistle. It was designed to
                    give a fair view of the religious principles of the reformed, which had already
                    been confounded by their enemies with those of the Anabaptists and other sects.
                    In these circumstances, it is not surprising that it obtained immediate
                    popularity. It went rapidly through several editions, and was translated into
                    all the principal modern languages. The boldness and originality of the
                    speculations, the talent with which the work was composed, and the effects which
                    it has produced upon the religious belief of Christians, entitle it to be looked
                    upon as one of the most remarkable books that ever appeared. After its
                    publication, the author repaired to Italy on a visit to the Duchess of Ferrara,
                    a convert to his doctrines; and returning to France, took Geneva on his way,
                    where, at the urgent request of several eminent reformers, he was induced to
                    remain, filling the offices of preacher and professor of divinity. He entered
                    upon these in 1536, and soon evinced the firmness and vigourof his mind, by
                    obliging the people to abjure Popery, and swear to a code of religious belief.
                    He carried the assumption of ecclesiastical authority so far, however, that
                    resistance succeeded; and the Catholic party prevailing, he was compelled to
                    quit Geneva. He went to Strasburg, where he established a French church
                    according to his own plan, and was also preferred to the professorship of
                    divinity. Here he married the widow of an Anabaptist, and published his <hi
                    rend="italic">Commentaries on the Epistle to the Romans.</hi> He also wrote an
                    able reply to Cardinal Sadolet, who had published a work exhorting the Genevese
                    to return again to the Catholic church. In the mean time, his party at Geneva
                    having laboured assiduously for his recal, he yielded at last to their
                    entreaties, and triumphantly returned to the scene of his former labours in
                    1541.</p>
                <p>His plan of church government he now matured and established. Indeed his whole
                    system, both of doctrine and ecclesiastical discipline, was maintained and
                    promoted with all the energy, firmness, and perseverance for which he was so
                    distinguished. He formed the lofty idea of making Geneva the mother and seminary
                    of all the reformed churches; and for this purpose he established an academy,
                    the character of which was eminently sustained by his own great learning and
                    ability, as well as by that of Beza and other distinguished reformers. The
                    result realized his hopes; for every country on which the reformation had shed
                    its propitious influence sent forth a portion of its youth to study at the feet
                    of the new Gamaliel. The three great points distinguishing the system of Calvin
                    from that of the other reformed churches consisted in the independence of church
                    government of the civil power; the real though spiritual presence of the Saviour
                    in the sacrament; and the absolute decree of God by which portions of the human
                    race are predestined from all eternity to everlasting happiness or misery. With
                    the same boldness which he had displayed in conceiving, did he maintain his
                    system, not only by his writings and extensive influence^ which reached wherever
                    the new opinions prevailed, but also by his form of ecclesiastical discipline,
                    and a consistorial jurisdiction which had the power of inflicting canonical
                    punishments. The latter were sometimes dispensed with unpardonable severity; so
                    much so, indeed, that many apprehended that the reign of papal tyranny was to be
                    revived under a new disguise. One or two facts show that Calvin had imbibed a
                    portion of the persecuting spirit of that church which he had forsaken. His
                    treatment of Castalio and others was .extremely harsh, but his conduct to
                    Servetus was altogether barbarous. That ill-fated individual having fled from
                    papal wrath, was seized at the instigation of Calvin, and condemned to the
                    flames. The spirit of the age was of a persecuting character, and had its full
                    influence on the mind of Calvin. Besides, religious liberty was not the primary
                    object of the reformers; it has rather been the result of their labours. Thus
                    philosophy may, to a certain extent, palliate the crime, for such it must be
                    called; but it has left a blot upon Calvin, from which it will be vain for his
                    warmest eulogist even to attempt to purify his name. But though the rigour of
                    his proceedings sometimes occasioned great tumults in the city, nothing could
                    shake his steadiness and inflexibility. Amongst all the disturbances of the
                    commonwealth, he exercised a paternal solicitude for the foreign churches in
                    England, France, Germany, and Poland; and did more by his pen than his presence,
                    sending his advice and instructions by letter, and writing a number of works.
                    After a life of incessant labour and study, which, it is reasonable to believe,
                    materially shortened his days, this great reformer died in May 1564, having
                    nearly completed the fifty-fifth year of his age.</p>
                <p>Calvin possessed in an eminent degree those qualities <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193347380" xml:id="kp-eb0706-7380-0029"/>which fit an individual for
                    being the head of a party. The leading characteristic of his mind was commanding
                    power. He had a clear and comprehensive understanding, which not only enabled
                    him with facility to unravel the tangled web of sophistry, but also to construct
                    from the wreck he had made a system of his own; and a firmness and inflexibility
                    of purpose which tended to wed him for ever to the cause he had espoused, with a
                    devotcdness which no opposition could overcome, and no vicissitude could shake.
                    There was certainly an alloy of human error and weakness in his temper and
                    character; but this is only saying that nothing human reaches the standard of
                    perfect rectitude. His faults primarily resulted from those very energies which
                    gave him pre-eminence. Indomitable firmness imparts a certain sternness to the
                    deportment, and not unfrequently degenerates into a spirit of persecution. But
                    the benefits which mankind derive from such a constitution of intellect, when
                    the moral bias is good, are generally of such a magnitude as totally to
                    counterbalance those minor defects to which the rancour of party spirit would
                    wish to give undue prominence. In this light we must view Calvin; not so much a
                    patron to be imitated in all respects, as a benefactor to be revered. He must
                    take his place beside the illustrious Luther. They are twin stars, the brightest
                    of that constellation of lights by whose effulgence was dispelled the long night
                    of darkness under the cloud of which the energies of men had suffered eclipse;
                    and having emerged, they shone forth with a brilliance and glory unparalleled in
                    the history of the world. In his principles Calvin was devoutly sincere, and the
                    purity of his “walk and conversation'’ in private life is unimpeachable. His
                    writings are numerous; for, besides the <hi rend="italic">Institutes,</hi> and
                    many controversial productions, he published learned commentaries upon most of
                    the books of the New, and on the Prophets of the Old Testament. His opinions are
                    now, however, better known than his writings; and his doctrine of predestination
                    in particular, connected as it is with the philosophy of necessity, will
                    probably supply matter of speculative debate for the controversialists of all
                    future times.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
