<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0716-1038-0321-08" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ODESSA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206891">Poland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208963">Turkey</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207170">Malta</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821579">Austrians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1174325">Wheat</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:948571">Growth</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n29p91c">Wheat</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45q4rq88">Growth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194561038?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">ODESSA</label>, a city of Russia in Europe, within
                    the circle of Tiraspol, in the government of Cherson. It owes its present state,
                    and the rapid advance it has made, to its position on the north-western shore of
                    the Black Sea, between the mouths of two great rivers, the Dniester and the
                    Dnieper, and being not more than twenty-four miles from the Bug, which is
                    navigable from Poland.</p>
                <p part="N">From the reign of Peter the Great, Russia had been steadily looking
                    forward to a maritime preponderance, both military and commercial, on the Black
                    Sea; and soon after the peace of Oczakow, by which the province of Cherson was
                    ceded to Catharine, that princess selected as the place for a commercial
                    emporium a village called Kodschabey, then inhabited only by a few fishermen. At
                    first several regiments were marched to the spot, and the erections of public
                    buildings commenced. The first civil settlers were a number of Greek families,
                    who were induced to remove thither from other portions of the country which had
                    been recently given up by the Turks. When the Emperor Alexander ascended the
                    throne, he entered with zeal into the project which Catharine had formed. The
                    French emigrant Duke of Richelieu, who had entered the Russian service, was
                    appointed governor, and displayed great zeal and judgment. By an imperial ukase,
                    all taxes were suspended for sixty years; in consequence of which a considerable
                    number of persons were induced to fix themselves in Odessa, so that by the year
                    1804 the inhabitants had increased to 15,000. With the progress of population
                    that of public buildings kept pace. A fortress, a lighthouse, and a lazaretto,
                    were constructed, as well as a mole to secure 300 sail of vessels from the
                    south-west winds, which sometimes blow with prodigious force. The war between
                    Russia and Turkey, which was terminated by the general European peace on the
                    capture of Paris, had impeded till that event the growth of the city; but soon
                    afterwards the port of Odessa was declared to be an open one. All goods of every
                    kind could be imported without duty for the consumption of the city, or for
                    re-exportation, but were chargeable with duty on passing into the surrounding
                    country. This gave a great impetus to its advancement, which still operates,
                    till the population has increased to nearly 50,000 persons. The inhabitants, as
                    is natural in new settlements, are of very mixed races. The chief part of them
                    consists of Russians, Greeks, and Jews; but German handicraftsmen are found
                    amongst them in considerable numbers, whilst the more extensive mercantile
                    houses are composed of Italians, English, French, or Armenians. In no spot
                    perhaps in Europe are there so great a number of languages spoken as on the
                    exchange of Odessa. The admixture of oriental dresses, manners, and languages,
                    presents a very novel and lively picture. A stranger might imagine himself
                    translated into one of the trading towns of the Levant; for the bazaars contain
                    all the productions of the East, from Persian shawls down to rose-pastilles; and
                    the Italian language is universally understood.</p>
                <p part="N">1he prosperity of Odessa has risen in a great measure from its maritime
                    accessibility. It has a spacious bay, <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:194561051?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0716-1051-0322"/>which,
                    though open to the easterly winds, is tolerably secure; it is very extensive,
                    and the anchorage ground is good. There is a kind of harbour formed by two
                    moles, about two thirds of a mile in length, and a handsome quay capable of
                    receiving vessels of 500 tons burden. The situation of the town on the shore,
                    the land rising very gradually, gives it a good appearance on approaching it
                    from the sea. Like most new places, it is regularly built; the streets are wide
                    and straight, crossing each other at right angles; and the houses are for the
                    most part built of stone, and two stories in height. The streets are however
                    unpaved, and consequently in rainy weather present a mass of mud and dirt; and,
                    on the other hand, when the weather is dry, the clouds of sand which arise prove
                    a terrible annoyance. The place is defended by a strong citadel on the
                    northeast, which has a double ditch, and also several outworks. The walls that
                    surround the city are of more use in a financial than a military point of view.
                    Amongst the public edifices, the most conspicuous is the cathedral, a large and
                    elegant pile. There are eight other churches for the Greek worship, some
                    belonging to the orthodox faith, and others to schismatics. The Jews, Roman
                    Catholics, and German Lutherans, have their respective places of worship. A
                    co∏ege has been established, with a museum and botanic garden. There is a large
                    hospital, an assembly room, and a theatre, where plays are performed alternately
                    in the Russian and Greek language, and which is sometimes used for the
                    performance of Italian operas. There are several institutions for educating the
                    poorer classes of both sexes; those for females being under the superintendence
                    of the wife of the governor of the province, who resides here. Most of the water
                    is brackish, and to provide that necessary element in purity, an aqueduct has
                    been constructed, at an expense of more than a million roubles, which conveys it
                    from a distance of nearly twenty miles. All the absolute necessaries of life are
                    remarkably cheap, as must be the case where a single town draws its supplies
                    from a vast and fruitful plain like that which surrounds this city on the land
                    side.</p>
                <p part="N">As the rapid growth of Odessa, and the prospect of its continued and
                    increasing extent, depend wholly upon its commerce, it is desirable to take a
                    view of the sources of that commerce. These are to be found in the fertility of
                    its surrounding soil, and that of the more distant districts, to which there is
                    easy access. The steppes, which form a semicircle around Odessa, being the <hi
                        rend="italic">Sors Deserta</hi> of the ancients, extend to nearly 100 miles
                    from the city. This district is destitute of trees and of water, but the soil is
                    said to be favourable to the growth of corn, especially of wheat. From February
                    to May the growth of grass is most luxuriant, so that it is said to become so
                    high as to hide the cattle; but in the latter month it begins to wither, and in
                    the summer the land is so totally deprived of all verdure, as to present the
                    picture of a dry sand-bank on the sea-shore. The first rains of autumn cause
                    vegetation to shoot forth again with rapidity, till it is checked by the sharp
                    frosts, sometimes of November, but more commonly of December. The slight
                    attempts which have been made to cultivate this portion of land have for the
                    most part been abandoned, and the labour of the residents has been chiefly
                    applied to the feeding and propagating of sheep, and that more for the sake of
                    the wool than of the flesh.</p>
                <p part="N">It is from districts bordering upon the northern side of the steppes
                    that the land is to be found, the soil of which, even with the negligent
                    husbandry it receives, is the most abundantly productive of wheat. Whether from
                    the climate or the soil, or from the combination of both, or from other causes
                    of which we are ignorant, there is no part of the world known in which, in
                    propitious seasons, the increase of that grain is so great It is, however,
                    liable to great variations in its growth, and sometimes years occur when the
                    increase is very insignificant.</p>
                <p part="N">There are two kinds of wheat cultivated in the district, distinguished
                    by the properties of the hardness or the softness of the grain. They are both
                    white. The hard wheat is most proper for the countries bordered by the
                    Mediterranean Sea, where it is not ground in mills, but is pounded in mortars,
                    and used as food under the names of macaroni, vermicelli, and other similar
                    preparations, which are eaten in those countries as a substitute for bread. The
                    soft wheat comes from the most distant parts. It is the same as that grown in
                    Poland, and brought to England sometimes by way of Dantzic, and occasionally by
                    way of Odessa, and is, by grinding, converted into excellent flour. The hard
                    wheat is sown in the spring of the year, and ripens almost as speedily as
                    barley. The soft wheat is sown in October or November, before the frost sets in,
                    and both ripen nearly together. The extent sown is in some measure regulated by
                    the intelligence received of the productiveness of the preceding harvest in the
                    several countries of Europe. If an extensive failure in the west of Europe is
                    known to have occurred, the intelligence must arrive too late for any great
                    extent of additional land being sown with winter or soft wheat; but as soon as
                    the frost ceases, great activity in the labours of the field is applied to the
                    preparation of the land, for the reception of the seed of spring or hard wheat.
                    Thus the proportion which the two kinds of wheat bear to each other varies with
                    the state of the annual product in those remote countries which draw their
                    supplies from the Black Sea.</p>
                <p part="N">The greater portion of the wheat comes from a distance of 200 miles,
                    some of it 250 miles; and in years when the demand is very great, a portion is
                    brought even a distance of 400. A part of it is sent by the growers, or by mer∙
                    chants who have purchased of them, to be sold by the commission-houses in
                    Odessa; but in some seasons large contracts are entered into for the wheat by
                    Odessa merchants at a fair, to which sellers and buyers resort in great numbers,
                    and which is held at the city of Kiew, from the l5th to the 25th of January in
                    each year. The contracts are made for the corn to be delivered on shipboard by
                    the sellers at their own expense, and the money to be paid on delivery; but it
                    has occurred, in seasons when a very great demand was expected, as in 1817, that
                    money has been advanced beforehand on the credit of the future delivery.</p>
                <p part="N">The wheat is brought in small waggons, drawn by two bullocks, and the
                    number arriving in Odessa in one day has sometimes amounted to 500 or 600, and
                    in several instances to 1000. Each of these waggons conveys eight sacks of
                    wheat, and the whole load is three quarters and a half, weighing about 1700
                    pounds. They are dragged along at the rate of about ten miles a day. Though the
                    cattle are grazed free of expense, on the pasture-land on the way, except over
                    the steppes, where, in the months from May to July, the greatest periods of
                    shipment, there are no vestiges of vegetation, the expense is still so
                    considerable, that it has been often found to amount, when the prices have been
                    low, to as much, and in some instances to even more, than the load would sell
                    for at Odessa; and that, too, although the value of a day’s labour for a man and
                    two bullocks is only sixpence in Podolia, the province from which most of the
                    wheat is brought.</p>
                <p part="N">The wheat is not dried before shipping at Odessa, as is done at Dantzic,
                    and is, therefore, not well calculated for a long sea voyage, when, from
                    heating, it becomes spoiled This has been the case with cargoes sent to London,
                    where, on its arrival, the grain has so run together as to be utterly unfit for
                    food, and has been dug out with pickaxes and thrown into the Thames. The
                    principal portion of the wheat from Odessa is sent thence to Constantinople,
                    Malta, and the ports cf Italy, France, and other depots in <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:194561064?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0716-1064-0323"/>the
                    Mediterranean. It is there often a substitute for wheat grown near them; and
                    when this grain is scarce in England, and other distant markets, the produce of
                    their own harvests is exported. The following table will show the fluctuations
                    in the exports.</p>
                <p part="N">An Account of the Quantities of Wheat exportedfrom Odessa in each Year
                    from 1814 to 1836, <hi rend="subscript"> ι</hi> ∕∕wa consular returns.</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1814...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">...187,685
                            quarters.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1815...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">...372,309 ...</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1816...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">...801,591 ...</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1817...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">...870,893 ...</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1818...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">...538,513 ...</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1819...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">...627,926 ...</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1820...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">...534,199 ...</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1821...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">...435,305 ...</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1822...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">...342,752 ...</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1823...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">...443.035 ...</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1824...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">...427,767 ...</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1825...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">...170,370 ...</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1826...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">...Little or no demand,
                                freights high, and no ships to be had.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1827...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">...No trade in corn; all
                                affairs suspended, from the state of public matters in
                                Constantinople.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1828...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">...Trade suspended by the
                                war with Turkey.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1829...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">...No trade in corn this
                                year.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1830...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">...149,209 quarters. All
                                exported in the last three months of the year, when peace was
                                concluded.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1831...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">...No returns.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1832...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">...401,981
                            quarters.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1833...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">...101,000 quarters. All
                                exported in the first three months of the year.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1834...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">... 45,000 quarters. Crops
                                partially failed.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1835...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">...283,575 ...</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1836...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">...452,714 ...</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p part="N">The variations in price during this series of years were excessive. Thus
                    the average price of the year 1825, which was the lowest, was only 13s. 6d. the
                    English quarter; and the average price of the year 1817, which was the highest,
                    was 49s. 1 Id., being fluctuations to the extent of 375 per cent. The excessive
                    fluctuations in the price <hi rend="subscript"> k</hi> as well as the quantity
                    of the exports, have had a great influence on the prosperity of the city, the
                    chief export consisting of a single article. In the year 1817, the wheat shipped
                    at Odessa was 870,893, at an average of 50s. the quarter, and thus amounting to
                    L.2,177,232. The quantity shipped in 1825 was 170,370, at !3s. 6d. the quarter,
                    thus amounting to no more than L.l 15,100. It is natural to suppose that a
                    declension in the amount of a single article of exportable produce, to the
                    extent of more than nineteen parts in twenty of its value, must have caused a
                    great convulsion amongst the mercantile establishments at Odessa; and
                    accordingly, in the eight years from 1817 to 1825, almost the whole of them were
                    reduced to a state of "insolvency. As regards the producers of the article in
                    question, they too suffered severely. The high prices obtained in 1816 and 1817
                    gave an impulse to agriculture, which induced the proprietors of land to apply
                    to its cultivation whatever capital they could obtain, either by their own
                    credit, or by mortgaging their estates. The latter was effected with great
                    facility, and to an extent which was severely felt for a long period by the
                    larger proprietors. Many of the small cultivators, who occupied land belonging
                    to the crown, on long leases, with neither rent nor taxes to pay for die first
                    twenty-five years, were induced, by the low prices of wheat, to abandon their
                    holdings, and to repair to die city, where they could obtain employment in the
                    commonest kind of labour, with a better reward than cultivation yielded.
                    Experience has taught the inhabitants the very fluctuating state of the commerce
                    of wheat, and at length many of them have applied their capital and their
                    industry to the cultivation of other articles. The soil is found to be highly
                    favourable to the growth of flax, but more especially to hemp; and large
                    quantities of both are now raised. The breeding of black cattle has also been
                    much extended, and creates a large export of hides and tallow. The tallow
                    shipped increased between the years 1816 and 1831, from the value of 100,000
                    roubles to that of 2,000,000. Large flocks of sheep have also been reared, and
                    the ancient breeds in many cases have been so effectually crossed by sheep of
                    the Merino race, that much wool of an improved and still improving quality is
                    despatched to Italy, France, England, and Germany. The old commercial houses,
                    who had been ruined by the great depreciation in the price of wheat subsequently
                    to 1817, have been replaced by new firms from Russia, Italy, Germany, France,
                    and England, furnished with ample capital and credit. Some manufactures have
                    been established, which yield a surplus of sail-cloth, cordage, and soap. The
                    value of the exports, since the decline in the wheat trade, has more than
                    doubled during the last ten years. The imports consist for the most part of
                    coffee, sugar, olive-oil, cotton wool, wine, cotton, silk, and woollen goods,
                    timber, coals, fruit, dye-stuffs, tea, and hardware. Odessa has also become a
                    dépôt for an increasing trade with the ports of Asia on the Black Sea.</p>
                <p part="N">The number of vessels, and the flags they bore, that entered Odessa in
                    the course of six years, were—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Austrian</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">953 French</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">17</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Russian</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">732 Swedish</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">11</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Sardinian</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">675 Spanish</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">8</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">British</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">598 Dutch</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">7</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Greek</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">81 Tuscan</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">3</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Turkish</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">32 American</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">2</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Neapolitan</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">25</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p part="N">The tonnage of these is not known; but as the Austrian and Russian
                    vessels must have chiefly consisted of coasters from the ports of these nations
                    within the Black Sea, it is probable they were of much lighter burden than the
                    vessels of the other nations which had come through the Bosphorus. The vessels
                    under the British flag belonged mostly to Malta and the Ionian Islands. The
                    situation of Odessa is in latitude 46. 28. 54. north, and longitude 30. 43. 22.
                    east. The climate is healthy, and the winter, though short, is severe, the sea
                    being more or less frozen for about two months. The summer is intensely hot, but
                    it is deemed salubrious.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
