<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0716-3924-0543-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ORMUZ</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:960068">Hope</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1099409">Rocks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1104215">Salt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1104337">Salts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g6z">Rocks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k931f29">Ruins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43b5w92m">Salts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40p0ww6s">Journeys</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194563924?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">ORMUZ</label>, a barren island in the Persian Gulf,
                    on which was formerly built a city, forming a vast emporium of Indian trade, and
                    celebrated for its wealth and its extended commerce all over Asia. This island
                    is about twelve miles in circumference, and resembles, when viewed from the sea,
                    a mass of rocks and shells thrown up by some violent convulsion from the bottom
                    of the ocean. Not more than 500 inhabitants are contained within the walls of
                    the fort and a wretched suburb. A range of hills intersects the island from east
                    to west, from the suburb to these heights is about a mile and a half, and the
                    ground continues level about two miles along the northern shore. This whole
                    space is one mass of ruins; and it is only where the reservoirs of water have
                    been made that the buildings are in any thing like a perfect state. According to
                    the account of Kinneir, these appear to have been made in the shape of a hollow
                    cylinder, covered by an arch of solid masonry; and it is probable, he adds, that
                    every house of consequence had one of these reservoirs, as there is only a
                    record of one well of fresh water ever having been on the island, and that is
                    now dry. The rocks of Ormuz consist almost entirely of fine crystal salt; and,
                    from various specimens which are found on the surface, there can be little doubt
                    of its abounding with sulphur and a variety of metals, especially iron and
                    copper. It is mentioned that the southern part of the island is one entire heap
                    of cliffs and rocks. These sink abruptly, towards its northern extremity, into a
                    plain, comprising an extent of six or eight square miles of comparatively level
                    country, terminating in a sandy spit that divides the harbour of Ormuz into two
                    parts, and on which stands the old Portuguese fort. The harbour is tolerably
                    good, being surrounded on all sides by the land, though the bottom affords good
                    anchorage. The fort, which is still in a good state of repair, is built on a
                    narrow neck of land jutting into the sea, by which the walls are washed on the
                    northern and western sides, and was never of great extent or regular figure. The
                    walls have been most carefully and substantially built of the rock afforded by
                    the island. Strong bastions command each face, and the height from the water to
                    the ramparts may be about eighty feet. The walls are in good repair, but the
                    interior is in ruins. Two large reservoirs for supplying them with water still
                    subsist, and both are covered in. The roof of one rests on two rows of massy
                    pillars, and its diameter is about 100 feet. The fort was formerly separated
                    from the mainland by a canal cut through the neck of land, and this was crossed
                    by a drawbridge; but it is now chiefly filled up, the eastern part serving as a
                    dock for repairing boats. A rotten plank is the only passage to the gateway,
                    which is strongly defended by guns from the neck of the opposite bastion.
                    Several iron and two brass guns are mounted on the walls, bearing the Portuguese
                    arms. The carriages of the guns are so bad that they would not bear a single
                    discharge. A mud wall, just beyond the old ditch, encloses between itself and
                    the fort the few miserable huts that are occasionally tenanted on the island.
                    “Beyond this,” says Frazer, in his Narrative of a Journey through Khorassan (p.
                    47), “upon the plain extending to the feet of the mountains, lie scattered the
                    ruins of the ancient Arabian and Portuguese city, with its villas and seats,
                    which are constructed of such perishable materials that scarcely <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:194563937?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0716-3937-0544"/>any relics
                    of importance are to be seen.” The only remarkable object is a tower near the
                    wall, which Frazer conjectures to have been a minaret built by Shah Abbas after
                    he had captured the place. Along the shore both of the eastern and western bays,
                    not far from the water’s edge, may be still seen a row of ruined houses, arcaded
                    into apartments of various sizes and dimensions, which, in the opinion of
                    Frazer, have been sirdabs or underground apartments for retiring to in warm
                    weather, or cellars for receiving merchandise. The whole was of the same solid
                    architecture as the first. The ground beyond, for a considerable space towards
                    the mountains, was thickly strewed with broken tiles, pottery, glass, and the
                    other usual destructible relics of an eastern city thrown into heaps of rubbish.
                    Ormuz thus was possessed of no natural advantages, either from soil or climate;
                    the heats during the summer being scarcely supportable by the human frame. It
                    produces no articles of provision, not even a drop of water; so that it required
                    a great exertion to render it habitable. The greater portion of the island
                    consists of volcanic rocks, and the remainder of uneven stony places, strongly
                    impregnated with salt; so that the means of improving the country do not exist.
                    Not a tree nor a shrub can be raised; for the first necessary, water, is
                    entirely wanting, and all vegetable supplies come from Kishmee or the mainland.
                    Considering the barrenness of the island, Frazer doubts where the blooming and
                    aromatic shrubs, that in former times were said to have decorated the streets,
                    could have been found. The surface of the plain, though level when contrasted
                    with the mountains beyond it, is still found extremely rugged on a nearer
                    approach, and broken into ravines. The rocks are strongly impregnated with iron;
                    they rise in rugged amorphous masses, strewing the ground with ruins, from which
                    the mountains rise abruptly in bare desolate crags, and sharp, lofty peaks, of
                    every variety of form and hue. “In many parts,” says Frazer, “these, as well as
                    the plains below, have a volcanic appearance, and a looseness of texture that
                    alarms the traveller lest the surface should give way under his foot, and
                    swallow him up in yet smoking ashes.” The only products of Ormuz are iron in
                    various shapes, sulphur; salt, which is produced from several salt springs, and
                    is the only source of revenue in the island. The export in the company’s ships
                    is prohibited, lest it should interfere with the monopoly of salt in India. But
                    the export to other places is considerable. The garrison of Ormuz consists of
                    eighty soldiers belonging to the imaum of Muscat, who live immured in this
                    desolate spot in great wretchedness. The broadsword and the target are their
                    chief arms. These swords are sharp and thin, and previous to an attack they make
                    them quiver and ring in the hand, with a jerk, whilst held in an upright
                    position, and then charge with loud shouts. Ormuz was entirely indebted for its
                    pre-eminent splendour to commerce, and it was long the great dépôt both of
                    Indian and European produce. When the Portuguese fleet had found their way to
                    India round the Cape of Good Hope, they soon cast a covetous eye on the wealth
                    of Ormuz. They made several attempts to gain possession of it, but without
                    effect, till in 1514 it surrendered to Albuquerque, who approached with an
                    overwhelming force. It continued to be one of the chief seats of the Portuguese
                    power till the reign of Shah Abbas, who conceived the plan of its conquest, and
                    of attaching it as an appendage to the Persian empire. His attempt would have
                    been vain had he not been aided by an English squadron which happened to be
                    cruizing in these seas; and the commanders of which, being hostile to the
                    Portuguese, readily fell in with the schemes of the Persian monarch. Their
                    combined forces having landed, obliged the Portuguese to evacuate the town and
                    to retire to the castle, which was at last reduced, chiefly by famine. Under the
                    Persian regime the town decayed; the trade was ordered by the Shah to be
                    transferred to Gombroon, on the opposite coast; and all the inhabitants at last
                    followed, leaving only a Persian garrison. About the end of the last century
                    Ormuz was taken possession of by the imaum of Muscat, and the inhabitants were
                    then reduced to forty families. But the fort has since been repaired, and now
                    contains 500 families. Long. 56. 40. E. Lat. 27. 8. N.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
