<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0709-0432-0398-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">EULER, Leonard</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 9, page 398</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:828168">Basil</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:804885">Algebra</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1080735">Prussians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1095153">Research</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:935174">Friendship</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2df3t">Moon</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4348gn83">Mind</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k877">Research</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b47p8th29">Sight</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b40r9m368">Algebra</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4222rd9g">Robin</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4js9hb31">Motion</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4cf9j663">Planets</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193750432" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">EULER, <hi rend="smallcaps">Leonard</hi></label>, professor
                    of mathematics, member of the Imperial Academy of Petersburg, ancient director
                    of the Royal Academy of Berlin, and fellow of the Royal Society of London, as
                    also a corresponding member of the Royal Academy of Sciences at Paris, was born
                    at Basil on the 15th of April 1707, of reputable parents. The years of his
                    infancy were passed in a rural retreat at the village of Richen, of which place
                    his father was minister. Being sent to the university of Basil, he attended
                    regularly the different professors; and as his memory was prodigious, he
                    performed his academical tasks with uncommon rapidity; but all the time he thus
                    gained was consecrated to geometry, which soon became his favourite study. The
                    early progress which he made in this science only gave new ardour to his
                    application; and thus he obtained a distinguished place in the esteem of John
                    Bernoulli, who was at that time one of the first mathematicians in Europe, as
                    well as in the friendship of Daniel and Nicoas Bernoulli, who were already the
                    rivals of their illustrious father. In 1723 Euler took his degree as master of
                    arts, and delivered on that occasion a Latin discourse, in which he drew a
                    comparison between the philosophy of Newton and the Cartesian system, which was
                    received with the greatest applause. At his father’s desire he afterwards
                    applied himself to the study of theology and the oriental languages, and though
                    these studies were foreign to his predominant propensity, his success was
                    considerable; but, with his father’s consent, he returned to geometry as his
                    principal pursuit. He continued to avail himself of the counsels and
                    instructions of John Bernoulli; he contracted, as already stated, an intimate
                    friendship with his two sons, Daniel and Nicoas; and it was in consequence of
                    these connexions that he became afterwards the principal ornament of the Academy
                    of Petersburg. The project of erecting this academy, which had been formed by
                    Peter the Great, was executed by Catherine I.; and the two young Bernoullis
                    being invited to Petersburg in 1725, promised Euler, who was desirous of
                    following them, that they would use their utmost endeavours to procure for him
                    an advantageous settlement in that city. In the meantime, by their advice, he
                    applied himself with ardour to the study of physiology, to which he made a happy
                    application of his mathematical knowledge; and he also attended the medical
                    lectures of the most eminent professors of Basil. This study, however, did not
                    wholly engross his time, nor even relax the activity of his powerful and
                    comprehensive mind in the cultivation of other branches of natural science. For
                    whilst he was keenly engaged in physiological researches, he composed a
                    dissertation on the nature and propagation of sound, and an answer to a
                    prizequestion concerning the masting of ships, to which the Academy of Sciences
                    adjudged the <hi rend="italic">accessit,</hi> or second rank, in the year 1727.
                    From this latter discourse, and other circumstances, it appears that Euler had
                    early embarked in the curious and important study of navigation, which he
                    afterwards enriched with so many valuable discoveries.</p>
                <p>Euler s merit would have given him an easy admission to honourable preferment,
                    either in the magistracy or university of his native city, if both civil and
                    academical honours had not been there distributed by lot. But chance having
                    decided against him in regard to a certain situation to which he aspired, he
                    left his country, set out for Petersburg, and was made joint professor with his
                    countrymen Hermann and Daniel Bernoulli in the university of that city. At the
                    commencement of his new career he enriched the academical collection with many
                    memoirs which excited a noble emulation between him and the Bernoulli's; and
                    this emulation always continued, without either degenerating into a selfish
                    jealousy, or producing the least alteration in their friendship. It was at this
                    time that he carried to a new degree of perfection the integral calculus,
                    invented the calculation of sines, reduced analytical operations to a greater
                    simplicity, and threw new light on all the parts of mathematical science. In
                    1730 he was promoted to the professorship of natural philosophy; and in 1733 he
                    succeeded his friend Daniel Bernoulli in the mathematical chair. In 1735 a
                    problem was proposed by the academy which required expedition, and for the
                    solution of which several eminent mathematicians had demanded the space of some
                    months. The problem was solved by Euler in three days, to the great astonishment
                    of the academy; but the violent and laborious efforts it cost him threw him into
                    a fever, which endangered his life, and deprived him of the use of his right
                    eye. The Academy of Sciences at Paris, which in 1738 had adjudged the prize to
                    his memoir concerning the nature and properties of fire, proposed for the year
                    1740 the important subject of the tides; a problem the solution of which
                    required the most arduous calculations, and comprehended the theory of the solar
                    system. Euler’s discourse on this question was considered as a masterpiece of
                    analysis and geometry; and it was more honourable for him to share the
                    academical prize with such illustrious competitors as Colin Maclaurin and Daniel
                    Bernoulli, than to have carried it away from rivals of inferior reputation.
                    Rarely if ever did such a brilliant competition adorn the annals of the academy;
                    and no subject, perhaps, proposed by that learned body, was ever treated with
                    such accuracy of investigation and force of genius, as that which here displayed
                    the philosophical powers of these three extraordinary men.</p>
                <p>In the year 1741 Euler was invited to Berlin in order to augment the lustre of
                    the academy which was there rising into fame. He enriched the last volume of the
                    <hi rend="italic">Mélanges</hi> or Miscellanies of Berlin with five memoirs,
                    which make an eminent, perhaps the principal, figure in that collection; and
                    these were followed, with an astonishing rapidity, by a great number of
                    important researches, which are scattered throughout the memoirs of the Prussian
                    academy, of which a volume was regularly published every year. The labours of
                    Euler will appear more astonishing when it is considered, that whilst he was
                    enriching the Academy of Berlin with a prodigious number of memoirs on the
                    deepest parts of mathematical science, containing always some new views, often
                    sublime truths, and sometimes discoveries of great importance, he did ∏θ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> t</hi> discontinue his philosophical contributions to the
                    Academy of Petersburg, which granted him a pension in 1742, and the memoirs of
                    which display the marvellous fecundity of Euler’s genius. It was with much
                    difficulty that this great man obtained, in 1766, permission fro® the king of
                    Prussia to return to Petersburg, where he desired to pass the remainder of his
                    days. Soon after his return, which was graciously rewarded by the munificence
                    Catherine IL, he was seized with a violent disorder, wħι terminated in the total
                    loss of his sight. A cataract,! <hi rend="superscript"> 13</hi> ' ing formed in
                    his left eye, which had been essentia J <pb break="no" facs="nls:193750445"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0709-0445-0399"/>damaged by a too ardent application to study,
                    deprived ' him entirely of the use of that organ. It was in this distressing
                    situation that he dictated to his servant, a tailor’s apprentice, who was
                    absolutely devoid of mathematical knowledge, his <hi rend="italic">Elements of
                    Algebra</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> which, by their intrinsical merit in point
                    of perspicuity and method, and the unhappy circumstances in which they were
                    composed, have excited equal applause and astonishment. This work, though purely
                    elementary, discovers the characteristics of an inventive genius; and it is here
                    alone that we meet with a complete theory of the analysis of Diophantus.</p>
                <p>About this time Euler was honoured by the Academy of Sciences at Paris with the
                    place of foreign member of that learned body; and after this, the academical
                    prize was adjudged to three of his memoirs, <hi rend="italic">Concerning the
                    Inequalities in the Motions of the Planets.</hi> The two prizequestions proposed
                    by the same academy for 1770 and 1772 were designed to obtain from the labours
                    of astronomers a more perfect theory of the moon. Euler, assisted by his eldest
                    son, was a competitor for these prizes, and obtained both. In this last memoir
                    he reserved for further consideration several inequalities of the moon’s motion,
                    which he could not determine in his first theory, on account of the complicated
                    calculations in which the method he then employed had engaged him. But he had
                    the courage afterwards to review his whole theory, with the assistance of his
                    son and Messrs Krafft and Lexell, and to pursue his researches until he had
                    constructed the new tables, which appeared, together with the great work, in
                    1772. Instead of confining himself, as before, to the fruitless integration of
                    three differential equations of the second degree, which are furnished by
                    mathematical principles, he reduced them to the three ordinates, which determine
                    the place of the moon; and he divided into classes all the inequalities of that
                    planet, as far as they depend either on the elongation of the sun and moon, or
                    upon the eccentricity, or the parallax, or the inclination of the lunar orbit.
                    All these means of investigation, employed with such art and dexterity as could
                    only be expected from analytical genius of the first order, were attended with
                    the greatest success; and it is impossible to observe without admiration such
                    immense calculations on the one hand, and on the other the ingenious methods
                    employed by this great man to abridge them, and to facilitate their application
                    to the real motion of the moon. But this admiration will become astonishment
                    when we considerat what period and in what circumstances all this was effected.
                    It was when he was totally blind, and consequently obliged to arrange all his
                    computations by the sole powers of his memory and his genius; when he was
                    embarrassed in his domestic circumstances by a dreadful fire, which had consumed
                    the greater part of his substance, and forced him to quit a ruined house, every
                    corner of which was known to him by a habit that in some measure supplied the
                    place of sight ;—it was in these circumstances, and under these privations, that
                    Euler composed a work, which alone is sufficient to render his name immortal· I
                    he heroic patience and tranquillity of mind which he displayed need no eulogy
                    here; and he derived them not only fro <hi rend="subscript"> m</hi> the love of
                    science, but from the power of religion. His philosophy .was too genuine and
                    sublime to stop its analysis at mechanical causes; it led him to that divine
                    philosophy of religion which ennobles human nature, and is alone capable of
                    forming a habit of true magnanimity and patience under suffering.</p>
                <p>. ome time after this the celebrated Wenzell, by couching the cataract, restored
                    Euler’s sight; but the satisfac- <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> ° <hi
                    rend="superscript"> n</hi> and joy which this successful operation produced were
                    <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> short duration. Some instances of negligence on
                    the Part of his surgeons, and his own impatience to use an organ the cure of
                    which was not complete, deprived him of vision a second time; and this relapse
                    was accompanied with tormenting pain. With the assistance of his sons, and of
                    Messrs Krafft and Lexell, however, he continued his labours; neither the loss of
                    his sight nor the infirmities of an advanced age being sufficient to damp the
                    ardour of his genius. Having engaged to furnish the Academy of Petersburg with
                    as many memoirs as would be sufficient to complete its acts for twenty years
                    after his death, he in the space of seven years transmitted to the academy above
                    seventy memoirs, and left above two hundred more, which were revised and
                    completed by the author of this notice. Such of the memoirs as were of ancient
                    date were separated from the rest, and form a collection which was published in
                    the year 1783, under the title of <hi rend="italic">Analytical Works.</hi></p>
                <p>Euler’s knowledge was more universal than could well be expected in one who had
                    pursued with such unremitting ardour mathematics and astronomy as his favourite
                    studies. He had made very considerable progress in medical, botanical, and
                    chemical science; he was an excellent scholar, and possessed what is generally
                    called erudition in a very high degree. He had read, with attention and taste,
                    the most eminent writers of ancient Rome; the civil and literary history of all
                    ages and all nations was familiar to him; and foreigners who were only
                    acquainted with his works were astonished to find in the conversation of a man
                    whose long life seemed to have been wholly occupied in mathematical and physical
                    researches and discoveries, such an extensive acquaintance with the most
                    interesting branches of literature. In this respect, no doubt, he was much
                    indebted to an uncommon memory, which seemed to retain every idea that was
                    conveyed to it, either from reading or meditation. He could repeat the Aeneid of
                    Virgil from the beginning to the end without hesitation, and indicate the first
                    and last line of every page of the edition which he used.</p>
                <p>But several attacks of vertigo, in the beginning of September 1783, which did not
                    prevent his calculating the motions of the aerostatical globes, proved the
                    forerunners of his mild and happy passage from this scene to a better. His death
                    was sudden; he ceased to calculate and to live at nearly the same instant of
                    time. Whilst he was amusing himself at tea with one of his grandchildren, he was
                    struck with apoplexy, which terminated his illustrious career at the age of
                    seventy-six. Euler, says Condorcet, was one of those men whose genius was
                    equally capable of the greatest efforts and of the most continued labour; who
                    multiplied his productions beyond what might have been expected from human
                    strength, and who notwithstanding was original in each; whose head was always
                    occupied, and his mind always calm. The nature of his pursuits, by withdrawing
                    him from the world, preserved that simplicity of manners for which he was
                    originally indebted to his character and his education; and he employed none of
                    those means to which men of real merit have sometimes recourse in order to
                    enhance the importance of their discoveries. It is true that fecundity such as
                    his renders useless all the little calculations of self-love; but still great
                    lucidity of mind and uprightness of character are necessary to trace, as he has
                    done, the history of his thoughts, even when his investigations have proved
                    fruitless, or the results disappointed the expectations which he had formed.
                    Euler’s constitution was uncommonly vigorous; his health was good; and the
                    evening of his long life was serene, being sweetened by the fame which follows
                    genius, the public esteem and respect which are never withheld from exemplary
                    virtue, and several domestic comforts, which he was capable of feeling, and
                    therefore deserved to enjoy.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193750458" xml:id="kp-eb0709-0458-0400"/>
                <p>The works which Euler published separately are, 1. <hi rend="italic">Dissertatio
                    physica</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic">Sono,</hi> Bâle, 1727, in
                    4to; 2. <hi rend="italic">Mechanica, sive Motus scientia, analytice
                    exposita,</hi> Petersburg, 1736, in 2 vols. 4to; 3. <hi rend="italic">Einleitung
                    in die Arithmetik,</hi> or Introduction to Arithmetic, ibid. 1738, 2 vols. 8vo,
                    in German and Russian; 4. <hi rend="italic">Tentamen</hi><hi rend="italic">Novae
                    Theoriae Musicae,</hi> ibid. 1739, in 4to; 5. <hi rend="italic">Methodus
                    inveniendi Lineas curvas, maximi minimive proprietate gaudentes, sive solutio
                    proble-matica isoperimetrici latissimo sensu accepti,</hi> Lausanne, 1744, in
                    4to; 6. <hi rend="italic">Theoria motuum Planetarum et Cometarum, continens
                    methodum facilem ex aliquot observationibus ambitas,</hi> etc. <hi rend="italic"
                    >determinandi,</hi> Berlin, 1744, in 4to; 7. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Beantwortung,</hi> etc. or Answers to different Questions respecting Comets,
                    ibid. 1744, in 8vo; 8. <hi rend="italic">Neue</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Grundsoetze,</hi> etc. or New Principles of Artillery, translated from the
                    English of Benjamin Robins, with notes and illustrations, ibid. 1745, in 8vo; 9.
                    <hi rend="italic">Opuscula varii</hi><hi rend="italic">argumenti,</hi> ibid.
                    1746- 1751, in 3 vols. 4to; 10. <hi rend="italic">Novae</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >et</hi><hi rend="italic">correctoe Tabulae ad loca Lunae</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >computanda,</hi> ibid. 1746, in 4to; 11. <hi rend="italic">Tabulae
                    Astro-nomicae Solis</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">Lunae,</hi>
                    ibid. 4to; 12. <hi rend="italic">Gedanken,</hi> etc. or Thoughts on the Elements
                    of Bodies, ibid. 4to; 13. <hi rend="italic">Bettung der Göttlichen
                    Offenbarung,</hi> etc. Defence of Divine Revelation against Freethinkers, ibid.
                    1747, in4to; 14. <hi rend="italic">Introductio</hi><hi rend="italic">in
                    Analysin</hi><hi rend="italic">Infinitorum,</hi> Lausanne, 1748, in 2 vols. 4to;
                    15. <hi rend="italic">Scientia Navalis, seu Tractatus de construendis ac
                    dirigendis Navibus,</hi> Petersburg, 1749, in 2 vols. 4to; 16. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Theoria motus</hi><hi rend="italic">Lunae,</hi> Berlin, 1753, in 4to; 17. <hi
                    rend="italic">Dissertatio de principio</hi><hi rend="italic">minimae</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">actionis, una cum examine Objectionum</hi><hi rend="italic">cl.
                    prof-</hi><hi rend="italic">Kcenigii,</hi> ibid. 1753, in 8vo; 18. <hi
                    rend="italic">Institutiones Calculi Differentiatis, cum ejus usu in analysi
                    Infinitorum ac doctrina</hi><hi rend="italic">Serierum,</hi> ibid. 1755, in 4to;
                    19. <hi rend="italic">Constructio Lentium Objectivarum,</hi> etc. Petersburg,
                    1762, in 4to; 20. <hi rend="italic">Theoria motus Corporum solidorum seu
                    rigido-</hi> rum, Rostoch, 1765, in 4to; 21. <hi rend="italic">Institutiones
                    Calculi Integratis,</hi> Petersburg, 1768-1770, in 3 vols. 4to; 22. <hi
                    rend="italic">Lettres a une Princesse d’Allemagne sur quelques sujets de
                    Physique et Philosophie,</hi> Petersburg, 1768-1772, in 3 vols. 8vo; 23. <hi
                    rend="italic">Anleitung zur Algebra,</hi> or Introduction to Algebra,
                    Petersburg, 1770, in 8vo; 24. <hi rend="italic">Dioptrica,</hi> Petersburg,
                    1767-1771, in 3 vols. 4to; 25. <hi rend="italic">Theoria motuum</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Lunae nova</hi><hi rend="italic">methodo pertractata,</hi> ibid.
                    1772, in 4to; 26. <hi rend="italic">Novae Tabulae</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Lunares,</hi> ibid, in 8vo; 27. <hi rend="italic">Theorie</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >complete de la construction</hi><hi rend="italic">et de la manoeuvre des
                    Vaisseaux,</hi> ibid. 1773, in 8vo; 28. <hi rend="italic">Eclaircissements sur
                    les etablissements en faveur tant des Veuves que des Morts,</hi> without a date;
                    29. <hi rend="italic">Opus-culà Analytica,</hi> Petersburg, 1783-1785, in 2
                    vols. 4to.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
