<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0709-9990-0364-06" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">ERSKINE, Thomas, Lord
                    Erskine</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 9, page 364</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1155838">Treason</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:975732">Intellect</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1129153">Speech</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:935399">Frost</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:933481">Foxes</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1166896">Views</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93d6n">Bar</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4348gn83">Mind</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4f47gw8z">Treason</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4377609d">Intellect</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r546">Speech</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4j09w777">Frost</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b46h4ct7t">Fox</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4w669c71">Views</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1207649">Wales</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193749990" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">ERSKINE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Thomas, Lord
                    Erskine</hi></label>, a distinguished lawyer and statesman, was the third and
                    youngest son of David Henry Erskine, tenth earl of Buchan, in Scotland. He was
                    born in Scotland, and received his education partly at the high school of
                    Edinburgh, and partly at the university of St Andrews. From the contracted
                    resources of his family, it was necessary for him to fix upon a profession. He
                    chose the navy, and having embarked at Leith as a midshipman, he quitted his
                    native country, which he did not revisit until a few years before his death. In
                    the navy he experienced no advancement, and, after four <hi rend="subscript">
                    ζ</hi> years ’ service, he entered the army in the year 1768. In 1770 he
                    married, and shortly after this event he accompanied his regiment to Minorca,
                    where he remained during three years. It is not certain whether his abilities as
                    an officer ever rendered him conspicuous, but the versatility of his talents,
                    and the acuteness of his intellect, thus early brought him a high reputation. By
                    the earnest persuasion of his mother, who, it would appear, was a woman of more
                    than ordinary penetration, he was induced to quit the army after six years of
                    military probation. The legal profession was the one which appeared best adapted
                    for the character of his mind; and in 1777 he entered as a fellow commoner at
                    Trinity College, Cambridge, for the purpose of obtaining a degree, which he was
                    entitled to as the son of a nobleman, and thereby of shortening his passage to
                    the bar. At the same time he entered himself as a student at Lincoln’s Inn. In
                    1778 he was called to the bar, where his success was immediate and remarkable.
                    In a ease of libel, in which he advocated the cause of Captain Baillie, the
                    defendant, he displayed so much eloquence and talent, that the legal world was
                    astonished, and thirty retainers were put into his hand by attomies before he
                    left the court. A few months after this event he was honoured by being chosen to
                    appear at the bar of the House of Commons, as counsel against a bill of Lord
                    North’s to restore to the universities the monopoly in almanacks. The bill was
                    lost by a large majority, and the speech which Mr Erskine made upon the occasion
                    so established his reputation for forensic skill, that he was from this period
                    engaged, either on one side or another, m every case of importance, during a
                    practice of twenty-fiy <hi rend="superscript"> e</hi> years. To this period also
                    belongs his famous speech m defence of Lord George Gordon, which was a case of
                    what <pb break="no" facs="nls:193750003" xml:id="kp-eb0709-0003-0365"/>is called constructive treason. Erskine procured a
                    clear acquittal of his client, which was for the time a deathblow to the
                    tremendous doctrine of constructive treason. In May 1783 he received a silk
                    gown, and the same year was elected member of parliament for Portsmouth, for
                    which borou <hi rend="superscript"> σ</hi> h he was on every election re-chosen,
                    until his advancement to the peerage rendered that honour unnecessary. When the
                    eldest son of George III. obtained his establishment as Prince of Wales, he
                    chose Mr Erskine as his attorney-general. But there is nothing in the life of
                    this eminent man which reflects so much honour on his memory as his exertions in
                    defence of the privileges of juries. The rights of those <hi rend="italic">pro
                    tempore</hi> judges he strenuously maintained upon all occasions, particularly
                    in the celebrated trial of the Dean of St Asaph, for libel, when Justice Buller
                    refused to receive the verdict of <hi rend="italic">guilty of publishing
                    only,</hi> as returned by the jury. In 1789 another opportunity was afforded him
                    to display his peculiar powers. This was the defence of a Mr Stockdale, a
                    bookseller, who was tried on an information filed by the attorney-general, for
                    publishing what was charged as a libellous pamphlet in favour of Mr Hastings.
                    The situation of the latter, whose celebrated but protracted trial was then
                    dragging its slow length along, gave Erskine admirable scope for that animated
                    appeal to the feelings, by which his speeches are so much distinguished. It is
                    one of his finest orations; and, whether we regard the wonderful skill with
                    which the argument is conducted, the soundness of the principles laid down, and
                    their happy application to the case, the vividness of fancy with which these are
                    illustrated, and the touching language in which they are conveyed, it is justly
                    to be regarded as a consummate specimen of the art of addressing a jury. This
                    masterly defence procured a clear acquittal for Stockdale, although the fact of
                    publication was admitted. Not long afterwards he advocated the cause of Mr
                    Perry, editor of a London newspaper, who was also charged with publishing what
                    the jealous loyalty of those times construed into a libel; and his speech
                    produced a similar result. But the most arduous effort of his professional life
                    arose out of the part cast upon him, in conjunction with Mr, afterwards Sir
                    Vicary, Gibbs, in the trials of Hardy, Tooke, and others, for high treason in
                    1794. These trials lasted several weeks, and the ability displayed by Mr Erskine
                    upon this memorable occasion was acknowledged and admired by men of all parties.
                    His speech in defence of Mr Frost, which, however, preceded those above
                    mentioned, is another of those almost miraculous exertions, which, in that
                    momentous crisis, Mr Erskine made for the liberties of his country. Frost was
                    accused of uttering seditious words, which, however, turned out to have been
                    spoken at random in a coffee-house whilst the accused was in a state bordering
                    on intoxication. In the violence of that day, the exertions of Erskine failed of
                    their accustomed effect, and Frost was found guilty. But the impression of his
                    defence; <hi rend="superscript"> vas</hi> not lost; and it deterred the
                    government from risking its credit on such precarious speculations, until, as we
                    have noticed, the charges of high treason were brought forward, when the whole
                    force of the bar was marshalled against the prisoners, and every effort used to
                    beat down and paralyse their undaunted defender. But his spirit rose superior to
                    <hi rend="superscript"> e</hi> ' <hi rend="superscript"> er</hi> y difficulty,
                    and then it was that his consummate talents ’hone forth in their native lustre.
                    His indefatigable patience, his sleepless watchfulness, his unceasing activity
                    of body and mind, his untameable spirit, his quickness and subtilty of
                    intellect, together with a herculean strength of institution, counterbalanced
                    the host to which he was opposed. Such were the gigantic powers of the man; the
                    " <hi rend="superscript"> 0l</hi> jderful eloquence of the forensic orator is
                    only to be <hi rend="superscript"> n</hi> °f <hi rend="superscript"> secon</hi>
                    ð <hi rend="superscript"> t0</hi> these.</p><p>r Erskine was a warm partizan of Mr Fox, and the liberal party of that time. He
                    strenuously opposed the war with France, and published a pamphlet against it,
                    entitled <hi rend="italic">A View of the Causes and Consequences of the War with
                    France,</hi> which had an immense sale. In 1802 the Prince of Wales not only
                    restored him to his office of attorney-general, of which he had been deprived,
                    but made him keeper of the seals for the duchy of Cornwall. On the death of Pitt
                    in 1806, when Lord Grenville received orders to form a new administration, Mr
                    Erskine was created a peer, by the title of Lord Erskine, of Restormel Castle in
                    Cornwall, and elevated to the dignity of lord high chancellor of Great Britain.
                    His previous experience in the courts of common law scarcely fitted him for the
                    judicial functions of this dignified office; but there seems little doubt that
                    his natural quickness of intellect would have triumphed over every difficulty,
                    had not a dissolution of the administration of which he formed part been
                    accelerated by the obstinacy of the king on the subject of the Catholic claims.
                    His public career may be said to have terminated with this event, and the
                    remainder of his life was undistinguished by any great exertion, whilst it was
                    unhappily embittered by pecuniary difficulties, which were enhanced, it is said,
                    by an unfortunate second marriage. His mind, however, retained its native
                    elasticity, and in his retirement he employed himself in editing several of the
                    state trials. He also wrote the preface to Fox’s speeches, a political romance
                    entitled <hi rend="italic">Armata,</hi> and several pamphlets in support of the
                    Greek cause. Whilst accompanying one of his sons by sea to Edinburgh, he was
                    seized with an inflammation of the chest, which compelled him to land at
                    Scarborough. He reached Scotland by easy stages, but expired on the 17th of
                    November 1823, at the seat of his brother, situated a few miles from Edinburgh.
                    The peculiar character of Lord Erskine’s eloquence has already in some measure
                    been described. In his capacity of advocate he possessed the power of summoning
                    upon the instant all the resources of his mind, and bringing them to bear upon
                    the subject before the court with extraordinary effect. In this respect his
                    speeches bear a resemblance to those of Mr Pitt, whilst they far surpass them in
                    impassioned fervour, in brilliancy of imagination, in copiousness of imagery,
                    and in that quality of mind expressed by the emphatic word genius. His dexterity
                    was likewise unrivalled at the bar; and these qualifications, united with a
                    courage which nothing could daunt, and a firmness which was never overcome,
                    rendered him almost irresistible on the defensive side of political persecution.
                    Amidst all the struggles of the constitution in parliament, in council, and in
                    the field, during that momentous period of our national history, there was no
                    man to whose individual exertions it owed so much as to those of this celebrated
                    advocate. In stemming the tide of state prosecutions, this single patriot may be
                    said to have saved his country from the horrors of a general proscription. As a
                    senatorial orator his claims were but secondary; and as a political writer he is
                    not entitled to much distinction. His sphere was the bar, and there, as the
                    advocate of injured worth or persecuted political honesty, he never had a rival
                    before, and he has left no equal behind him.</p><p>By his first wife, who died in 1805, Lord Erskine had three sons and five
                    daughters. His speeches have been frequently printed; the last edition is in 5
                    vols. 8vo. <hi rend="smallcaps">(r.</hi> R. R.)</p></div></body></text></TEI>